var questions=[
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"1","question":"What is the name of the science that studies the structure of the animal's body and the relationship of its parts?","answer":"Anatomy  <br/> <br/>ref:DET10"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"2","question":"What is the name of the science that studies the function of the body systems?","answer":"Physiology  <br/> <br/>ref:DET211"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"jr bonus","number":"3","question":"Name 3 of the horse's body systems.","answer":"Skeletal, muscular, respiratory, circulatory (cardiovascular), digestive, reproductive, nervous, endocrine, integumentary (skin), urinary, lymphatic (also accept musculoskeletal and genitourinary)  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHAiv,v"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"4","question":"Name 5 of the horse's body systems.","answer":"Skeletal, muscular, respiratory, circulatory (cardiovascular), digestive, reproductive, nervous, endocrine, integumentary (skin), urinary, lymphatic (also accept musculoskeletal and genitourinary)  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHAiv,v"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"5","question":"What is the easiest way to tell if the cardiovascular system is working properly?","answer":"Check the pulse or listen to the heart (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH830-1; HSm350-2"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"6","question":"Which body system of the horse consists of blood, blood vessels, and the heart?","answer":"Circulatory (cardiovascular)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH830-1; HSm350-1; DET57"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"7","question":"Name 3 parts of the circulatory or cardiovascular system.","answer":"Heart, blood, and blood vessels (arteries, veins, and capillaries) [accept general or specific]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH830-1; HSm350-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"jr bonus","number":"8","question":"Name the 3 MAIN types of blood vessels.","answer":"Arteries, veins, and capillaries  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH830-1; HSm350-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"9","question":"Which structures carry blood AWAY from the heart?","answer":"Arteries  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH830-1; HSm350-1; CAHA57"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"10","question":"Explain the DIRECTIONAL differences between arteries and veins.","answer":"Arteries carry blood AWAY from the heart; veins carry blood to the heart.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH830-1; HSm350-1; CAHA57"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"11","question":"Name 3 ways that veins differ from arteries.","answer":"Veins contain a larger volume of blood; veins have thinner walls; veins have valves; veins carry blood to the heart; arteries have thicker walls; arteries carry blood away from the heart.  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA23; CAHA57"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"12","question":"What is the name of the primary vessel that carries blood from the heart to the rest of the body?","answer":"Aorta  <br/> <br/>ref:DET13; HSm350-1 (picture); CAHA57 (picture)"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"13","question":"What artery is the main blood supply to the head?","answer":"Carotid artery (FYI:  The left and right common carotid arteries each divide into internal and external carotid arteries.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET48; CAHA61"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"14","question":"The coronary arteries are the first branches off the aorta and carry blood to what structure?","answer":"Heart  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA58"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"15","question":"The medial and lateral digital arteries furnish blood to what part of the horse?","answer":"Foot  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA23"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"16","question":"The blood supply to the foot is furnished by what TWO digital arteries?","answer":"Medial and lateral digital arteries  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA23"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"17","question":"What artery is located under the jawbone at the last cheek tooth and can be used to take a pulse?","answer":"Facial artery  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA62"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"18","question":"Where is the femoral artery?","answer":"Hind leg  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA38; ES208"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"19","question":"What organ receives oxygenated blood from the left gastric artery?","answer":"Stomach  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA60 (pic)"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"20","question":"The blood leaving the right ventricle of the heart by the pulmonary artery flows into what organ?","answer":"Lungs  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm350-1; CAHA57; DET222"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"21","question":"Which artery carries oxygen-poor blood from the heart to the lungs?","answer":"Pulmonary artery  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm350-1; CAHA57; DET222"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"22","question":"What organ receives oxygenated blood from the renal artery?","answer":"Kidney  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA60; DET232"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"23","question":"How much blood does an adult horse's body contain?","answer":"About 50 liters, 13.2 gallons, or around 13 gallons (accept any)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH830-1; HSm350-2"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"24","question":"Name the TWO MAJOR components of blood.","answer":"Plasma and blood cells (FYI:  Blood cells include red blood cells, white blood cells, and platelets.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH830-1; DET214"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"25","question":"What is the name of the clear, yellowish fluid portion of blood in which various blood cells are suspended?","answer":"Plasma  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH80-1; DET214"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"26","question":"2-part question:  What is the name of the fluid in whole blood and what is the name of the fluid in blood after the cells and clotting factors have been removed?","answer":"Plasma is the fluid in whole blood; serum is the fluid left after the blood cells and clotting factors have been removed.  <br/> <br/>ref:DET214; DET242; FCH401,403"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"27","question":"Name 3 functions of the blood.","answer":"Transports nutrients, transports gases, transports hormones, removes wastes, fights infections, regulates pH, clots blood, regulates body temperature, regulates blood pressure (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH830-1; DET32"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"28","question":"What is the term for low oxygen saturation in the ARTERIAL blood?","answer":"Arterial hypoxemia  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH810-2; HIH895-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"29","question":"In what part of the vascular system does the majority of exchange of gases and nutrients occur?","answer":"Capillaries  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH830-1; HSm350-1; DET47"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"30","question":"Which are the smallest blood vessels?","answer":"Capillaries  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH830-1; HSm350-1; DET47"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"31","question":"2-part question:  Which are the smallest blood vessels and what do they connect?","answer":"Capillaries; connect arteries with veins  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH830-1; HSm350-1; DET47"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"32","question":"2-part question:  Give the common names and scientific names for the 3 types of blood \"cells\".","answer":"Red blood cells (erythrocytes), white blood cells (leukocytes), platelets (thrombocytes) [FYI: Platelets are not considered true cells because they have no nuclei.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH830-1; DET230; DET293; DET214"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"33","question":"What is the common name for thrombocytes?","answer":"Platelets  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH830-1; DET214; DET267"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"34","question":"Which cell-like components of blood aid in clotting?","answer":"Platelets (thrombocytes) [FYI: Platelets are not considered true cells because they have no nuclei.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH830-1; DET214; DET267"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"35","question":"What is the main physiological function of thrombocytes?","answer":"Blood clotting (FYI:  Thrombocytes are platelets.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH830-1; DET214; DET267"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"36","question":"What are erythrocytes?","answer":"Red blood cells  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH830-1; HSm430-8; DET99; DET230"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"37","question":"Where does formation of red blood cells occur?","answer":"Bone marrow  <br/> <br/>ref:DET34; CAHA63"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"38","question":"What is the main function of erythrocytes?","answer":"Transport oxygen (to the tissues and organs)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH830-1; HSm430-8; DET99; DET230"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"39","question":"What is the main function of red blood cells?","answer":"Transport oxygen (to the tissues and organs)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH830-1; HSm430-8; DET99; DET230"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"40","question":"To what does oxygen attach on the red blood cells?","answer":"Hemoglobin  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH810-1; DET138"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"41","question":"What is the name of the iron-containing protein found in erythrocytes that binds to oxygen?","answer":"Hemoglobin  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm430-8; HIH830-1; DET138"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"42","question":"In order to successfully transport oxygen, hemoglobin must combine with what mineral?","answer":"Iron  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm430-8; FCH38"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"43","question":"Name 3 of the 5 types of leucocytes or white blood cells.","answer":"Neutrophils, basophils, eosinophils, lymphocytes, and monocytes  <br/> <br/>ref:DET97,173,182,190; HIH445-9,12"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"44","question":"What are leukocytes?","answer":"White blood cells  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH830-1; DET168"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"45","question":"What SPECIFIC type of white blood cell is found in the spleen and lymph nodes and is important in fighting infection?","answer":"Lymphocytes  <br/> <br/>ref:DET173"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"46","question":"You do the math...If the cardiac output is 35 liters per minute and the heart rate is 35 beats per minute, what is the stroke volume?","answer":"1 liter (FYI:  Cardiac Output = stroke volume x heart rate)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH830-1; HSm350-2; DET48"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"47","question":"You do the math...If the resting heart rate is 32 beats per minute and the stroke volume is one liter, what is the cardiac output?","answer":"32 liters per minute (FYI: Cardiac output = stroke volume x heart rate)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH830-1; HSm350-2; DET48"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"48","question":"What is cardiac output?","answer":"How much blood the heart can pump in one minute (FYI: Cardiac output=stroke volume x heart rate.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH830-1; HSm350-2; DET48"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"49","question":"In reference to the heart, what is stroke volume?","answer":"Amount of blood the heart pumps with each beat  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH830-1; HSm350-2; DET258"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"50","question":"What large muscular organ in the cardiovascular system pumps blood to the rest of the body?","answer":"Heart  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH830-1; HSm350-1; CAHA57,58"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"51","question":"What is the cone-shaped muscular organ located between the lungs that propels blood through the body by muscular contractions?","answer":"Heart  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH830-1; HSm350-1; CAHA57,58"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"52","question":"How many chambers are in a horse’s heart?","answer":"4 (four) (FYI: Left and right atria and left and right ventricles)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH830-1; HSm350-1; CAHA57,58"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"53","question":"2-part question:  The heart is composed of how many chambers and what are their names?","answer":"4 (four) chambers; left ventricle, right ventricle, left atrium, right atrium  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm350-1; CAHA57-58"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"54","question":"Simultaneously, blood enters the right atrium from the body and the left atrium from where?","answer":"Lungs (FYI:  Oxygenated blood from the lungs enters the left atrium through the pulmonary vein.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH830-1; HSm350-2; CAHA57"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"55","question":"To which side of the horse’s heart does blood return from the body?","answer":"Right side (FYI: Blood from the body returns to the right atrium through the cranial and caudal vena cavae.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH830-1; HSm350-1; CAHA57"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"56","question":"What chamber of the heart does oxygenated blood from the lungs enter first?","answer":"Left atrium  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH830-1; HSm350-2; CAHA57"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"57","question":"Which chamber of the heart is the primary pumping chamber for moving oxygenated blood to the body?","answer":"Left ventricle  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH830-1; HSm350-2; CAHA57"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"58","question":"Which chamber of the heart does blood returning from the body by the cranial and caudal vena cavae enter first?","answer":"Right atrium  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH830-1; HSm350-1; CAHA57"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"59","question":"Correctly organize the blood flow through the following areas starting with the cranial vena cava: cranial vena cava, left ventricle, pulmonary vein, right atrium, pulmonary artery, lungs, and aorta.","answer":"Cranial vena cava, right atrium, pulmonary artery, lungs, pulmonary vein, left ventricle, aorta  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH830-1; HSm350-1; CAHA57"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"60","question":"In what organ would Purkinje FIBERS be found?","answer":"Heart (FYI:  Purkinje FIBERS are specialized cardiac muscle fibers that conduct the electrical impulses that are responsible for the contractions of the ventricles.  Purkinje CELLS are neurons in the cerebellum.)  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA58"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"61","question":"What is the function of the sinoatrial node which is located in the right atrium of the heart? (sign-oh-AY-tree-al)","answer":"Pacemaker of the heart  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA58"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"62","question":"In reference to anatomy, why is it best to listen to the heartbeat from the left side of the horse's body?","answer":"Heart is closer to the left side.  <br/> <br/>ref:ES160"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"63","question":"Name ONE function of the heart that causes a sound that can be heard with a stethoscope.","answer":"Opening of heart valves; closing of heart valves  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA58"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"64","question":"Name 3 valves found in the heart.","answer":"Tricuspid valve (right atrioventricular valve), mitral or bicuspid valve (left atrioventricular valve), pulmonic valve (semilunar valve between the RV and pulmonary artery), aortic valve (semilunar valve between the LV and aorta)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm350-2; CAHA58"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"65","question":"What organ in the abdominal cavity stores red blood cells, filters blood, removes old blood cells, and assists in combating infections?","answer":"Spleen  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm350-2; HIH830-2; FCH404"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"66","question":"How does the spleen help the racehorse increase its level of arterial oxygen and maintain levels of physical exertion?","answer":"Spleen stores red blood cells; when needed, it contracts releasing additional red blood cells to carry oxygen.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm350-2; HIH830-2; FCH404"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"67","question":"What is the MAIN function of the horse's spleen?","answer":"Stores red blood cells (FYI:  Spleen also filters blood and removes old blood cells.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm350-2; HIH830-2; FCH404"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"68","question":"What vein in the horse's neck is commonly used to draw blood samples?","answer":"Jugular vein  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA59; DET159"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"69","question":"Veins from the stomach, spleen, intestines, and pancreas all join to form the portal vein which carries blood to an important organ in the abdominal cavity where essential metabolic functions are performed.  What is the name of this organ?","answer":"Liver  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA60"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"70","question":"What is the ONLY vein that carries oxygenated blood?","answer":"Pulmonary vein  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm350-2; CAHA57"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"71","question":"What TWO veins bring unoxygenated blood from the head and body back to the heart?","answer":"Cranial and caudal vena cavae  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm350; CAHA59"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"72","question":"What is the term for the process of preparing food for absorption?","answer":"Digestion  <br/> <br/>ref:DET81; HSc27"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"73","question":"The mouth, esophagus, stomach, and intestines are all parts of what system of the horse?","answer":"Digestive system  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm405-1; HIH705-1-3; HSc27-31"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"74","question":"Which system of the horse converts feed into forms that can be used by the body for energy?","answer":"Digestive system  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH705-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"75","question":"What is the name of the tract that consists of a musculomembranous tube that extends from the mouth to the anus?","answer":"Digestive tract,  gastrointestinal tract, or alimentary canal (accept any)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET6,81,118"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"76","question":"Name 3 MECHANICAL factors in digestion.","answer":"Grasping food (prehension), chewing (mastication), swallowing (deglutition), peristalsis (movements of stomach and intestines), and defecation (pooping)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH705-1-3; HSc27-28"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"77","question":"Explain how each of the following 4 parts of the horse is involved in the process of digestion:  lips, incisors, molars, and tongue.","answer":"Lips pick up feed, incisors bite off grass, molars chew or grind food, and tongue moves feed in the mouth.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH705-1; HSc27-28"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"78","question":"Name 3 functions of the horse's gastrointestinal tract.","answer":"Prehension (grasping food), mastication (chewing food), salivation (moisturizing of food), deglutition (swallowing food), mixing food, digestion, absorption, peristalsis (movement of food), defecation (elimination of food)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH4-5; HSc27-31"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"79","question":"Give ONE reason why horse owners should have knowledge of the horse's digestive system.","answer":"So you'll know how to feed them correctly or so you'll know how to look for signs of colic  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH705-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"jr bonus","number":"80","question":"Name 5 parts of the digestive tract.","answer":"Mouth, pharynx, esophagus, stomach, small intestine (duodenum, jejunum, ileum), large intestine (cecum, large colon, small colon, rectum)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm405-1; HIH705-1-3; HSc27-31"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"81","question":"Name 7 parts of the digestive tract.","answer":"Mouth, pharynx, esophagus, stomach, small intestines (duodenum, jejunum, ileum, cecum, large colon (right ventral colon, sternal flexure, left ventral colon, pelvic flexure, left dorsal colon, diaphragmatic flexure, right dorsal colon), rectum  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm405-1; HIH705-1-3; HSc27-31"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"82","question":"The salivary glands, pancreas, and liver are accessory organs of what body system?","answer":"Digestive system  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm405-2; HIH705-1-3; HSc27-31"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"83","question":"What TWO organs deliver enzymes and products into the duodenum to assist in the digestive process?","answer":"Pancreas and liver  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm405-1; HIH705-2; CAHA51; HSc29"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"84","question":"Name 3 accessory organs of the digestive system.","answer":"Teeth, tongue, salivary glands, pancreas, and liver  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm405-2; HIH705-1-3; HSc27-31"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"85","question":"Most farm animals have an organ that stores bile, but horses do not.  What is this organ?","answer":"Gall bladder  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH705-2; HSc29"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"86","question":"What is the largest INTERNAL ORGAN and “gland” in the horse’s body?","answer":"Liver  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA54"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"87","question":"Explain how bile is released in the horse's digestive system.","answer":"(Continuously) secreted by the liver directly into the bile duct (which empties into the duodenum) [FYI:  Horses do NOT have gallbladders to store bile.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc29; HIH705-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"88","question":"What is the name of the dark green-yellow substance secreted by the liver?","answer":"Bile  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc29; HSm405-1; HIH705-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"89","question":"Name 3 substances that are secreted into the duodenum.","answer":"Bile, pancreatic lipase, amylase, trypsin (trypsinogen), chymotrypsin (chymotrypsinogen), bicarbonate  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc29"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"90","question":"What does the pancreatic enzyme amylase do?","answer":"Breaks down starches  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc29"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"91","question":"Which enzyme assists in the digestion of fats?","answer":"Lipase  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc29"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"92","question":"What does the enzyme pepsin do?","answer":"Breaks down proteins  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc29; HIH705-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"93","question":"Name ONE digestive enzyme that helps break down proteins.","answer":"Pepsin, trypsin, chymotrypsin  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc29; HIH705-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"94","question":"What does the enzyme trypsin do?","answer":"Breaks down proteins  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc29"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"jr bonus","number":"95","question":"Name 3 parts of the horse's foregut.","answer":"Mouth, esophagus, stomach, small intestine (Do NOT accept small colon which is part of the hindgut.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm405-1; HIH705-1-3; HSc27-31"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"96","question":"From cranial to caudal, name the 4 parts of the horse's FOREGUT.","answer":"Mouth, esophagus, stomach, small intestine (Do NOT accept small colon which is part of the hindgut.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm405-1; HIH705-1-3; HSc27-31"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"97","question":"What is the muscular tube that’s 50 – 60 inches in length that extends from the pharynx to the stomach?","answer":"Esophagus  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm405-1; HIH710-2; HSc28"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"98","question":"What is the esophagus?","answer":"Tube that connects the mouth to the stomach  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm405-1; HIH705-1; HSc28"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"99","question":"In reference to digestion, give TWO functions of the horse's mouth.","answer":"Intake food (prehension), chew food (mastication), wet food with saliva (salivation), and swallow food (deglutition)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH705-1; HSc27-28"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"100","question":"What is the FIRST part of the digestive tract?","answer":"Mouth  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm405-1; HIH705-1; HSc27"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"101","question":"What is the medical term for swallowing?","answer":"Deglutition  <br/> <br/>ref:DET78; HSc28"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"102","question":"What does deglutition mean?","answer":"Swallowing  <br/> <br/>ref:DET78; HSc28"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"103","question":"What structure in the horse's mouth is forced up by the tongue during swallowing to keep food out of the nose?","answer":"Soft palate (FYI:  The soft palate and the epiglottis direct feed into the esophagus and keep food out of the respiratory tract.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET250; HIH810-1; HSc28"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"104","question":"In reference to digestion, what does the term mastication mean?","answer":"Chewing of food  <br/> <br/>ref:DET176; HSc27; HIH770-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"105","question":"What is the medical term for chewing?","answer":"Mastication  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH705-1; DET176"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"106","question":"What are TWO functions of the pharynx?","answer":"Food passage between the mouth and the esophagus; air passage between the nostrils and the trachea  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH705-1; DET210; HSc28; CAHA50"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"107","question":"What is the pharynx?","answer":"Funnel-shaped tube between the mouth and the esophagus (also accept the throat) [FYI:  There's an oropharynx and a nasopharynx.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH705-1; DET210; HSc28; CAHA50"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"108","question":"What is the short, funnel-shaped tube between the mouth and the esophagus?","answer":"Pharynx  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH705-1; DET210; HSc28; CAHA50"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"109","question":"What TWO tracts does the pharynx belong to?","answer":"Respiratory and digestive tracts  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH705-1; DET210; HSc28; CAHA50"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"110","question":"What does prehension mean?","answer":"Grasping of food  <br/> <br/>ref:DET220; HSc27"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"111","question":"What is the horse's main structure for grasping food such as grain?","answer":"Lips  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH705-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"jr bonus","number":"112","question":"2-part question: Name 3 anatomical structures that aid in prehension or the grasping of food and tell what each does.","answer":"Lips pick up food; incisors bite off grass; tongue moves feed into the mouth; tongue moves food around in the mouth; tongue curls to draw water into the mouth.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH705-1; HSc27"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"113","question":"What is the term for the grasping of food in order to get the food into the mouth?","answer":"Prehension  <br/> <br/>ref:DET220; HSc27"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"114","question":"In what part of the digestive tract are fats digested and absorbed?","answer":"Small intestine  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm405-1; HSc27"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"115","question":"In what part of the digestive tract does the majority of digestion and absorption occur?","answer":"Small intestine  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm405-1; HIH705-2; HSc29"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"116","question":"In what part of the digestive tract are soluble carbohydrates digested into simple sugars and absorbed for use as energy?","answer":"Small intestine  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm405-1; HIH705-2; HSc29"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"117","question":"In what part of the digestive tract is 50% – 70% of protein in grain-based diets broken down into amino acids and absorbed?","answer":"Small intestine (FYI:  Less than 1/3 of hay protein is absorbed in foregut.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm405-1; HIH705-2; HSc29"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"118","question":"The small intestine is located between what two parts of the horse's digestive system?","answer":"Stomach and large intestine (specifically the cecum)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm405-1; HIH705-2; HSc-29-30"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"119","question":"What is the capacity of the small intestine?","answer":"48 quarts, 12 gallons, or 30% of the digestive tract (accept any; may accept 10 – 12 gallons from ES111) [Do NOT accept 68 quarts from HIH705-2 Figure because it conflicts with other sources.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm405-1; HIH705-2"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"120","question":"What is name of the material leaving the stomach and entering the small intestine?","answer":"Chyme (pronounced kime)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET56"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"121","question":"Give TWO reasons why the horse's small intestines are susceptible to displacement, telescoping, and twisting.","answer":"Great length; loose attachment to the abdominal wall (mesentery)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH435a-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"122","question":"Give ONE reason why the great length of the small intestine can cause problems.","answer":"Intestine can twist or telescope (FYI: Twisted intestine is called a volvulus; telescoped intestine is called intussusception.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH435a-1; HSm335-2"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"123","question":"What is the length of the horse's small intestine?","answer":"70 feet (may accept 60 feet from HIH435a-1 or 65 feet from HSc30)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm405-1; HIH705-2; HIH435a-1; ES111; HSc30"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"124","question":"Name the 3 parts of the small intestine.","answer":"Duodenum, jejunum, and ileum  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA51; HSc29-30"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"125","question":"Into what part of the small intestine do the bile duct and pancreatic duct empty?","answer":"Duodenum  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA51; HSc29-30"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"126","question":"What is the name for the terminal portion of the small intestine?","answer":"Ileum (FYI: Ilium is in the pelvis.)  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA51; HSc29-30"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"127","question":"Passage of feeds through the small intestine takes approximately how long?","answer":"30 – 90 minutes (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm405-1; HIH705-2"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"128","question":"What are the small projections in the small intestine called?","answer":"Villi  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm405-1; HSc30"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"129","question":"What is the capacity of the horse's stomach?","answer":"8 – 19 quarts, 2 – 4.75 gallons, or 8% – 10% of the digestive tract’s capacity (accept any number within these ranges)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm405-1; HIH705-1; HSc30"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"130","question":"How many compartments are in a horse's stomach?","answer":"1 (one) compartment  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH705-1; HSc28"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"131","question":"Give ONE reason why horses can't vomit.","answer":"Blocking action of the soft palate; angle at which the esophagus meets the stomach; tight cardiac sphincter prevents food from re-entering the esophagus  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH705-1; HSc28"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"132","question":"What SPECIFIC part of the stomach connects to the esophagus?","answer":"Cardia (FYI: There's a tight, ring-like muscle at the cardia called the cardiac sphincter which prevents the horse from vomiting.)  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA51; DET48"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"133","question":"What powerful, ring-like muscle closes the opening of the esophagus into the stomach?","answer":"Cardiac sphincter  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA51; HSc28"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"134","question":"The angle at which the esophagus meets the stomach and the powerful sphincter at that junction makes it nearly impossible for FEED to do what?","answer":"Re-enter the esophagus once it's deposited in the stomach  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH705-1; HSc2"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"135","question":"What ring-like muscle regulates the flow of stomach contents into the duodenum?","answer":"Pyloric sphincter (FYI:  The cardiac sphincter regulates flow between the esophagus and the upper part of the stomach.)  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA51"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"136","question":"What SPECIFIC part of the stomach empties into the duodenum?","answer":"Pylorus  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA51; DET224"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"137","question":"What TWO areas of the digestive tract are connected by the pylorus?","answer":"Stomach and small intestine (duodenum)  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA51; DET224"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"138","question":"Food remains in the stomach for about how long before it starts passing into the small intestine?","answer":"15 – 45 minutes (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm405-1; HIH705-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"139","question":"Of the following 3 organs, where does food stay the LEAST amount of time in the digestive system:  stomach, small intestine, or large intestine?","answer":"Stomach (FYI:  stomach 15 – 45 minutes, small intestine 30 – 90 minutes, large intestine 24 – 72 hours)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm405-1; HIH705-2"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"140","question":"Name TWO substances secreted by the stomach.","answer":"Hydrochloric acid, pepsin, gastric lipase (FYI:  Lipase is predominantly secreted by the pancreas.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm405-1; HIH705-1; CAHA51; HSc28"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"141","question":"What acid secreted by the stomach helps digest food?","answer":"Hydrochloric acid (HCl)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm405-1; HIH705-1; CAHA51; HSc28"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"142","question":"Where in the horse's digestive tract is hydrochloric acid secreted?","answer":"Stomach (lining of the stomach)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm405-1; HIH705-1; CAHA51; HSc28"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"143","question":"In what GENERAL part of the horse's digestive tract does water absorption occur?","answer":"Large intestine or hindgut (FYI:  Water absorption starts in the cecum, water is absorbed in the large colon, and the remaining water is absorbed in the small colon where fecal balls are formed.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm405-1,2; HIH705-2,3; HSc30,31; ES112-114"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"jr bonus","number":"144","question":"Name 3 parts of the horse's hindgut.","answer":"Cecum, large colon, small colon, rectum (Do NOT accept small intestine which is part of the foregut.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm405-1; HIH705-2; HSc30"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"145","question":"From cranial to caudal, name the 4 parts of the horse’s HINDGUT.","answer":"Cecum, large colon, small colon, rectum (Do NOT accept small intestine which is part of the foregut.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm405-1; HIH705-2; HSc30"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"146","question":"What is the capacity of the horse’s hindgut or large intestine?","answer":"32 gallons or 128 quarts  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc31"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"147","question":"Why is the cecum sometimes called a \"blind pouch\"?","answer":"Because feed stuffs both enter and exit at the top  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH705-2; HSc31"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"148","question":"What part of the horse's digestive tract functions similar to the rumen in cattle and sheep?","answer":"Cecum  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH705-2"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"149","question":"What part of the digestive system is referred to as a \"blind pouch\"?","answer":"Cecum (FYI:  It's called a blind pouch because feedstuffs both enter and exit at the top.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH705-2; HSc31"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"150","question":"The cecum lies between what TWO parts of the horse's digestive system?","answer":"Small intestine (ileum) and large colon  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm405-1; HIH705-2; HSc31; ES112"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"151","question":"The fiber in hay is digested in what part of the digestive system?","answer":"Hindgut or large intestine (also accept cecum) [FYI: Microbes break down fiber into short-chained volatile fatty acids (VFA’s) which provide up to 80% of the horse’s energy needs.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm405-2; HIH705-2; HSc31; ES112"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"152","question":"2-part question:  Where in the horse’s digestive tract is fiber digested and how is it digested?","answer":"Hindgut or large intestine (also accept cecum); by microbial fermentation (FYI: Microbes break down fiber into short-chained volatile fatty acids (VFA’s) which provide up to 80% of the horse’s energy needs.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm405-2; HIH705-2; HSc31; ES112"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"153","question":"What causes the intestinal or gut sounds that can be heard with a stethoscope pressed to the horse's abdomen?","answer":"Movement of gas or fluids through the intestines (also accept cecal activity) [FYI:  The medical term is borborygmus.]  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA55; HSc31"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"154","question":"What is the capacity of the cecum?","answer":"32 quarts, 8 gallons, or 15% of the digestive tract’s capacity (accept any) [may accept any number between 28 – 32 quarts or 7 – 8 gallons from ES112]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm405-1; HIH705-2; HSc31; ES112"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"155","question":"How long is the cecum?","answer":"4 (four) feet  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm405-1; HIH705-2; HSc31; ES112"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"156","question":"Give ONE reason why the pelvic flexure in the large colon a common site of impaction.","answer":"Tight turn; large colon narrows in diameter (FYI: The pelvic flexure is tight turn between the left ventral colon and the left dorsal colon.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH705-2; HSc31"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"157","question":"What is the capacity of the horse’s large colon?","answer":"80 quarts, 20 gallons, or 38% – 40% of the digestive tract’s capacity (accept any)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm405-2; HIH705-2; HSc31"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"158","question":"Which part of the horse's large intestine or hindgut has the largest capacity?","answer":"Large colon (FYI: The capacity of the large colon is about 80 quarts, 20 gallons, or 38% – 40% of the digestive tract’s capacity.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm405-1; HIH705-2; HSc31"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"159","question":"How long is the large colon?","answer":"10 – 12 feet (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm405-1; HIH705-2; HSc31"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"160","question":"How long is the hindgut or large intestine of the horse?","answer":"25 feet  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc31"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"161","question":"What is the FINAL part of the horse's digestive system?","answer":"Rectum  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm405-1; HIH705-2; HSc31"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"162","question":"What is the length of the small colon?","answer":"10 – 12 feet (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm405-1; HIH705-2; HSc31"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"163","question":"The horse's small colon lies between what TWO other parts of the horse's hindgut?","answer":"Large colon and rectum  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm405-1; HIH705-2; CAHA52; HSc31"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"164","question":"Name TWO things that occur in the small colon.","answer":"Water is absorbed; fecal balls are formed.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH705-1; HSc31"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"165","question":"What is the capacity of the small colon?","answer":"4 gallons, 16 quarts, or 9% of the digestive tract’s capacity (accept any)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm405-1; HIH705-1; HSc31"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"166","question":"Referring to the digestive system, what does VFA mean?","answer":"Volatile fatty acids (FYI:  VFA's are produced by the cellulose-digesting microbes in the horse's hindgut.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH705-2; HSm405-2; HSc30-31"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"167","question":"What is the MEDICAL TERM for the waste matter of digestion?","answer":"Manure or feces (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET105"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"168","question":"What does defecation mean? (pronounced deaf-ee-CAY-shun)","answer":"Pooping (eliminating feces)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET78"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"169","question":"On average, how many TONS of manure does the average 1000-pound horse produce in one year?","answer":"9 tons (also accept 7 – 9 tons from ES114 or 730 cubic feet from HSm245-1)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH365-1; ES114"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"170","question":"The average 1000-pound horse can produce how much manure in one day?","answer":"About 40 pounds (accept any number between 28 – 50 pounds) [FYI: According to Horse Smarts, horses produce about 31 pounds of feces and about 2.4 gallons of urine adding up to about 51 pounds of waste daily.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm245-1; HIH365-1; HSc31; ES114305-2"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"171","question":"What is the medical term for the lining of the abdominal wall?","answer":"Peritoneum (pronounced pair-ih-toe-NEE-um) [FYI: Visceral peritoneum lines the organs and parietal peritoneum lines the abdominal cavity.]  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA56; DET209"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"172","question":"What are commercial preparations of dried beneficial intestinal microorganisms?","answer":"Probiotics [FYI:  Probiotics are also called direct fed microbials (DFM).]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH742-4"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"173","question":"What are probiotics used for?","answer":"To increase the population of beneficial microorganisms in the digestive tract [FYI:  Probiotics are also called direct fed microbials (DFM).]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH742-4"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"174","question":"What is intestinal flora?","answer":"Bacteria normally present in the intestine  <br/> <br/>ref:DET154"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"175","question":"Name 3 important digestive actions of the bacteria and protozoa in the cecum and colon.","answer":"Digest or breakdown fiber, cellulose, or complex carbohydrates (by fermentation); produce volatile fatty acids (VFA’s) that are used for energy; synthesize B vitamins; synthesize Vitamin K; break down protein into amino acids  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm405-2; HIH705"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"176","question":"What is the general term for the bacteria and other microorganisms that normally reside in the large intestine?","answer":"Intestinal flora  <br/> <br/>ref:DET154"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"177","question":"How long does it take food to pass from the mouth to the anus?","answer":"1 ½ – 3 days or 36 – 72 hours (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:ES114"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"178","question":"Which takes MORE time to pass from the horse’s stomach into the small intestine, hay or water?","answer":"Hay (FYI:  Although 75% of the horse’s stomach’s content has emptied in 30 minutes, some dry matter may stay in the stomach up to 12 hours.)  <br/> <br/>ref:ES110"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"179","question":"Describe a non-ruminant digestive system.","answer":"Carbohydrates, proteins, and fats are digested in the foregut (by enzymes) and fiber is digested in the hindgut (by bacterial fermentation). [accept any reasonable wording]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm405-1; HIH705-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"180","question":"Describe a ruminant digestive system.","answer":"Fiber is digested in the rumen, there's enzymatic digestion in foregut, and there's minimal digestion in the hindgut. (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm405-1; HIH705-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"181","question":"Digestively speaking, how is the horse categorized?","answer":"Non-ruminant herbivore  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm405-1; HIH705-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"182","question":"What stimulates the secretion of saliva in the horse?","answer":"Chewing (mastication) [FYI:  Horses produce and swallow 8 – 10 gallons of saliva a day!]  <br/> <br/>ref:ES109; HSc27"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"183","question":"Located beneath the ear, what is the largest of the horse's 3 salivary glands?","answer":"Parotid gland [FYI:  Other salivary glands include sublingual (under the tongue), submaxillary or mandibular (between the jaws), and buccal (in the cheeks).]  <br/> <br/>ref:DET205"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"184","question":"2-part question: Name TWO pairs of the MAIN salivary glands in the horse and give their locations.","answer":"Parotid glands are below the ear; submaxillary (mandibular) glands are between the jaws; sublingual glands are beneath the tongue. (FYI:  Buccal glands are minor salivary glands in the mucous membranes of the cheeks.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET204; DET258; DET41; CAHA44; HSc28"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"185","question":"What is produced by the salivary glands?","answer":"Saliva (spit) [FYI: The parotid, sublingual, and submaxillary (mandibular) are the main salivary glands. There are also buccal (cheek) salivary glands.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH705-1; HSc27,28"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"186","question":"In reference to digestion, name ONE purpose of saliva or spit.","answer":"Saliva moistens food; enzymes in saliva start digesting or breaking down food.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH705-1; HSc28"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"187","question":"What is the COMMON term for the vallate, foliate, and fungiform papillae that are found on the tongue?","answer":"Taste buds  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA50"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"188","question":"What is an enterolith?","answer":"Intestinal stone-like mass (that forms around feeds or foreign objects that’ve been ingested) [FYI:  “Entero” means small intestine and “lith” means stone.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm335-2; HIH435a-2; FCH294; DET93"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"189","question":"What is the mesentery?","answer":"Membranous sheet that connects the small intestines to the abdominal wall (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET179; CAHA56"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"190","question":"What is the name for the wave-like muscular contractions that move food down the digestive tract?","answer":"Peristalsis  <br/> <br/>ref:DET209; HSm505-6; HIH435a-1; HSc28; ES109"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"191","question":"What is peristalsis?","answer":"Wave-like movements that move food through the digestive tract  <br/> <br/>ref:DET209; HSm505-6; HIH435a-1; HSc28; ES109"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"192","question":"Give ONE of the scientific names for the horse’s external ear.","answer":"Auricle; pinna (FYI: Auricles are also outpouchings on the atria in the heart.)  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA43; DET212"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"193","question":"What is a hormone?","answer":"Body-regulating chemical secreted by an endocrine gland into the bloodstream  <br/> <br/>ref:DET143; HIH920-5"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"194","question":"Which body system has glands that produce hormones to regulate growth, reproduction, metabolism, and digestion?","answer":"Endocrine system  <br/> <br/>ref:DET92"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"195","question":"What body system produces chemical substances called hormones?","answer":"Endocrine system  <br/> <br/>ref:DET92"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"196","question":"What is the study of hormones and their effects called?","answer":"Endocrinology  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-5; HSm515-4; DET91"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"197","question":"Name 3 of the horse's body functions that are controlled by the endocrine system.","answer":"Growth; reproduction; lactation; metabolism; digestion; stress response; regulation of blood sugar, blood pressure, pulse, respiration, mood, and sleep cycles; excretion of wastes; fluid and mineral balance; homeostasis (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET92"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"198","question":"What is endocrinology?","answer":"Study of endocrine glands and/or hormones  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-5; HSm515-4; DET91"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"199","question":"Where in the horse's body is epinephrine produced?","answer":"Adrenal gland  <br/> <br/>ref:DET4,98; CAHA5,80"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"200","question":"Adrenaline is a hormone secreted by the central portion of the adrenal gland. Give another name for adrenaline.","answer":"Epinephrine  <br/> <br/>ref:DET4,98; CAHA5,80"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"201","question":"What structure in the brain controls the release of hormones by the pituitary gland?","answer":"Hypothalamus  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH980-1; DET147"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"202","question":"What is the function of insulin?","answer":"Controls blood sugar levels (by storing excess sugars in the liver as glycogen)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET153; CAHA54; HIH785-2; HSc29"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"203","question":"Explain how insulin and glucagon act.","answer":"Insulin moves extra glucose from blood to storage in body; glucagon moves stored glucose back into the blood when needed.  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA54; HSc29"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"204","question":"Insulin controls glucose levels in the horse's body.  Where is insulin produced?","answer":"Pancreas (FYI: in the Islets of Langerhans)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET153; CAHA54; HIH785-2; HSc29"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"205","question":"Name ONE function of the horse's pancreas.","answer":"Secretes insulin (endocrine gland); secretes digestive enzymes (exocrine gland)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET203; CAHA54; HIH705-2; HSm405-1; HSc29"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"206","question":"Which endocrine gland is responsible for the maintenance of calcium levels in the blood?","answer":"Parathyroid gland (also accept thyroid due to the hormone calcitonin)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET204"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"207","question":"Identify this endocrine gland:  increased daylight hours send signals through the optic nerve to this endocrine gland which decreases its production of melatonin; this gland is a pine-cone shaped gland that is attached to the base of the brain.","answer":"Pineal gland (FYI:  This decrease in melatonin signals the hypothalamus to secrete GnRH which causes the pituitary to secrete FSH and LH.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm520-3; HIH920-7,8; HIH980-3; DET212; CAHA77"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"208","question":"Name ONE function of the hormone melatonin.","answer":"Stimulates other hormones to cause the mare to start cycling; stimulates other hormones to cause spermatogenesis in the stallion (also accept helps with sleep)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm520-3; HIH920-7,8; HIH980-3"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"209","question":"Name ONE hormone produced by the pituitary gland.","answer":"Anterior pituitary—Prolactin, FSH, LH, Growth Hormone, TSH, ACTH; posterior pituitary—Oxytocin and Vasopressin  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-6; HSm515-4"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"210","question":"Oxytocin and Vasopressin are hormones secreted by the posterior pituitary.  Name 3 hormones produced by the ANTERIOR pituitary.","answer":"FSH (Follicle Stimulating Hormone), LH (Luteinizing Hormone), Prolactin, TSH (Thyroid Stimulating Hormone or Thyrotropin), ACTH (Adrenocorticotropic Hormone), GH (Growth Hormone)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-6; HSm515-4"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"211","question":"What is the major function of the thyroid gland?","answer":"Controls metabolic rate [FYI:  Thyroid also helps with protein synthesis and regulation of calcium (through the hormone calcitonin).]  <br/> <br/>ref:DET268; HSc36"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"212","question":"What gland controls the metabolic rate?","answer":"Thyroid gland  <br/> <br/>ref:DET268; HSc36"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"213","question":"Give ONE other name for the chin area of a horse.","answer":"Curb groove or chin groove  <br/> <br/>ref:DET55; DET75; HH29-31"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"214","question":"Give ONE name for the area on a horse's head where the curb chain rests.","answer":"Curb groove or chin groove  <br/> <br/>ref:DET55; DET75; HH29-31"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"215","question":"What is located between the forehead and the muzzle?","answer":"Face  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-3; HSm385-8; HH8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"216","question":"What do you call the lock of hair falling forward over the horse’s face?","answer":"Forelock  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA4; DET112; HH39"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"217","question":"What is the horse’s forelock?","answer":"Lock of hair that falls forward over the horse’s face  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA4; DET112; HH39"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"218","question":"What is the horse’s muzzle?","answer":"Area at the end of the head that includes the nose and lips (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-3; HSm385-8; HH8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"219","question":"What is the name of the area at the end of the horse's head that includes the nose and lips?","answer":"Muzzle  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-3; HSm385-8; HH8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"220","question":"What is the name for the top of a horse's head just back of the ears?","answer":"Poll  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-3; HSm385-8; HH8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"221","question":"Where is the horse’s poll?","answer":"Top of the horse’s head just back of the ears  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-3; HSm385-8; HH8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"jr bonus","number":"222","question":"Name 3 PARTS of a horse's front leg below the knee.","answer":"Cannon, fetlock or ankle, pastern, coronet or coronary band, hoof (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-3; HSm385-8; HH8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"223","question":"What part of the horse lies between the knee and the fetlock?","answer":"Cannon  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-3; HSm385-8; HH8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"224","question":"Where is the horse’s cannon?","answer":"Lower leg (bone) between the knee or hock and the fetlock or ankle  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-3; HSm385-8; HH8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"225","question":"Give ONE name for the band that's directly above the horse's hoof.","answer":"Coronet, coronet band, or coronary band  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-3; HSm385-8; DET69"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"226","question":"Where is the coronet band located?","answer":"Hairline above the hoof (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-3; HSm385-8; DET69"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"227","question":"2-part question:  Where is the coronary band and why should handlers  be careful with this area?","answer":"Hairline between the top of the hoof and the bottom of the pastern; because the growth of the hoof starts at the coronary band  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm230-1; DET69; HH8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"228","question":"What is another name for the fetlock joint?","answer":"Ankle  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-3; HSm385-8; HH8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"229","question":"Where is the horse’s fetlock?","answer":"Between the cannon and the pastern (on the front legs and hind legs)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-3; HSm385-8; HH8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"230","question":"What is the name of the joint above the pastern?","answer":"Fetlock or ankle (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-3; HSm385-8; HH8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"231","question":"The forearm of the horse lies between what TWO parts of the horse?","answer":"Elbow and knee (accept any correct answer) [FYI:  The horse’s knee is like our wrist.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-3; HSm385-8; HH8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"232","question":"What part of the horse is located between the elbow and the knee?","answer":"Forearm  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-3; HSm385-8; HH8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"233","question":"The elbow, knee, and fetlock are all joints on which leg?","answer":"Front leg (FYI: The 6 joints on the front leg are shoulder, elbow, knee, fetlock, pastern, and coffin joint.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-3; HSm385-8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"234","question":"Name the 6 main joints of the foreleg from proximal to distal.","answer":"Shoulder, elbow, knee, fetlock, pastern, and coffin  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA14"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"jr bonus","number":"235","question":"Name 3 joints on the front leg.","answer":"Shoulder, elbow, knee, fetlock, pastern, coffin  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-3; HSm385-8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"236","question":"Where is the horse’s elbow?","answer":"Between the horse’s arm and forearm (also accept between the horse’s shoulder and knee) [FYI:  The elbow is on the horse’s front leg.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-3; HSm385-8; HH8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"237","question":"What JOINT is located between the shoulder and the knee?","answer":"Elbow (FYI:  A joint is where two or more bones meet.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-3; HSm385-8; HH8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"238","question":"What joint is located between the elbow and the fetlock?","answer":"Knee (carpus) [FYI:  The horse’s knee is like our wrist.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-3; HSm385-8; HH8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"239","question":"Where is the horse’s knee?","answer":"On the front leg between the forearm and the cannon (or between the elbow and the fetlock)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-3; HSm385-8; HH8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"240","question":"Give the SCIENTIFIC names for 3 of the following joints on the FRONT leg:  coffin, pastern, fetlock, and knee","answer":"Coffin is the distal interphalangeal joint, pastern is the proximal interphalangeal joint, fetlock is the metacarpophalangeal joint, and knee is the carpus.  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA14"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"241","question":"What is the main role or purpose of the hindquarters?","answer":"Propulsion  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc11"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"242","question":"Which muscle helps to pull the hind leg forward and to enable propulsion giving the horse a long, powerful stride?","answer":"Gaskin  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-3; HSm385-8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"243","question":"What is the name of the muscular part of the hind leg above the hock?","answer":"Gaskin  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-3; HSm385-8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"244","question":"What is the horse’s gaskin?","answer":"Muscular part of the hind leg between the stifle and the hock  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-3; HSm385-8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"245","question":"The stifle, hock, and fetlock are all joints on which leg?","answer":"Hind leg (FYI: The 7 joints of the hind leg are sacroiliac, hip, stifle, hock, fetlock, pastern, and coffin joint.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-3; HSm385-8; HH8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"246","question":"Do the front or the hind legs have the most joints?","answer":"Hind legs (FYI: Hind legs have 7 joints; front legs have 6 joints.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-2; CAH14; CAH28-32"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"247","question":"Name 6 joints of the hind leg.","answer":"Sacroiliac, hip, stifle, hock, fetlock, pastern, and coffin  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-2; CAHA28-32"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"jr bonus","number":"248","question":"Name 3 joints on the hind leg.","answer":"Sacroiliac, hip, stifle, hock, fetlock, pastern, coffin  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-3; HSm385-8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"249","question":"What JOINT is located between the stifle and the fetlock?","answer":"Hock  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-3; HSm385-8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"250","question":"What is the name of the pointed area on the hind leg between the gaskin and the cannon?","answer":"Hock (FYI:  The hock is like our ankle.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-3; HSm385-8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"251","question":"Where is the horse’s hock?","answer":"On the hind leg between the gaskin and the cannon  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-3; HSm385-8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"252","question":"Give the SCIENTIFIC names for 3 of the following joints on the HIND leg:  coffin, pastern, fetlock, and hock.","answer":"Coffin is the distal interphalangeal joint, pastern is the proximal interphalangeal joint, fetlock is the metatarsophalangeal joint, and hock is the tarsus.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-2; CAHA28-32"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"253","question":"Where is the horse’s stifle?","answer":"On the hind leg between the thigh and the gaskin (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-3; HSm385-8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"254","question":"What JOINT is located between the hip and the hock?","answer":"Stifle  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-3; HSm385-8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"255","question":"What part of the horse is located directly above the stifle?","answer":"Thigh (FYI:  The horse's stifle is like our knee.)  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA1; HSc8,11"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"256","question":"What part of the horse is located between the coronet and the ground?","answer":"Hoof  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-3; HSm385-8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"257","question":"What is the name of the curved covering of horn over the foot?","answer":"Hoof  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-3; HSm385-8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"258","question":"2-part question:  How many pasterns does a horse have and what is the best angle?","answer":"4 pasterns; 45 – 50 degree angle (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-5"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"259","question":"Where is the horse’s pastern?","answer":"Between the coronet band and the fetlock (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-3; HSm385-8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"260","question":"What part of the horse is between the fetlock and the coronet band?","answer":"Pastern  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-3; HSm385-8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"261","question":"What is the name for the curved, upper part of the horse's neck?","answer":"Crest  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA1; HH9"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"262","question":"On a horse, what is the crest?","answer":"Part of the neck under the mane, the top line of the neck, or the curved upper part of the neck (accept any)  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA1; HH9"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"263","question":"Where is the throatlatch on a horse located?","answer":"Between the jawbone and the neck (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-3; HSm385-8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"264","question":"On a horse, what is the distinct space between the jawbone and the neck?","answer":"Throatlatch  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-3; HSm385-8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"265","question":"Together, the withers, back, loin, and croup make up what?","answer":"Top line  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-5"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"jr bonus","number":"266","question":"Name 4 parts of the horse's topline.","answer":"Poll, crest, withers, back, loin or coupling, and croup or rump  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"267","question":"Name the 6 parts of the horse's topline.","answer":"Poll, crest, withers, back, loin or coupling, and croup or rump  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"268","question":"What part of the horse's top line is between the withers and the loin?","answer":"Back  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-5"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"269","question":"Where is the horse’s back?","answer":"Between the withers and the loin or coupling  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-3; HSm385-8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"270","question":"Give TWO names for the area of the horse between the loin and the buttock.","answer":"Croup and rump  <br/> <br/>ref:HH9"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"271","question":"Give ONE name for the part of the horse's top line that is just in front of the tail.","answer":"Croup or rump  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-3; HSm385-8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"272","question":"Where is the croup of the horse?","answer":"Part of the top line just in front of the tail; the area between the loin or coupling and the dock of the tail (accept any)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-3; HSm385-8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"273","question":"What is the dock of the horse's tail?","answer":"Bony part or base of the tail  <br/> <br/>ref:DET83; DET262"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"274","question":"What is the base or the bony part of the horse’s tail called?","answer":"Dock or tail head (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET83; DET262"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"275","question":"Where is the horse’s loin or coupling?","answer":"Between the back and the croup or rump  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-6; HSm385-8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"276","question":"What part of the horse's top line is located between the back and the croup?","answer":"Loin or coupling (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-6; HSm385-8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"277","question":"What are the horse’s withers?","answer":"Pointy area between the neck and the back  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-3,6; HSm385-8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"278","question":"What part of the horse's top line lies between the neck and the back?","answer":"Withers  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-3,6; HSm385-8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"279","question":"What part of the horse is important in keeping the saddle in place?","answer":"Withers  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-3,6; HSm385-8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"280","question":"What is the name for the rounded trunk area of the horse?","answer":"Barrel  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-3; HSm385-8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"281","question":"What is the horse’s barrel?","answer":"Rounded trunk or belly area  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-3; HSm385-8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"282","question":"Where is the horse known for being ticklish?","answer":"Flank  <br/> <br/>ref:DET109; HIH1220-2"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"283","question":"Where is the horse’s heart girth?","answer":"Belly area directly behind the front legs; measurement around the body just back of the withers (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm155-1; HIH220-3; HIH775-2; DET120; HH27; PNW157"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"284","question":"What is the term for the measurement around the horse's body just back of the withers?","answer":"Girth or heart girth (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm155-1; HIH220-3; HIH775-2; DET120; HH27; PNW157"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"285","question":"The cornea, sclera, lens, iris, and retina are all parts of what?","answer":"Eye  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH465-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"286","question":"What is the fluid-filled space between the iris and the cornea?","answer":"Anterior chamber (FYI: The anterior chamber contains aqueous humor.)  <br/> <br/>ref:ES214; CAHA11"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"287","question":"What is the name of the substance in the anterior chamber of the eye?","answer":"Aqueous humor  <br/> <br/>ref:ES214"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"288","question":"What color are MOST horses' eyes?","answer":"Brown  <br/> <br/>ref:HH7"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"289","question":"Describe a \"glass eye\" in a horse.","answer":"Eye (iris) is clear, white or blue.  <br/> <br/>ref:HH7; DET122; DET287"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"290","question":"What term is used for a horse's eye that has a blue or light-colored iris?","answer":"Glass eye (also accept wall eye)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH7; DET122; DET287"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"291","question":"In a wall-eyed horse, which SPECIFIC structure of the eye is light blue or hazel in color?","answer":"Iris  <br/> <br/>ref:HH7; DET287"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"292","question":"In horses, what does the term \"glass eye\" mean?","answer":"Iris of the eye is clear, white, or blue.  <br/> <br/>ref:HH7; DET122"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"293","question":"What is the term for the membrane that lines the inside of the eyelid?","answer":"Conjunctiva (pronounced con-junk-TIE-va)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET67"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"294","question":"What is the FIRST structure that light entering the horse's eye would pass through?","answer":"Cornea  <br/> <br/>ref:DET69; DET102"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"295","question":"What is the name for the outer protective layer of the horse's eye?","answer":"Cornea  <br/> <br/>ref:DET69; DET102"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"296","question":"When fluorescein dye is applied to the surface of the eye, it will indicate any damaged areas of what structure of the eye? (pronounced FLOOR-eh-scene)","answer":"Cornea  <br/> <br/>ref:DET110"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"297","question":"Name TWO clear or translucent structures that light must pass through to reach the retina in the horse's eye.","answer":"Cornea and lens  <br/> <br/>ref:DET69; DET102; DET167"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"298","question":"Name ONE part of the eye that allows light to pass through to the lens.","answer":"Cornea; pupil  <br/> <br/>ref:DET69; DET102; DET223"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"299","question":"Name ONE structure that protects the horse’s eye.","answer":"Eyelids; eyelashes; bony eye socket (orbital cavity); haw, 3rd eyelid or nictitating membrane; feeler or tactile hairs (FYI:  With the “menace reflex”, an animal closes its eyelids to protect the eye.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH465-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"300","question":"Give ONE function of a horse's third eyelid.","answer":"Cleans the eye, removes foreign bodies, prevents foreign bodies from getting into the eye, protects the eye from trauma, keeps the eye moist (by spreading the tear film over the eye)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH465-1; HSm340-1; DET130; HSc4"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"301","question":"Give TWO purposes of the nictitating membrane.","answer":"Cleans the eye, removes foreign bodies, prevents foreign bodies from getting into the eye, protects the eye from trauma, keeps the eye moist (by spreading the tear film over the eye)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH465-1; HSm340-1; DET130; HSc4"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"302","question":"What is the COMMON name for the membrane that helps remove foreign materials from the eye?   It's also called the third eyelid or nictitating membrane.","answer":"Haw  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH465-1; HSm340-1; DET130; HSc4"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"303","question":"This membrane in front of the eye removes foreign bodies.  Give ONE other term for the horse’s third eyelid.","answer":"Haw or nictitating membrane  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH465-1; HSm340-1; DET130; HSc4"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"304","question":"In connection with the eye, what does the term \"haw\" mean?","answer":"Third eyelid or nictitating membrane  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH465-1; HSm340-1; DET130; HSc4"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"305","question":"What gland secretes tears?","answer":"Lacrimal gland  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA5"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"306","question":"The tear film is necessary for the health of the cornea.  Name TWO things the tear film does for the cornea.","answer":"Supplies nutrition, moisture, oxygen to the cornea, important components of the immune system  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH465-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"307","question":"What is the COMMON term for the fluid that's produced by the lacrimal glands, collects in the medial canthus, and flows down the nasolacrimal duct?","answer":"Tears (FYI:  Medical term is lacrimal fluid.)  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA45"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"308","question":"The horse's eye is lubricated or moistened by what fluid?","answer":"Tears (FYI: Medical term is lacrimal fluid.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH465-2; CAHA45"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"309","question":"In the horse's eye, focused light rays which form the image on the retina are transmitted to the brain by what nerve?","answer":"Optic nerve (2nd cranial nerve)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH465-1; HSm520-3; DET196; CAHA78"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"310","question":"Research indicates that horses do see in color.  However, they may have more difficulty seeing which color?","answer":"Red  <br/> <br/>ref:ES60"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"311","question":"In the horse's eye, there are cells known as rods and cones.  Which of these is responsible for day and color vision?","answer":"Cones  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH465-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"312","question":"In the horse's eye, there are cells known as rods and cones.  Which of these is responsible for low light vision and motion detection?","answer":"Rods  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH465-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"313","question":"2-part question:  In the horse's eye, there are TWO main photoreceptor cell types.  What are they called and what type of vision is each used for?","answer":"Rods are used for low light vision and motion detection; cones are used for day and color vision.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH465-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"314","question":"What is the term for the opening in the iris of a horse's eye?","answer":"Pupil  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH465-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"315","question":"2-part question:  How is the shape of the horse's pupil different in comparison to other mammals and how does the shape of the pupil benefit the horse?","answer":"Pupil is more horizontal; its shape enables the horse to see predators more easily (by increasing their visual field).  <br/> <br/>ref:ES56"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"316","question":"The lens focuses light rays to form an image on what structure?","answer":"Retina  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH465-1; DET167"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"317","question":"Name 3 of the horse's body fluids.","answer":"Feces, urine, tears, sweat, saliva, blood, semen, breast milk, mucus, bile, cerebrospinal fluid, amniotic fluid, lymph (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-2; HIH425-2"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"318","question":"The body of an adult horse is approximately what percent water?","answer":"60% – 75% (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH710-1 (more than 60%); ES115 (65-75%); HSc32 (65-75%)"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"319","question":"Name 3 functions of the horse's skin.","answer":"Protection, sensation, thermoregulation, controls water loss, absorption (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm355-1; CAHA5.5"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"320","question":"The integumentary system refers to what part of the body?","answer":"Skin  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm355-1; DET153"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"321","question":"What is the name for a horny growth on the inside of the horse’s leg?  This term is also used to describe a coat color.","answer":"Chestnut  <br/> <br/>ref:DET55; CAHA4; HH8; ES20"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"322","question":"Night eyes are another name for what structures on the horse?","answer":"Chestnuts  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA4; HH8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"323","question":"Give ONE term for the horny growths on the insides of horses' legs.","answer":"Chestnuts or night eyes  <br/> <br/>ref:DET55; CAHA4; HH8; ES20"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"324","question":"What are chestnuts?","answer":"Horny growths on the inside of a horse's legs (above the knees and at the lower part of the hocks)  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA5; HH8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"325","question":"What is another name for the chestnuts on a horse’s leg?","answer":"Night eyes  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA4; HH8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"326","question":"What do a horse's chestnuts and a human's fingerprints have in common?","answer":"Both have unique patterns that can be used to identify individuals  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA4"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"327","question":"What part of the horse has a distinctive pattern that can be used to positively identify a particular horse?","answer":"Chestnuts  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA4"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"328","question":"Being specific, where are chestnuts located on a horse?","answer":"Front legs on the inside surface above the knees; hind legs on the inside surface at the bottom of the hocks  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA4"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"329","question":"2-part question:  How many chestnuts do donkeys have and where are they located?","answer":"2 (two); on the insides of the front legs only  <br/> <br/>ref:ES21"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"330","question":"What is the name of the structural protein in the extracellular space of connective tissues that forms the basic framework of body tissues and gives the skin elasticity?","answer":"Collagen  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm355-1; CAHA5; DET61"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"331","question":"What is the term for the horny growth found at the back of the fetlock?","answer":"Ergot  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA4; HH9"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"332","question":"What is an ergot?","answer":"Horny growth at the back of the fetlock  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA4; HH9"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"333","question":"What is the name of the layers of loose, dense fibrous connective tissue that's found superficially under the skin and deep covering the muscles?","answer":"Fascia  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA15; DET104"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"334","question":"2-part question:  For a horse, what is the first line of defense against the cold and what is the second line of defense?","answer":"First line of defense is the hair coat; second line of defense if fat (which provides insulation).  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH188"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"335","question":"What causes horses to grow their winter coats?","answer":"Shorter length of daylight  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-6; HIH420-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"336","question":"How does a horse's coat keep him warm in the winter?","answer":"Traps heat between the hair fibers  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-6; HIH420-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"337","question":"Name ONE part of the horse where cowlicks or whorls occur.","answer":"Face, head, neck, throatlatch, flank (FYI:  On solid-colored horses such as Friesians, whorls can be used as an identifying marking.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-9; DET293"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"338","question":"Why do horses have hair in their ears?","answer":"To prevent dirt or insects from entering the ears  <br/> <br/>ref:HH39"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"339","question":"What is the term for the light-colored hairs seen along the mane and at the base of the tail on dun-colored horses such as Fjords?","answer":"Guard hairs (FYI:  The appearance of light-colored guard hairs along a dark mane and tail are sometimes called “frosting”.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH154B-1; HSm105-9; HSm110-6"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"340","question":"Name TWO locations on the horse where tactile hairs are found.","answer":"Around the eyes, nostrils, lips, muzzle (FYI: Tactile hairs are also called vibrissae.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-2; HIH465-1; CAHA4; DET262; HH39"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"341","question":"What are the horse’s “whiskers” or tactile hairs?","answer":"Coarse \"feeler\" hairs around the muzzle and eyes (FYI: Tactile hairs are also called vibrissae.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-2; HIH465-1; CAHA4; DET262; HH39"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"342","question":"What is the purpose of the long feeler hairs around the muzzle?","answer":"Help the horse make contact with its surroundings (especially in the dark) [FYI: The long “feeler” hairs are called tactile hairs or vibrissae.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-2; HIH465-1; CAHA4; DET262; HH39"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"343","question":"What is the scientific name for the “whiskers” or coarse “feeler hairs” that protrude from around the nostrils, lips, and eyelids?","answer":"Tactile hairs (FYI:  Tactile hairs are also called vibrissae.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-2; HIH465-1; CAHA4; DET262; HH39"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"344","question":"What is a tufted tail?","answer":"Tail that has short hair (somewhat like a cow) towards the top with a tuft of longer hair beginning about halfway down the tail  <br/> <br/>ref:ES22"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"345","question":"What is the outermost layer of skin?","answer":"Epidermis  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm355-1; CAHA5; DET97"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"346","question":"Name TWO layers of the horse's skin.","answer":"Epidermis; dermis; subcutis, hypodermis, or subcutaneous tissue  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm355-1; CAHA5; ES214; DET97; DET79; DET258"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"347","question":"2-part question:  Describe the location and function of the sebaceous glands.","answer":"Located at the base of the hair follicles (in the dermis); produce sebum (which is an oily, waxy substance that protects and insulates the skin)  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA5; DET241; ES214"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"348","question":"Where are each of the 3 following serous membranes found in the horse:  pleura, peritoneum, and pericardium?","answer":"Pleura covers the lungs and lines the thoracic cavity, peritoneum covers the abdominal organs and lines the abdominal cavity, and pericardium is the outer lining of the heart.  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA56, 76; DET214; DET209; DET208"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"349","question":"Where on the horse are there NO sweat glands?","answer":"Legs  <br/> <br/>ref:DET260"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"350","question":"What is the COMMON name for the apocrine tubular glands of the horse?","answer":"Sweat glands  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA5"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"351","question":"Name 3 parts of the horse's body that belong to the immune system.","answer":"Lymph nodes, lymph vessels, spleen, bone marrow, thymus  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA63,64"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"352","question":"What are the filters found in the horse's body that remove bacteria, cancer cells, and foreign materials from circulation?  They are connected to the vascular system by the thoracic duct.","answer":"Lymph nodes  <br/> <br/>ref:DET173; CAHA64"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"353","question":"What organ in the thoracic cavity that produces lymphocytes is at its largest in the 6 - 8 week old foal and it decreases in size with age becoming difficult to find in older horses?","answer":"Thymus  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA63"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"354","question":"What is the largest TISSUE MASS in a horse’s body?","answer":"Muscles  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH840-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"355","question":"During exercise, body heat is primarily produced by what system?","answer":"Muscular system  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH199"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"356","question":"What provides the energy for muscle contraction?","answer":"ATP (adenosine triphosphate)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm360-1; HIH840-2"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"357","question":"When a horse’s muscle shortens, is the muscle contracting or relaxing?","answer":"Contracting  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH840-1; HSm380-5"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"358","question":"When a horse’s muscle lengthens, is the muscle contracting or relaxing?","answer":"Relaxing  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH840-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"359","question":"What is the basic contractile unit of skeletal muscles?","answer":"Sarcomere  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH840-1; HSm380-5"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"jr bonus","number":"360","question":"Name 3 things that cause shivering in a horse.","answer":"Cold, fear, excitement, illness, pain, fever (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH403; HSm360-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"361","question":"Where are the intercostal muscles located?","answer":"Between the ribs  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH895-1; DET153"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"362","question":"Which muscles expand the chest during inspiration?","answer":"Diaphragm and intercostal muscles  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-4; HIH810-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"363","question":"What is the name of the muscles located between the ribs that are involved in respiration?","answer":"Intercostal muscles  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH895-1; DET153"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"364","question":"What is the name of the WIDEST muscle in the horse's body?","answer":"Latissimus dorsi (FYI: Longissimus dorsi is the longest muscle.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm360-19; ES204"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"365","question":"2-part question:  Name and give the function of the large muscle located on either side of the face that sits beneath the ears and covers the mandible.","answer":"Masseter muscle; used for chewing (opens and closes the jaw)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm360-19; HSm340-1; HSm360-3; HIH680-1; DET176"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"366","question":"2-part question:  Where is the panniculus muscle and what is its function?","answer":"Muscle under the skin; enables the horse to flick flies off its skin.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm360-19; HSm340-1; HSm360-3; HIH680-1; DET176"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"367","question":"What muscle lies under the horse's skin and enables the skin to twitch and shake flies off the body?","answer":"Panniculus (also accept cutaneous trunci HSm355-2) (FYI:  The panniculus reflex or response is the twitching of the skin in response to gentle stimulation such as a fly landing on the horse.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm360-1; DET203"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"368","question":"Where is the trapezius muscle located in the horse?","answer":"On each side of the withers (FYI:  There are cervical and thoracic trapezius muscles.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm360-3; CAHA16; ES204"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"369","question":"Muscles that work together to accomplish a movement are called synergists.  What is the term for muscles that oppose each other and limit movement?","answer":"Antagonists  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm360-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"370","question":"The muscles that control leg movement end where?","answer":"At the knees and hocks (FYI:  Tendons control leg movement below the knees and hocks.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm360-19 (pic); CAHA16 (pic); CAHA19 (pic); HSc9"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"371","question":"The forces exerted by muscles in the foreleg are transmitted by tendons.  Generally, muscles are NOT found below what joint of the foreleg?","answer":"Knee (carpus)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm360-19 (pic); CAHA16 (pic); CAHA19 (pic); HSc9"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"372","question":"Muscles are attached to bones by what?","answer":"Tendons  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-1; DET264"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"373","question":"What tendon is responsible for the extension of the horse's toe and hoof?","answer":"Digital extensor tendon (extensor tendon)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH48; DET81; DET101; HSm360-3"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"374","question":"What is the purpose of the digital extensor tendon?","answer":"Extends (or straightens) the hoof and leg  <br/> <br/>ref:HH48; DET81; DET101; HSm360-3"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"375","question":"What is the purpose of the deep digital flexor tendon?","answer":"Flexes (or bends) the hoof and leg  <br/> <br/>ref:HH48; DET78; DET110; HSm360-3"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"376","question":"What tendon connects the deep muscles of the back of the leg to the coffin bone?","answer":"Deep digital flexor tendon (also accept deep flexor tendon)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH48; DET78; DET110; HSm360-3"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"377","question":"The navicular bone and bursa are associated with which tendon?","answer":"Deep digital flexor tendon (also accept deep flexor tendon)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm375-9; HIH455-2; CAHA27"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"378","question":"Name the 3 types of muscles found in a horse's body.","answer":"Smooth, cardiac, and skeletal  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm360-1; HIH840-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"379","question":"Name 4 types of skeletal muscles.","answer":"Type 1, Type 2A, Type 2B, and Type 2C (FYI:  Type 1 is slow twitch and types 2A, B, and C are fast twitch.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-5; HIH840-2,3"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"380","question":"Which GENERAL type of skeletal muscle is used for long-term, non-strenuous work and provides endurance?","answer":"Slow oxidative, slow twitch, or Type 1 (accept any)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-5; HIH840-2"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"381","question":"Give 3 characteristics of Type 1 skeletal muscle fibers.","answer":"Slow twitch (slow contracting), low glycolytic activity (low ability to oxidize glucose or glycogen rapidly), resistant to fatigue, use fuels aerobically, provide endurance, used for long-term non-strenuous work  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm360-1; HSm380-5; HIH840-2"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"382","question":"Which of the following breeds has the largest number of slow twitch muscles–Arabian, Thoroughbred, or Quarter Horse?","answer":"Arabian  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm360-2; HSm380-5"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"383","question":"Which GENERAL type of skeletal muscle is used for activities that require high levels of strength or force production over a short period of time?  This type of skeletal muscle is fatigues easily.","answer":"Fast glycolytic, fast twitch, or Type 2 (accept any) [FYI:  Fast twitch muscles are divided into Type 2A, Type 2B, and Type 2C.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm360-2; HSm380-5"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"384","question":"2-part question:  Name the 3 subtypes of type 2 muscle fibers and explain their uses.","answer":"Type 2A—speed at intermediate distances; Type 2B—quick bursts of speed for short distances; Type 2C—training can recruit them to either type 2A or type 2B  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH840-3"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"385","question":"Which of the following breeds has the largest number of type 2A muscles–Arabian, Thoroughbred, or Quarter Horse?","answer":"Thoroughbred  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-5; HIH850-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"386","question":"Which of the following breeds has the largest number of type 2B muscles–Arabian, Thoroughbred, or Quarter Horse?","answer":"Quarter Horse  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-5; HIH850-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"387","question":"Type 2B muscles are used for what?","answer":"Quick bursts of speed for short distances  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-5; HIH840-3"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"388","question":"Name 3 systems in the horse's body that use smooth muscles.","answer":"Digestive system, circulatory or cardiovascular system, respiratory system, reproductive system, and urinary system  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH840-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"389","question":"Name 3 locations in the horse's body where muscles with involuntary control are found.","answer":"Digestive system, circulatory or cardiovascular system, respiratory system, reproductive system, and urinary system  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH840-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"390","question":"2-part question:  The muscles of a horse's body are classified as smooth, cardiac, and skeletal.  Which are voluntary and which are involuntary?","answer":"Skeletal muscles are voluntary; smooth and cardiac muscles are involuntary.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH840-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"391","question":"Are skeletal muscles voluntary or involuntary?","answer":"Voluntary (FYI:  Smooth muscles and cardiac muscles are involuntary.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH840-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"392","question":"What system in the horse's body includes the brain, spinal cord, and nerves?","answer":"Nervous system  <br/> <br/>ref:DET53; ES212"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"393","question":"Name TWO parts of the central nervous system.","answer":"Brain; spinal cord (CORRECTED 2021)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET53; ES212"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"394","question":"What part of the brain controls basic body functions such as respiration and heart rate?","answer":"Brainstem (FYI:  In humans, the brainstem includes the midbrain, the pons, and the medulla oblongata)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET37"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"395","question":"Which part of the brain controls the coordination of movement?","answer":"Cerebellum  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm505-5; DET53"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"396","question":"Where is the hypothalamus located?","answer":"Base of the brain  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-5; CAHA77; DET147"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"397","question":"Where is the pituitary gland located?","answer":"Base of the brain  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-6; CAHA77; DET213"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"398","question":"The central nervous system consists of the brain and the spinal cord.  What does the peripheral nervous system consist of?","answer":"Nerves that branch off the brain and spinal cord (such as cranial, spinal, and peripheral nerves)  <br/> <br/>ref:ES212; DET209"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"399","question":"The autonomic nervous system regulates many of the internal operations of the body and also regulates unconscious responses to external stimuli.  What are the TWO divisions of the autonomic nervous system?","answer":"Sympathetic and parasympathetic (FYI: Sympathetic is the \"fight or flight\" part and parasympathetic is the \"breed and feed\" part.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET18; CAHA80; ES212"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"400","question":"Name 3 cranial nerves.","answer":"I. Olfactory, II. optic, III. oculomotor, IV. trochlear, V. trigeminal, VI.  abducens, VII. facial, VIII. vestibulocochlear, IX. glossopharyngeal, X.  vagus, XI. accessory, XII. Hypoglossal  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA78"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"401","question":"To what structure does the 12th cranial nerve—the hypoglossal nerve—provide motor control?","answer":"Tongue  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA47,78"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"402","question":"What cranial nerve provides the horse with a sense of smell?","answer":"Olfactory nerve (1st cranial nerve)  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA78"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"403","question":"What type of nerves transmit sensations of pressure, pain, heat, and cold from the nerve endings?","answer":"Sensory nerves  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA5"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"404","question":"The sense of taste in the horse is similar to that of humans.  Name 4 tastes horses are capable of sensing.","answer":"Bitter, sweet, sour, and salty  <br/> <br/>ref:ES67"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"jr bonus","number":"405","question":"The sense of taste in the horse is similar to that of humans.  Name 3 tastes horses are capable of sensing.","answer":"Bitter, sweet, sour, and salty  <br/> <br/>ref:ES67"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"407","question":"What is the name of the tiny air sacs in the lungs where oxygen and carbon dioxide are exchanged?","answer":"Alveoli (pronounced al-VEE-oh-lie)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH810-1; HIH895-1; CAHA57; DET7"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"408","question":"What is the name of the muscle that separates the abdominal and thoracic cavities?","answer":"Diaphragm  <br/> <br/>ref:DET80"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"409","question":"What is the name of the cartilaginous flap that prevents food or water from entering the larynx?","answer":"Epiglottis  <br/> <br/>ref:DET97; CAHA50"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"410","question":"What is the function of the epiglottis?","answer":"Prevents food or water from entering the respiratory system (larynx and trachea).  <br/> <br/>ref:DET97; CAHA50"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"411","question":"What structure equalizes air pressure in the ear?","answer":"Eustachian tube (pronounced you-STAY-shun)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET100"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"412","question":"In the gallop, when does the horse exhale?","answer":"When the front legs touch the ground (FYI:  At the gallop, respiratory rate and stride rate are in a one to one (1:1) ratio.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH810-2"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"414","question":"What is the PRIMARY purpose of the respiratory system?","answer":"To oxygenate blood (FYI:  Other functions are phonation or vocalization, temperature regulation, prevention of foreign bodies from entering the respiratory tract, and smelling or olfaction.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH810-1; DET233"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"415","question":"Name ONE gas that is exhaled when breathing.","answer":"Carbon dioxide, oxygen, nitrogen  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH810-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"416","question":"What anatomical structure of the horse is described as a diverticulum of the auditory tube?","answer":"Guttural pouch (FYI:  Guttural pouches can get infected and can get abnormal quantities of air or \"tympany\".)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET126; CAHAvii,46"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"417","question":"Name 3 functions of the larynx.","answer":"Controls air flow (regulates the amount of air entering the trachea); protects the airway (prevents foreign material from entering the trachea); phonation (vocalization)  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA66; HIH810-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"418","question":"Why is it important for a horse to have large nostrils?","answer":"So it can breathe better (FYI:  Horses are obligate nasal breathers which means they can only breathe through their noses.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-4; HSc9"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"419","question":"What is an obligate nasal breather?","answer":"Animal that breathes only through the nose (animal that can't breathe through the mouth).  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH705-1; HSc9"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"420","question":"Why can’t a horse breath through its mouth?","answer":"Blocking action of the soft palate (FYI:  During inspiration, the pharynx and the soft palate form a smooth passage for air flow into the trachea.  During swallowing, they move so that food is directed into the esophagus.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH810-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"421","question":"Explain how the pharynx functions within the RESPIRATORY tract.","answer":"Connects the nasal passages to the trachea or windpipe (FYI:  During inspiration, the pharynx and the soft palate form a smooth passage for air flow into the trachea.  During swallowing, they move so that food is directed into the esophagus.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET210; HIH810-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"422","question":"At a gallop, respiration rate and stride rate are almost always coupled in what ratio?","answer":"1 : 1 (one to one)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-4; HIH810-2"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"423","question":"What is respiratory frequency?","answer":"Number of breaths taken per minute (FYI:  It’s also called the respiratory rate.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-4; HIH810-1; HIH895-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"424","question":"What is the MEDICAL name for the windpipe?","answer":"Trachea  <br/> <br/>ref:DET272"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"425","question":"What is the COMMON name for the trachea?","answer":"Windpipe  <br/> <br/>ref:DET272"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"426","question":"What is the term for the amount of air inspired in ONE MINUTE?","answer":"Minute volume  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-4; HIH810-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"427","question":"If the horse increases its movement, does the minute volume go up or down?","answer":"Up (FYI: Minute volume is the amount of air inspired in one minute; minute volume = tidal volume x respiratory rate.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-4; HIH810-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"428","question":"In measuring respiratory capabilities of the horse, tidal volume and respiratory rate are used to determine what respiratory parameter?","answer":"Minute volume (FYI:  Minute volume is the total amount of air inspired or expired in one minute.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-4; HIH810-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"429","question":"What is the term for the total amount of air inspired in one breath?","answer":"Tidal volume  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-4; HIH810-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"430","question":"Name TWO components of the skeletal system.","answer":"Bones, ligaments, tendons, cartilage  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"431","question":"What is the name of the structure that protects the vital organs such as the brain, heart, and lungs?","answer":"Skeleton  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-1; DET246; CAHA6"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"jr bonus","number":"432","question":"Name 3 functions of a horse's skeleton.","answer":"Provides framework, protects internal organs, locomotion or movement, stores minerals, produces blood cells (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-1; DET246"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"433","question":"Name 4 functions of a horse's skeleton.","answer":"Provides framework, protects internal organs, locomotion or movement, stores minerals, produces blood cells (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-1; DET246"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"434","question":"How many bones are in the horse's body?","answer":"205 (FYI:  There are 54 bones in the spine, 36 ribs, 34 bones in the skull, 80 bones in the legs, and 1 sternal or breastbone.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-1; DET246; CAHA6"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"435","question":"At what age do horse’s skeletons usually reach full maturity?","answer":"4 years of age or older  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH851-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"436","question":"What is the anatomical name for a natural passageway or opening in the body that blood vessels and nerves pass through?","answer":"Foramen (pronounced fore-AY-men)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET111; CAHA41"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"437","question":"2-part question:  What do the terms fossa and tuberosity mean when used to describe bones?","answer":"Fossa is a hollow or depressed area; tuberosity is a prominence or projection.  <br/> <br/>ref:DET113"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"438","question":"What does interosseous mean? (pronounced in-ter-AH-see-us)","answer":"Between bones  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA10; DET154"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"439","question":"Name ONE place in the horse's skeleton where an interosseous ligament is found.","answer":"Between the radius and ulna; between the cannon and splint bones  <br/> <br/>ref:DET154; CAHA14; HIH455-6; HSm345-7"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"440","question":"Where on a long bone would the periosteum NOT be found? (pronounced pair-ee-AH-stee-um)","answer":"At the ends, points of articulation, or epiphyses (accept any)  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA9; HSm345-7; HIH455-6"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"441","question":"2-part question:  What is the periosteum and what does it do?","answer":"Bone-producing membrane that covers the bones (except at the ends); it protects the bone and is a site of healing.  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA9; HSm345-7; HIH455-6"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"442","question":"What structure begins the healing process when a bone fracture occurs?","answer":"Periosteum (pronounced pair-ih-AHS-tee-um)  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA9; HSm345-7; HIH455-6"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"443","question":"What is the name of the membrane that covers non-articulating surfaces of bone?","answer":"Periosteum (pronounced pair-ih-AHS-tee-um)  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA9; HSm345-7; HIH455-6"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"444","question":"Which breed often has 17 pairs of ribs (instead of 18) and 5 lumbar vertebrae (instead of 6)?","answer":"Arabian  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"445","question":"Name 3 classifications of bones.","answer":"Long, short, flat, irregular, sesamoid  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-1; DET34"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"446","question":"Which type bones enclose the body cavities containing vital organs and provide large areas for muscle attachment?","answer":"Flat bones (FYI:  Examples are ribs, sternum, scapula, skull bones, and pelvic bones.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"447","question":"What classification of bone protects the spinal cord?","answer":"Irregular bones  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-1; CAHA7"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"448","question":"2-part question: Where are the irregular bones located and what is their main purpose?","answer":"Irregular bones are found in the spinal column; their purpose is to protect the spinal cord.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-1; CAHA7"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"449","question":"Give ONE purpose of the long bones in the horse's body.","answer":"Act as levers, support weight, provide locomotion, store minerals (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"450","question":"What is the diaphysis of a long bone? (pronounced die-AA-fiss-siss)","answer":"Shaft  <br/> <br/>ref:DET80; CAHA9"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"451","question":"What is the COMMON name for the epiphyseal plates? (pronounced eh-pih-FISS-ee-al)","answer":"Growth plates  <br/> <br/>ref:DET98; CAHA13"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"452","question":"Short bones are located in complex joints such as the knee and hock.  What is the function of short bones?","answer":"Shock absorption  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"453","question":"The thoracic vertebrae, the ribs, and the sternum form the thoracic cavity.  Name 3 body systems these bony structures protect.","answer":"Respiratory, circulatory, and digestive systems  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-6"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"454","question":"What 3 bony structures form the thoracic cavity?","answer":"Spine (vertebrae), ribs, and sternum  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-6"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"455","question":"The head of each rib of a horse is attached to what structure?","answer":"Vertebrae (specifically thoracic vertebrae)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-6; CAHA8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"456","question":"How many PAIRS of ribs does a horse have?","answer":"18 pairs  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-6; CAHA8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"457","question":"How many ribs does a Percheron have?","answer":"36 or 18 pairs (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-6; CAHA8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"458","question":"The costal cartilages of the first 8 ribs articulate with what bony structure?","answer":"Sternum  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"459","question":"What is the difference between true and false ribs?","answer":"True ribs connect to the sternum (by costal cartilages); false ribs do NOT connect directly to the sternum. (FYI: False ribs connect to each other through the costal arch.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-6; CAHA8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"460","question":"What is the term for the ribs that do NOT connect directly to the sternum?","answer":"False ribs (asternal ribs) [FYI: Floating ribs are final ribs that lack costal cartilage attachment and do not attach to the sternum at all, either directly or indirectly. HSm345-6 has the number of true ribs and false ribs mixed up.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-6; CAHA8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"462","question":"Which pairs of ribs are fastened to the sternum by cartilage and are called \"true ribs\"?","answer":"First 8 pairs of ribs (FYI:  HSm345-6 has the numbers of true ribs and false ribs mixed up.)  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"463","question":"Where on the horse is the sternum?","answer":"Chest (FYI: The sternum is the breastbone.)  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA8; DET255"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"464","question":"Where are the manubrium and xiphoid process found in the horse's body? (pronounced man-OOH-bree-um and ZIE-foid)","answer":"Sternum (FYI: The sternum consists of 7 sternebrae.  The cranial segment is the manubrium; the caudal segment is the xiphoid process.  When calculating the number of bones in the horse’s skeleton, the sternum is counted as one bone.)  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA8"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"465","question":"How many bones are in the skull?","answer":"34 bones in the skull  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"466","question":"Name the 3 passages of the facial portion of the skull.","answer":"Orbital, nasal, and oral passages  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-5"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"467","question":"Where is the horse's occipital crest located?","answer":"Poll area (top of the head between the ears)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET194"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"468","question":"Name 3 bones found in the horse’s head.","answer":"Premaxilla or incisive, nasal, maxilla, mandible, frontal, temporal, parietal, occipital, zygomatic, pterygoid, presphenoid, vomar, palatine, hyoid, lacrimal, sphenoid, turbinates, malleus (hammer), incus (anvil), stapes (stirrup)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-5,6"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"469","question":"What is the structural basis for the ears?","answer":"Cartilage (specifically auricular cartilage)  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA43,65"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"470","question":"What bony structure separates the oral cavity from the nasal cavity?","answer":"Hard palate (also accept palatine bone)  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA50; HSm345-6"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"471","question":"Name ONE of the structures that the hyoid bone supports.","answer":"Larynx, base of tongue, guttural pouches, and pharynx (FYI: Guttural pouches are diverticula of the auditory tube and are present only in some animals such as equines.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET146; CAHA42"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"472","question":"What is the mandible?","answer":"Lower jawbone  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-5; CAHA41; DET174"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"473","question":"What is the correct term for the lower jawbone?","answer":"Mandible  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-5; CAHA41"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"474","question":"What is the largest bone in the horse's head?","answer":"Mandible or lower jaw (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-5; HIH230-2"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"475","question":"What is the name of the upper jawbone?","answer":"Maxilla  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-5; CAHA41; DET176"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"476","question":"What is the orbital cavity?","answer":"Bony socket that surrounds and protects the eye  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-5; DET197"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"477","question":"In the skull, what is protected by the orbital cavity?","answer":"Eye  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-5; DET197"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"478","question":"What is the name of the bony socket that surrounds and protects the eye?","answer":"Orbital cavity  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-5; DET197"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"479","question":"2-part question: Where are the turbinate bones and what is their purpose?","answer":"Bones in the nasal passages; they filter and warm inspired air.  <br/> <br/>ref:DET276"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"480","question":"What does the prefix “arthro” mean?","answer":"Joint  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm310-1,3"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"481","question":"What is the term for an area where two or more bones meet?","answer":"Joint  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-1; DET158"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"482","question":"What is the term for a moveable joint that is lined by synovial membrane?","answer":"Synovial joint  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-1"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"483","question":"What is the COMMON name for the coxofemoral joint?","answer":"Hip joint  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA31; DET71"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"484","question":"Which joint of the horse is similar to the human ankle?","answer":"Hock or tarsus (FYI: The pointy part of the hock is the calcaneus which is our heel bone.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm140-2"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"485","question":"Which TWO joints in the hind leg have reciprocal action?","answer":"Stifle and hock  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA36"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"486","question":"What is the joint between the femur and the tibia?","answer":"Stifle  <br/> <br/>ref:DET256"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"487","question":"What joint has a fibro-cartilage structure called a meniscus that's located between the articulating surfaces of the joint?","answer":"Stifle  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA13; DET179"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"488","question":"What joint of the horse is like the human knee?","answer":"Stifle  <br/> <br/>ref:DET256"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"489","question":"What is the purpose of synovial fluid?","answer":"Lubricate joints  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-1; DET261"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"490","question":"What is the name of the fluid that fills the sheaths around tendons and lines the inside of joints?","answer":"Synovial fluid  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-1; DET261"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"491","question":"Synovial joints are classified on the basis of the type of motion.  Name 3 types of synovial joints.","answer":"Ball and socket (hip), hinge (elbow), pivot (atlantoaxial), sliding or gliding (knee or carpus), ellipsoid (antebrachiocarpal joint)  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA13"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"492","question":"What type of joint is the horse's elbow?","answer":"Hinge joint (ginglymus)  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA13"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"493","question":"Name TWO of the bones in the fetlock joint.","answer":"Cannon, long pastern, and two proximal sesamoid bones  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA6,12,14; ES201"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"494","question":"What 4 bones make up the fetlock joint?","answer":"Cannon, long pastern, and two proximal sesamoid bones  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA6,12,14; ES201"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"495","question":"Name 4 bones of the lower leg below the knee or hock.","answer":"Cannon, splint, long pastern, short pastern, coffin, navicular or distal sesamoid, proximal sesamoids  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-4; CAHA6,12"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"496","question":"What are the 3 main bones of the foot?","answer":"Coffin, navicular (proximal sesamoid), and short pastern  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA12; ES201"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"497","question":"From proximal to distal, name the 3 joints of the horse's leg that are common to all 4 legs.","answer":"Fetlock, pastern, and coffin  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-4"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"498","question":"What are the COMMON names of the 3 phalanx bones?","answer":"Long pastern (1st or proximal phalanx), short pastern (2nd or middle phalanx), and coffin (3rd or distal phalanx)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-4; CAHA12; ES201,203"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"499","question":"The first phalanx is just below what long bone?","answer":"Cannon bone (3rd metacarpal or 3rd metatarsal)  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA6,12; HIH505-5; HH49"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"500","question":"What COMMON name is given to the 3rd phalanx bone of the foot?","answer":"Coffin bone (also accept pedal bone)  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA12; HSm345-4"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"501","question":"What bone is located at the lowest point in the hoof?","answer":"Coffin bone (also called pedal bone, distal phalanx, or 3rd phalanx)  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA6,12; HIH505-5; HH49"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"502","question":"Where is the coffin bone?","answer":"In the foot (FYI:  It's the lowest bone in the foot.)  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA6,12; HIH505-5; HH49"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"503","question":"What is the SCIENTIFIC term for the coffin joint?","answer":"Distal interphalangeal joint (DIP joint) [pronounced en-ter-fay-LAN-gee-al]  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA14"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"504","question":"Where are the lateral cartilages located?","answer":"On the sides or wings of the coffin bone (FYI:  Lateral cartilages are also called the collateral cartilages.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH505-5; HSm345-4; HSm125-4"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"505","question":"The cannon, long pastern, and proximal sesamoid bones make up what joint?","answer":"Fetlock (also accept ankle)  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA14; ES201"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"506","question":"What bone is located between the cannon bone and the short pastern?","answer":"Long pastern (1st or proximal phalanx)  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA12; HIH505-5; HSm345-4"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"507","question":"Where in the foot is the navicular bone located?","answer":"Behind the coffin bone or behind and below the short pastern (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH455-2; DET188"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"508","question":"The proximal and distal sesamoid bones serve as pulleys to change the direction of what structure?","answer":"Deep digital flexor tendon  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA12"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"509","question":"Which bone of the foot acts as a fulcrum point to redirect the pull of the deep digital flexor tendon against the coffin bone?","answer":"Navicular bone (also accept distal sesamoid or shuttle bone)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm375-9,20; HIH540-3"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"510","question":"What is another name for the distal sesamoid bone?","answer":"Navicular bone (also called shuttle bone)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-4; CAHA12; DET188"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"511","question":"What TWO bones articulate with the distal sesamoid bone?","answer":"Short pastern and coffin bone  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA12"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"512","question":"How many bones form the basis of locomotion in the horse?","answer":"80 bones (20 bones in each leg)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-1; CAHA6"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"513","question":"Where are the proximal sesamoid bones located?","answer":"At the rear of fetlock joint (FYI:  The distal sesamoid or navicular bone is in the hoof.)  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA6; DET242"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"514","question":"What TWO sets of bones serve as pulleys to change the direction of the deep digital flexor tendon?","answer":"Proximal sesamoids and distal sesamoid (navicular)  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA12"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"515","question":"In the hind legs, what is the anatomical term for the short pastern bone?","answer":"Middle phalanx or 2nd phalanx (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-4; CAHA12"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"516","question":"In the evolution of the horse, the two side toes of the lower leg were reduced to what bones in the leg?","answer":"Splint bones (FYI:  Chestnuts are thought to be vestiges of the carpal and tarsal pads; ergots are thought to be vestiges of metacarpal and metatarsal pads.)  <br/> <br/>ref:ES9"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"517","question":"Give the SCIENTIFIC names for 3 bones in the FRONT leg.","answer":"Scapula, humerus, radius, ulna, carpal bones, 3rd or large metacarpal,  2nd and 4th or small metacarpals, proximal sesamoids, proximal or 1st phalanx, middle or 2nd phalanx, distal or 3rd phalanx, distal sesamoid  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-2; HIH230-2; CAHA6,10,12"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"518","question":"What is the COMMON name of the largest metacarpal?","answer":"Cannon bone (FYI: The cannon bone is the 3rd metacarpal and the splint bones are the 2nd and 4th metacarpals. MetaCARPALS are on the front legs and metaTARSALS are on the hind legs.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-2; CAHA6"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"519","question":"What is the proper anatomical name for the bones between the horse's knee and fetlock?","answer":"Metacarpal bones (FYI: Cannon is the 3rd metacarpal; splint bones are the 2nd and 4th metacarpals.  Metacarpals are on the FRONT leg.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-2; CAHA6,12; DET179"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"520","question":"2-part question:  How many carpal bones are there in the knee and how are they arranged?","answer":"7 or 8 carpal bones (accept either); arranged in 2 rows (FYI: The proximal carpal bones are radial, intermediate, ulnar, and accessory carpal bones. The distal carpal bones are the 1st (may be absent), 2nd, 3rd, and 4th carpal bones.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-2; CAHA11"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"521","question":"What is anatomical term for the horse's knee?","answer":"Carpus  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-2; HIH230-2"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"522","question":"2-part question:  If the horse has a fracture of the olecranon, what bone and joint would be involved?","answer":"Bone is the ulna; joint is the elbow.  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA10; HSm345-7"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"523","question":"The elbow joint in the horse is the articulation site of what 3 bones?","answer":"Humerus, radius, and ulna  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA6; HIH230-2"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"524","question":"What is the SPECIFIC location of the metaCARPOphalangeal joint?","answer":"CHANGED FRONT fetlock or ankle (Must specify front.)  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA14"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"525","question":"2-part question:  How many bones comprise the forearm and what are their names?","answer":"2 (two) bones; radius and ulna  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-2; HIH230-2; CAHA10"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"526","question":"The radius and ulna comprise what structure of the horse?","answer":"Forearm  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-2; HIH230-2; CAHA10"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"527","question":"What bone extends from the shoulder to the elbow?","answer":"Humerus  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-2; HIH230-2; DET144"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"528","question":"What is another name for the horse's shoulder blade?","answer":"Scapula  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-2; HIH230-2; DET240"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"529","question":"What is another name for the scapula?","answer":"Shoulder blade  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-2; HIH230-2; DET240"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"530","question":"Name the 4 bones that form the stifle joint.","answer":"Femur, patella, tibia, and fibula  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA6"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"531","question":"Give the SCIENTIFIC names for 3 bones in the HIND leg.","answer":"Femur, patella, tibia, fibula, tarsal bones, 3rd or large metatarsal, 2nd and 4th or small metatarsals, proximal sesamoids, proximal or 1st phalanx, middle or 2nd phalanx, distal or 3rd phalanx, distal sesamoid  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-4; CAHA6,30,12"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"532","question":"Name 4 of the bones in the horse's hind leg from the stifle distally.","answer":"Tibia, fibula, tarsal bones, cannon, splint bones, long pastern, short pastern, coffin bone, navicular bone or distal sesamoid, proximal sesamoids  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-4; HIH230-2; CAHA6,12"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"533","question":"What is the anatomical name for the bone that forms the point of the hock?","answer":"Calcaneus (pronounced cal-CANE-ee-us)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-7; HIH775-2; HIH1160-3"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"534","question":"What is the anatomical term for the HIND cannon bone?","answer":"3rd or large metatarsal (Do NOT accept metaCARPAL which is on the front leg.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-4; CAHA6,30"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"535","question":"What is the name of the large bone in the thigh?","answer":"Femur  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-4; DET106"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"536","question":"What is the COMMON name for the patella?","answer":"Kneecap  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA6; DET206"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"537","question":"What is the SCIENTIFIC name of the triangular sesamoid bone that's situated at the front of the stifle joint?  It’s also called the “kneecap”.","answer":"Patella  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA6; DET206"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"538","question":"What is the name of the larger bone located between the stifle and the hock?","answer":"Tibia  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-4; CAHA1,6; DET268"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"539","question":"In the horse's skeleton, what tissues connect bones to bones?","answer":"Ligaments  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-1; DET168"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"540","question":"What is the difference between ligaments and tendons?","answer":"Ligaments connect bones to bones; tendons connect muscles to bones.  (FYI:  Ligaments also connect bones to cartilage, connect cartilage to cartilage, and help hold joints together.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-1; DET168; DET264"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"541","question":"2-part question: What is the \"stay apparatus\" and what is its purpose?","answer":"Locking mechanism of the joints of the legs (by muscles and ligaments); allows the horse to sleep standing up; also prevents over-extension and decreases concussion of the legs  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA36; DET254"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"542","question":"Name ONE function of the stay apparatus.","answer":"Locks the horse’s legs so the horse can sleep standing up, prevents overextension, reduces concussion  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA36; DET254"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"543","question":"Why can a horse rest standing up?","answer":"Stay apparatus (locking mechanism of the legs)  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA36; DET254"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"544","question":"What is the primary function of the suspensory ligament?","answer":"Helps prevent overextension of the fetlock joint (FYI: Suspensory ligament starts at the upper back of the cannon, splits, and inserts on the proximal sesamoid bones behind the fetlock.)  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA8; ES206"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"545","question":"Name 3 of the bones that make up the horse's pelvic girdle.","answer":"Ilium, ischium, pubis, sacrum, and caudal  or coccygeal vertebrae  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-6; CAHA28"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"546","question":"The ilium, ischium, and pubis are 3 bones that make up what structure of the horse?","answer":"Pelvis (pelvic girdle)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-6; CAHA28"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"547","question":"Where are the ischium and pubis located?","answer":"Pelvis (pelvic girdle)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-6; CAHA28"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"548","question":"How many TOTAL vertebrae do horses have?","answer":"51 – 57 (accept any number within this range) [FYI: 7 cervical, 18 thoracic, 6 lumbar, 5 sacral, 15 – 21 (average is 18) coccygeal or caudal]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-6; CAHA7"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"549","question":"2-part question:  Name 4 regions of the spinal column and give the number of vertebrae in each of those regions.","answer":"Cervical 7, thoracic 18, lumbar 6, sacrum 5, and coccygeal or caudal 15 – 21 (average is 18)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-6; CAHA7"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"550","question":"How many cervical vertebrae do horses have?","answer":"7 (seven)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-6; DET53"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"551","question":"2-part question:  What are the names and functions of the first and second vertebrae of the horse's spinal column?","answer":"Atlas—flexion and extension of the neck (up and down movement); axis—lateral movement of the neck (left and right movement)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-6; DET17,19"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"552","question":"Where are the cervical vertebrae located?","answer":"Neck (FYI: There are 7 cervical vertebrae.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-6; DET53"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"553","question":"What are the first TWO cervical vertebrae called?","answer":"Atlas and axis  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-6; CAHA7"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"554","question":"What joint is commonly referred to as the yes-no joint?","answer":"Atlas-axis joint, atlantoaxial joint, or joint between the 1st and 2nd cervical vertebrae (accept any)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-6; DET17,19"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"555","question":"Where in the spinal column are the coccygeal or caudal vertebrae?","answer":"Tail (FYI: There are 15 – 21 coccygeal or caudal vertebrae. The average is 18.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-6; CAHA7; DET60"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"556","question":"The coupling is the pivot point of the horse's back and is supported by which section of the horse's vertebral column?","answer":"Lumbar (FYI:  There are 6 lumbar vertebrae.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET70"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"557","question":"The terms transverse process, spinous process, foramen, and arch are used to describe which bones?","answer":"Vertebrae (spinal bones)  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA7"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"558","question":"What term refers to the upper surface of the vertebrae?","answer":"Spinous process  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA7"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"559","question":"Which region of the spinal column is joined securely to the hipbone?","answer":"Sacrum (FYI:  The 5 sacral vertebrae are fused together.  They connect with the ilium bone of the hip at the sacroiliac joint.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-6; CAHA28"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"560","question":"Over which section of the vertebral column does most of the saddle sit?","answer":"Thoracic (FYI:  There are 18 thoracic vertebrae, one for each pair of ribs.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-6; CAHA7"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"561","question":"The increased height of the 3rd, 4th, and 5th thoracic vertebrae make up what part of the horse?","answer":"Withers  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-6; CAHA7"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"562","question":"Describe the difference between adduction and abduction as it applies to the movement of the horse's limbs.","answer":"Adduction is movement toward the body; abduction is movement away from the body.  <br/> <br/>ref:DET1,3"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"563","question":"To what part of the horse's body does the term \"cranial\" refer?","answer":"Skull or head (FYI: The directional term cranial means towards the head.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET72"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"564","question":"2-part question:  What directional term refers to a structure located closer to the head and what term refers to a structure closer to the tail?","answer":"Cranial means closer to the head; caudal means closer to the tail.  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA2"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"565","question":"2-part question:  Define the directional terms proximal and distal.","answer":"Proximal means closer to body; distal means further from body.  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA2"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"566","question":"What system is responsible for collecting and removing the fluid waste materials from the body?","answer":"Urinary system  <br/> <br/>ref:DET280; DET161"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"567","question":"Horses urinate 5 – 7 times a day. How much urine do horses produce a day?","answer":"4 – 7 quarts (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-2; HIH425-2"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"568","question":"Name 4 parts of the urinary system.","answer":"Kidneys, ureters, bladder, and urethra  <br/> <br/>ref:DET280"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"569","question":"Where is urine stored in the horse?","answer":"Bladder  <br/> <br/>ref:DET30; DET280; CAHA68"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"570","question":"What organ provides a blood filtering system that is responsible for the excretion of many waste products from the body?","answer":"Kidney  <br/> <br/>ref:DET280; DET161"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"571","question":"Name 3 functions of the horse's kidneys.","answer":"Remove waste products, filters blood, control water balance, control pH, control electrolyte levels, regulate blood pressure, hormone production, absorb minerals, regulate red blood cells  <br/> <br/>ref:DET161; CAHA66"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"572","question":"In the horse's urinary system, what structure connects the kidney to the bladder?","answer":"Ureter  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA68"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"573","question":"When the bladder is full, urine is discharged through what?","answer":"Urethra  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA68; DET280"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"574","question":"What substance produced by the horse contains products of nitrogen and sulfur metabolism, inorganic salts, and pigments?","answer":"Urine  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA68; DET280"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"575","question":"What is the normal color of a horse's urine or \"pee\"?","answer":"Clear yellow to orange  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH425-2; HSm305-2; CAHA68"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"576","question":"How many times a day do horses urinate?","answer":"5 – 7 times daily (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-2; HIH425-2"},
    {"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"577","question":"What does the term \"viscera\" describe?","answer":"Internal organs  <br/> <br/>ref:DET283"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"578","question":"Fortunately, there are few vicious horses. Give ONE reason why horses may exhibit aggressive behaviors.","answer":"Situational (feeding time, estrus, etc.); maternal aggression; learned behavior; abuse; pecking order (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH376"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"novice","number":"579","question":"Name ONE time when a horse might squeal or strike at another horse.","answer":"When angry; when they feel threatened; when scared, when in pain, when being fed in a group, when standing nose to nose with a strange horse, when mare is not receptive to a stallion, when establishing pecking order (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-1; HSm330-3; FCH153"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"jr bonus","number":"580","question":"Name 3 aggressive behaviors in horses.","answer":"Lunging, biting, kicking, crowding, striking, snapping, baring teeth, pinning ears, charging, rearing (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH377"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"sr bonus","number":"581","question":"Name 4 aggressive behaviors in horses.","answer":"Lunging, biting, kicking, crowding, striking, snapping, baring teeth, pinning ears, charging, rearing (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH377"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"intermediate","number":"582","question":"In reference to aggressive horse behavior, what is charging?","answer":"When a horse suddenly attacks or savages a person, horse, or another animal  <br/> <br/>ref:DET54"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"sr bonus","number":"583","question":"Name 4 horse vices that are dangerous to man.","answer":"Biting, nipping, kicking, striking, charging, crowding, rearing, bucking, shying, bolting or running away, halter pulling (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH376-378"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"jr bonus","number":"584","question":"Name 3 horse vices that are dangerous to man.","answer":"Biting, nipping, kicking, striking, charging, crowding, rearing, bucking, shying, bolting or running away, halter pulling (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH376-378"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"jr bonus","number":"585","question":"Name 3 ways to avoid aggressive behavior when group feeding horses.","answer":"Use separate feeders, ensure open space, space feeders far apart, use extra feeders (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH735-1; HSm420-4"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"586","question":"When feeding groups of horses, what may develop because of dominance issues and may cause aggressive behavior?","answer":"Pecking order  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH735-1; HSm330-3"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"587","question":"When feeding a group of horses together in open areas, how far apart should the feeders be placed?","answer":"40 – 50 feet apart (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH735-1"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"novice","number":"588","question":"Name ONE way a horse shows its dominant position within the herd.","answer":"Pinning ears, baring teeth, biting, turning rear toward other horse, kicking, threatening to kick, aggression (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH152"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"589","question":"When the dominant horse in a group makes a threat, less aggressive horses will do what?","answer":"Retreat or get away (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH152"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"590","question":"How is a pecking order established in a herd of horses?","answer":"Through aggression (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-3; HIH735-1; FCH152"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"intermediate","number":"591","question":"What is the term for the \"boss mare\" or most dominant mare in a herd?","answer":"Alpha  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-3"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"592","question":"What is the term for the action when a horse lashes out with a front leg when mad?","answer":"Striking  <br/> <br/>ref:DET258; FCH376"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"593","question":"Referring to vices, what is striking?","answer":"When a horse strikes out with a front leg  <br/> <br/>ref:DET258; FCH376"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"sr bonus","number":"594","question":"Name 3 psychological types of behaviors seen in herds of horses.","answer":"Contactual, ingestive, investigative, eliminative, agonistic, epimeletic, et-epimeletic, allelomimetic, and sexual behaviors  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-3,4"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"hard","number":"595","question":"In reference to horses, what is agonistic behavior?","answer":"Behavior that involves aggression (FYI: HSm330-4 has agonistic misspelled as agnostic.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSM330-4"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"hard","number":"596","question":"Horses in a group are likely to run simply because another horse is running.  If the running is NOT in response to fright, what type of behavior is it?","answer":"Allelomimetic behavior (also accept mimicry)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-4"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"hard","number":"597","question":"In herds, the mimicking of another horse's actions is called what?","answer":"Allelomimetic behavior (also accept mimicry)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-4"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"hard","number":"598","question":"Give ONE name for the type of behavior when horses huddle together during inclement weather.","answer":"Contactual behavior or social behavior (also accept herding)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-2"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"601","question":"If a horse has the ability needed to work cattle, the horse is said to possess what?","answer":"Cow sense or a lot of cow (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET71"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"602","question":"What does it mean if a horse is said to have \"a lot of cow\"?","answer":"Horse has \"cow sense\" (the mental abilities needed to work cattle).  <br/> <br/>ref:DET71"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"hard","number":"603","question":"What is eliminative behavior?","answer":"Any behavior associated with elimination (such as urination or defecation) [FYI:  Types of behavior include contactual, ingestive, investigative, eliminative, agnostic, epimeletic, et-epimeletic, allelomimetic, and sexual behaviors.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-3"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"hard","number":"604","question":"What is the proper name of the behavior when a mare gives attention and care to her foal?","answer":"Epimeletic behavior (FYI: Et-epimeletic behavior is when the foal asks for attention.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-3; DET97"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"hard","number":"605","question":"What is epimeletic behavior?","answer":"Giving of care and attention between two horses  (FYI: Et-epimeletic behavior is when a horse asks for attention.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-3; DET97"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"hard","number":"606","question":"In reference to horses, what is et-epimeletic behavior?","answer":"Any behavior associated with the desire for care and affection (FYI: “Et” means without.  Examples of et-epimeletic behavior would be a foal asking for attention from its dam or a barn buddies calling each other.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-3,4"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"novice","number":"607","question":"What prompts the horse's immediate instinct to kick or run?","answer":"Fear  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-2; HSm205-2; HIH320-1; ES58; FCH376"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"608","question":"The horse has TWO choices in response to fear.  What are they?","answer":"Fight or flight  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-2; HSm205-2; HIH320-1; ES58; FCH376"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"609","question":"What is a horse's PRIMARY defense?","answer":"Flight (running away)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-2; HSm205-2; HIH320-1; ES58; FCH376"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"novice","number":"610","question":"What does the horse's instinct tell it to do when it's afraid?","answer":"Kick or run (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-2; HSm205-2; HIH320-1; ES58; FCH376"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"sr bonus","number":"611","question":"Name 3 fight or flight vices of the horse.","answer":"Lunging, bolting, aggression, biting, nipping, kicking, striking, exaggerated alarm reaction, balking, snapping, shying, startle reaction, crowding, rearing, charging (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH376"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"novice","number":"612","question":"The horse's first reaction to strange and frightening objects is to what?","answer":"Panic and/or run away  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-2; HSm205-2; HIH320-1; ES58; FCH376"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"613","question":"Why do horses want to stay together and not leave other horses?","answer":"Horses are herd animals and they feel safer in groups.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-2; HIH1120-1; DET139"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"hard","number":"614","question":"In reference to horse behavior, what are harems?","answer":"Smaller social groups in wild herds of horses [FYI:  Each harem will have a boss mare (also called alpha mare or lead mare).]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-3"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"hard","number":"615","question":"What is ingestive behavior?","answer":"Any behavior associated with eating or drinking (FYI:  Ingestive behaviors include bolting feed, pica, coprophagia, wood chewing, etc.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-2, 3"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"medium","number":"616","question":"What is investigative behavior?","answer":"Any behavior where the horse uses its senses to investigate its environment (including smelling, touching, and tasting)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-3"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"novice","number":"617","question":"What is the term for the way horses use their bodies to show other horses or people how they feel?","answer":"Body language  <br/> <br/>ref:DET34; FCH153"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"novice","number":"618","question":"How do you read your horse's mood or intentions as you approach it?","answer":"By reading its body language (watching its head, ears, etc.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET34; FCH153"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"novice","number":"619","question":"What does the term \"body language\" mean?","answer":"Way horses use their bodies to show other horses or people how they feel  <br/> <br/>ref:DET34"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"jr bonus","number":"620","question":"Name 3 things that will tell the mood of a horse.","answer":"Eyes, ears, nostrils, mouth, teeth, muscles, tail, licking, chewing (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH153"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"sr bonus","number":"621","question":"Name 4 things that will tell the mood of a horse.","answer":"Eyes, ears, nostrils, mouth, teeth, muscles, tail, licking, chewing (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH153"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"novice","number":"622","question":"What does it mean if a horse has its ears pinned back?","answer":"That it's mad (anger or aggression)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH153"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"sr bonus","number":"623","question":"Give 4 physical signs that a horse is afraid.","answer":"Eyelids wide open, snorting, whinny of distress, nostrils flared, tail tucked between legs, flight, raising head (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH153"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"624","question":"Eyelids wide open, flared nostrils, snorting, tail tucked between legs, balking, shying, and a whinny of distress are all signs of what?","answer":"Fear  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH376"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"jr bonus","number":"625","question":"Give 3 physical signs that a horse is afraid.","answer":"Eyelids wide open, snorting, whinny of distress, nostrils flared, tail tucked between legs, flight, raising head (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH153"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"novice","number":"626","question":"What does it mean if a horse has its ears pricked forward?","answer":"That it's interested in something (interest or suspicion)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH153"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"627","question":"In problem solving intelligence tests, does the horse place high, medium, or low?","answer":"Low (FYI:  Most intelligence tests check an animal's ability to reason.  Dogs score low, too.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-6; HIH1240-7"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"novice","number":"628","question":"What does a nervous handler cause?","answer":"Nervous or unsafe horse  <br/> <br/>ref:HH51"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"jr bonus","number":"629","question":"Name 3 senses of the horse.","answer":"Sight, smell, hearing, touch, and taste  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm205-1-4; HIH1220-1,2; ES55"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"sr bonus","number":"630","question":"Name 4 senses of the horse.","answer":"Sight, smell, hearing, touch, taste  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm205-1-4; HIH1220-1,2; ES55"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"631","question":"Which sense of the horse is better, sight or hearing?","answer":"Hearing  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-2; HIH1220-2; ES63,64"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"632","question":"Give ONE reason why a horse might react to a sound that a person can't hear.","answer":"Horses can hear sounds that people can't, horses can move their ears, horses can hear in almost any direction.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-2; HIH1220-2; ES63,64"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"633","question":"Horses have very good hearing.  What can they do with their ears to help localize the source of the sounds they hear?","answer":"Turn their ears toward the direction of the sound  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-2; HIH1220-2; ES63,64"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"novice","number":"634","question":"Who has better hearing, you or your horse?","answer":"Your horse (FYI: Horses may hear sounds that humans cannot hear, especially in the higher frequencies, but humans hear lower frequency sounds better.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-2; HIH1220-2; ES63,64"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"sr bonus","number":"635","question":"Name 5 sensitive places on a horse.","answer":"Eyes, ears, nose, mouth, feet, legs, neck, shoulders, withers, belly, ribs, flank (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-2; HIH1220-2; ES65"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"jr bonus","number":"636","question":"Name 3 sensitive places on a horse.","answer":"Eyes, ears, nose, mouth, feet, legs, neck, shoulders, withers, belly, ribs, flank (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-2; HIH1220-2; ES65"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"jr bonus","number":"637","question":"Name 3 things for which the horse uses its sense of smell.","answer":"Locate food, locate water, ensure quality of food or water, identify other horses, identify people, identify objects, smell predators or other dangers, identify marked territory of other horses or herds, initiate sexual or breeding behavior  <br/> <br/>ref:ES61; HSm205-2"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"sr bonus","number":"638","question":"Name 3 things for which the horse uses its olfactory sense.","answer":"Locate food, locate water, ensure quality of food or water, identify other horses, identify people, identify objects, smell predators or other dangers, identify marked territory of other horses or herds, initiate sexual or breeding behavior  <br/> <br/>ref:ES61; HSm205-2"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"medium","number":"639","question":"What is the term for the curling of the upper lip by stallions when teasing mares?","answer":"Flehmen reflex (Flehmen response)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-4; HSm520-4; HIH425-5; FCH389; DET109; ES61,62"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"medium","number":"640","question":"What is the Flehmen response?","answer":"Horse raises its head and curls its upper lip back  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-4; HSm520-4; HIH425-5; FCH389; DET109; ES61,62"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"medium","number":"641","question":"What is the tactile sense?","answer":"Sense of touch  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-2; ES64"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"642","question":"All of the horse's senses are important in training.  Which sense is the most important for responding to cues?","answer":"Touch (FYI:  Touch is the tactile sense.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-2; ES65"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"643","question":"What is the term for the type of vision where the horse sees the same scene with both eyes?","answer":"Binocular vision  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1220-1; HSm330-1; ES56; HSc5"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"644","question":"Which type of vision is a horse using when he looks at something head on?","answer":"Binocular vision  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1220-1; HSm330-1; ES56; HSc5"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"645","question":"To judge distance, the horse uses which type of vision?","answer":"Binocular vision  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1220-1; HSm330-1; ES56; HSc5"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"646","question":"Name TWO areas where a horse does NOT see anything.","answer":"Directly in front; directly behind; over its head, neck, or back; under its  head; directly downward  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1220-1; HSm330-1; ES58-60; HSc5"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"novice","number":"647","question":"A horse cannot see directly BELOW what part of its body?","answer":"Head (also accept neck and body)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1220-1; HSm330-1; ES58-60; HSc5"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"648","question":"A horse cannot see directly BEHIND what part of its body?","answer":"Hindquarters (accept any reasonable answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1220-1; HSm330-1; ES58-60; HSc5"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"jr bonus","number":"649","question":"Name 3 of the horse's blind spots.","answer":"Directly in front; directly behind; over its head, neck, or back; under its head; directly downward  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1220-1; HSm330-1; ES58-60; HSc5"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"650","question":"An object must be at what distance in front of a horse for the object to be seen by the horse using its binocular vision?","answer":"4 (four) feet  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1220-1; HSm330-1"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"651","question":"What must the horse do with its head to see faraway objects?","answer":"Lower its head  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1220-1; HSm330-1"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"652","question":"What must the horse do to see close objects?","answer":"Raise its head  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1220-1; HSm330-1"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"653","question":"2-part question:  Describe where the object is that a horse is focusing on when he raises his head and when he lowers his head.","answer":"Raises head—focusing on a nearby object; lowers head—focusing on a faraway object  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1220-1; HSm330-1"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"medium","number":"654","question":"In reference to behavior, what is the \"menace reflex\"?","answer":"Horse closes its eye when a hand or object moves toward the eye.  <br/> <br/>ref:DET179"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"655","question":"What is monocular vision?","answer":"Ability to see separate objects with each eye at the same time  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1220-1; HSm330-1; ES54; HSc5"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"656","question":"What is the term for the ability to see separate objects with each eye at the same time?","answer":"Monocular vision  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1220-1; HSm330-1; ES54; HSc5"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"657","question":"What has been a prime feature of the horse's ability to survive?","answer":"Monocular vision (its ability to see objects on either side at the same time)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1220-1; HSm330-1; ES54; HSc5"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"658","question":"What survival advantage does the horse have because of its monocular vision?","answer":"Monocular vision allows horse to detect predators from either side without turning its head (which is particularly important while grazing)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1220-1; HSm330-1; ES54; HSc5"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"659","question":"Explain the difference between monocular and binocular vision.","answer":"Monocular vision is when the horse sees different objects with each eye; binocular vision is when the horse uses both eyes to see the same object.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1220-1; HSm330-1; ES54; HSc5"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"hard","number":"660","question":"What is the range of a horse's BINOCULAR vision?","answer":"65 degrees (directly in front of its head)  <br/> <br/>ref:ES57"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"hard","number":"661","question":"Experts disagree on horses’ degree of visual field.  Give ONE possible answer for a horse’s TOTAL degrees of vision.","answer":"300 degrees (HSm and HIH); 350 degrees (ES); 320 – 340 (PNW)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-3; HIH220-4; ES57"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"medium","number":"662","question":"Name ONE thing that allows horses to have a larger field of vision than most other animals.","answer":"Size of the eye, position of the eye, width of the head, width of the body, horizontal pupil  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-4; HSm330-1; ES65; ES56"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"sr bonus","number":"663","question":"Name 3 things that determine the field of vision of the horse.","answer":"Size of the eye, position of the eye, width of the head, width of the body, horizontal pupil  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-4; HSm330-1; ES65; ES56"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"intermediate","number":"664","question":"What is the loud, prolonged call of a horse?","answer":"Neigh (also accept whinny) [FYI:  A whinny may denote happiness, anticipation, or anxiety.]  <br/> <br/>ref:DET189; DET292; FCH153"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"intermediate","number":"665","question":"What is the term for a soft, welcoming greeting made by a content horse?","answer":"Nicker  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH153"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"intermediate","number":"666","question":"What sound acts as a warning signal used to alert a group of horses of impending danger?","answer":"Snort (FYI:  A snort is made by blowing air out through the nostrils.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET250; FCH153"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"intermediate","number":"667","question":"What sound does a horse make in response to anger?","answer":"Squeal  <br/> <br/>ref:DET253; FCH153"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"668","question":"What is the definition of a vice?","answer":"Bad or annoying habit (that may interfere with the health or usefulness of the horse)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET283; FCH370; FCH408; HSc4"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"669","question":"What is the general term for a bad or annoying habit that may affect a horse's health, usefulness, or dependability?","answer":"Vice  <br/> <br/>ref:DET283; FCH370; FCH408; HSc4"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"intermediate","number":"670","question":"Explain the difference between bolting and shying.","answer":"Bolting is when the horse goes forward; shying is when the horse goes to the side.  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH378; FCH382; FCH403; DET34; DET245"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"intermediate","number":"671","question":"In reference horse behavior, what are TWO ways the term \"bolting\" can be used?","answer":"Eating too fast; running off or charging forward  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH382; FCH382; DET34"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"intermediate","number":"672","question":"In reference to a horse's behavior, what does the term “freezing” mean?","answer":"Horse refuses to move (horse becomes stiff or immobile)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH378; FCH390"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"sr bonus","number":"673","question":"Name 3 vices that are dangerous to the horse.","answer":"Cribbing (aerophagia), wood chewing (lignophagia), mane or tail chewing (trichophagia), eating dirt (geophagia), eating feces (coprophagia), bolting food, fighting, shying, halter pulling  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH376-378"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"674","question":"Name TWO vices that are often copied by other horses.","answer":"Cribbing, weaving, wood chewing, pawing (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH Chapter 20"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"intermediate","number":"675","question":"2-part question:  Describe an escape vice and give TWO examples.","answer":"Horse is unhappy in a certain place and would like to escape; examples are pawing, pacing, stall walking, trying to jump out of the stall or paddock, crowding, weaving, or head nodding. (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH370"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"676","question":"Name ONE way to prevent vices such as stall kicking, cribbing, and wood chewing.","answer":"Regular exercise; provide plenty of forage; put out to pasture; increase feeding frequency; increase feeding volume  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH372"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"677","question":"Describe the vice \"head nodding\".","answer":"Horse rhythmically nods its head (either up and down or back and forth)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH392"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"intermediate","number":"678","question":"What vice is often associated with head nodding?","answer":"Weaving  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH408"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"679","question":"Give ONE reason why stabled horses develop vices.","answer":"Boredom, lack of exercise, lack of long stem forage or \"chew time\", copying other horses  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm215-1; HIH320-1"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"intermediate","number":"680","question":"What is the common negative BEHAVIORAL consequence for failing to provide your horse with adequate roughage?","answer":"Horse will develop vices.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH710-5"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"681","question":"Do horses prefer to spend their time in an enclosed area such as a stall or in the open such as a pasture?","answer":"In the open  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm215-1; HIH320-1"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"jr bonus","number":"682","question":"Stable vices can consist of “escape” vices and “oral” vices.  Name 3 stable vices.","answer":"Pawing, pacing, stall walking, trying to jump out of stall or paddock, crowding, weaving, head nodding, cribbing, wood chewing, mane or tail chewing (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH425-5,6"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"sr bonus","number":"683","question":"Stable vices can consist of “escape” vices and “oral” vices.  Name 5 stable vices.","answer":"Pawing, pacing, stall walking, trying to jump out of stall or paddock, crowding, weaving, head nodding, cribbing, wood chewing, mane or tail chewing (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH425-5,6"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"684","question":"What is the name of the vice where the horse constantly paces or circles around its stall?","answer":"Stall walking  <br/> <br/>ref:DET254; FCH371,400"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"685","question":"Describe the stable vice called weaving.","answer":"Horse moves its head and upper body from side to side; horse rocks side to side or back and forth (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-4; HIH425-6; FCH371,408"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"intermediate","number":"686","question":"2-part question:  In reference to vices, what is weaving and where is it commonly seen?","answer":"Moving the head or body from side to side; seen in the stall or along a  fence line  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-4; FCH382"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"intermediate","number":"687","question":"The placement of several large, round rocks in a horse's feed tub helps to decrease the incidence of what vice?","answer":"Bolting its feed  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH372,382; DET34"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"intermediate","number":"688","question":"What term describes the habit horses have of eating too fast?","answer":"Bolting their feed  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH372,382; DET34"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"medium","number":"689","question":"Why would you mix chaff or chopped hay in with your horse's grain?","answer":"To discourage horse from bolting its feed  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH94"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"690","question":"Give ONE term for when a horse doesn't like its cinch tightened.","answer":"Cinch-bound, girth-bound, cold-backed, cinchy  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH385; DET57"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"691","question":"What is a cinch-bound horse?","answer":"Horse that doesn't like being cinched up  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH385; DET57"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"692","question":"What is it called when a horse kicks with a forward and sideward motion?","answer":"Cow-kick  <br/> <br/>ref:DET71; HSm205-2"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"693","question":"In reference to horses, describe a cow-kick.","answer":"Horse kicks with a forward and sidewards motion  <br/> <br/>ref:DET71; HSm205-2"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"694","question":"In reference to vices, what is the term used when a horse consciously squeezes the handler against the stall wall?","answer":"Crowding  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH377"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"695","question":"When your horse it tied to a fixed object, why should you untie the lead rope before removing the halter?","answer":"To help prevent him from pulling back  <br/> <br/>ref:DET129; HH52"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"696","question":"What does \"head shy\" mean?","answer":"Horse doesn't like to be touched on the head or face.  <br/> <br/>ref:DET136; HSc4"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"sr bonus","number":"697","question":"Name 3 oral vices in horses.","answer":"Cribbing, windsucking (aerophagia), wood chewing (lignophagia), mane or tail chewing (trichophagia), eating feces (coprophagia), eating dirt or bedding (geophagia), tongue displacement (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH372-376,408; HSm305-4; HIH425-6"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"698","question":"What is cribbing?","answer":"Biting or setting the teeth against an object while sucking air  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-4; HIH425-6; FCH386; DET72; HH4; PNW21"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"699","question":"Which vice is characterized by biting or setting the teeth against a fence or some other object while sucking air?","answer":"Cribbing  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-4; HIH425-6; FCH386; DET72; HH4; PNW21"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"intermediate","number":"700","question":"A strap buckled around the neck in a way that will compress the larynx when the head is flexed is a common remedy for what vice?","answer":"Cribbing  <br/> <br/>ref:DET72; FCH374; PNW21"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"sr bonus","number":"701","question":"Name 3 possible causes of oral vices such as wood chewing, eating dirt, tail chewing, or eating tree bark.","answer":"Boredom, lack of long stem forage or “chew time”, lack of exercise, changes in weather, taste of bark of certain trees (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH450-3,740-1,741-1,2; FCH372,373,409"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"702","question":"Name ONE possible cause of oral vices such as wood chewing, eating dirt, tail chewing, or eating tree bark.","answer":"Boredom, lack of long stem forage or “chew time”, lack of exercise, copying other horses, nutrition problems  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH450-3,740-1,741-1,2; FCH372,373,409"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"hard","number":"703","question":"What is meant by the behavioral term pica?","answer":"Eating unnatural substances (such as dirt, feces, bones, wood, and hair) [FYI:  Those vices are called geophagia, coprophagia, osteophagia, lignophagia, and trichophagia.]  <br/> <br/>ref:DET211; FCH399,400"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"hard","number":"704","question":"What GENERAL term is used to describe when horses eat unnatural substances such as dirt?","answer":"Pica (FYI:  Geophagia is the SPECIFIC term for eating dirt.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET211; FCH399,400"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"hard","number":"705","question":"Name ONE dietary deficiency that may cause the act of pica in horses.","answer":"Sodium chloride (salt), potassium, phosphorus, protein  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH399,400"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"hard","number":"706","question":"What is coprophagy? (pronounced coe-pro-FAY-gee)","answer":"Eating feces (FYI:  Coprophagy is common in foals and young horses, but it’s considered to be abnormal behavior for adult horses.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-4; HIH425-5,975-5; FCH375,386; DET68; ES190"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"707","question":"What GENERAL age horse is usually involved in the oral vice of tail chewing?","answer":"Foals or young horses (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH375,147"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"medium","number":"708","question":"What is the name for the oral vice in which a horse sticks its tongue out the side of the mouth?","answer":"Tongue displacement  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH372,407"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"sr bonus","number":"709","question":"It was thought—falsely—in the past, that in proud-cut, rig, or false rig geldings, the epididymis was left which produced testosterone.  Give 3 reasons why geldings may show stallion-like behaviors.","answer":"Learned behavior (often occurs if castrated at an older age), an undescended testicle that was not removed, or too much testosterone from the adrenal gland.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm520-3,4; FCH226,400,401"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"intermediate","number":"710","question":"What type of behavior would be exhibited by a gelding that is described as being “proud-cut”?","answer":"Stallion-like behavior (FYI:  Research shows that “proud cut” geldings have stallion-like behavior for 3 reasons—learned behavior, an undescended testicle that was not removed, or too much testosterone from the adrenal gland.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm520-3,4; FCH226,400"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"711","question":"What is the term for a horse that acts up because it doesn’t want to leave the barn?","answer":"Barn sour  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-2; PNW51; FCH152"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"712","question":"What is a barn sour horse?","answer":"Horse that doesn't want to leave the barn (and acts up when being ridden away from the barn)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-2; PNW51; FCH152"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"intermediate","number":"713","question":"What movement is being described? The horse leaps into the air, keeping his back arched, kicks out with his back legs, and lands with his forelegs stiff and his head held low.","answer":"Bucking  <br/> <br/>ref:DET41"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"intermediate","number":"714","question":"When a saddled horse stands with its back pushed up or bowed upward, what may this indicate?","answer":"That it's going to buck when the rider mounts  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH383"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"715","question":"What are mild bucking motions called?","answer":"Crow hops  <br/> <br/>ref:DET74"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"716","question":"In reference to horses, what are \"crow hops\"?","answer":"Mild bucking motions  <br/> <br/>ref:DET74"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"717","question":"What is the term for a horse that refuses to leave a group of other horses?","answer":"Herd bound  <br/> <br/>ref:DET138; HSc4; HSm330-13; HIH265-2"},
    {"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"718","question":"What does \"herd bound\" mean?","answer":"Horse refuses to leave a group of other horses.  <br/> <br/>ref:DET138; HSc4; HSm330-13; HIH265-2"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"719","question":"In what city is the American Horse Council located?","answer":"Washington, DC  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1910-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"720","question":"Identify the 3 following breeds from their nicknames:  Aristocrat of the Show Ring, Living Fossil, Peacock of the Show Ring.","answer":"Aristocrat of the Show Ring—Hackney Horse; Living Fossil—Exmoor Pony; Peacock of the Show Ring—Saddlebred  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH158B-1; HSm120-8; HSm135-3"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"721","question":"Identify the 3 following breeds from their nicknames:  Bloodhorse, Breed of Blacks and Grays, and Palouse Horse.","answer":"Breed of Blacks and Grays—Percheron; Bloodhorse—Thoroughbred; Palouse horse—Appaloosa  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-5; HSm125-6; HIH152B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"722","question":"Name the country of origin for 3 of the following breeds:  Bashkir Curly, Haflinger, Hanoverian, and Exmoor.","answer":"Bashkir Curly is Russia, Haflinger is Austria, Hanoverian is Germany, and Exmoor Pony is England (also accept Great Britain or United Kingdom).  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-17; HSm130-5; HIH157B-1; DET8; DET25"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"723","question":"Name the country of origin for 3 of the following breeds:  Thoroughbred, Welsh Pony, Clydesdale, and Belgian.","answer":"Thoroughbred is England, Welsh Pony is Wales, Clydesdale is Scotland, and Belgian is Belgium.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH173B-1; HIH175B-1; HSm125-6; HSm125-5"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"724","question":"Name 3 breeds that are named after different US states.","answer":"Tennessee Walking Horse, Missouri Fox Trotter, and Colorado Ranger Horse (which is also called the Rangerbred)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm135-1; HSm135-4; DET62"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"725","question":"What draft-type horse from Austria commonly has a leopard spotting pattern?","answer":"Noriker  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-17; DET191"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"726","question":"Name TWO colors registered in the International Buckskin Horse Association.","answer":"Buckskin, dun, grulla, red dun, brindle dun  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH154B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"727","question":"Name 3 disqualifications for registration in the International Buckskin Association.","answer":"Draft-type conformation, mature horses less than 14 hands (unless registered in Miniature division), palominos with dorsal stripes, spotted horses, white horses, line back sorrels, chestnuts, greys, bays, roans  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH154B-1,2"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"728","question":"Which breed organization was formed in 1971 to preserve the pedigrees and promote the activities of buckskin and dun horses?","answer":"International Buckskin Horse Association (FYI:  There’s also an American Buckskin Registry Association.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH154B-1; DET8"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"729","question":"What is a Sorraia? (pronounced sore-EYE-ya)","answer":"Dun or buckskin breed from Spain  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH154B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"730","question":"True buckskin and dun horses originated from which TWO breeds?","answer":"Sorraia and Norwegian Dun (pronounced sore-EYE-ya)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH154B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"731","question":"The breed description of a Palomino describes the ideal color to be what?","answer":"Color of a newly minted gold coin (also accept 14 karat gold coin)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH164B-2"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"732","question":"What is the difference between a Paint and a Pinto?","answer":"Pinto is a spotted horse; Paint can only have Thoroughbred, Quarter Horse, or Paint breeding.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-3; HSm510-5; HIH163B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"733","question":"Into which Pinto breed conformation type would a horse of Thoroughbred breeding fit?","answer":"Hunter  <br/> <br/>ref:HH59"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"734","question":"Arabian or Morgan type horses would fit into which Pinto breed conformation type?","answer":"Pleasure (FYI:  The 4 Pinto breed conformation types are Stock, Hunter, Saddle, and Pleasure.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH59"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"735","question":"Which Pinto breed conformation type would be represented by a horse of Saddlebred, Hackney, or Tennessee Walking Horse breeding?","answer":"Saddle (FYI:  The 4 Pinto breed conformation types are Stock, Hunter, Saddle, and Pleasure.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH59"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"736","question":"Which Pinto breed conformation type would be represented by a horse of Quarter Horse breeding?","answer":"Stock  <br/> <br/>ref:HH59"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"737","question":"Name 3 conformation types of the Pinto.","answer":"Stock, pleasure, saddle, and hunter  <br/> <br/>ref:HH59"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"738","question":"Giving only one number, what is the general height of a draft horse?","answer":"17 hands (accept any number within the 16 – 19 hand range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125; DET84"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"739","question":"Giving only one number, what is the general weight of a draft horse?","answer":"2000 pounds (accept any number between 1400 – 2000 pounds)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"740","question":"What is the general term for large, heavy-boned work horses that usually weigh 2000 pounds and stand 17 - 18 hands tall?","answer":"Draft horses  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-1; DET84"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"741","question":"Name 4 breeds of draft horses.","answer":"Clydesdale, Shire, Belgian, Percheron, Suffolk, American Cream Draft, Gypsy Vanner, Ardennes, Dutch Draft, Irish Draft, Noriker, Spotted Draft Horse, Brabant (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"742","question":"Name 6 breeds of draft horses.","answer":"Clydesdale, Shire, Belgian, Percheron, Suffolk, American Cream Draft, Gypsy Vanner, Ardennes, Dutch Draft, Irish Draft, Noriker, Spotted Draft Horse, Brabant (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"743","question":"Name TWO draft breeds that originated in America.","answer":"American Cream Draft and Spotted Draft (North American Spotted Draft)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH155B-1; HSm125-10"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"744","question":"Identify this breed: weighs 1400 – 2000 pounds, is 15.1 – 16.3 hands tall, traces back to a foundation mare from Iowa, is cream in color.","answer":"American Cream Draft (FYI:  The foundation mare was named Old Granny.  The cream color is a result of a champagne gene on a chestnut base.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH155B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"745","question":"Name TWO color features of the American Cream Draft horse.","answer":"Cream-colored body; white mane and tail; pink skin; amber eyes (FYI:  The color of the American Cream Draft Horse is caused by a champagne gene, NOT a cream gene; therefore, they are NOT cremellos.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET8; HIH155B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"746","question":"Give 3 characteristics of the American Cream Draft Horse.","answer":"Cream-colored body; white mane and tail; pink skin; amber eyes (FYI:  The color of the American Cream Draft Horse is caused by a champagne gene, NOT a cream gene; therefore, they are NOT cremellos.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET8; HIH155B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"intermediate","number":"747","question":"Based on registry, which draft breed is the MOST numerous in the US?","answer":"Belgian  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-5"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"748","question":"Name 3 predominant colors of Belgians.","answer":"Blond, sorrel, chestnut, roan (FYI:  Belgians usually have “light points”—lighter lower legs and flaxen manes and tails.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-5"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"749","question":"Name 3 breed characteristics of the Belgian.","answer":"Tall (can be 18 hands or over); heavy (can be over 2000 lbs.); can be blond, sorrel, roan, or chestnut; flaxen mane and tail (preferred); no feathering; does not have high action  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-5"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"750","question":"Name TWO colors of the Clydesdale.","answer":"Bay, brown, black, sorrel (chestnut), occasional roan (FYI:  4 white legs are common; white spots can occur on the body.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-6"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"751","question":"Which draft breed is famous for being used in multi-horse hitches, especially one advertising a brewery?","answer":"Clydesdale  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-6"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"752","question":"Identify this draft breed:  can grow to over 18 hands tall, can weigh between 1600 and 2400 pounds, it’s a descendant of the Great Flemish Horse, its country of origin is Scotland, most common color is bay, has feathering.","answer":"Clydesdale  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-6; DET59"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"753","question":"Name 3 standards Clydesdales must meet in order to qualify for the Budweiser hitch.","answer":"Must be at least 4 years of age; must be a gelding; must stand 72 inches (18 hands); must weight 1800 – 2400; must be bay with 4 white socks and a blaze  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-6"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"754","question":"In what country did the Clydesdale originate?","answer":"Scotland (near the River Clyde)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-6"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"755","question":"Name 3 breed characteristics of Clydesdales.","answer":"Tall (15 – 19 hands), heavy (1600 – 2400 pounds), usually bay or brown, often have 4 white legs, have feathering, have large feet (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-1,3,5-7"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"756","question":"Name 3 characteristics of Percherons.","answer":"Tall; heavy; black or gray color; lack of feathering on legs; speed at the walk; bold trot; considerable knee action; large, prominent eye; broad, full forehead; straight face; long, level croup; close-coupled; wide and deep through chest  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-6"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"757","question":"What is the temperature-sounding term for a horse of draft horse breeding?","answer":"Cold blooded (FYI:  All horses are warm-blooded mammals.  \"Cold blooded\" draft horse types are known for their calm temperaments.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-1; DET61; HH56"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"758","question":"In reference to horses, what does the term \"cold-blooded\" mean?","answer":"Draft horse breeding  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-1; DET61; HH56"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"759","question":"Name 3 characteristics of cold-blooded horse breeds.","answer":"Heavy-bodied, heavy-boned, thicker hair coat, quiet disposition, slower speed, origin from colder climates  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"760","question":"What is the term for the long hair around horses' fetlocks that is common in draft breeds?","answer":"Feathers or feathering  <br/> <br/>ref:DET105"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"761","question":"What is feathering?","answer":"Long, silky hair on the lower legs  <br/> <br/>ref:DET105"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"762","question":"Name TWO breeds of draft horses that do NOT have feathering on their lower legs.","answer":"Percheron, Suffolk, Belgian (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"763","question":"Name TWO breeds of draft horses that have feathering on their lower legs.","answer":"Shire and Clydesdale  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"764","question":"Name 3 breeds of horses that have feathering on their lower legs.","answer":"Clydesdale, Shire, Gypsy Vanner, Friesian, Ardennes, Fell Pony, Dales Pony, Highland Pony (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125; HSm120"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"765","question":"Name 4 breeds of horses that have feathering on their lower legs.","answer":"Clydesdale, Shire, Gypsy Vanner, Friesian, Ardennes, Fell Pony, Dales Pony, Highland Pony (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125; HSm120"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"766","question":"Name 3 draft breeds that are descendants of the \"Great Horses\" of Europe.","answer":"Belgian (Great Horse), Brabant, Clydesdale (Great Flemish Horse), Shire (English Great Horse)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-5,6,7"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"767","question":"What breed of draft horse is considered to be the purest survivor of the English Great Horse?","answer":"Shire  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-6"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"768","question":"Name 3 breed characteristics of the Gypsy Vanner.","answer":"13.2 – 15.2 hands; heavy-boned; feathering; long mane and tail; forelock covers eyes; may have a beard, whiskers, or muzzle hair; animated trot; often has spotted color (piebald, skewbald, or blagdon—solid color with white splashed on underbelly)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-9"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"769","question":"What is the origination of the name Gypsy Vanner?","answer":"Came from the gypsies who created a horse suitable to pull a caravan  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-9"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"770","question":"Identify the following breed:  average height is 16 – 17 hands tall, temperament is calm, breed was established in New Mexico and Minnesota in the 1990’s, color is pinto with 40% spots.","answer":"Spotted Draft (North American Spotted Draft)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-10"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"771","question":"Name TWO colors of the Percheron.","answer":"Black and gray (occasionally bay, sorrel, and roan)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-6"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"772","question":"In what country did the Percheron originate?","answer":"France (La Perche, France)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-6"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"773","question":"What draft breed’s foundation sire was Jean le Blanc? (pronounced zjhon leh blonk)","answer":"Percheron  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-6"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"774","question":"Which draft breed is known as the \"breed of blacks and grays\"?","answer":"Percheron  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-6"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"775","question":"Which draft breed is thought to be the only one with Arabian or Barb blood?","answer":"Percheron  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-6"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"776","question":"What is the most common color of the Shire?","answer":"Black (FYI:  Shires can also be brown, gray, and bay.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-6"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"777","question":"Where did the Shire get its name?","answer":"English Shires (specifically Lincolnshire and Cambridgeshire)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-6"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"778","question":"Which draft breed is generally the tallest?","answer":"Shire  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-6"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"779","question":"What is the color of the Suffolk?","answer":"Chestnut or sorrel  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-7"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"780","question":"What breed is being described?  This draft breed is a descendant of the medieval charger breed.  Its color is all shades of chestnut.  It originated in Suffolk County, England.","answer":"Suffolk (Suffolk Punch)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-7; DET259"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"781","question":"Cosmetically speaking, how does the Suffolk differ from the other two British draft breeds?","answer":"Suffolk doesn't have feathering on its legs. (FYI:  The other British breeds are the Shire from England and the Clydesdale from Scotland.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-7"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"782","question":"Because of its rounded or \"punched up\" appearance, what was the Suffolk originally called?","answer":"Suffolk Punch (FYI: It's now just called the Suffolk.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-7"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"783","question":"Where did the Suffolk originate?","answer":"Suffolk, England  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-7"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"784","question":"Name 3 general uses of draft horses.","answer":"Farming, pulling heavy loads, logging, driving, trail riding, show, parade, companion (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-2"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"785","question":"In which country did the Asiatic Wild Horse originate?","answer":"Mongolia  <br/> <br/>ref:DET16"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"786","question":"What is the term for a wild Australian horse?","answer":"Brumby  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm130-3; DET41"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"787","question":"What breed of pony is the descendant of the survivors of a shipwreck off the coast of Virginia?","answer":"Chincoteague  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm120-7; DET55"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"788","question":"What is the term for a domesticated animal species that lives in the wild?","answer":"Feral (FYI:  True wild horses and their ancestors have never been domesticated.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET106; FCH405; HIH170B-1; HIH425-5"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"789","question":"What is a feral horse?","answer":"Wild horse (FYI:  Feral animals are domesticated animals that live in the wild.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET106; FCH405; HIH170B-1; HIH425-5"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"790","question":"Who were responsible for spreading the Spanish horses over the West?","answer":"American Indians (especially the Apaches)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH170B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"791","question":"Name 3 characteristics of the Spanish Mustang.","answer":"Chestnuts are small and smooth or are missing, bones are big, legs join the chest in an A shape, forehead is straight or concave, nose is convex or Roman, ears are small to medium-sized.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH170B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"792","question":"What breed registry is attempting to maintain the bloodlines of horses brought to the New World by the Spanish?","answer":"Spanish Mustang Registry  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH170B-2"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"793","question":"What is the first and oldest Mustang registry?","answer":"Spanish Mustang Registry  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH170B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"794","question":"What subspecies of small, dun-colored horse is also called Takhi and the Mongolian Wild horse?","answer":"Przewalski’s Horse  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm120-11; DET222"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"795","question":"What subspecies of small, dun-colored horse originated in Poland and became extinct in Russia in 1876?","answer":"Tarpan  <br/> <br/>ref:DET263; HSm140-5,6"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"796","question":"Name TWO breeds that perform the running walk.","answer":"Tennessee Walking Horse and Galiceño (pronounced gal-ee-SANE-yo)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-2; HSm120-9"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"797","question":"Gaited horses are horses that perform intermediate gaits other than trot.  Name 3 gaited horse breeds.","answer":"Saddlebred, Tennessee Walking Horse, Missouri Fox Trotter, Rocky Mountain Horse, Standardbred, Racking Horse, Paso Fino, Peruvian Paso, Icelandic, Galiceño (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm135-1-4; HSm115-1-4"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"798","question":"Gaited horses are horses that perform intermediate gaits other than trot.  Name 4 gaited horse breeds.","answer":"Saddlebred, Tennessee Walking Horse, Missouri Fox Trotter, Rocky Mountain Horse, Standardbred, Racking Horse, Paso Fino, Peruvian Paso, Icelandic, Galiceño (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm135-1-4; HSm115-1-4"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"799","question":"Name 3 colors of the Missouri Fox Trotter.","answer":"ANY COLOR, black, bay, brown, chestnut, palomino, roan (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH56,57"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"800","question":"Name 3 breeds from which the Missouri Fox Trotter breed was developed.","answer":"Arabian, Morgan, Saddlebred, Tennessee Walking Horse, Standardbred, Plantation horses  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH162B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"801","question":"Which breed was developed from saddle horses by settlers in the Ozark Mountains?","answer":"Missouri Fox Trotter  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH161B-1; HSm135-3; DET181"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"802","question":"What breed of horse is known for its distinctive gait in which the horse performs a brisk walk with the front legs and trots with the back legs?  This breed originated in the Ozark Mountains of Missouri and Arkansas.","answer":"Missouri Fox Trotter  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH161B-1; HSm135-3; DET181"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"803","question":"Where did the Orlov Trotter originate?","answer":"Russia  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm130-4; DET197"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"804","question":"Giving only one number, how tall is the Paso Fino?","answer":"14 hands (accept any number within the 13 – 15.2 hand range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-4; HIH165B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"805","question":"Name 3 breeds from which the Paso Fino was developed.","answer":"Andalusian, Barb, Spanish Jennet, and Friesian (FYI:  The Spanish Jennet was a gaited breed of the Middle Ages in Europe that often had pinto or Appaloosa patterns.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-4; HIH165B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"806","question":"Who brought the Paso Fino to the New World?","answer":"Columbus  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-4; HIH165B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"807","question":"Which breed is ridden over a long, narrow wood board to assess gait quality and rhythm?","answer":"Paso Fino  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm135-3"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"808","question":"There are two distinct types of Paso horses.  Which type allows pintos, roans, and cremellos in the registry?","answer":"Paso Fino  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-4; HIH165B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"809","question":"Name this breed of gaited horse:  originally from Spain, imported to the US from Puerto Rico and Columbia; performs the paso fino, paso corto, and paso largo gaits.","answer":"Paso Fino  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-4; HIH165B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"810","question":"Which breed was called “los caballos de paso fino” by the Spanish explorers?","answer":"Paso Fino  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-4"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"811","question":"Which breed was first imported from Peru in the mid-1960's?","answer":"Peruvian Paso  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-3; HSm135-3; HIH166B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"812","question":"What Paso breed is known for the gaits paso llano and sobreandando and for its characteristic leg motion called the termino?","answer":"Peruvian Paso (FYI: The termino has outward swinging front leg motion originating at the shoulders.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm135-3"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"813","question":"What is a racking horse?","answer":"Horse that racks (FYI:  Racking Horses can be of Tennessee Walking Horse, Spotted Saddle Horse, and Standardbred breeding.  Racking Horse is shown at 3 gaits—show or trail walk, slow rack, and fast rack.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm135-2"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"814","question":"Name 3 gaits of a Racking Horse.","answer":"Show or trail walk, slow rack, fast rack, style rack (FYI:  Racking Horses can be of Tennessee Walking Horse, Spotted Saddle Horse, and Standardbred breeding.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm135-2"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"815","question":"What breed performs the trail walk, show gait, and pleasure gait, but can also canter?","answer":"Rocky Mountain Horse  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm135-2"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"816","question":"What gaited breed originated in the Appalachian Mountains of Eastern Kentucky?  The breed association was formed in 1986.  This breed exhibits a natural ambling 4-beat gait.","answer":"Rocky Mountain Horse (FYI:  The Saddlebred breed association was formed in 1891.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm135-2; DET235"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"817","question":"Give 3 breed characteristics of the American Saddlebred.","answer":"Long arched neck, refined head, small ears, height at the withers higher than the height at the hips, high action, gaits (stepping pace and rack), well-defined withers, level croup, high tail carriage  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-3"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"intermediate","number":"818","question":"In what city and state is the breed headquarters for the American Saddlebred Horse Association?","answer":"Lexington, Kentucky (FYI:  It’s located at the Kentucky Horse Park.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH169B-2"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"819","question":"Name 3 colors of the American Saddlebred.","answer":"ANY COLOR, black, bay, brown, chestnut, gray, palomino, buckskin, roan, pinto (FYI:  Chestnut is the most common color.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-3; HIH156-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"820","question":"What are the color restrictions of the American Saddlebred Horse?","answer":"NO color restrictions  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH169B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"822","question":"Describe the color of the Golden American Saddlebred.","answer":"Palomino (Body color is yellow or golden; mane and tail are white or flaxen.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH164B-2; DET122"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"823","question":"What phrase is commonly used to describe the American Saddlebred?","answer":"Peacock of the Show Ring (also accept Peacock of the Show World)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm135-3"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"824","question":"In what US state did the American Saddlebred originate?","answer":"Kentucky (FYI:  The Saddlebred was originally known as the Kentucky Saddler.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET9; HSm115-3; HIH169B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"825","question":"What was the original name of the American Saddlebred?","answer":"Kentucky Saddler (also accept American Horse)  <br/> <br/>ref:TH29; HSm115-3"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"826","question":"Giving only one number, how tall is the American Saddlebred?","answer":"16 hands (accept any number within the 15 – 17 hand rage)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-3"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"827","question":"Identify the following breed:  looks like a longer, more-muscled Thoroughbred; often used for police work due to its “bombproof” personality; often bay in color; most commonly used for harness racing.","answer":"Standardbred  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-4"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"828","question":"99% of all Standardbreds trace to which stallion?","answer":"Hambletonian  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH171B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"829","question":"Name the breed that includes the following famous names in its history:  Messenger, Greyhound, Hambletonian, Dan Patch, and Niatross.","answer":"Standardbred  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH171B-1; HSm175-11"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"830","question":"Messenger, a gray Thoroughbred, is generally considered to be the foundation sire of which breed?","answer":"Standardbred  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH171B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"831","question":"Name ONE of the predominant colors of the Standardbred.","answer":"Bay, brown, or black  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-4; HIH171B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"832","question":"Which breed is used primarily for harness racing?","answer":"Standardbred  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH171B-1; HSm115-4; HSm135-4"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"833","question":"What are the TWO racing gaits of the Standardbred?","answer":"Trot and pace  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-4; HIH160-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"834","question":"What is the term for a Standardbred that races with a diagonal gait?","answer":"Trotter (FYI: 80% of Standardbred racehorses are pacers. The pace is faster than the trot.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-4; HIH171B"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"835","question":"Today's Standardbreds are able to trot or pace at what speed?","answer":"30 miles per hour  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH171B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"intermediate","number":"836","question":"What is the origination of the name Standardbred?","answer":"Horse had to trot (or pace) a mile in a standard amount of time in order to be registered.  (FYI:  The standard amount of time was 2 ½ minutes or less. Pacers came into registry later.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH171B-1; HH59"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"837","question":"Giving only one number, how tall is the Standardbred?","answer":"15 hands (FYI:  Height range is 14 – 17 hands; average height is 15 – 16 hands.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-4; HIH171B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"838","question":"Giving only one number, what is the weight of the Standardbred?","answer":"1000 pounds (accept any number between 900 – 1100 pounds)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-4; HIH171B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"intermediate","number":"839","question":"Name TWO uses of the Standardbred.","answer":"Harness racing, driving, police horse, jumping, eventing, dressage, trail riding, showing, pleasure, all around family horse  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-4"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"840","question":"Which breed does the United States Trotting Association represent?","answer":"Standardbred  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH171B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"841","question":"What is the name of the breed association for the Standardbred?","answer":"United States Trotting Association  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH171B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"842","question":"Giving only one number, how tall is the Tennessee Walking Horse?","answer":"15 hands (accept any number within the 14.2 – 17 hand range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-1; HIH172B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"843","question":"Name 3 breeds that contributed to the development of the Tennessee Walking Horse.","answer":"Standardbred, Morgan, Thoroughbred, American Saddle Horses (Saddlebreds), Canadian Pacer, Narragansett Pacer  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH172B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"novice","number":"844","question":"In what US state did the Tennessee Walking Horse originate?","answer":"Tennessee  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm135-1; HIH172B-1; HH58"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"845","question":"Which breed nods its head in rhythm with its walk?","answer":"Tennessee Walking Horse (FYI:  Nodding its head and overstriding—where the rear feet overstep the prints of the front feet—are two distinguishing characteristics of the Tennessee Walking Horse.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-2; HIH152-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"846","question":"The Tennessee Walking Horse was crossed with what other breed to develop the American Walking Pony?","answer":"Welsh Pony  <br/> <br/>ref:DET10"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"847","question":"Allan P-1, formerly known as Black Allan, was the foundation sire of which breed?","answer":"Tennessee Walking Horse  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH162B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"848","question":"What is a \"light\" horse?","answer":"Horse used primarily for riding or driving; all breeds except draft; a saddle horse (accept any)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET168; HH9"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"849","question":"What is the term for any horse used primarily for riding, all breeds except draft breeds?","answer":"Light horse  <br/> <br/>ref:DET168; HH9"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"850","question":"What is a \"combination horse\"?","answer":"Horse used for both riding and driving  <br/> <br/>ref:DET62; HH40"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"851","question":"In reference to horse breeds, what does the term \"hot-blooded\" mean?","answer":"Horse of Eastern or Oriental blood (FYI:  Examples are Arabians and Thoroughbreds.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-1; DET144; HH56"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"852","question":"What is the term for a horse of Eastern or Oriental blood?","answer":"Hot-blooded  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-1; DET144; HH56"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"853","question":"Name 3 characteristics of hot-blooded horse breeds.","answer":"Lighter build, thinner hair coat, more spirited disposition, faster speed, endurance over long distances, origin from hot climates  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"854","question":"Name ONE breed used as a foundation for developing many modern breeds.","answer":"Arabian, Thoroughbred, Morgan  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH153B-1; HIH173B-1; HIH162B-1; HH56"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"855","question":"Name the breed associated with 3 of the following horses: Figure, Hambletonian, Black Hand, Black Allan, and Janus.","answer":"Figure—Morgan; Hambletonian—Standardbred; Black Hand—POA; Black Allan, who was later known as Allan F-1—Tennessee Walking Horse; Janus—Quarter Horse  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH162B-1; HIH171B-1; HIH167B-1; HIH172B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"856","question":"Name 3 stock horse breeds.","answer":"Quarter Horse, Paint, Appaloosa, Australian Stock Horse (FYI:  A stock horse is a breed that is well suited for working with livestock such as cattle.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-2; HSm130-3; HSm115-3; HIH220-7"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"857","question":"Identify this breed: able to withstand severe weather in its countries of origin Turkmenistan and Russia; known for its stubbornness, speed, jumping ability, and metallic coat sheen.","answer":"Akhal-Teke  <br/> <br/>ref:DET6; HSm130-10; HSm110-4"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"858","question":"Cave drawings of what spotted breed can be dated back as far as 20,000 years ago in Europe and Asia?","answer":"Appaloosa  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH152B-1; HH56"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"859","question":"Mottled skin, striped hooves, and sclera around the eye are all characteristics of which breed?","answer":"Appaloosa or POA (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH152B-1; HSm115-3; HIH167B-2; HH59"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"860","question":"Name ONE breed that characteristically has vertically striped hooves.","answer":"Appaloosa; POA (Pony of the Americas)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH152B-1; HSm115-3; HIH167B-2; HH59"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"861","question":"Name 3 characteristics of Appaloosas.","answer":"Mottled skin, white sclera around the eyes, vertically striped hooves, approved coat pattern  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH152B-1; HSm115-3; HH59"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"862","question":"What breed was developed by the Nez Perce Indians?","answer":"Appaloosa  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH152B-1; HH59"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"863","question":"What breed has its headquarters in Moscow, Idaho?","answer":"Appaloosa  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH152B-2; HH59"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"864","question":"Historians believe that which Native American tribe was the first to practice selective breeding?","answer":"Nez Perce  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH152B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"865","question":"In what 3 western states was the Appaloosa developed?","answer":"Oregon, Washington, and Idaho  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH152B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"866","question":"What breed was formerly known as the \"Palouse Horse\"?","answer":"Appaloosa  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH152B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"867","question":"What is the origination of the name \"Appaloosa\"?","answer":"Slurring of the words \"a Palouse\" (refers to the Palouse region where the breed was developed)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH152B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"868","question":"With which Appaloosa coat pattern does the horse have a solid-colored body with white over the hindquarters?","answer":"Blanket or snowcap (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-6; HIH140-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"869","question":"Describe a leopard Appaloosa.","answer":"White background with colored spots (and Appaloosa characteristics)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-6; HIH140-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"870","question":"Name 3 color patterns of the Appaloosa.","answer":"Leopard, blanket or snowcap, blanket with spots, few spot leopard, snowflake, frost, mottled, varnish roan  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-6; HIH167B-2; HIH1040-3"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"871","question":"Name 4 color patterns of the Appaloosa.","answer":"Leopard, blanket or snowcap, blanket with spots, few spot leopard, snowflake, frost, mottled, varnish roan  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-6; HIH167B-2; HIH1040-3"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"872","question":"What breed of horse is sometimes called \"rat-tailed\" because of its characteristic sparse mane and tail?","answer":"Appaloosa  <br/> <br/>ref:ES51"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"873","question":"Which breed consistently outlives other breeds?","answer":"Arabian  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH153B-2"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"874","question":"What is the oldest purebred breed?","answer":"Arabian  <br/> <br/>ref:HH56"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"novice","number":"875","question":"Where did the Arabian horse originate?","answer":"Arabia  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH153B-1; HH56"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"876","question":"Who were the first breeders of Arabians?","answer":"Arabian tribesmen (Bedouins) [pronounced BED-oh-wins]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-1; HIH153B-1; HH56"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"877","question":"The Arabian's Arabic name is Kohl-ani.  Where did it get this name?","answer":"Arabian's skin is the same blue-black color as the kohl that Arabian women wear as eyeliner.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH153B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"878","question":"Name 3 distinguishing characteristics of the Arabian.","answer":"Beautiful head, dished face, fine muzzle, large nostrils, arching neck, high tail carriage, free way of going, great endurance, short coupling, small build, docility (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-1; HIH153B-1; HH56"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"879","question":"Name 4 distinguishing characteristics of the Arabian.","answer":"Beautiful head, dished face, fine muzzle, large nostrils, arching neck, high tail carriage, free way of going, great endurance, short coupling, small build, docility (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-1; HIH153B-1; HH56"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"880","question":"In reference to breed characteristics, what is a “jibbah”?","answer":"Bulge between the eyes of an Arabian  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH153B-2"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"881","question":"Name 3 colors of the Arabian.","answer":"Black, bay, chestnut, gray, occasional roan, occasional white (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-1; HH57"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"882","question":"What color skin does the Arabian always have?","answer":"Dark (Also except black or bluish-black.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-1; HIH153B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"883","question":"The popularity of Arabians in the US began with the introduction of 45 horses showcased in 1892 at what event?","answer":"Chicago World's Fair  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH153B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"884","question":"Which breed must have an ancestry of 50% or higher of Arabian blood?","answer":"Half-Arabian  <br/> <br/>ref:HH56"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"intermediate","number":"885","question":"What breed of horse is part Arabian and part Thoroughbred?","answer":"Anglo-Arabian (FYI:  An Anglo-Arabian can have any combination of Arabian (greater than 25% but not less than 75%) and Thoroughbred lineage.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm130-1; DET11"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"intermediate","number":"886","question":"What is an Anglo-Arabian?","answer":"Horse that is part Arabian and part Thoroughbred (FYI:  An Anglo-Arabian can have any combination of Arabian (greater than 25% but not less than 75%) and Thoroughbred lineage.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm130-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"887","question":"What is the name of the breed developed in the US that is a cross between a Saddlebred and an Arabian?","answer":"National Show Horse  <br/> <br/>ref:DET188"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"888","question":"Giving only one number, how tall is the Arabian?","answer":"15 hands (accept any number within the 14.0 – 15.1 hand range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-1; HIH153B-2"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"889","question":"Giving only one number, what is the weight of the Arabian?","answer":"1000 pounds (accept any number between 800 – 1100 pounds)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"890","question":"Give ONE use of the Arabian.","answer":"Endurance, show, pleasure, stock, racing, driving, costume classes (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH153B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"891","question":"What TWO breeds were combined in the development of the Azteca?","answer":"Andalusian and Quarter Horse  <br/> <br/>ref:DET19"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"892","question":"Which breed of horse originated in Mexico as a result of crossing Andalusian stallions with Quarter Horse mares?","answer":"Azteca  <br/> <br/>ref:DET19"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"893","question":"Which African breed has existed almost as long as the Arabian breed and was used by the Moors in their conquests?","answer":"Barb (FYI:  Barbs are found in present day Morocco, Tunisia, and Algeria.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm130-7; DET23"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"894","question":"In what area of the world did the Barb originate?","answer":"Northern Africa (in the Barbary States) [FYI:  The Barbary states are current day Morocco, Tunisia, and Algeria.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm130-7; DET23"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"895","question":"What breed of horse originated in the Ural Mountains of Russia? It's well-adapted to cold weather and it’s noted for its long, curly hair coat.","answer":"Bashkir Curly  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-14; DET8"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"896","question":"What is the distinguishing characteristic of the Bashkir Curly?","answer":"Curly hair coat  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-14; DET8"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"intermediate","number":"897","question":"How did the American Bashkir Curly get its name?","answer":"Named after the curly-coated horses raised in the Bashkir region (of the Ural Mountains of Russia)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET8"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"898","question":"From what country did the American Bashkir Curly originate?","answer":"United States (from feral horses in Nevada)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET8"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"899","question":"What breed of horse is ALWAYS bay?","answer":"Cleveland Bay (FYI:  Cleveland Bays are large bay horses from the Cleveland District of Yorkshire, England.  Numbers greatly decreased after WWII.  They are used as carriage horses by the British Royal Stables.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET58"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"900","question":"Which breed originated in England from Norfolk Trotters, Yorkshire Trotters, and Thoroughbreds?","answer":"Hackney Horse (FYI:  The Hackney Pony was developed from crossing Hackney Horses with Fell and Welsh Ponies.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm120-3; HSm130-5; HIH158B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"901","question":"Name 3 distinguishing characteristics of the Lipizzan.","answer":"Agility, temperament, good character, docility, intelligence, strength, sturdy compact body, brilliant action, proud carriage, crested neck, broad back and loins, muscular hindquarters, short strong legs, athletic ability (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm130-4; HIH159B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"intermediate","number":"902","question":"Describe the coloring of the Lipizzan from birth to maturity.","answer":"Born dark and gets lighter each year (appears \"white\" between 6 – 10 years of age)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm130-4; HIH159B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"903","question":"What is the predominant color of the Lipizzan?","answer":"Gray (FYI:  The Spanish Riding School keeps one dark colored Lipizzan in the stables for good luck!)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm130-4; HIH159B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"904","question":"What breed was developed in what is now Slovenia from Spanish horses, Karst Horses, and Old Neapolitan Horses?","answer":"Lipizzan (also accept Lipizzaner)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm130-4,5; HIH159B-2"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"905","question":"Which breed was developed by the Hapsburg family of Austria?","answer":"Lipizzan (also accept Lipizzaner)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm130-4; HIH159B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"906","question":"Which breed is world famous because of its connection with the Spanish Riding School?","answer":"Lipizzan (also accept Lipizzaner) [FYI:  The Spanish Riding School is in Vienna, Austria.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm130-4; HIH159B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"intermediate","number":"907","question":"In what city and country is the Spanish Riding School?","answer":"Vienna, Austria  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm130-4; HIH159B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"908","question":"Name ONE breed that was threatened with extinction during World War II.","answer":"Lipizzan, Dales Pony, Cleveland Bay (FYI: Lipizzan breed and Spanish Riding School were saved by US Army, General Patton, and the director of the Spanish Riding School.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH159B-2; HSm120-6"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"909","question":"In addition to the stallion lines, how many dominant female families are recognized by the Lipizzan registry?","answer":"35 female lines  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH159B-2"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"910","question":"Name 3 classic Lipizzan stallion lines.","answer":"Conversano, Favory, Maestoso, Neapolitano, Pluto, and Siglavy  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH159B-2"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"911","question":"Horses from what European breed must trace directly, without interruption, to the recognized male and female lines?","answer":"Lipizzan (also accept Lipizzaner)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH159B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"912","question":"Giving only one number, how tall is the Lipizzaner?","answer":"15 hands (accept any number within the 14.2 – 15.2 hand range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH159B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"913","question":"What breed of horse is noted for its distinguishing ear carriage where the ears point inward towards each other?","answer":"Marwari (FYI:  The Marwari originated in India in the Marwar region.  The breed possibly descended from Mongolian horses and horses from Iran.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm130-8"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"914","question":"Which breed is the only breed to be named after an individual horse?","answer":"Morgan  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-1; HIH162B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"915","question":"Identify this breed:  essential in the development of other American breeds; USDA had a farm in Middlebury, Vermont; known for its all-purpose abilities on the farm or in the show ring; only breed named after a single horse.","answer":"Morgan  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-1; HIH162B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"916","question":"Name 3 breed characteristics of the Morgan.","answer":"Compact, muscular, refined, expressive eyes, chiseled face, up-headedness, stylish gaits, soundness, power, agility, endurance, easy keeper, docility  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-1; HIH162B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"917","question":"Name 3 colors of the Morgan.","answer":"Black, bay, brown, chestnut (including liver or black chestnut), buckskin, palomino, gray, pinto, dun, perlino, smoky cream (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-1; HIH162B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"918","question":"The dark liver or black chestnut color is most common in which breed?","answer":"Morgan  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"919","question":"In what country did the Morgan breed originate?","answer":"United States (New England, specifically Vermont)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH162B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"920","question":"Who is the foundation sire of the Morgan breed?","answer":"Figure (Justin Morgan)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-1; HIH162B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"921","question":"Who was Figure?","answer":"Foundation sire of the Morgan breed (later called Justin Morgan)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-1; HIH162B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"922","question":"What was the name of the Thoroughbred stallion that was the sire of Figure or Justin Morgan?","answer":"True Briton (FYI:  True Briton was also known as Beautiful Bay and Traveler.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH162B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"923","question":"Giving only one number, how tall is the Morgan?","answer":"15 hands (accept any number within the 14.1 – 15.2 hand range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH162B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"924","question":"A horse of Paint breeding who does NOT meet the color requirements may be registered in the division known as what?","answer":"Breeding Stock Paint (FYI: They are now called Solid Paint-Bred by APHA.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH163B-2"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"925","question":"Name TWO basic requirements for registering an American Paint Horse.","answer":"Must have Paint, Thoroughbred, or Quarter Horse breeding; must meet minimum color requirements  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-3; HIH163B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"926","question":"In reference to breed associations, what does APHA stand for?","answer":"American Paint Horse Association (FYI: Headquarters are in Fort Worth, Texas.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH163B-1; HH56"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"927","question":"In what city and state is the American Paint Horse Association headquarters?","answer":"Fort Worth, Texas  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH159-3; HH56"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"novice","number":"928","question":"Giving only one number, how tall is the Quarter Horse?","answer":"15 hands (accept any number in the 14 – over 17 hands range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH168B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"929","question":"In reference to breed associations, what does AQHA stand for?","answer":"American Quarter Horse Association (FYI:  AQHA was founded in 1940 in Fort Worth, TX, but was later moved to Amarillo.  Wimpy P-1 was the first permanently registered Quarter Horse.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH168B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"novice","number":"930","question":"How did the Quarter Horse get its name?","answer":"From its ability to sprint a quarter mile  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH168B-1; HH59"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"931","question":"In what city and state is the American Quarter Horse Association headquarters located?","answer":"Amarillo, Texas  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH168B-2; HH58"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"932","question":"Which breed is noted for its \"cow sense\"?","answer":"Quarter Horse  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH180D-2; HH59"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"933","question":"Which breed of horse is known for its ability to gain speed in a matter of seconds over short distances?","answer":"Quarter Horse  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-2; HIH168B-1; HH59"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"934","question":"Identify this breed: head is short and broad with large nostrils and short, foxy ears; its disposition is calm; muscling is short, compact, and powerful which gives it the ability to gain speed quickly.","answer":"Quarter Horse  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH168B-1; HH59"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"935","question":"Name 3 distinguishing characteristics of the Quarter Horse.","answer":"Cow sense, compact muscling, speed over short distances, short foxy ears, short broad head, large eyes, calm disposition (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-2; HIH168B-1; HH59"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"936","question":"Name 4 distinguishing characteristics of the Quarter Horse.","answer":"Cow sense, compact muscling, speed over short distances, short foxy ears, short broad head, large eyes, calm disposition (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-2; HIH168B-1; HH59"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"937","question":"What is the most prominent color of the Quarter Horse?","answer":"Sorrel (chestnut)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH168B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"938","question":"What is the small, short-coupled horse named for an Indian tribe that was an ancestor of the Quarter Horse?","answer":"Chickasaw Horse  <br/> <br/>ref:DET55"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"939","question":"In what country was the Quarter Horse breed developed?","answer":"United States (FYI:  Breed was first developed in the colonies (eastern US) for racing short distances; breed was later developed on cattle ranches in Texas.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH168B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"940","question":"Most Quarter Horse foundation sires trace back to which stallion?","answer":"Janus (FYI:  Janus was a Thoroughbred foaled in 1746.  He was the grandson of the Godolphin Arabian.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH173B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"943","question":"What current breed of horse was known as \"Steeldusts\" in the early 1900’s?","answer":"Quarter Horse (FYI:  They were named after Steel Dust, a famous sire foaled in 1843.  He and his progeny were perfect for ranch work and cattle drives in the Western US.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-2; TH16"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"944","question":"Who was the first permanently registered Quarter Horse?","answer":"Wimpy (Wimpy P-1) [FYI: Wimpy was foaled in 1937 on the King Ranch. He was the grandson of Old Sorrel. Because he was the 1941 Grand Champion stallion at the Southwestern Exposition and Fat Stock Show, he was elected to become the first registered QH.]  <br/> <br/>ref:DET292"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"intermediate","number":"945","question":"What breed of horse that is named after a US state often resembles an Appaloosa?","answer":"Colorado Ranger Horse (which is also called the Rangerbred)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET 62"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"947","question":"Where did the Thoroughbred originate?","answer":"England  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm130-5; HIH173B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"intermediate","number":"948","question":"To which breed does the term \"bloodhorse\" refer?","answer":"Thoroughbred  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-5; DET32"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"949","question":"Who are the 3 foundation sires of the Thoroughbred?","answer":"Darley Arabian, Godolphin Arabian, and Byerly Turk  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm175-2; DET266"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"intermediate","number":"950","question":"What do the Darley Arabian, Byerly Turk, and Godolphin Arabian have in common?","answer":"Foundation sires of the Thoroughbred  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm175-2; DET266"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"951","question":"What was the name of the first Thoroughbred stallion imported to the US?","answer":"Bulle Rock (FYI:  Bulle Rock was foaled in 1709 and imported to the US in 1730.  His sire was the Darley Arabian.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-5"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"952","question":"To what famous Thoroughbred, unbeaten in 24 races in 1764, do 90% of all modern Thoroughbreds trace their ancestry?","answer":"Eclipse (FYI: Eclipse’s topline traces back to Darley Arabian and its distaff side traces back to Godolphin Arabian.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET88"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"953","question":"Name ONE country, other than the US, whose Thoroughbred foals are registered with the Jockey Club.","answer":"Canada; Puerto Rico  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm175-3; HIH173B-2; DET10"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"954","question":"Which breed is represented by the Jockey Club?","answer":"Thoroughbred  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm175-3; HIH173B-2; DET10"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"955","question":"What breed organization is responsible for the American Stud Book?","answer":"Jockey Club  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm175-3; HIH173B-2; DET10"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"956","question":"Which breed of horse is in the American Stud Book?","answer":"Thoroughbred  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm175-3; HIH173B-2; DET10"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"957","question":"The American Stud Book is a register of Thoroughbred horses from what 3 countries?","answer":"US, Canada, and Puerto Rico  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm175-3; HIH173B-2; DET10"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"intermediate","number":"958","question":"The Thoroughbred exceeds other breeds at racing over what distance?","answer":"6 furlongs (3/4 mile) – 1 ½ miles (12 furlongs) [accept any number within these ranges]  <br/> <br/>ref:HH59"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"novice","number":"961","question":"Giving only one number, what is the weight of the Thoroughbred?","answer":"1100 pounds (accept any number between 1000 – 1250 pounds)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-5; HIH173B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"962","question":"Giving only one number, how tall is the Thoroughbred?","answer":"16 hands (accept any number in the 15.2 – 17 hand range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-5"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"963","question":"Which breed was developed from small English and Dutch mine horses?","answer":"Miniature Horse  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH160B-1; HH56"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"964","question":"Where did the Falabella originate?","answer":"Argentina  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm120-10; DET103"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"965","question":"Which one of the following breeds would NOT be considered a pony breed:  Exmoor, Falabella, or Trottingbred?","answer":"Falabella  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm120-10; DET103"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"966","question":"What is the small horse breed from Argentina that’s noted for its excellent conformation and its extremely small size?","answer":"Falabella  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm120-10; DET103"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"967","question":"Approximately how much does an average mature American Miniature Horse weigh?","answer":"300 pounds (accept any number between 200 – 350 pounds)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-3"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"968","question":"What is the maximum height for a horse registered in the American Miniature Horse Association?","answer":"34 inches (FYI: American Miniature Horse REGISTRY Division B horses are 34 – 38 inches tall.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-3; HIH160B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"969","question":"An American Miniature Horse is registered on a temporary basis until it reaches 3 years of age. What requirement must it meet at that time to be permanently registered in the American Miniature Horse Association?","answer":"Not exceed the 34-inch height requirement (FYI:  For the AMHA, height must not exceed 34-inches at 3 years of age.  For the AMHR, Division A Minis are up to 34 inches and Division B Minis are between 34 and 38 inches tall.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-3; HIH160B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"970","question":"What is the average height for a newborn Miniature Horse?","answer":"18 inches  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-2"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"971","question":"How much does a Miniature Horse foal weigh at birth?","answer":"20 pounds (accept any number between 15 – 30 pounds)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-2"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"972","question":"Give 4 uses of the Miniature Horse.","answer":"Companions, driving, circus, in-hand jumping, in-hand trail, halter, showmanship (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH160B-1; HH57"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"973","question":"Give 3 uses of the Miniature Horse.","answer":"Companions, driving, circus, in-hand jumping, in-hand trail, halter, showmanship (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH160B-1; HH57"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"intermediate","number":"974","question":"What is the term for the offspring of a mule and hinny?","answer":"A miracle! (It's impossible because both are sterile.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-11; HIH156B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"intermediate","number":"975","question":"By looking at the tail, how can you tell if an equine is a donkey or a mule?","answer":"Donkeys have tails with tufts of hair at the end; mules have more horse-like tails.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-11; HIH156B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"976","question":"What is the term for the vocal sound made by a jack?","answer":"Bray  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-11; DET37"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"977","question":"What type of equine is known for having a dorsal stripe that is intersected by the arms of a cross at the withers?","answer":"Donkey  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-11; HIH156B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"978","question":"Give 4 differences between a horse and a donkey.","answer":"Donkey has longer ears, sparser mane and tail, stiffer and more upright mane, smaller hooves, rounder hooves, straighter neck and back, fewer chestnuts, lighter color muzzle and underbelly, shorter gestation period, and brays instead of whinnies.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-11; HIH156B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"979","question":"What is the legend associated with the cross on the donkey's back?","answer":"Donkey's reward for carrying Jesus to Jerusalem (also accept for carrying Mary to Bethlehem)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-6,7"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"980","question":"What is the term for a male donkey?","answer":"Jack  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-11; HIH156B-1; HSc21; TH45"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"981","question":"What is the term for a female donkey?","answer":"Jenny or jennet (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-11; HIH156B-1; HSc21; TH45"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"982","question":"What is the COMMON name for a female of the species Equus asinus?","answer":"Jenny or jennet (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:ES16; HSm140-4; HSm125-11; HIH156B-1; HSc21; TH45"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"983","question":"Name 4 of the classifications of donkeys based on size.","answer":"Miniature Mediterranean (36 inches and under), Small Standard, Standard, Large Standard, and Mammoth  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-11; TH46"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"984","question":"Give 3 differences between a horse and a donkey.","answer":"Donkey has longer ears, sparser mane and tail, stiffer and more upright mane, smaller hooves, rounder hooves, straighter neck and back, fewer chestnuts, lighter color muzzle and underbelly, shorter gestation period, and brays instead of whinnies.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-11; HIH156B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"989","question":"What is a cross between a stallion and a jennet?","answer":"Hinny  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-11; HIH156B-1; HSc21"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"990","question":"Where did the Miniature Donkey originate?","answer":"Mediterranean area (FYI:  North Africa and cost of Italy; Sicily and Sardinia)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-11; TH46"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"991","question":"What is a mule?","answer":"Cross between a jack and a mare  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-11; HIH156B-1; HSc21"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"992","question":"Who was the first breeder of mules in North America?","answer":"George Washington  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-12; HH56"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"993","question":"Explain the difference in the parentage of a mule and a hinny.","answer":"Mule is a cross between a jack and a mare; hinny is a cross between a stallion and a jenny or jennet.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-11; HIH156B-1; HSc21"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"994","question":"What is the result of breeding a horse to a donkey?","answer":"Mule or hinny (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-11; HSc21"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"995","question":"Name 3 uses of mules.","answer":"Saddle, packing, draft or farm work, driving, showing, pets (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-11; HIH156B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"996","question":"Name 4 uses of mules.","answer":"Saddle, packing, draft or farm work, driving, showing, pets (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-11; HIH156B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"intermediate","number":"997","question":"2-part question:  What are the common names for a male mule and a female mule?","answer":"Male mule is called a John; female mule is called a Molly.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-11"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"998","question":"What would be the result of crossing a zebra and a horse?","answer":"Zebrass (also accept zorse or zebroid)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET298"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"999","question":"Name 3 AMERICAN breeds of pony.","answer":"POA (Pony of Americas), Chincoteague, Quarter Pony, American Gaited Pony, American Shetland Pony, American Walking Pony, North American Sport Pony, Banker, Corolla  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm120; HIH167B; HH58"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1000","question":"You are looking at a sale poster for a pretty chestnut mare.  The information states that the animal is 57 inches tall.  Is the mare a horse or a pony?","answer":"Pony (FYI: The dividing line is 58 inches or 14.2 hands.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm130-2"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"1001","question":"Name 3 breeds of pony that originated in the UNITED KINGDOM.","answer":"Shetland, Welsh, Hackney, Exmoor, Dartmoor, Dales, Fell, Eriskay, Highland, New Forest  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm120"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"1002","question":"Name 3 breeds of pony.","answer":"Shetland, Welsh, Connemara, POA, Hackney, Chincoteague, Exmoor, Dales, Quarter Pony, New Forest, American Sport Pony, Dartmoor, Fells, Gotland (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm120"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"1003","question":"Name 5 breeds of pony.","answer":"Shetland, Welsh, Connemara, POA, Hackney, Chincoteague, Exmoor, Dales, Quarter Pony, New Forest, American Sport Pony, Dartmoor, Fells, Gotland (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm120"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"intermediate","number":"1004","question":"Which pony breed originated in County Galway, Ireland?","answer":"Connemara  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm120-6; DET67"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"intermediate","number":"1005","question":"Where did the Connemara Pony originate?","answer":"Ireland (County Galway)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm120-6; DET67"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"intermediate","number":"1006","question":"Connemara ponies are noted for what ability?","answer":"Jumping ability  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm120-7; DET67"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"intermediate","number":"1007","question":"Giving only one number, how tall is the Connemara Pony?","answer":"14 hands (accept any number within the 13 – 15 hand range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm120-6; DET67"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1008","question":"Name this breed of pony:  known for its solid build, endurance, and calm, agreeable nature; used as pack ponies in the lead mining industry; originated in the dales of Great Britain.","answer":"Dales Pony  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm120-6; DET77"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1009","question":"From where did the Exmoor Pony get its name?","answer":"Moorlands known as Exmoor (in southwest England)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm120-8; HIH157B-1; DET101"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1010","question":"Name TWO characteristics Exmoor ponies developed that help them survive harsh winter conditions.","answer":"Double-layered winter coat; toad eye (fleshy eyelids to keep out elements); snow chute tail (short hairs at the base of the tail to keep out elements)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm120-8; HIH157B-1,2"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"1011","question":"Give 3 characteristics of the Exmoor Pony.","answer":"Primitive coat pattern (buff coloring around eyes, muzzle, belly and flank), broad forehead, toad or hooded eye (fleshy eyelids), low tail set, double layer coat, snow chute or ice tail (short hairs at the base of the tail), uniformity of appearance  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm120-8; HIH157B-1,2"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1012","question":"What is meant by the term \"toad eye\" or \"hooded eye\"?","answer":"Thick or fleshy eyelids (that keep out the wind and rain) [CORRECTED 2021]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm120-8; HIH157B-1,2"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1013","question":"Which breed can be traced through archeological records to England over 60,000 years ago, making it a contemporary of the Przewalski’s Horse?","answer":"Exmoor Pony  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH157B-1; HSm120-8"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1014","question":"What is Britain’s oldest pony breed?  It has existed since the Stone Age and has been referred to as a \"living fossil\".","answer":"Exmoor Pony (FYI:  The earliest written records of the Exmoor Pony are in the Doomsday Book of 1085.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm120-8; HIH157B-1; DET101"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"1015","question":"Name 3 things that are considered signs of impurity and will result in denying registration for an Exmoor Pony.","answer":"White markings; white hairs on the body, mane, or tail; hooves with white soles  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH157B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1016","question":"Giving only one number, how tall is the Exmoor Pony?","answer":"12 hands (accept any number within the 11.2 – 12.3 hand range) [CORRECTED 2018]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm120-8; HIH157B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"1017","question":"Name 3 of the 5 types of dun coloring in the Fjord breed.","answer":"Brown dun (brunblakk, 90%), red dun (rødblakk), grey dun (grå; grulla), white dun or uls dun (ulsblakk), yellow dun (gulblakk; rarest)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-10,11"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1018","question":"Describe the coloring of the Fjord.","answer":"Dun with dun characteristics of mane and tail frosting, dorsal stripes,  and zebra stripes  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-10,11; DET108"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"1019","question":"Name 3 breed characteristics of the Fjord.","answer":"Dun, primitive markings (dorsal stripe, transverse stripe, zebra stripes), pangare effect (lighter hair on muzzle, belly, inside of legs, over eyes), mane frosting, dark mane strip (midstol), dark middle tail hair (halefjaer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-10,11; DET108"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1020","question":"Identify this breed: sometimes used as a pack animal; resembles the wild horses of the Ice Age; dun color with black and silver mane and tail and dun markings; country of origin is Norway.","answer":"Fjord  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-10,11; DET108"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"1021","question":"Identify the following breed:  This pony-sized equine originated in Spain as a result of Spanish Jennet and Barb breeding. It performs four natural gaits that include the walk, trot, canter, and running walk.","answer":"Galiceño (pronounced gal-ee-SANE-yo)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm120-9; DET117"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1022","question":"What are the colors of the Galiceño? (pronounced gal-ee-SANE-yo)","answer":"All SOLID colors (NO spotted horses, pintos, Appaloosa patterns)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm120-9"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1023","question":"The Galiceño may naturally trot and/or exhibit which other intermediate gait? (pronounced gal-ee-SANE-yo)","answer":"Running walk  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm120-9; DET117"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1024","question":"Where did the Galiceño breed originate? (pronounced gal-ee-SANE-yo)","answer":"Spain (FYI:  It was formerly known as the Galicia Mountain Pony.  Breed is now in southern Mexico.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm120-9; DET117"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1025","question":"Giving only one number, how tall is the Galiceño? (pronounced gal-ee-SANE-yo)","answer":"13 hands (accept any number within the 12 – 13.2 hand range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm120-9; DET117"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1026","question":"In reference to horse and pony breeds, where did the Gotland originate?","answer":"Sweden  <br/> <br/>ref:DET123"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1027","question":"Name ONE use of the Hackney Pony.","answer":"Driving; shown in harness (single, pairs, or tandem); shown in Roadster (harnessed to a road “bike”); Roadster Under Saddle; shown in hand (weanlings, yearlings, and two-year olds)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm120-3; HIH158B-2"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1028","question":"Name ONE breed that was crossed with the Hackney horse to produce the Hackney pony.","answer":"Fell Pony; Welsh Pony (CORRECTED 2021)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm120-3; HIH158B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"1029","question":"Name 3 show classifications of Hackney ponies.","answer":"Roadster pony (under 13 hands), Hackney or Cobtail pony (14.2 hands and under), Harness or Longtail pony (12.2 hands and under), Pleasure pony (docked or long tail; 14.2 hands and under); In-Hand Pony (weanlings, yearlings, and 2 year olds)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm120-3"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"1030","question":"Name 3 breed characteristics of the Haflinger.","answer":"54 – 60 inches (13.2 – 15 hands), heavy-boned, light chestnut or golden-colored with a white mane and tail, white face markings are desirable, long-lived, people-loving, willing, forgiving temperament  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-9"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1031","question":"Where did the Haflinger originate?","answer":"Austria (FYI: Haflingers are from the South Tyrol region of Austria and northern Italy and are named for the Tyrolean village of Halfing.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-9"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1032","question":"What is the small, general purpose mountain horse from Austria that resembles a small Belgian?","answer":"Haflinger  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-9"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"intermediate","number":"1033","question":"What is the only breed to originate from Iceland?","answer":"Icelandic horse (FYI:  The Icelandic horse is a hardy, sturdy, pony-sized horse that performs two additional gaits, the tolt and the flying pace.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm135-4; DET149"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1034","question":"What is the country of origin for the New Forest Pony?","answer":"England  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm120-8; DET190"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1035","question":"What is the primary use of the POA?","answer":"Children's mount (FYI: POA is the Pony of the Americas.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH167B-1; HH59"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1036","question":"Referring to horse breeds, what do the letters POA mean?","answer":"Pony of the Americas  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm120-1; HIH167B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1037","question":"In what country was the POA or Pony of the Americas breed developed?","answer":"United States (Mason City, Iowa)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH167B-1; HH58"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"1038","question":"Name 3 characteristics of the POA.","answer":"Mottled skin, white sclera around the eyes, vertically striped hooves, approved coat pattern, size (46 – 56 inches)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-5; HIH167B-1,2; HH59"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1039","question":"Identify this PONY breed:  mottled skin around the muzzle and eyes, white sclera encircling the eyes, vertically striped hooves, and an approved coat pattern.","answer":"POA (Pony of the Americas)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-5; HIH167B-1,2; HH59"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"novice","number":"1040","question":"Which breed of pony is colored similar to an Appaloosa?","answer":"POA (Pony of the Americas)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-5; HIH167B-1,2; HH59"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"intermediate","number":"1041","question":"Who was Black Hand?","answer":"Foundation sire of the POA  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-5; HIH167B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"intermediate","number":"1042","question":"Black Hand was the foundation sire of the POA breed.  How did Black Hand get his name?","answer":"Spots on his flank formed an image of a black handprint.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-5; HIH167B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1043","question":"Giving only one number, how tall is the POA or Pony of the Americas?","answer":"46 – 56 inches (11.2 – 14 hands; accept any number within these ranges)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-5; HIH167B-1; HH59"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1044","question":"Give ONE use of the Shetland Pony.","answer":"Children's mount, driving, in-hand classes, racing in the UK, pleasure, therapeutic  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm120-2; HH59"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"novice","number":"1045","question":"Where did the Shetland Pony originate?","answer":"Shetland Isles (off the coast of Scotland)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm120-1; HH59"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"novice","number":"1046","question":"What pony originated in the Shetland Isles?","answer":"Shetland Pony (FYI:  The Shetlands Isles are off the northern coast of Scotland and are part of the United Kingdom—Great Britain (England, Wales, and Scotland) and Northern Ireland.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm120-1; HH59"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"1047","question":"Name 3 types of Shetland Ponies.","answer":"Foundation (max 42”), Classic American (max 46”), Modern American (under 43” and 43 – 46”), Modern Pleasure (under 43” and 43 – 46”), Standard in UK ( over 34 – 42”), Miniature in UK (34” and under)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm120-1; HH59"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"novice","number":"1048","question":"What are the colors of the Shetland Pony?","answer":"ALL colors  <br/> <br/>ref:HH59"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"intermediate","number":"1049","question":"What is the UPPER height limit for an American Shetland Pony?","answer":"46 inches (FYI:  The maximum height is 46 inches for the American Shetland Pony and 42 inches for Shetland ponies in the UK.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm120-2; HH59"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1050","question":"Name ONE distinguishing characteristic of the Shetland Pony.","answer":"Small size; great strength; hardiness (FYI:  The maximum height is 46 inches for the American Shetland Pony and 42 inches for Shetland ponies in the UK.  Shetland ponies can pull twice their weight.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm120-1,2; HH59"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1051","question":"Where did the Welsh Pony originate?","answer":"Wales  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm120-3; HIH175B-1; HH59"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1052","question":"What color pattern is NOT permitted in the Welsh Pony breed?","answer":"Any spotted patterns (piebald, skewbald, or leopard)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm120-4; HIH175B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"1053","question":"Name 3 sections of the Welsh Pony and Cob registry.","answer":"Welsh Mountain Pony (Section A); Welsh Pony (Section  B); Welsh Pony of Cob Type (Section C); Welsh Cob (Section D) (accept either the name or the section)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm120-4; HIH175B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"intermediate","number":"1054","question":"What is a Welsh Cob?","answer":"Larger version of the Welsh Pony or Section D (over 13.2 hands with no upper height limit)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm120-4; HIH175B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"intermediate","number":"1055","question":"What is the upper height limit for a Welsh Cob?","answer":"No upper height limit (FYI:  Must exceed 13.2 hands; has no upper height limit.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm120-5; HIH175B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1056","question":"What is the height limit in the UNITED KINGDOM for a Section A Welsh Mountain Pony?","answer":"12 hands (FYI:  The height limit in the US is 12.2 hands.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm120-4; HIH175B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1057","question":"What is another name for the Section A Welsh Pony?","answer":"Welsh Mountain Pony (FYI:  The 4 divisions of the Welsh Pony are Section A Welsh Mountain Pony, Section B Welsh Pony, Section C Welsh Pony of Cob Type, and Section D Welsh Cob. The Section A Welsh Mountain Pony is not to exceed 12 hands.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm120-4; HIH175B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1058","question":"What is the term for a group of horses having common origin and possessing certain traits that are passed on to their offspring?","answer":"Breed  <br/> <br/>ref:DET38; HH56"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"novice","number":"1059","question":"Name ONE basic difference between breeds of horses.","answer":"Body type, coloring, markings, gaits, size, location and amount of muscling (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-2; HIH220-8"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1060","question":"Body type, color patterns, gaits, and way of going are all examples of what type characteristics?","answer":"Breed characteristics  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-2; HIH220-8"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1061","question":"What is the term for the characteristics that are unique to a particular breed?","answer":"Breed characteristics  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-2; HIH220-8; HH56"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1062","question":"What is the difference between the terms breed characteristics and sex characteristics?","answer":"Breed characteristics are characteristics that are unique to a breed (such as body type, color patterns, and gaits); sex characteristics refer to masculinity in males and femininity in females.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-2; HIH220-8; HH56"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1063","question":"What is a breed standard?","answer":"Standard of excellence set up by an association for its breed  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1064","question":"In reference to BREED TYPES, give ONE definition of a broomtail.","answer":"Western range horse; ill-kept horse of inferior quality (FYI:  Horses and Horsemanship defines “broom-tailed” as a heavy, coarse tail.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET41"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1065","question":"What is the term for a short-legged horse that's built like a heavyweight hunter and is capable of carrying a substantial weight?","answer":"Cob  <br/> <br/>ref:DET60"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1066","question":"What is the term for a horse that has parents of different breeds?","answer":"Crossbred  <br/> <br/>ref:DET73; HH56"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1067","question":"What is a crossbred?","answer":"Horse with parents of two different breeds  <br/> <br/>ref:DET73; HH56"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1068","question":"What is the term for a group of animals within a breed that trace directly to a common ancestor?","answer":"Family  <br/> <br/>ref:DET104; HH56"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1069","question":"What term is used to identify the original horses used in a breeding program?","answer":"Foundation stock  <br/> <br/>ref:DET113"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1070","question":"What is the term for a horse of unknown breeding or ancestry?","answer":"Grade  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH110-5; DET123; HH56"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1071","question":"What is a grade animal?","answer":"Unregistered horse or horse with unknown ancestry (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH110-5; DET123; HH56"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1072","question":"What is the term for a horse ridden to a hunt meet, a pleasure ride, or a riding horse for hire?","answer":"Hack  <br/> <br/>ref:DET127; HH39"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1073","question":"What is the term for a horse that’s used to chase foxes and jump over fences?","answer":"Hunter (also accept hack)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET144"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1074","question":"What is a pedigree?","answer":"Written record of an animal's ancestry  <br/> <br/>ref:DET207; HH56"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"1075","question":"What term refers to the female side of the pedigree?","answer":"Distaff (bottom line) [FYI:  The sire's side of the pedigree is the \"top line\".]  <br/> <br/>ref:DET82"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1076","question":"What part of a pedigree is referred to as the \"top line\"?","answer":"Stallion side (FYI: The female side is the distaff side or bottom line.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET271"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1077","question":"What is the term for a horse whose parents are recorded in the same breed association?","answer":"Purebred  <br/> <br/>ref:DET223; HH56"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1078","question":"What is the term for recording an animal from registered parents in a breed association?","answer":"Registration  <br/> <br/>ref:DET231"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1079","question":"What is a written record of an animal's ancestry that's issued by the registry association?","answer":"Registration certificate  <br/> <br/>ref:HH58"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1080","question":"What is a written record of an animal's ancestry?  It may or may not be used to refer to a registration certificate.","answer":"Pedigree  <br/> <br/>ref:DET207; HH56"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1081","question":"What is a registry association?","answer":"Organization formed for the purpose of keeping records of the ancestry of individuals within a breed and to promote the breed (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH58"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1082","question":"What is a studbook?","answer":"Register of all horses foaled for a breed (record book published by the breed registry association for purebred horses, ponies, or jacks)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH58"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"novice","number":"1083","question":"What is recognized as the universal birthdate for many breeds?","answer":"January 1st (FYI: The universal birthdate in the southern hemisphere is August 1st.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-5"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1084","question":"The Hanoverian, Oldenburg, and Holsteiner breeds developed in which country?","answer":"Germany (FYI:  Trakehners are now German horses, but they were originally from Prussia which was a German state on the Baltic Sea.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm130-5; DET273; DET141; DET128"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"1085","question":"Name 3 German Warmblood breeds.","answer":"Hanoverian, Holsteiner, Trakehner, Oldenburg [FYI:  The Trakehner was originally from Trakehnen in East Prussia, which is now in a section of Russia between Poland and Lithuania.]  <br/> <br/>ref:DET273; DET141; DET128; DET195"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1086","question":"In reference to horses, what is a Warmblood?","answer":"Horse that is a combination of hot-blooded and cold-blooded breeds.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH151B-1; HSm125-1; DET287"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"1087","question":"The American Warmblood Society (AWS) is focused on the qualities and/or performance of the sport horse. What are 3 disciplines that the AWS supports?","answer":"Dressage, Show Jumping, Eventing, Combined Driving (FYI:  AWS registers ponies and horses 12.2 hands and over.  AWS focuses on the qualities of sport horses and ponies instead of their sizes and breeding.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH151B-1,2"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"intermediate","number":"1088","question":"What color is the Friesian?","answer":"Black (FYI: Solid black with no white markings is preferred.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-8; DET114"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1089","question":"What breed of horse was developed in Northern Holland as a war horse, has a distinctive flowing trot, and is described as a black horse with feathering on the legs?","answer":"Friesian (FYI:  Friesians may have small white stars on their foreheads.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-8; DET115"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1090","question":"Where did the Friesian originate?","answer":"Holland (Netherlands)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-8; DET114"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"1091","question":"Which breed was developed by crossing the Thoroughbred and Irish Draft breeds?","answer":"Irish Hunter, Irish Sport Horse, or Irish Warmblood (accept any)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET155"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1092","question":"Giving only one number, how tall is the Trakehner? (pronounced tra-KAY-ner)","answer":"16 hands (accept any number within the 16 – 17 hand range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH174B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1093","question":"Because of its elegant way of moving, the Trakehner excels in what discipline? (pronounced tra-KAY-ner)","answer":"Dressage  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH174B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1094","question":"What breed is branded on the left hip with a double moose antler brand?","answer":"Trakehner (pronounced tra-KAY-ner)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH174B-2"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1095","question":"What are the 3 main colors of horses that provide the basis for many other coat colors?","answer":"Bay, black, chestnut (FYI:  Horses and Horsemanship states there are 5 basic coat colors—black, bay, brown, sorrel or chestnut, and white.  The base colors of black, bay, and chestnut can be modified with dilutions, spotting, roaning, and graying.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1040-1; HSm510-3"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"sr bonus","number":"1096","question":"Name 3 base colors that can be modified with dilutions, roaning, and spotting.","answer":"Black, chestnut, and bay  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105; HIH1040; HH5"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1097","question":"What color is a horse that has a reddish-brown body and a black mane and tail?","answer":"Bay  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-1; HIH140-1; HH4"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1098","question":"What is the difference in coloring between a bay and a chestnut?","answer":"Bays have black points (mane, tail, and lower legs); chestnuts have red, reddish-brown, or flaxen manes and tails.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-1; HIH140-1; HH4"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1099","question":"Describe the color bay.","answer":"Body is reddish-brown; mane, tail, and lower legs (points) are black.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-1; HIH140-1; HH4"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1100","question":"You are looking at two horses.  Both are reddish-brown.  One has black points and the other does not.  What are the basic colors of these horses?","answer":"Horse with black points is a bay; other horse is a chestnut or sorrel.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-1; HIH140-1; HH4"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1101","question":"What color horse has a black body, black mane and tail, and NO areas of brown?","answer":"Black  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-1; HIH140-1; HH4"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1102","question":"Many brown horses are mistakenly called what color?","answer":"Black  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-2; HIH140-1; HH4"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1103","question":"How can you tell whether a horse is black or seal brown?","answer":"Black horses have no areas of brown; seal brown horses have tan or brown hairs on their muzzle, flanks, and/or buttocks.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-1,2; HIH140-1; HH4"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1104","question":"What color horse has a black mane and tail and a body color of black with brown areas on the muzzle, eyes, flanks, and buttocks?","answer":"Brown or seal brown (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-2; HIH140-1; HH4"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1105","question":"What color are the muzzle and the flanks of a brown horse?","answer":"Brown or tan (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-2; HIH140-1; HH4"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1106","question":"Describe the color chestnut.","answer":"Body is some shade of red or reddish-brown; mane and tail are red, reddish-brown, or flaxen.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-1; HIH140-1; HH4"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1107","question":"What term describes both a horse color and a horny growth found on the inside of a horse's legs?","answer":"Chestnut  <br/> <br/>ref:DET55; HH4,8"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1108","question":"What color horse is reddish brown with a reddish brown or flaxen mane and tail?","answer":"Chestnut or sorrel (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-1; HIH140-1; HH4"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1109","question":"A chestnut horse whose mane and tail are lighter in color than the body is called what?","answer":"Flaxen  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-1; HIH140-1; HH4"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"hard","number":"1110","question":"When referring to chestnut horses, what does the term “alazán” mean?","answer":"Red colored horse with red mane and tail (FYI:  Old Sorrel from the King Ranch was called El Alazán Viejo.)  <br/> <br/>ref:ES41"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"hard","number":"1111","question":"When referring to chestnut horses, what does the term \"ruano\" mean?","answer":"Red colored horse with lighter points or a flaxen mane and tail  <br/> <br/>ref:ES41"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"hard","number":"1112","question":"When referring to chestnut horses, what does the term “tostada” mean?","answer":"Red colored horse with darker red colored points  <br/> <br/>ref:ES41"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1113","question":"Give ONE name for a very dark, chocolate shade of chestnut.","answer":"Liver chestnut or black chestnut  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-1; DET170"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1114","question":"When referring to color, what is another name for chestnut?","answer":"Sorrel  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-1; DET250; HH4"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"medium","number":"1115","question":"Describe the unusual markings of a brindle-colored horse.","answer":"Brindle coloring consists of irregular strips that are vertical over the body (FYI:  Head and legs are usually unaffected.  Any base coat color can be brindle.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-12; HIH154B-1"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"medium","number":"1116","question":"Describe a brindle dun horse.","answer":"Dun horse with zebra stripes or teardrop markings on its body  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH154B-1"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"medium","number":"1117","question":"What rare color consists of irregular vertical strips over the body of the horse as if dribbled with another color?","answer":"Brindle (FYI:  This can occur on any color.  The head and legs are usually not affected.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-12; HIH154B-1"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1118","question":"Describe the color buckskin.","answer":"Body color is some shade of yellow; mane, tail, and lower legs are black.  (FYI:  Buckskin color resembles the color of a newly tanned deer hide.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-8; HIH140-1"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1119","question":"Which color is described as the color of a \"newly tanned deer hide\" with black points?","answer":"Buckskin (FYI:  Buckskin is a single cream dilution of bay.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH154B-1"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"intermediate","number":"1120","question":"What color horse has a cream-colored body, white mane and tail, pink skin, and blue eyes?","answer":"Cremello (FYI:  Cremello is a double cream dilution of chestnut.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm510-3; HSm105-11; HIH1040-2; DET72"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"intermediate","number":"1121","question":"Describe TWO features of the color cremello.","answer":"Cream-colored body; white mane and tail; pink skin; blue eyes (FYI: Cremello is a double cream dilution of chestnut.) [CORRECTED 2021]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm510-3; HSm105-11; HIH1040-2; DET72"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1122","question":"Describe the color palomino.","answer":"Body is some shade of yellow (color of a newly minted gold coin); mane and tail are white.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-10; HIH140-2; HIH164B-2; HH5"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1123","question":"What color horse has a golden body color and a white mane and tail?","answer":"Palomino (FYI:  Palomino is a single cream dilution of chestnut.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-10; HIH140-2; HIH164B-2; HH5"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"intermediate","number":"1124","question":"Describe the color perlino.","answer":"Ivory color body with rusty points (mane, tail, and lower legs)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET209"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"intermediate","number":"1125","question":"What color is a horse with an ivory coat color and rusty points?","answer":"Perlino (FYI:  Perlino is a double cream dilution of bay.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET209"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"intermediate","number":"1126","question":"Describe the color silver dapple.","answer":"Bluish or chocolate brown body; very light mane, tail, and lower legs; may have dappling (FYI: Silver dapple is also called Taffy (in Australia) and blue silver.  A silver gene (Z) on black with no dappling is called chocolate or chocolate flax.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1040-2; HSm105-10"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"intermediate","number":"1127","question":"Name ONE breed that can have a silver dapple coat color.","answer":"Shetland Pony, Miniature Horse, Missouri Fox Trotter, Rocky Mountain Horse, Kentucky Mountain Horse, French Comtois, Tennessee Walking Horse, Icelandic horse, Welsh pony, Morgan, Saddlebred, Missouri Fox Trotter, Quarter Horse, Mustang  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-10; HIH1040-2"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"medium","number":"1128","question":"The Taffy color common to the Australian pony is the same as what color seen in Shetland ponies.","answer":"Silver Dapple (also accept black silver or blue silver)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-10"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"sr bonus","number":"1129","question":"2-part question:  Name 3 types of dun and give the base color of each.","answer":"Classic dun (dun), bay dun, zebra dun, or coyote dun—base color is bay; red dun, clay bank dun, fox dun, or apricot dun—base color is chestnut; grullo, blue dun, mouse dun, or lobo dun—base color is black  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-9; HIH154B-1"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"jr bonus","number":"1130","question":"In reference to horse coat colors, name 3 types of duns.","answer":"Classic dun (dun), red dun, grullo, brindle dun  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-9; HIH154B-1"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1131","question":"Identify the following coat color:  body color is yellowish; mane and tail may be black, red, or frosted; has a dorsal stripe; usually has zebra stripes on the legs and transverse stripe over the withers.","answer":"Dun (Buckskins do NOT have dorsal stripes, zebra stripes, and mane and tail frosting.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-9; HSm510-4; HIH140-1; DET42; DET86"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"medium","number":"1132","question":"What CANINE term, describes a dun horse with black points and a black dorsal stripe?","answer":"Coyote dun (FYI:  A classic or coyote dun is a dun dilution of bay.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET71"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"medium","number":"1133","question":"What is a “coyote dun”?","answer":"Dun horse with black points and a black dorsal stripe  <br/> <br/>ref:DET71"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1134","question":"Identify the following coat color:  body appears smoky or mouse-colored; mane, tail, and lower legs are black; has a dorsal stripe; usually has zebra stripes.","answer":"Grullo (FYI:  Grullo is a dun dilution of black.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH140-1; HH4"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1135","question":"Describe the color grullo.","answer":"Type of dun that is mouse-colored and has black points, dorsal stripe, and may have other dun markings  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH140-1; HH4"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1136","question":"Describe the color red dun.","answer":"Body color is reddish-orange or reddish-yellow, mane and tail are dark red, has a red dorsal stripe  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH140-1; HH4"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"hard","number":"1137","question":"What type of red dun has a body color of light copper and a mane and tail that are a darker shade?","answer":"Clay bank dun  <br/> <br/>ref:DET58"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"hard","number":"1138","question":"Describe the color clay bank dun.","answer":"Very light red or light copper dun (with darker mane, tail, and lower legs and red dorsal stripe)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET58"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1139","question":"What color does the following describe?   The foal's coat will be a solid color, but with each consecutive hair coat, more white hairs are added.","answer":"Gray  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-7; HH4"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1140","question":"Most so-called \"white\" horses are really which color?","answer":"Gray  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH140-1HSm105-7"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1141","question":"Both gray and roan horses are a mixture of white and colored hairs.  What is the difference between these two colors?","answer":"Gray horses get progressively lighter with age; roan horses stay the same color.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-7; HH4; HH51"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1142","question":"What causes a gray horse's coat to lighten with age?","answer":"More white hairs growing into the coat  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-7; HH4"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"jr bonus","number":"1143","question":"Name 3 color variations of a gray horse.","answer":"Dapple gray, flea-bitten gray, steel or iron gray, rose gray, rosettes, porcelain gray (light gray) [accept any correct answers]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-7; ES45; HH4-5"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"sr bonus","number":"1144","question":"Name 4 color variations of a gray horse.","answer":"Dapple gray, flea-bitten gray, steel or iron gray, rose gray, rosettes, porcelain gray (light gray) [accept any correct answers]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-7; ES45; HH4-5"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"intermediate","number":"1145","question":"Describe a dappled gray horse.","answer":"Gray horse with spots on its coat that are a different shade of gray (can be darker or lighter)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-3"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1146","question":"Describe a flea-bitten gray horse.","answer":"Gray horse with small black or reddish specks on a white background  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-7; HH5"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"medium","number":"1147","question":"What is the base color of a rose gray horse?","answer":"Chestnut or bay (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-7"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"medium","number":"1148","question":"The gray color pattern on a bay or chestnut horse is called what type of gray?","answer":"Rose gray  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-7"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"medium","number":"1149","question":"What term refers to bursts of white on a gray coat color?","answer":"Rosettes  <br/> <br/>ref:ES45"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1150","question":"What is the term used for a gray horse that has a lot of black in its coat?","answer":"Steel gray or iron gray (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-7; DET155; HH4"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"hard","number":"1151","question":"2-part question:  The pigment melanin comes in TWO forms.  Name them and give the colors they control.","answer":"Eumelanin controls black and brown; pheomelanin controls red and yellow. (pronounced YOU-mel-a-nin and FEE-oh-mel-a-nin)  <br/> <br/>ref:ES93"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"medium","number":"1152","question":"What is the name of the pigment that is responsible for the color of the skin, hair, and eyes?","answer":"Melanin  <br/> <br/>ref:DET129"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"sr bonus","number":"1153","question":"In reference to horse coat color, name 3 dilution genes.","answer":"Cream, dun, silver or silver dapple, champagne, pearl (accept any correct answers) [FYI:  Agouti, white, gray, and roan are NOT dilution genes.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-9-12; HSm510-3,4"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"sr bonus","number":"1154","question":"Name 4 ways the basic coat colors of the horse can be modified.","answer":"Dilution, roaning, graying, and spotting  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-7-12; HSm510-3-7"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"jr bonus","number":"1155","question":"Roan horses have a combination of white and colored hairs.  What are the 3 most common BASE colors of a roan?","answer":"Black (seen in blue roan), bay (seen in bay roan), and chestnut (seen in red or strawberry roan)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-8; HH5"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"sr bonus","number":"1156","question":"2-part question: Name 3 types of roan horses and give the base color for each.","answer":"Blue roan (base color black), bay roan (or red roan; base color bay), red roan (or strawberry roan; base color chestnut), lilac roan (base color liver chestnut), honey roan (base color palomino or blond sorrel)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-8; HH5"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1157","question":"Name TWO areas that are generally darker or more solid colored on a roan horse.","answer":"Head, neck, lower legs, mane, and tail  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-8; HIH140-1,2; HIH1040-3"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1158","question":"Describe a roan horse.","answer":"Mixture of white and colored hairs (FYI:  Roans are darker on the head, neck, and lower legs. They do NOT get lighter with age.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-8; HIH140-1,2; HIH1040-3; HH5"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1159","question":"Name this color.  The base color is BAY with a uniform mix of white hairs on the body.  The head, neck, and legs are darker.  Its color does NOT get lighter with age.","answer":"Bay roan (also accept red roan)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-9; HIH1040-3"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1160","question":"Describe the color bay roan.","answer":"Roan horse with a mixture of reddish brown and white hairs; mane, tail, and lower legs are black (FYI:  Roans are darker on the head, neck, and lower legs.  They do NOT get lighter with age.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-9; HIH1040-3"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1161","question":"Name this color. The base color is black with a uniform mix of white hairs on the body. The head, neck, and legs are darker. Its color does NOT get lighter with age.","answer":"Blue roan  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-9; HIH140-1; HIH1040-3; HH5"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1162","question":"Describe the color blue roan.","answer":"Roan horse with a mixture of black and white hairs (FYI:  Roans are darker on the head, neck, and lower legs. They do NOT get lighter with age.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-9; HIH140-1; HIH1040-3; HH5"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1163","question":"Name this color.  The base color is chestnut with a uniform mix of white hairs on the body.  The head, neck, and legs are darker.  Its color does NOT get lighter with age.","answer":"Red roan (also accept strawberry roan)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-9; HIH140-2; HIH1040-3; HH5"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1164","question":"Describe the color red roan or strawberry roan.","answer":"Roan horse with a mixture of chestnut and white hairs (FYI:  Roans are darker on the head, neck, and lower legs. They do NOT get lighter with age)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-9; HIH140-2; HIH1040-3; HH5"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1165","question":"Describe the color pinto.","answer":"Combination of white and colored markings in irregular patches or spots  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-3; HIH140-1; HH5"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"medium","number":"1166","question":"What is the term used for a horse that is almost entirely white except for colored areas over the ears, eyes, chest, and base of the tail?","answer":"Medicine hat (FYI:  War bonnet has a patch of dark on the head only.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-2,3"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"intermediate","number":"1167","question":"Native Americans thought Spanish Mustangs with what color pattern possessed supernatural powers of protection?","answer":"Medicine hat or war bonnet (accept either) [FYI:  War bonnet has a patch of dark on the head only; Medicine hat has patches of dark on the head and chest.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-2,3"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"medium","number":"1168","question":"Describe the difference between a \"war bonnet\"  and a \"medicine hat\" pinto.","answer":"War bonnet has a patch of dark on the head only; Medicine hat has patches of dark on the head and chest.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-2,3"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"jr bonus","number":"1169","question":"Name 3 color patterns of the Paint or Pinto.","answer":"Tobiano, overo (frame overo), tovero, calico (overo), splashed white, white (white spotting pattern), sabino, manchado, War Bonnet, Medicine Hat  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-2-4; HIH1040-3"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"sr bonus","number":"1170","question":"Name 4 color patterns of the Paint or Pinto.","answer":"Tobiano, overo (frame overo), tovero, calico (overo), splashed white, white (white spotting pattern), sabino, manchado, War Bonnet, Medicine Hat  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-2-4; HIH1040-3"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"sr bonus","number":"1171","question":"Name 3 characteristics of the overo color pattern.","answer":"Irregular, jagged, or splashy spots; white usually does NOT cross the back; one or more legs are dark; tail is usually dark; large white facial markings (bald, bonnet, or apron face); can be predominantly dark or white  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-3; HSm510-5; HIH140-1"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"hard","number":"1172","question":"The frame pattern falls within which more general Paint color pattern, overo or tobiano?","answer":"Overo  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-3; ES48"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"intermediate","number":"1173","question":"Identify this pinto pattern:  two solid legs and two white stockings; wide blaze; white body markings are irregularly spotted; white does NOT cross the back.","answer":"Overo  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-3"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"sr bonus","number":"1174","question":"Give 3 features of the sabino coat pattern.","answer":"Ranges from minimally white to almost entirely white; usually has white face markings; usually has white feet or legs; has irregular spotting on barrel with roaning around edges; very common in Clydesdales and Shires  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-4; ES49"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"hard","number":"1175","question":"Identify this type of spotted coat pattern:  white rises from the bottom side of the horse; legs are white with clearly defined edges between the colored and white areas; extensive white on the face.","answer":"Splashed white  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-3; ES50"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1176","question":"What is the most common pinto pattern?","answer":"Tobiano  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1040-3"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1177","question":"Which paint or pinto color pattern has rounded or oval-shaped spots?","answer":"Tobiano  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-3; HSm510-6; HIH140-2"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"intermediate","number":"1178","question":"Identify this pinto pattern:  all 4 lower legs are white; horse has a star and stripe; white body markings are regular, oval-shaped, and distinct and they extend down the neck and chest; white crosses the back.","answer":"Tobiano  <br/> <br/>ref:HSM105-3; HSm510-6; HIH159-3"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"sr bonus","number":"1179","question":"Name 3 characteristics of the tobiano color pattern.","answer":"White crosses the back; head is solid-colored (may have white facial markings); all 4 legs are white below the knees and hocks; spots are regular, oval-shaped, and distinct; one or both flanks are usually solid-colored  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-3; HSm510-6; HIH140-1"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"intermediate","number":"1180","question":"Describe the tovero color pattern.","answer":"Combination of the tobiano and overo patterns (doesn't belong in either one)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm510-6; HIH159-3; HIH163B-1; HIH1040-3"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"intermediate","number":"1181","question":"Describe the color piebald.","answer":"Black and white pinto  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm510-5; DET246; ES47"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"intermediate","number":"1182","question":"What is the term for a black and white pinto?","answer":"Piebald  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm510-5; DET246; ES47"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"intermediate","number":"1183","question":"Describe the color skewbald.","answer":"Pinto that's any color except black with white spotting  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm510-5; DET246; ES47"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"intermediate","number":"1184","question":"What is the GENERAL term for a chestnut and white pinto?","answer":"Skewbald (FYI: A piebald is a black and white pinto.  Bay or buckskin pintos are called tri-colored.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm510-5; DET246; ES47"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"intermediate","number":"1185","question":"Describe a tri-colored Pinto or Paint horse.","answer":"Spotted horse with 3 colors (FYI:  Bay is the most common tri-color with reddish-brown and white coat and black mane and tail.  Buckskin is another tri-color with yellowish and white body with black mane and tail.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm510-5"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1186","question":"Give TWO features of a \"true white horse\".","answer":"Born white, dies white, white hair, pink skin, dark eyes (brown, blue, or hazel) [UPDATED 2021]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH140-2; HSm105-4; ES45; HH4"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1187","question":"What is the USUAL color of a white horse’s eyes?","answer":"Brown (FYI: Most white horses have brown eyes, but their eyes can be blue or hazel. They do NOT have pink eyes because there are no true albino horses.) [UPDATED 2021]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH140-2; HSm105-4; ES45; HH4"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1188","question":"2-part question:  What is the color of the skin and what is the USUAL color of the eyes of a white horse?","answer":"Skin is pink; eyes are usually brown.  (FYI:  The genetics of white horses is much more complicated than originally believed and is now known to be due to several different alleles.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH140-2; HSm105-4; ES45; HH4"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"jr bonus","number":"1189","question":"Name 3 characteristics of white horses.","answer":"White hair, pink skin, dark eyes (brown, blue or hazel), born white, dies white (FYI: White horses are due to several different white spotting genes, not to a lethal dominant white gene as it was formerly thought.) [UPDATED 2021]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH140-2; HSm105-4; ES45; HH4"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"medium","number":"1190","question":"What is the term for the congenital absence of pigment in the skin, hair, and eyes of an animal?","answer":"Albinism (albino) [FYI: There are no true albino horses because white horses have pigmented eyes.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-4; DET6"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"medium","number":"1191","question":"Why are white horses NOT considered albinos?","answer":"White horses have pigmented eyes.  (FYI:  True albino animals have pink eyes with no pigment.  There are no true albino horses.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-4; DET6"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1192","question":"Name ONE color of horse that ALWAYS has black points.","answer":"Bay, brown, buckskin, grulla, and dun (classic dun) [Do NOT accept red dun which has dark red points.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-1; HSm510-2; ES42,43; HH4,6"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1193","question":"Where are the black points on a horse?","answer":"Mane, tail, lower legs (also ear edges and tips)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-1; HIH140-1; HH4,6"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1194","question":"Describe the difference between a stripe and a blaze.","answer":"Blaze is wider.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-1; DET30"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"jr bonus","number":"1195","question":"Name 5 white FACIAL markings.","answer":"Star, stripe, snip, blaze, bald face, flame, bonnet or apron face, badger face  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-1; HIH140-2; HH5"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1196","question":"Name 3 white FACIAL markings.","answer":"Star, stripe, snip, blaze, bald face, flame, bonnet or apron face, badger face  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-1; HIH140-2; HH5"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"hard","number":"1197","question":"In reference to facial markings of the horse, what is a “badger face”?","answer":"Badger face is like a reverse (colored) blaze that is lined with white on the edges.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-1"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1198","question":"Name ONE white facial marking where most of the horse’s face is white.","answer":"Bald face, apron face, bonnet face, paper face (accept any) [FYI:  Medicine Hat and War Bonnet are named for the DARK coloring on the poll and ears of a mostly white pinto.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-1,2; HIH140-2; ES30; HH7"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1199","question":"Describe the marking bald face.","answer":"White over the entire face (FYI:  White may extend down the sides of the head, over the eyes, and underneath the jaw.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-1; HIH140-2; HH7"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1200","question":"What do you call a wide white stripe running down the face to the lips?","answer":"Blaze  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-1; HIH140-2; HH7; CAHA4"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"medium","number":"1201","question":"To be classified as a blaze, the white must cover the full width of which bones?","answer":"Nasal bones  <br/> <br/>ref:DET30"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1202","question":"Describe the facial marking blaze.","answer":"Wide white stripe running down the face to the lips  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-1; HIH140-2; HH7; CAHA4"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1203","question":"Describe the facial marking flame.","answer":"Few white hairs in the middle of the forehead  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-3; HH4"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1204","question":"The mealy-mouthed description is most likely to be found in what color horse?","answer":"Bay, brown, or seal brown (accept any)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-4; HH7"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1205","question":"In references to facial coloration, describe “mealy mouthed”.","answer":"Faded out color around the horse's mouth (brown or tan hairs on the horse’s muzzle).  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-4; HH7"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1206","question":"What is the term for faded out color around the horse's mouth?","answer":"Mealy mouth  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-4; HH7"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1207","question":"Name TWO facial markings that have more white than a blaze.","answer":"Bald face; bonnet or apron face  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-2; ES30"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1208","question":"Describe the facial marking snip.","answer":"Patch of white hairs on the muzzle  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-1; HIH140-2; HH7"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1209","question":"What facial marking has a patch of white hairs on the muzzle that may include white on the lips?","answer":"Snip  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-1; HIH140-2; HH7"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1210","question":"Describe the facial marking star.","answer":"Patch of white hairs on the forehead  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-1; HIH140-2; HH7"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1211","question":"What is the term for a patch of white located between a horse's eyes?","answer":"Star  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-1; HIH140-2; CAHA4; HH7"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1212","question":"Describe the facial marking stripe.","answer":"Long, narrow band of white from the forehead down towards the muzzle  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-1; HIH140-2; HH7"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1213","question":"What do you call a long, narrow band of white running from the forehead down towards the muzzle?","answer":"Stripe  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-1; HIH140-2; HH7"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"sr bonus","number":"1214","question":"Name 3 types of DARK leg markings.","answer":"Ermine spots (dark spots on a white coronet); distal or Belton spots (spots of dark surrounded by white above the ankle); zebra stripes (also called tiger stripes or leg barring)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-2,6; DET11; DET205; DET298"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"medium","number":"1215","question":"What do leg barring, ermine spots, and distal spots have in common?","answer":"They are all dark spots on the legs.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-2,6; DET11; DET205; DET298"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"jr bonus","number":"1216","question":"Name 5 white LEG markings.","answer":"Coronet, half pastern, pastern, sock, half stocking, full stocking, inside heel, outside heel  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-2; HIH140-2; HH7"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1217","question":"Name 3 white LEG markings.","answer":"Coronet, half pastern, pastern, sock, half stocking, full stocking, inside heel, outside heel  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-2; HIH140-2; HH7"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1218","question":"What white leg marking is a narrow band of white just above the hoof?","answer":"Coronet  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH140-2; HH6"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1219","question":"Describe the leg marking coronet.","answer":"White covers the coronet band  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH140-2; HH6"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"hard","number":"1220","question":"In reference to leg markings, what are ermine spots?","answer":"Dark spots on a white coronet (FYI:  They may be associated with vertical hoof striping.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-2"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"hard","number":"1221","question":"A chestnut horse has a white coronet on his left hind leg.  In this white area, there are small, dark spots.  What are these spots called?","answer":"Ermine spots (FYI:  Distal or Belton spots are spots of dark surrounded by white above the ankle.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-2"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1222","question":"What leg marking has white extending from the coronet to and including the knee or hock?","answer":"Full stocking (also accept stocking)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-2; HIH140-2; HH6"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1223","question":"Describe a full stocking.","answer":"White extends from the coronet to the knee or hock  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-2; HIH140-2; HH6"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1224","question":"What leg marking is white from the coronet to the middle of the cannon?","answer":"Half stocking  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-2; HIH140-2; HH6"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1225","question":"Describe a half stocking.","answer":"White extends from the coronet to the middle of the cannon  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-2; HIH140-2; HH6"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1226","question":"What white leg marking extends from the coronet to and including the pastern?","answer":"Pastern  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH140-2; HH6"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1227","question":"Describe the leg marking pastern.","answer":"White extends from the coronet to the pastern  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH140-2; HH6"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1228","question":"What white leg marking extends from the coronet to the fetlock?","answer":"Sock  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-2; HIH140-2; HH6"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1229","question":"Describe the leg marking sock.","answer":"White extends from the coronet to the fetlock  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-2; HIH140-2; HH6"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1230","question":"What is the term for a mane that is blonde or straw-colored?","answer":"Flaxen  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-1; HIH140-2; HH7"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1231","question":"What does the term \"flaxen\" mean?","answer":"Mane and tail are \"blonde\", straw-colored, light yellow, or whitish (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-1; HIH140-2; HH7"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"intermediate","number":"1232","question":"Which term means a mane or tail that is white with a few black hairs?","answer":"Silver  <br/> <br/>ref:DET246; HH7"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"hard","number":"1233","question":"In reference to coat color markings, what are birdcatcher spots?","answer":"Small white dots on the coat that appear at random (FYI:  Birdcatcher spots can be confused with snowflake Appaloosa, but it can occur in any breed or color.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-5"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"hard","number":"1234","question":"A dark colored (usually red or brown) splotch on the base coat color is called what?","answer":"Blood mark or handprint  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-7; ES39"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"hard","number":"1236","question":"On a roan horse, scars grow back as small, base-colored spots on the roan background.  What are these dark spots called?","answer":"Corn spots  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-9; HSm110-8,9; ES47"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"medium","number":"1237","question":"In reference to coat color markings, what is countershading?","answer":"Appearance of a dorsal stripe on a horse that is NOT dun  <br/> <br/>ref:HSM105-11"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"intermediate","number":"1238","question":"In reference to colors, define dappled.","answer":"Circular spots on the coat that are two different shades of the same color (accept any reasonable wording) [FYI:  Reverse dapples are light rings with dark centers.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-3; DET77; ES39; HH6"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"intermediate","number":"1239","question":"What term describes circular spots on the coat that are two slightly different shades of the same color?","answer":"Dappled  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-3; DET77; ES39; HH6"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"hard","number":"1240","question":"Referring to markings, what is an ink spot?","answer":"Small, dark-colored spot seen on the white area of a Paint or Pinto (FYI:  Also called cat tracks, paw prints, or ink blots)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-3; ES40"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"hard","number":"1241","question":"In reference to coat colors, what does rabicano mean?","answer":"Solid-colored horse with a limited roaning pattern (FYI: In Spanish “rabo” means tail and “cano” means white.  White hairs are concentrated around the flanks and tail head. It’s not a true roan.  It’s most often seen in Arabians.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-9"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"hard","number":"1242","question":"What does the color term \"sooty\" mean?","answer":"Darker hairs intermingled with a base color (FYI:  Both palominos and buckskins with the sooty trait can get dramatic dark shading—especially over the top line—and dapples.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-11; HSm110-3"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"hard","number":"1243","question":"Referring to color, what is the pangare effect? (pronounced pan-gu-RAY)","answer":"Light areas of color on the muzzle, over the eyes, on the flanks, and on the inside of the legs  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-3,4"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"hard","number":"1244","question":"What is the term for light areas of color on the muzzle, over the eyes, on the flanks, and inside the legs?","answer":"Pangare (pronounced pan-gu-RAY)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-3,4"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"jr bonus","number":"1245","question":"Name 3 primitive marking or dun factors of the horse or ass.","answer":"Dorsal stripe, cross, transverse or shoulder stripe, zebra stripes (leg barring), cobwebbing on forehead, black ear tips or edging, mane and tail frosting, zippers, dorsal barbs, neck striping or shadowing, mask, countershading  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-9; HSm110-6"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"sr bonus","number":"1246","question":"Name 4 primitive marking or dun factors of the horse or ass.","answer":"Dorsal stripe, cross, transverse or shoulder stripe, zebra stripes (leg barring), cobwebbing on forehead, black ear tips or edging, mane and tail frosting, zippers, dorsal barbs, neck striping or shadowing, mask, countershading  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-9; HSm110-6"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1247","question":"Give ONE term for a dark line over the withers that goes from side to side.","answer":"Transverse stripe (also accept cross, shoulder stripe, shadow, or cape)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-6; HIH140-1; HH4,6"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1248","question":"In reference to coat color markings, what is a \"line back\"?","answer":"Dark line running along the back from the mane to the tail (also called a dorsal stripe or eel stripe)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1040-2; HH4,6"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1249","question":"In reference to dun horses, what is a dorsal stripe?","answer":"Dark line that runs down the topline from the mane to the tail (FYI:  Black dorsal stripes are seen in classic dun and grullo horses; red dorsal stripes are seen in red dun horses.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-6; DET84,89"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1250","question":"Describe an \"eel stripe\".","answer":"Dark stripe down the horse's back from the mane to the tail (also called a dorsal stripe or line back)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-6; DET84"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1251","question":"Give TWO terms that mean a dark line running down the back from the mane to tail.","answer":"Dorsal stripe, eel stripe, line back, or ray  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-9; HSm110-6; DET84,89; HH4"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1252","question":"What are the TWO most common dorsal stripe colors?","answer":"Black and red (FYI:  A black dorsal stripe is seen on a bay or classic dun and a grulla.  A red dorsal stripe is seen on a red dun.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1040-2; HH4,6"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1253","question":"Be specific:  A red dorsal stripe appears with which coat color?","answer":"Red dun (also accept clay bank dun, fox dun, or apricot dun) [FYI: A red dun is a dun dilution of chestnut.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HH4"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"medium","number":"1254","question":"As seen in dun horses such as Fjords, what is mane and tail frosting?","answer":"Center of the mane and tail are dark; outer hair is white (which is caused by light-colored guard hairs). [FYI: Midstol is the dark hair in the mane and halefjaer is the dark hair in the middle of the tail.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-9; HSm110-6; HSm125-10"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1255","question":"In reference to dun horses what do the terms zebra stripes or leg barring mean?","answer":"Dark stripes on the legs  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-9; HSm110-6; HIH140-1"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1256","question":"In reference to coat color markings, what does the term \"zebra\" mean?","answer":"Dark stripes on the legs and/or withers  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-6; HIH140-1"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1257","question":"What is a zebra dun horse?","answer":"Dun horse with zebra stripes on the legs and/or withers  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-10 picture; HH4"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1258","question":"Give ONE term that means dark stripes on the legs of a dun horse.","answer":"Zebra stripes, leg barring, or tiger stripes (accept any)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-9; HSm110-6; HIH140-2"},
    {"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"medium","number":"1259","question":"In reference to primitive or dun markings, what are “zippers”?","answer":"Lighter line of faded hair along the back of the leg  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-9; HSm110-6"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1260","question":"At a standstill, where is the center of gravity located on a horse?","answer":"6 inches behind the elbow, about the rider's knee, near the outer edge of the 8th rib (accept any)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET52"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1261","question":"Where is the center of motion?","answer":"Over the 15th vertebrae or 10 inches behind the center of gravity (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET53"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"jr bonus","number":"1262","question":"Name 3 conformation faults of the horse's body EXCLUDING its legs.","answer":"Coarse head, pig eye, cow eye, parrot mouth, monkey mouth, thick throatlatch, short, thick neck, ewe neck, mutton withers, swayback, roach back, goose rump, paunchy, wasp waisted or tucked up, narrow chest, slab sided (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345; HSm385; HIH230; HH8-13"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"sr bonus","number":"1263","question":"Name 5 conformation faults of the horse's body EXCLUDING its legs.","answer":"Coarse head, pig eye, cow eye, parrot mouth, monkey mouth, thick throatlatch, short, thick neck, ewe neck, mutton withers, swayback, roach back, goose rump, paunchy, wasp waisted or tucked up, narrow chest, slab sided (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345; HSm385; HIH230; HH8-13"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"jr bonus","number":"1264","question":"Name 3 conformation faults whose common name refers to another animal species.","answer":"Parrot mouth, monkey mouth, ewe neck, calf knee, pigeon toe, cow hocked, coon footed, pig eye, roach back, cow eyes, goose rump, wasp waist, herring gutted, hound gutted (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345; HSm385; HIH230; HH8-13"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"sr bonus","number":"1265","question":"Name 5 conformation faults whose common name refers to another animal species.","answer":"Parrot mouth, monkey mouth, ewe neck, calf knee, pigeon toe, cow hocked, coon footed, pig eye, roach back, cow eyes, goose rump, wasp waist, herring gutted, hound gutted (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345; HSm385; HIH230; HH8-13"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"jr bonus","number":"1266","question":"Name 3 conformation faults of the head.","answer":"Roman nose, pig eye, bug eye or bovine eye, parrot mouth, monkey mouth, mule ears, lop ears, large head, coarse head (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-5; HSm385-3; HIH220-4; HH10-11"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"sr bonus","number":"1267","question":"Name 4 conformation faults of the head.","answer":"Roman nose, pig eye, bug eye or bovine eye, parrot mouth, monkey mouth, mule ears, lop ears, large head, coarse head (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-5; HSm385-3; HIH220-4; HH10-11"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1268","question":"Describe a horse with lop ears.","answer":"Ears are positioned on the sides of the head (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-3; DET172"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"intermediate","number":"1269","question":"Explain the difference between the conformation faults mule ears and lop ears.","answer":"Mule ears are long, thick and heavy; lop ears are carried to the side.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-3; DET172; DET183"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1270","question":"What is the term for large, protruding eyes?","answer":"Bug eyes (also accept bovine eyes)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc8"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1271","question":"What is a bug-eyed horse?","answer":"Horse with large, protruding eyes  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc8"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"novice","number":"1272","question":"What is a pig-eyed horse?","answer":"Horse with small eyes  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-3; HIH220-4; HH10-11"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"novice","number":"1273","question":"What is the term for a horse with small eyes?","answer":"Pig eyes  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-3; HIH220-4; HH10-11"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1274","question":"What is Roman nosed?","answer":"Face bows out instead of being flat (convex face)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-5; HIH220-3; HH10"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1275","question":"What is the term for the convex profile of a horse's face?","answer":"Roman nose  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-5; HIH220-3; HH10"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"hard","number":"1276","question":"What term refers to an overhanging of the top lip?","answer":"Elk lip  <br/> <br/>ref:DET90"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"novice","number":"1277","question":"Name the defect where the upper jaw is SHORTER than the lower jaw.","answer":"Monkey mouth (also called undershot jaw, sow mouth and prognathism)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-5; HSm385-3; HIH220-4; HH9"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"novice","number":"1278","question":"Describe monkey mouth.","answer":"Upper jaw is SHORTER than the lower jaw (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-5; HSm385-3; HIH220-4; HH9"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"novice","number":"1279","question":"Name the defect where the upper jaw is LONGER than the lower jaw.","answer":"Parrot mouth (also called overshot jaw and brachygnathism)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-5; HSm385-3; HIH220-4; HH10-11"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"novice","number":"1280","question":"Describe parrot mouth.","answer":"Upper jaw is LONGER than the lower jaw (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-5; HSm385-3; HIH220-4; HH10-11"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"jr bonus","number":"1281","question":"Name 3 conformation faults of the front legs.","answer":"Base narrow, base wide, camped in, camped out, bench or offset knees, bow legged, buck knee, calf knee, coon footed, straight pasterns, tied in at knee, knock knee, pigeon toe, splay foot (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345; HSm385; HIH230; HH12-13"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"sr bonus","number":"1282","question":"Name 4 conformation faults of the front legs.","answer":"Base narrow, base wide, camped in, camped out, bench or offset knees, bow legged, buck knee, calf knee, coon footed, straight pasterns, tied in at knee, knock knee, pigeon toe, splay foot (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345; HSm385; HIH230; HH12-13"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1283","question":"Describe a base-narrow horse.","answer":"Horse's front legs are closer together at the ground than they are at the chest. (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-3; HSm385-5; HIH230-2; HH12-13"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1284","question":"A base-narrow horse is predisposed to landing on what part of the foot?","answer":"Outside hoof wall  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-3; HSm385-5; HIH230-2; HH12-13"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"hard","number":"1285","question":"Base-narrow horses with large muscle mass are predisposed to landing on the outside of the hoof walls.  Name TWO unsoundnesses that this condition can cause.","answer":"Ringbone, sidebone, heel bruising  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH230-2,3"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1286","question":"Describe a base-wide horse.","answer":"Horse's front legs are further apart at the ground than they are at the chest. (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-3; HSm385-5; HIH230-3; HH12-13; CAHA39"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"hard","number":"1287","question":"Base-wide, toed-out horses with narrow chests land with more weight on the inside of the hoof walls.  Name TWO unsoundnesses that this condition can cause.","answer":"Ringbone and sidebone  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH230-3"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1288","question":"Are base-wide, narrow-chested horses usually pigeon toed or splay footed?","answer":"Toed out or splay footed (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-3; HSm385-5; HIH230-6; HH12-13"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1289","question":"Horses that are camped out in front are predisposed to what TWO conditions?","answer":"Navicular and laminitis or founder  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-3; HIH230-5"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"sr bonus","number":"1290","question":"Name 4 conformation faults of the horse's knee.","answer":"Calf knee, buck knee, bench or offset knee, knock knee, cut under at the knee, bow legged (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-3,4; HSm385-5; HIH230-5, 6; CAHA39; HH12-13"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"jr bonus","number":"1291","question":"Name 3 conformation faults of the horse's knee.","answer":"Calf knee, buck knee, bench or offset knee, knock knee, cut under at the knee, bow legged (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-3,4; HSm385-5; HIH230-5, 6; CAHA39; HH12-13"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"intermediate","number":"1292","question":"What conformation fault increases the possibility of a horse developing splints?","answer":"Bench or offset knees  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-3; HIH385-5; HIH230-3; CAHA39"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1293","question":"What is the name of the conformation fault where the cannon bones are not centered on the knees?","answer":"Bench or offset knees (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-3; HIH385-5; HIH230-3; CAHA39"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1294","question":"What are bench knees?","answer":"Offset knees where the cannon is not centered on the knee (or carpal bones)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-3; HIH385-5; HIH230-3; CAHA39"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1295","question":"What is the term for knees bent forward?","answer":"Buck knees  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-3; HSm385-5; HIH230-5; HH13"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1296","question":"What is buck knee?","answer":"Knee bent forward  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-3; HSm385-5; HIH230-5; HH13"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1297","question":"Which condition is more serious, over at the knee or back at the knee?","answer":"Back at the knee (FYI: Back at the knee or calf knee predisposes horses to carpal chip fractures.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-5; HIH230-6"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1298","question":"In reference to conformation, what is another term for \"back at the knees\"?","answer":"Calf knee  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-4; HSm385-5; HIH230-6; HH13"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"hard","number":"1299","question":"What conformation defect predisposes a horse to carpal chip fractures, especially in young racehorses?","answer":"Calf knee (back at the knee)  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA11"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1300","question":"What is calf knee?","answer":"Knee bent backward (FYI:  Calf knee is a serious conformation fault that often causes unsoundness.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-4; HSm385-5; HIH230-6; HH13"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"novice","number":"1301","question":"Describe a pigeon-toed horse.","answer":"Front toes turn in (and the heels turn out)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-2; HIH230-1; HH12"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"novice","number":"1302","question":"What is the term for the front toes pointing inward?","answer":"Pigeon toe (toed-in)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-2; HIH230-1; HH12"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1304","question":"What is the difference between splay foot and pigeon toe?","answer":"Splay foot is when the front toes turn out (and the heels turn in); pigeon toe is when the front toes turn in (and the heels turn out).  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-1,2; HIH230-1,2; HH12"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"novice","number":"1305","question":"Describe a splay-footed horse.","answer":"Front toes turn out (and heels turn in)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-2,3; HSm385-5; HIH230-2; HH12"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"novice","number":"1306","question":"What do you call a horse that toes out in front?","answer":"Splay footed or toed out (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-2,3; HSm385-5; HIH230-2; HH12"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"jr bonus","number":"1307","question":"Name 3 conformation faults of the hind legs.","answer":"Stands wide, stands close, bow legged (also called out at the hock, open behind, or bandy legged), cow hocked, sickle hocked, post legged, camped out, camped under (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-4,5; HSm385-6,7; HIH230-6,7; HH13"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"sr bonus","number":"1308","question":"Name 4 conformation faults of the hind legs.","answer":"Stands wide, stands close, bow legged (also called out at the hock, open behind, or bandy legged), cow hocked, sickle hocked, post legged, camped out, camped under (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-4,5; HSm385-6,7; HIH230-6,7; HH13"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1309","question":"Describe a horse that is \"camped out behind\".","answer":"Hind legs are naturally placed too far behind the horse. (When viewed from the side, the hind legs appear to reach out behind a line drawn from the buttock to the ground.) [accept any reasonable wording]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-7; DET46; HH13"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1310","question":"Describe a horse that \"stands under\" or is \"camped under behind\".","answer":"Hind legs are naturally placed too far underneath the horse.  (When viewed from the side, the line from the buttock to the ground does not touch the hock or the back of the fetlock.)  [accept any reasonable wording]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-7; DET254; HH13"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1311","question":"What is the slang term for thick, meaty hocks that lack in quality?","answer":"Beefy hocks  <br/> <br/>ref:DET26"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1312","question":"Which conformation fault interferes with movements that require work off the haunches such as stopping, turning, or sliding?","answer":"Cow hock  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-4; HSm385-6; HIH230-6,7; DET71; HH9"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1313","question":"What is the term for a horse whose hocks are too close together, when viewed from the rear?","answer":"Cow hocked  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-4; HSm385-6; HIH230-6,7; DET71; HH9"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1314","question":"Describe a cow-hocked horse.","answer":"Hocks are too close together (and feet are wide apart when viewed from the rear)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-4; HSm385-6; HIH230-6,7; DET71; HH9"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1316","question":"When viewed from the rear, name ONE term for a horse whose hocks are too far apart and whose feet are set close together.","answer":"Bow legged, out at the hock, open behind, or bandy legged  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-4; HSm385-6; HIH230-7"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1317","question":"Describe the term \"out at the hock\".","answer":"Hocks are too far apart (and hind feet are too close together when viewed from the rear) [also called bow legged, open behind, or bandy legged]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-4; HSm385-6; HIH230-7"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1318","question":"Describe a post-legged horse.","answer":"Horse has too little angle in the hocks (hocks are too straight as viewed from the side)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-5; HSm385-6; HIH230-7 Figure 11"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1319","question":"What is the term for a horse possessing too little angle in the hock?","answer":"Post legged (FYI:  Hind legs are straight like a post.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-5; HSm385-6; HIH230-7 Figure 11"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1320","question":"2-part question: What is the term for too little angle in the hock and the term for too much angle at the hock?","answer":"Too little angle at the hock is post legged; too much angle at the hock is sickle hocked.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-5; HSm385-6; HIH230-7"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1321","question":"What are limber or rotating hocks?","answer":"When points of hocks turn outward  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc11"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"hard","number":"1322","question":"If a horse is sickle hocked, excessive strain will be placed on what ligament?","answer":"Plantar ligament (FYI:  Sickle hocks predispose horses too curbs which are hard swellings of the plantar ligament below the point of the hock.)  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA40"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1323","question":"What is a common conformation fault of the hind limb that puts strain on the plantar ligament leading to a curb?","answer":"Sickle hock  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-5; HIH230-7; CAHA40"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1324","question":"When viewed from the side, what is the term for a horse with too much angle in the hock?","answer":"Sickle hocked (FYI:  Hock is shaped like a sickle which is a tool with a curved blade.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-5; HIH230-7; CAHA40; DET245; HH9"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1325","question":"Describe a sickle-hocked horse.","answer":"Too much angle at the hock (when viewed from the side) [Horse’s leg stands under its hip from the hock downward.] (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-5; HIH230-7; CAHA40; DET245; HH9"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"hard","number":"1326","question":"Describe a club foot.","answer":"Abnormally upright foot  <br/> <br/>ref:DET59; FCH385"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"hard","number":"1327","question":"This conformational problem causes the horse to walk on the toe, resulting in the heel growing long and the toe wearing off. The foot will have an upright appearance.  Name this defect.","answer":"Club foot  <br/> <br/>ref:DET59; FCH385"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1328","question":"A coon-footed horse has too much slope or angle at what joint?","answer":"Pastern  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-6; DET68; HH8"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1329","question":"Horses with long, sloping pasterns are predisposed to injuries of what TWO structures?","answer":"Tendons and ligaments (suspensory ligaments) [FYI:  DSLD or Degenerative Suspensory Ligament Desmitis can be a cause of a “coon foot”.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-5"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1330","question":"Describe a coon-footed horse.","answer":"Too much slope at the pasterns (long, sloping pasterns where the fetlock may hit the ground as the horse moves)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-6; DET68; HH8"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1331","question":"Describe a flat-footed horse.","answer":"When the angle of the foot is less than 45 degrees  <br/> <br/>ref:DET109"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1332","question":"Steep shoulders are usually associated with what type pasterns?","answer":"Short, steep pasterns  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-4; HIH220-6; HH11"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1333","question":"A horse with a short, steep pastern will endure more concussion and may be predisposed to what condition?","answer":"Navicular (FYI: Also called navicular disease, navicular syndrome, and caudal heel pain syndrome)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-4; HIH220-6; HH11"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1334","question":"Describe the conformation defect of the lower leg (not hoof) that predisposes a horse to navicular disease.","answer":"Short, steep pasterns  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-4; HIH220-6; HH11"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1335","question":"Short, straight pasterns are associated with what other conformation problem?","answer":"Straight, steep, or upright shoulder (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-4; HIH220-6; HH11"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1336","question":"What is the term for an excessively thick crest of the neck that flops to the side?","answer":"Broken crest or lop neck  <br/> <br/>ref:DET40"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1337","question":"What is a broken crest?","answer":"Excessively thick crest (of the neck) that flops to the side  <br/> <br/>ref:DET40"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1340","question":"What is the term for a horse’s neck that is concave on top and rounded on the bottom?","answer":"Ewe neck  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-6; DET100; HH9; FCH389"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1341","question":"Name ONE conformation fault of the neck.","answer":"Ewe neck; short thick neck  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-6; DET100; HH9; FCH389"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1342","question":"Describe an ewe-necked horse.","answer":"Upper part of the neck is concave (sags down)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-6; DET100; HH9; FCH389"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1343","question":"What is the term for a short, steep croup on a horse?","answer":"Goose rump  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-6; DET123; HH9"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1344","question":"Name an undesirable trait of the croup.","answer":"Goose rump (short, steep croup)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-6; DET123; HH9"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1345","question":"Describe a goose-rumped horse.","answer":"Short, steep croup  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-6; DET123; HH9"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1346","question":"What are mutton withers?","answer":"Low, flat withers  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-6; DET184"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1347","question":"2-part question:  What is the term for low, flat withers and why is this undesirable?","answer":"Mutton withers; don't hold the saddle very well  <br/> <br/>ref:DET184; HSm345-6; HIH220-6"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1348","question":"Describe a roached-back horse.","answer":"Back is arched up, convex, or thin and sharp (accept any)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-6; DET235; HH9"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1349","question":"What is the term for a thin, sharp, arched back?","answer":"Roached back  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-6; DET235; HH9"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"novice","number":"1350","question":"Describe a swaybacked horse.","answer":"Back sags down or is concave (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-6; DET260"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1351","question":"What is the term for a horse’s back that is concave or sags down?","answer":"Swayback (FYI:  The medical term is lordosis.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-6; DET260"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"intermediate","number":"1352","question":"Why does a thick neck cause increased shock to the front legs?","answer":"Thick neck adds excess weight to the front legs.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc9"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1353","question":"What does the term \"slab sided\" mean?","answer":"Horse’s ribs are flat (instead of rounded or “well sprung” which allows for a larger chest capacity).  <br/> <br/>ref:DET248; HH9"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1354","question":"What is the term for a flat-ribbed horse?","answer":"Slab sided  <br/> <br/>ref:DET248; HH9"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"sr bonus","number":"1355","question":"Give 3 common terms used to describe a horse that is weak in the coupling and shallow in the flank.","answer":"Hound gutted, herring gutted, wasp waisted, lady waisted, tucked up, light over the kidneys  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-6; HH4; DET275"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1356","question":"In reference to conformation, what is \"tucked up\" or “hound gutted”?","answer":"Thin and cut up in the flank like a greyhound (also described as shallow in the flank and weak in the coupling) [FYI:  Tucked up is also called herring gutted, wasp waisted, and lady waisted]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-6; HH4; DET275"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"sr bonus","number":"1357","question":"Name 3 features of conformation in horses.","answer":"Balance, structural correctness, muscling, form, type, action (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-2,3; HIH220; HH9-12"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1358","question":"Shoulder, pastern, and hoof should all have approximately what angle?","answer":"45 degrees (accept 45 – 50 degrees)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-4,5; HIH220-6; HH10-11"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"jr bonus","number":"1359","question":"Name 3 areas of the horse that should have 45-degree angles.","answer":"Head joined to neck, shoulder, pasterns (front), hoof to the ground  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-4,5; HIH220-6; HH10-11"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1360","question":"Give ONE reason why horses should have proper shoulder and pastern angles.","answer":"Shock absorption, length of stride, comfortable ride, less unsoundness, bad angles can cause other conformation faults  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-4; HIH220-6; HH10-11"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"intermediate","number":"1361","question":"Name TWO ideal conformation traits that are associated with a long, elastic, springy stride.","answer":"Sloping shoulders and sloping pasterns  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-4; HIH220-6"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"intermediate","number":"1362","question":"Give ONE reason why the croup should be long and sloping.","answer":"Increase stride length; adds dimension and muscling to the hindquarters  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-6; HIH220-7"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1363","question":"Describe how the croup in a stock horse breed, such as a Quarter Horse, differs from the croup in a pleasure breed, such as an Arabian.","answer":"Stock horse breeds have more sloping croups and pleasure breeds have flatter croups.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-6; HIH220-7"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1364","question":"At what angle should the head join the neck?","answer":"45 degrees  <br/> <br/>ref:HH10"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1365","question":"What is the ideal angle of the hoof to the ground?","answer":"45 degrees  <br/> <br/>ref:HH11"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1366","question":"2-part question:  What is the best angle for the front and for the rear pasterns?","answer":"Front pasterns—45 degrees; rear pasterns—50 degrees  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-5; HIH220-6; HIH230-6"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1367","question":"Give ONE reason why pasterns should have angles of 45 – 50 degrees.","answer":"Shock absorption, incorrect angle predisposes horse to injury or unsoundness such as navicular or laminitis, incorrect angle causes a rough ride  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-5; HIH220-6; HIH230-6"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1368","question":"What is the ideal slope or angle of the shoulder?","answer":"45 – 50 degrees (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-4; HIH220-6; HH10"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1369","question":"The angle of the shoulder is essential to the overall balance of the horse.  As the slope of the shoulder becomes straighter, what effect does this have on the length of the back?","answer":"Back gets longer  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-2; HIH220-6"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"sr bonus","number":"1370","question":"Name 3 things that are affected by the slope of the shoulder.","answer":"Shock absorption, length of stride, comfort of ride, soundness, length of back, length of neck, depth of heart (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-2; HIH220-6"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"intermediate","number":"1371","question":"How does the slope of the shoulder influence the length of the stride?","answer":"Steeper the shoulder, the shorter the stride  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-2; HIH220-6"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"intermediate","number":"1372","question":"Give ONE reason why the back and loin should be short and strong.","answer":"Support the weight of the rider, protect the internal organs, transmit propulsion from the hindquarters, lift the forequarters when the horse is in motion (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-6; HIH220-6; HH10"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1373","question":"What is the most critical conformational factor in the balance of the horse?","answer":"Slope of the shoulder  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-2; HIH220-6"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1374","question":"Name ONE way to determine if a horse has balance.","answer":"Forequarters and hindquarters are of equal size and development; height at withers equals height at hip; depth of heart equals length of legs; length from point of shoulder to buttocks equals height at withers.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-2; HH9"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"sr bonus","number":"1375","question":"Name 3 ways to determine if a horse has balance.","answer":"Forequarters and hindquarters are of equal size and development; height at withers equals height at hip; depth of heart equals length of legs; length from point of shoulder to buttocks equals height at withers.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-2; HH9"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"sr bonus","number":"1376","question":"Give 3 reasons why balance is the single most important characteristic in equine selection.","answer":"Forms the basis for movement (and ultimately performance), affects the length of stride, affects the length of back, affects shock absorption, decreases injury, decreases unsoundness (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-2; HIH220-5"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"hard","number":"1377","question":"Give ONE reason why balance is the single most important characteristic in equine selection.","answer":"Forms the basis for movement, affects the length of stride, affects performance, affects the length of back, affects shock absorption, decreases injury, decreases unsoundness (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-2; HIH220-6"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1378","question":"What percent of a horse's weight is carried on its forequarters?","answer":"60% – 65% (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-2; HIH203-1"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"jr bonus","number":"1379","question":"Name 3 GENERAL parts of the horse's forequarters.","answer":"Head, neck, shoulders, front legs  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc8,9"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"hard","number":"1380","question":"What are the TWO most important aspects of ideal conformation of the forelimbs?","answer":"Slope and angle of the bones; straightness of the limbs  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-4,5"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"hard","number":"1381","question":"When viewed from the front, how is the straightness of a horse's front legs determined?","answer":"Follow a straight line from the point of the shoulder down the entire leg to the toe  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-2; HIH230-1"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"sr bonus","number":"1382","question":"When viewed from the side, name 3 parts of the forequarters that should be in a straight line with the shoulders.","answer":"Forearm, knee, cannon, and hoof (FYI:  Straight line should run from the center of the scapula to the front edge of the knee and should bisect the hoof.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH230-3 Figure 2"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"hard","number":"1383","question":"What relationship should there be between a line from the point of shoulder through the shoulder blade and a line through the pastern to the ground?","answer":"They should be parallel.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH230-3 Figure 2"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"sr bonus","number":"1384","question":"Name 3 common characteristics of attractive, well-conformed heads for most breeds.","answer":"Short well-set ears; large bold eyes; refined muzzles; shallow mouth; large nostrils; short distance from eye to muzzle; well-defined jaw; refined chins; sex characteristics; breed characteristics  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-3; HIH220-3; HH10"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1385","question":"What term describes a face that is concave in appearance?","answer":"Dished face  <br/> <br/>ref:DET82"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1386","question":"In reference to conformation, what is a dished face?","answer":"Face that is concave in appearance (that’s often seen in Arabians)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET82"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"jr bonus","number":"1387","question":"Give 3 descriptive terms for the ideal ears for most breeds of horses.","answer":"Small, set wide apart, active, attractive, alert, proportional to head, sit squarely on top of head, point forward  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-3; HH10"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"jr bonus","number":"1388","question":"Name 3 ideal characteristics for horses' eyes.","answer":"Large, set wide apart, clear, bold, bright, tranquil or quiet, alert, deep, soft or kind expression, positioned 1/3 the distance from the poll to the muzzle  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-4; HSm385-3; HH10"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"novice","number":"1389","question":"Name ONE ideal characteristic for horses' eyes.","answer":"Large, set wide apart, clear, bold, bright, tranquil or quiet, alert, deep, soft or kind expression, positioned 1/3 the distance from the poll to the muzzle  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-4; HSm385-3; HH10"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"intermediate","number":"1390","question":"Give TWO descriptive terms for ideal stock horse pasterns.","answer":"Medium length, sloping at 45-degree angles, angles same as shoulder angles, strong, clean  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-5; HH1"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"sr bonus","number":"1391","question":"Name 3 parts of the horse that should be short.","answer":"Arm, cannon, back, loin (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-2-3 pictures; HIH220-3; HIH230-7"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1392","question":"In a balanced horse, the legs are approximately the same length as what measurement?","answer":"Depth of heart  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-6; HSm385-2"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"sr bonus","number":"1393","question":"Name 3 measurements that should be the same in a balanced horse.","answer":"Depth of heart and length of leg, height at withers and height at hips, height at withers and distance from point of the shoulder to buttock, width of shoulders and width of hindquarters  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-2"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1394","question":"On the front leg of a horse, which should be longer, the forearm or the cannon?","answer":"Forearm (FYI:  A long forearm makes a longer stride.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc10"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"sr bonus","number":"1395","question":"Tell whether each of the following 4 parts of the hindquarters should be short or long:  croup, thigh, gaskin, and cannon.","answer":"Long croup, short thigh, long gaskin, and short cannon  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-2 Figure 1; HIH220-3 Figure 2"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"sr bonus","number":"1396","question":"Tell whether each of the following 4 parts of the forequarters should be short or long:  shoulder, arm, forearm, and cannon.","answer":"Long shoulder, short arm, long forearm, and short cannon  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-2 Figure 1; HIH220-3 Figure 2"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"sr bonus","number":"1397","question":"Name 3 parts of the horse that should be long.","answer":"Shoulder, forearm, croup, gaskin, neck, underline (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-2-3 pictures; HIH220-3; HIH230-7"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"intermediate","number":"1398","question":"Ideally, in a balanced horse, what should be the relationship between the height of the horse at the withers and the length of the body from the point of the shoulder to the point of the hip?","answer":"They should be the same. (height = length from point of the shoulder to point of the hip)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-2"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1399","question":"What part of the horse needs to be deep and fairly thick with good V-muscling?","answer":"Chest  <br/> <br/>ref:HH9"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1400","question":"When viewed from the rear, which part of the horse's hindquarters should be the widest?","answer":"Stifle  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH230-7 Figure 10"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1401","question":"When viewed from the side or rear, name ONE desirable characteristic of the hind quarters.","answer":"Thick, deep, well-muscled  <br/> <br/>ref:HH11"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"sr bonus","number":"1402","question":"Name 3 areas of the hindquarters where the muscle should have thickness.","answer":"Thigh, gaskin, and stifle  <br/> <br/>ref:HH11"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1403","question":"Name ONE area of the hindquarters that should be deep, thick, and well-muscled.","answer":"Thigh, gaskin, or stifle  <br/> <br/>ref:HH11"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"hard","number":"1404","question":"What is the IDEAL top to bottom line neck ratio?","answer":"2 to 1  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-4; HIH220-5"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1405","question":"Name TWO characteristics of a good neck on a horse.","answer":"Long, lean, muscular, slightly arched, attached high on the shoulders, “clean” throatlatch; 2:1 top to bottom ratio; proportional to horse’s overall length and height; join head at 45-degree angle; blend smoothly into the shoulder  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-5; HSm345-6; HH10; HSc9"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1406","question":"The shape of the neck is due largely to the amount and shape of what?","answer":"Muscles  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc9"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1407","question":"What part of the body is used as a “balance arm”?","answer":"Neck  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-3; HIH220-5"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"hard","number":"1408","question":"The bottom line of a horse's neck is measured from where to where?","answer":"Throatlatch to the junction at chest (FYI: Top line is the distance from the poll to the withers.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-5"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"sr bonus","number":"1409","question":"Name 3 desirable characteristics of a horse's ribs.","answer":"Well-sprung, long, deep, close  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc10"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1410","question":"Why is it extremely important that the skeletal structure of the front limbs be correct?","answer":"Because the horse carries over 60% of his weight on his front legs  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH230-1; HSm345-2"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1411","question":"What is meant when it's said that a horse has \"clean legs\"?","answer":"No blemishes or unsoundness of the legs  <br/> <br/>ref:DET58"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1412","question":"What is the term for a trim throatlatch that allows the horse to flex at the poll without restricting air flow or blood flow?","answer":"“Clean” throatlatch  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-5; HSm385-3,4"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1413","question":"Give ONE reason why a trim throatlatch is desirable on a horse.","answer":"Doesn't restrict air flow, doesn't restrict blood flow, aids in balance  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-5; HSm385-3,4"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1414","question":"Give ONE reason why the bottom line of a horse should be longer than the top line.","answer":"Allows for a longer stride; so the legs don't interfere; type of stride; balance  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-6; HSm385-5"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1415","question":"Which should be longer:  the topline between the withers and the croup or the underline of the horse?","answer":"Underline should be longer.  (FYI: Back and loin should be short and strong to support the weight of the rider; underline should be long to allow for a longer stride.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-6; HSm385-5"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1416","question":"What TWO thoracic characteristics are desirable in the broodmare?","answer":"Good spring of rib and deep depth of heart  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-7; HSm385-6"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"intermediate","number":"1417","question":"Give TWO reasons why a horse should have a deep heart girth with well-sprung ribs.","answer":"Reproductive capacity; athletic performance (respiratory capacity, digestive capacity, and circulatory capacity)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-7"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"hard","number":"1418","question":"2-part question:  Describe the ideal shape of a horse's withers and explain why this shape is important.","answer":"Sharp, prominent, and well-defined; helps hold the saddle in place  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-6; HSm385-5; HSc8"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"jr bonus","number":"1419","question":"Name 3 features of ideal withers.","answer":"Sharp, prominent, well defined, same height as the hips  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-6; HSm385-5; HSc8"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1420","question":"Sharp, prominent, and well-defined describe what part of the horse?","answer":"Withers  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-6; HSm385-5; HSc8"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"sr bonus","number":"1421","question":"What are 3 measurements pertinent to a horse's size?","answer":"Height, weight, girth, bone  <br/> <br/>ref:DET137; DET129; DET120; DET34"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1422","question":"In reference to measurements in horses, how is “bone” measured?","answer":"Circumference of the cannon bone about halfway between the knee and the fetlock  <br/> <br/>ref:DET34"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1423","question":"Give ONE reason why you should NOT buy a horse with poor conformation.","answer":"Predisposes horse to unsoundness, causes a rough ride, could have genetic defects that could be passed to its offspring (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-5; HIH455-6,7; HIH910-2; HIH1090-1; HSm345-3"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1424","question":"Name ONE time when the front feet and legs serve primarily to support the horse.","answer":"At rest, when landing over a jump, when on the leading foreleg at the canter or gallop  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc6"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1425","question":"The spring-like action which absorbs concussion during movements is called what?","answer":"Shock absorption  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH505-4; HH7; HH10; HH48"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"hard","number":"1426","question":"Which of the following horses will most likely have a longer stride:  a horse with a long, gently sloping croup or a horse with a short, steep croup?","answer":"Horse with a long, sloping croup  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-7; HSm385-6"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1427","question":"A flatter and more level croup results in what type of hind leg action, more vertical or more horizontal?","answer":"More vertical hind leg action  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-7; HSm385-6"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1429","question":"Name ONE aspect of a horse’s conformation that determines its length of stride.","answer":"Slope of the shoulder, length of the shoulder, length of the forearm, slope of the croup, length of the gaskin, length of the neck (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc9-11"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"sr bonus","number":"1430","question":"Name 3 things that determine the length of a horse's stride.","answer":"Slope of the shoulder, length of the shoulder, length of the forearm, slope of the croup, length of the gaskin, length of the neck (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc9-11"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1431","question":"What is the term for a lack of refinement or a rough, harsh appearance?","answer":"Coarse  <br/> <br/>ref:HH8"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1432","question":"What is the general term that's used to describe a horse that's closely coupled and stoutly built?","answer":"Cobby  <br/> <br/>ref:DET60"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1433","question":"What is the term for the physical appearance of an animal due to the arrangement of muscle, bone, and other tissues?","answer":"Conformation (also accept phenotype)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-1; HSm385-1"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"hard","number":"1434","question":"What is the relationship of body parts to performance called?","answer":"Form to function (also accept functional anatomy)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc8"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"hard","number":"1435","question":"What slang term refers to legs in which the tendons lack definition and do not stand out clearly?","answer":"Gummy legged  <br/> <br/>ref:DET126"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1436","question":"In reference to horse conformation, what is a “hunter’s bump”?","answer":"Enlargement or bump at the top of the croup (FYI:  A hunter's bump or jumper's bump is subluxation of the sacroiliac joint.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-6"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"intermediate","number":"1437","question":"What term means an undesirable extension of the belly that’s usually caused by unhealthy conditions such as worms, disease, etc.?","answer":"Paunchy  <br/> <br/>ref:DET206; HH9"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"intermediate","number":"1438","question":"What SLANG term describes a short, thickset horse?","answer":"Pudgy  <br/> <br/>ref:DET222"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"intermediate","number":"1439","question":"What term means refinement in the horse?","answer":"Quality  <br/> <br/>ref:DET225; HH11"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"intermediate","number":"1440","question":"What term describes the condition when all of the parts of a horse blend together well, with long, tapering muscling?","answer":"Smoothness  <br/> <br/>ref:HH9"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1441","question":"What is the term for a condition of increased sensitivity to a specific protein, which may result in a rash, hives, sneezing, or respiratory difficulties?","answer":"Allergy  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH380"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1442","question":"What substance is produced in the body in response to an allergen?","answer":"Histamine (FYI: Antihistamines are medicines that treat allergies.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm370-7"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1443","question":"What is anaphylaxis or anaphylactic shock?","answer":"Acute, massive, often fatal allergic reaction (FYI: It's treated with a shot of epinephrine.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET10"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1444","question":"What is the term used for an acute, massive, often fatal allergic reaction?","answer":"Anaphylaxis (also accept anaphylactic shock)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET10"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"intermediate","number":"1445","question":"Small swellings or welts on the skin that appear suddenly and are caused by an allergic reaction are called what?","answer":"Hives (also called urticaria, wheals, or protein bumps)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH15,16,393"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1446","question":"Name 3 things that can cause urticaria or hives.","answer":"Immunologic:  insect bites, foods, medications, vaccines, chemicals, pollens, bacteria, viruses, fungi, protozoa, parasites; non-immunologic:  skin pressure, sunlight, heat, cold, exercise, stress, genetics  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm355-4; HSm370-7; FCH16"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1447","question":"When caused by feed, hives are often referred to as what?","answer":"Protein bumps  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH15,16,393"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1448","question":"What problem, characterized by inflammation of a joint, is more common in older horses?","answer":"Arthritis  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH450-3; FCH381; DET15"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1449","question":"Name TWO weather conditions that make arthritis more painful.","answer":"Cold and wet  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH450-5"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1450","question":"What is arthritis?","answer":"Inflammation of a joint (accept any reasonable explanation)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH450-3; FCH381; DET15"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1451","question":"What is another term for septic arthritis?","answer":"Joint ill  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH975-17,18"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1452","question":"What is anemia?","answer":"Decreased number of red blood cells (also the lowered ability of red blood cells to transport oxygen)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm430-8; HIH850-4; DET11"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1453","question":"Besides blood loss from trauma or parasites which causes iron deficiency, name 3 OTHER causes of anemia.","answer":"Infections (EIA), destruction of red blood cells (hemolytic anemia), toxins (red maple), dietary deficiencies (B12, folate, iron, etc.), decreased production of red blood, chronic disease, incompatible blood types (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm425-5; HSm320-6; FCH308"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1454","question":"What is an arrhythmia?","answer":"Any variation from the normal heartbeat or rhythm  <br/> <br/>ref:DET15"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1455","question":"What is the medical term for any variation from the normal heart rhythm?","answer":"Arrhythmia (FYI: Tachycardia is fast heart rate; bradycardia is slow heart rate.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET15"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1456","question":"What is the difference between bradycardia and tachycardia?","answer":"Bradycardia is a slower than normal heart rate; tachycardia is a faster than normal heart rate.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm310-13; HIH975-3; DET37; DET262"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1457","question":"What term is used to describe a slower than normal heartbeat?","answer":"Bradycardia  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm310-13; DET37"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1458","question":"What is tachycardia?","answer":"Rapid heart rate (FYI:  Tachycardia is when the horse has a sustained RESTING heart rate of over 60 beats per minute.  Fever, infection, stress, and other diseases are some of the causes of tachycardia.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH975-3; DET262"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1459","question":"Endocarditis is an inflammation or infection of the lining of what organ?","answer":"Heart (FYI:  Endocarditis is inflammation of the INNER lining of the heart; pericarditis is the inflammation of the OUTER lining of the heart.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm310-2; DET91"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1460","question":"What disease of older horses has characteristic signs of excessive hair growth and failure to shed?","answer":"Cushing’s disease (FYI: Cushing's disease is also called PPID or Pituitary Pars Intermedia Dysfunction.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm370-8; HIH795-3; HIH450-5; FCH191"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1461","question":"A pituitary tumor may cause what disease that's associated with heavy hair growth?","answer":"Cushing's disease (FYI: Equine Cushing's Disease (ECD) is also called PPID or Pituitary Pars Intermedia Dysfunction.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH795-3; HIH450-5; FCH191"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1462","question":"Cushing’s disease is more common in what GENERAL age of horses?","answer":"Older horses (over 15 years of age) [FYI:  With Cushing’s or PPID, the pituitary secretes too much ACTH (adrenocorticotropic hormone) which causes the adrenal glands to secrete high amounts of cortisol.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm370-8; HIH795-3; HIH450-5; FCH191"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1463","question":"Horses with laminitis and/or Cushing’s disease will benefit from a diet low in what?","answer":"Nonstructural carbohydrates (sugars or starches) [accept any]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm435-3; HIH770-2"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1464","question":"Name TWO signs, symptoms, or features of Cushing's disease.","answer":"Long wavy hair, failure to shed, excessive thirst (polydipsia), excessive urination (polyuria), weight loss, fragile bones, weakness, thin skin, stupor, sweating, loss of muscle mass, chronic lameness (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm370-8; HIH795-3; HIH450-5; FCH191"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1465","question":"Name 3 signs, symptoms, or features of Cushing’s Disease in horses.","answer":"Long wavy hair, failure to shed, excessive thirst (polydipsia), excessive urination (polyuria), weight loss, fragile bones, weakness, thin skin, stupor, sweating, loss of muscle mass, chronic lameness (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm370-8; HIH795-3; HIH450-5; FCH191"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1466","question":"Cushing's disease and Equine Metabolic Syndrome are often confused.  Name ONE thing that would visually indicate Cushing’s disease.","answer":"Long, wavy, or non-shedding hair coat (accept any)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm370-8; HIH795-3; HIH450-5; FCH191"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1467","question":"What is the MEDICAL term for the long, wavy, non-shedding hair coat associated with Equine Cushing’s disease?","answer":"Hirsutism (pronounced HER-sue-tiz-em or HERE-sue-tiz-em)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm370-8; HSm355-3; DET140"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1468","question":"Compared to other causes of obesity, name TWO areas where fat is deposited in Equine Metabolic Syndrome.","answer":"Crest and tail head  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH795-2; HSm435-3"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1469","question":"What syndrome is characterized by obesity, regional adiposity, insulin resistance, high blood triglycerides, and hyperleptinemia? (pronounced aa-dih-PAHS-ih-tee)","answer":"Equine Metabolic Syndrome  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH795-2; HSm435-3"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1470","question":"Name 3 management methods for Equine Metabolic Syndrome.","answer":"Exercise, maintain ideal body condition, feed rations low in sugar and starch (less than 10% nonstructural carbohydrates), feed high forage diet, test hay for sugar content, soak hay for at least an hour before feeding, limit pasture high in fructans  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH795-2,3"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1471","question":"Explain how insulin resistance in Equine Metabolic Syndrome predisposes horses to laminitis.","answer":"High insulin levels decrease blood flow to the feet.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH795-2; HSm435-3"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1472","question":"What is a goiter?","answer":"Enlarged thyroid gland (FYI:  Goiters in horses are usually due to iodine deficiency.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm430-8; HIH725-4; DET122"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1473","question":"What is the term for enlargement of the thyroid gland?","answer":"Goiter  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm430-8; HIH725-4; DET122"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1474","question":"What is hypothyroidism?","answer":"Low thyroid (FYI: Hypothyroidism can be caused by low iodine.  It can be seen in foals, but it's rare in adult horses.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET147"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"intermediate","number":"1475","question":"With eye problems in the horse, redness of the eye indicates inflammation.  What does closing the eye indicate?","answer":"Pain (FYI:  Blepharospasm is the abnormal closing of the eyelids.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH465-2"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1476","question":"Name 3 signs of eye disease in horses.","answer":"Redness, tearing, squinting (blepharospasm), drainage or discharge, color changes, small pupil (ERU), large pupil (glaucoma), scarring, growths, cloudiness, decreased vision, blindness (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH465-2"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1477","question":"Name 3 eye problems in horses.","answer":"Trauma, infection (conjunctivitis), blocked tear (nasolacrimal) duct, trauma, laceration (eyelids, cornea), squamous cell carcinoma (cancer), sarcoid, corneal ulcer, moon blindness (ERU), night blindness (CSNB), cataract, glaucoma, aniridia  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH465-2-4"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1478","question":"What is the COMMON name for inflammation of the conjunctiva resulting in redness or erythema? (con-junk-TIE-vah) (air-ee-THEME-ah)","answer":"Pink eye (FYI:  Conjunctivitis is the medical term.  The conjunctiva lines the inside of the eyelids and covers the sclera or the white part of the eye.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET212"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"intermediate","number":"1479","question":"In what breed is “night blindness” most common?","answer":"Appaloosa (FYI: “Night blindness” is the common term for CSNB (Congenital Stationary Night Blindness).  “Moon blindness” is the common term for ERU (Equine Recurrent Uveitis) which is also seen in Appaloosas.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-5"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1480","question":"What is the treatment for Equine Recurrent Uveitis?","answer":"Anti-inflammatory medications (topically and systemically will lessen the damage, but not cure the disease)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH465-3"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1481","question":"What is the most common infectious agent that causes Equine Recurrent Uveitis or ERU?","answer":"Leptospira  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH465-3"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1482","question":"What is the COMMON name for the eye disease that causes cloudiness of the uveal tract of the eye and may lead to blindness?","answer":"Moon blindness (FYI:  Other names are ERU, Equine Recurrent Uveitis, and Equine Periodic Ophthalmia.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH465-3; HSm105-5"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1483","question":"Name 3 INITIAL signs of ERU or moon blindness.","answer":"Tearing, redness, and squinting (FYI:  ERU is Equine Recurrent Uveitis which has also been called Periodic Ophthalmia and Moon Blindness.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH465-3"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1484","question":"What is the main sign of a blocked tear duct?","answer":"Wet face (FYI:  Epiphora is the scientific term for the overflow of tears onto the face when the nasolacrimal duct is blocked.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH465-2"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"intermediate","number":"1485","question":"Name ONE possible cause of choke.","answer":"Bolting food, bad teeth, lack of water, narrowing of esophagus (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-2; HIH741-1; HIH450-3"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"intermediate","number":"1486","question":"What is the term for a partial or complete blockage in the esophagus of a horse?","answer":"Choke  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-2; HIH741-1; HIH450-3; DET56"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"intermediate","number":"1487","question":"Name ONE sign of choke.","answer":"Inability to swallow, regurgitation of food or saliva from the nose, coughing, stretching and retracting neck, lump in the neck, shaking head side to side (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-2"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"intermediate","number":"1488","question":"In reference to horse diseases and conditions, what is “choke”?","answer":"Partial or complete blockage of the esophagus  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-2; HIH741-1; HIH450-3; DET56"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"novice","number":"1489","question":"What is colic?","answer":"Acute abdominal pain in horses (stomachache)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm335-2; HSm365-1; HIH435a-1; HIH795-1; HSc50"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"novice","number":"1490","question":"What should you do if you think your horse has colic?","answer":"Call the vet  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm335-2; HSm365-1; HIH435a-1; HIH795-1; HSc50"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"novice","number":"1491","question":"What is one of the most common medical emergencies in horses?","answer":"Colic  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"novice","number":"1492","question":"What is the common name for abdominal pain in horses?","answer":"Colic  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm335-2; HSm365-1; HIH435a-1; HIH795-1; HSc50"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1493","question":"A lack of what nutrient may increase the risk of impaction colic?","answer":"Water  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH710-2; HSm335-3; ES116"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1494","question":"Name TWO causes of colic.","answer":"Idiopathic; lack of water; diet changes; lack of exercise; parasites; bad teeth; moldy feed; overfeeding; eating sand; letting overheated horse gorge on cold water; riding hard after full feeding; twisted, telescoped, displaced, or trapped intestine  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm335-1,2; HSm365-1,2; HIH435a-1,2; HIH795-1; HSc50"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1495","question":"Name 4 causes of colic.","answer":"Idiopathic; lack of water; diet changes; lack of exercise; parasites; bad teeth; moldy feed; overfeeding; eating sand; letting overheated horse gorge on cold water; riding hard after full feeding; twisted, telescoped, displaced, or trapped intestine  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm335-1,2; HSm365-1,2; HIH435a-1,2; HIH795-1; HSc50"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"jr bonus","number":"1496","question":"Name 3 causes of colic.","answer":"Idiopathic; lack of water; diet changes; lack of exercise; parasites; bad teeth; moldy feed; overfeeding; eating sand; letting overheated horse gorge on cold water; riding hard after full feeding; twisted, telescoped, displaced, or trapped intestine  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm335-1,2; HSm365-1,2; HIH435a-1,2; HIH795-1; HSc50"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1497","question":"What can be fed daily in order to reduce sand-induced diarrhea or colic?","answer":"Psyllium (FYI:  Metamucil is a brand name for humans and Sand Clear is a brand name for horses.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH435a-5; FCH294; DET179"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1498","question":"Name ONE way to prevent colic.","answer":"ALWAYS HAVE FRESH WATER AVAILABLE, no sudden feed changes, don’t feed on ground, parasite control, regular exercise, dental care, keep grain locked up, psyllium for sand ingestion, restrict cold water to hot horse, prevent over-excitement  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm335-3; HIH435-4-5; HSc51"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"jr bonus","number":"1499","question":"Name 3 ways to prevent colic.","answer":"ALWAYS HAVE FRESH WATER AVAILABLE, no sudden feed changes, don’t feed on ground, parasite control, regular exercise, dental care, keep grain locked up, psyllium for sand ingestion, restrict cold water to hot horse, prevent over-excitement  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm335-3; HIH435-4-5; HSc51"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1500","question":"Name 4 ways to prevent colic.","answer":"ALWAYS HAVE FRESH WATER AVAILABLE, no sudden feed changes, don’t feed on ground, parasite control, regular exercise, dental care, keep grain locked up, psyllium for sand ingestion, restrict cold water to hot horse, prevent over-excitement  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm335-3; HIH435-4-5; HSc51"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1501","question":"The majority of cases of colic are “idiopathic”.  What does the term “idiopathic” mean?","answer":"Cause is unknown.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm335-1; HIH975-17; DET149"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1502","question":"A stethoscope is used to listen to your horse’s heart and lungs.  If your horse has colic, why would your vet use her stethoscope to listen to your horse’s belly?","answer":"To listen for gut sounds (FYI: Gut sounds are called borborygmus and are made by the propulsion of gas and fluids through the intestines.)  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA55"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1503","question":"Name TWO signs or symptoms of colic.","answer":"Acting sick, off feed, pawing, rolling, lying down, biting belly, kicking belly, sweating, change in pooping, change in gut sounds, bloating, lying on back, restless, yawning, grinding teeth, change in vital signs—TPR, CRT, mucous membrane color  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm335-2; HSm365-2; HIH435a-3"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"jr bonus","number":"1504","question":"Name 3 signs or symptoms of colic.","answer":"Acting sick, off feed, pawing, rolling, lying down, biting belly, kicking belly, sweating, change in pooping, change in gut sounds, bloating, lying on back, restless, yawning, grinding teeth, change in vital signs—TPR, CRT, mucous membrane color  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm335-2; HSm365-2; HIH435a-3"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1505","question":"Name 4 signs or symptoms of colic.","answer":"Acting sick, off feed, pawing, rolling, lying down, biting belly, kicking belly, sweating, change in pooping, change in gut sounds, bloating, lying on back, restless, yawning, grinding teeth, change in vital signs—TPR, CRT, mucous membrane color  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm335-2; HSm365-2; HIH435a-3"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1506","question":"Give 3 signs that indicate severe cases of colic.","answer":"Pulse higher than 55 bpm, rare or no gut sounds, horse is depressed or irrational, horse has clammy ears or extremities (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH435A-4"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"jr bonus","number":"1507","question":"Name 3 treatments for colic.","answer":"Walking horse (if directed by vet); pain relievers (Banamine); NG, nasogastric, or stomach tube; laxatives (mineral oil and Epsom salts); IV fluids; psyllium for sand colic; surgery (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm335-2,3; HIH435a-1,3,4; HSc50,51"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1508","question":"Name 4 treatments for colic.","answer":"Walking horse (if directed by vet); pain relievers (Banamine); NG, nasogastric, or stomach tube; laxatives (mineral oil and Epsom salts); IV fluids; psyllium for sand colic; surgery (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm335-2,3; HIH435a-1,3,4; HSc50,51"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"jr bonus","number":"1509","question":"Name 3 types of colic.","answer":"Gas, spasmodic, impaction, sand, displacement, volvulus or torsion (twist), intussusception (telescope), incarceration (trapped), verminous (worms), exercise-induced, ulcers (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm335-1,2; HSm365-1; HIH435a-1,2; HSc50"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1510","question":"Name 4 types of colic.","answer":"Gas, spasmodic, impaction, sand, displacement, volvulus or torsion (twist), intussusception (telescope), incarceration (trapped), verminous (worms), exercise-induced, ulcers (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm335-1,2; HSm365-1; HIH435a-1,2; HSc50"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"intermediate","number":"1511","question":"Why is impaction colic more common in winter?","answer":"Horses might not drink enough water.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH450-3; HIH710-1,2"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1512","question":"Name ONE part of the horse’s digestive tract where impaction may occur.","answer":"Pelvic flexure (between the left ventral and left dorsal colon), small intestine (ileal orifice—where the ileum joins the cecum), other flexures in the large colon, beginning of the transverse colon (CORRECTED 2021)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH435a-2; HIH705-2; CAHA52; HSc30"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"intermediate","number":"1513","question":"Which type of colic is caused by a blockage in the intestinal tract?","answer":"Obstruction (also accept impaction which is the most common cause of obstruction)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm335-2; HIH435-1,2"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"intermediate","number":"1514","question":"What is spasmodic colic?","answer":"Colic or abdominal pain caused by muscular spasms of the intestinal tract  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm335-1; HIH435-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1515","question":"What type of colic is a common and milder form of colic, can be caused by sudden diet changes and overexcitement, and results in muscular spasms in the intestinal tract?","answer":"Spasmodic colic or gas colic (FYI:  Gas colic, gastric dilation, or gastric dilatation occurs when the horse’s stomach fills up with gas or fluid causing painful expansion.  Gas can accumulate in the intestines and can lead to displacement colic.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm335-1; HSc50"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1516","question":"Name 3 types of colic that require surgery.","answer":"Displacement, incarceration (trapped), volvulus or torsion (twisting), intussusception (telescoping)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm335; HIH435; HIH635"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1517","question":"What happens with displacement colic?","answer":"Part of the intestine is displaced into an abnormal position (FYI:  Examples are left dorsal colon displacement and right dorsal colon displacement.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm335-1,2; HIH435a-1,2"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1518","question":"What is incarceration colic?","answer":"When a section of intestine gets trapped within the abdominal cavity (FYI: Examples are epiploic foramen entrapment and mesenteric rent entrapment.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm335-1,2; HIH435a-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1519","question":"What is intussusception? (pronounced in-tuss-suh-SEPT-shan)","answer":"Telescoping of the intestines (FYI: It usually occurs in the small intestines of young horses.  In most cases the ileum enfolds into an adjacent area of the cecum.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm335-2; HIH435a-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1520","question":"What is volvulus or torsion colic? (pronounced VOLV-you-luss)","answer":"Colic caused by twisted intestines (FYI: It occurs when the mesentery twists resulting in blockage of the intestines. Blood supply can be cut off and intestines can die or become necrotic.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm335-2; HIH435a-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1521","question":"What is verminous colic? (pronounced VERM-ih-nuss)","answer":"Colic caused by worms  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA60; DET282"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"intermediate","number":"1522","question":"What is the term for higher than normal amounts of water in the feces or for an animal defecating too frequently?","answer":"Diarrhea  <br/> <br/>ref:DET80; FCH259,387"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1523","question":"Give 3 observations that would indicate that a foal with diarrhea would require medical attention.","answer":"Large amount of diarrhea, watery diarrhea, bloody diarrhea, fever, depression, anorexia (loss of appetite), signs of dehydration (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH259"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1524","question":"What is the COMMON term for diarrhea in foals?","answer":"Scours  <br/> <br/>ref:DET240; FCH259"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1525","question":"2-part question:  What is scours and in what stage of life does it usually occur?","answer":"Watery diarrhea; occurs in foals (under 6 months of age)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET240; FCH259"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1526","question":"Name 3 causes of foal diarrhea.","answer":"Stress, diet, parasites (threadworms, roundworms), infections (rotavirus, coronavirus, Clostridium difficile, Clostridium perfringens, E. Coli, Salmonella, protozoa), foal heat, gastric ulcers, lactose intolerance, sandy soil (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET240; FCH259; HIH975-11-18"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1527","question":"What virus is a significant cause of diarrhea in very young foals?","answer":"Rotavirus (FYI:  Viral shedding lasts 10 days beyond the end of diarrhea but can last for 9 months!!  Contaminated areas should be cleaned with phenolic chemicals.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-14,15; HIH975-12"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1528","question":"Allowing a horse free-choice hay while recovering from gastric ulcers does what?","answer":"Keeps the gastric pH from becoming highly acidic  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH795-2"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1529","question":"Give 3 treatments for Equine Gastric Ulcer Syndrome.","answer":"Allow free-choice hay, turn out to green pasture, reduce concentrates, have alfalfa be 50% of the diet, feed alfalfa at 5 to 6 hour intervals (calcium buffers acid), reduce stress, medications  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm435-3; HIH795-2"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1530","question":"EGUS or Equine Gastric Ulcer Syndrome is seen in what TWO GENERAL types of horses?","answer":"Foals; horses under intense exercise  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm435-3; HIH795-2"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1531","question":"What is EGUS or Equine Gastric Ulcer Syndrome?","answer":"Ulcers of the horse’s stomach (FYI:  EGUS is often seen in foals and horses in intense training.  91% of Thoroughbreds in training and 100% of Thoroughbreds that are racing have EGUS.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH795-2; HSm435-3"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1532","question":"Name 3 risk factors for gastric ulcers.","answer":"Intense exercise, stall confinement, nervous temperament, stress (weaning), feeding high levels of concentrates (grain), low forage diet, disease, medications (such as corticosteroids or NSAIDs) [accept any correct answers]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH795-2; HSm435-3; FCH260"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1533","question":"Besides fever, depression, loss of appetite, and weight issues, name 3 clinical signs that a foal has a gastric ulcer.","answer":"Diarrhea, colic, slow growth, weight loss, grinding teeth (bruxism), gastric distension (pot-bellied appearance), lying on back, excessive salivation (ptyalism), froth around lips (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH260,261"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1534","question":"Cirrhosis is a chronic disease that affects which organ?","answer":"Liver (FYI:  Liver disease in horses can be caused by toxins, infections, drugs, tumors, etc.  Signs of liver disease may not show up until 60% – 80% of the liver has been destroyed.)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH385; DET57"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1535","question":"Name 3 feeding guidelines for horses with liver disease.","answer":"Feed at least 50% roughage in diet; feed simple grains; low protein diet (less than 8% – 10%); low fat diet (less than 5%); provide protein through branched-chain amino acids (beet pulp); add vitamin supplements (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm435-5; HIH450-5"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1536","question":"What is hepatitis?","answer":"Inflammation or infection of the liver (FYI:  Hepatitis can be caused by toxins, infections, and drugs.  Administration of tetanus antitoxin has been associated with hepatitis.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET138; HIH645-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1537","question":"Name 3 signs of liver disease in horses.","answer":"Jaundice (icterus), weight loss, diarrhea, colic, abnormal behavior (hepatic encephalopathy), photosensitivity, brownish-green urine (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm435-5; HIH425-2"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1538","question":"What is the term that describes the animal's ability to resist a particular organism?","answer":"Immunity  <br/> <br/>ref:DET149; HSc47"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1539","question":"2-part question:  What is immunity and how do horses develop immunity?","answer":"Immunity is the ability to resist a particular disease; horses develop immunity from vaccinations, previous exposure to disease, or colostrum.  <br/> <br/>ref:DET149; HSc47"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1540","question":"Name and describe 3 types of immunity.","answer":"Permanent lasts a long time; temporary lasts a short time; passive—antibodies are passed through colostrum; active—horse develops its own antibodies after vaccination or exposure to the disease  <br/> <br/>ref:DET149; DET3; DET205; HSm340-2; HIH975-2; ES169"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1541","question":"How do animals develop ACTIVE immunity?","answer":"Animal actively develops antibodies after being exposed to an antigen (either by vaccination or by exposure to the disease)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET14; HSm340-2"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1542","question":"What is the name for the disease-fighting substance produced by the immune system in response to the presence of an antigen?","answer":"Antibody  <br/> <br/>ref:DET12"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1543","question":"Active immunity is when animals make their own antibodies after being exposed to an antigen through disease or vaccine.  Passive immunity is when an animal is given antibodies.  Give ONE example of passive immunity in horses.","answer":"Giving a horse tetanus antitoxin; mare passing antibodies to the newborn foal through colostrum (FYI: In horses, mares do NOT pass antibodies through the placenta.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET205; HSm340-2; HIH975-2"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"1544","question":"To decrease the spread of pathological microorganisms, horse owners can make a homemade boot dip by adding what to water?","answer":"Bleach (FYI:  Add ¼ cup of bleach to 1 (one) gallon of water.)  <br/> <br/>ref:ES194"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1545","question":"Name 3 TYPES of microorganisms that cause infectious diseases.","answer":"Bacteria, virus, protozoa, fungus, rickettsia (bacteria-like obligate intracellular parasites), prion (Mad Cow Disease)  <br/> <br/>ref:ES167,168"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1546","question":"Name TWO SPECIFIC microorganisms that may be transmitted in horse manure.","answer":"E. Coli, Giardia, Salmonella  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH365-5"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1547","question":"Name ONE disease spread through the air when droplets of moisture are coughed or sneezed.","answer":"Strangles, influenza, rhinopneumonitis  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-4,5; HSc48"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1548","question":"Name ONE disease that can be contracted from contaminated food or water.","answer":"Strangles; leptospirosis (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-15,16; HIH445-6"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1549","question":"Name 3 diseases caused by soil-borne, spore-forming bacteria.","answer":"Tetanus, botulism, anthrax  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm340-1; HSm365-11,12; HIH445-2,6,8"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1550","question":"In what season are upper respiratory tract infections more common?","answer":"Winter  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH420-3"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1551","question":"Name 3 BACTERIAL diseases that affect both humans and horses.","answer":"Tetanus, botulism, anthrax, brucellosis, Lyme disease, leptospirosis, salmonellosis  <br/> <br/>ref:ES170,171"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1552","question":"Identify this disease:  all suspected or confirmed cases must be reported to the state veterinarian; this disease is listed as a bioterrorism alert in the US.","answer":"Anthrax  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-11; HIH445-13; DET12"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1553","question":"What disease is caused by the bacterium Bacillus anthracis?","answer":"Anthrax  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-11; HIH445-13; DET12"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1554","question":"Name 3 signs, symptoms, or features of anthrax.","answer":"Fever, colic, bloody diarrhea, difficulty breathing, muscle tremors, discharge of blood from body openings after death, abortions, blood-stained milk (FYI: Anthrax can be inhaled, ingested, or can enter through the skin!)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-11; HIH445-13; DET12"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1555","question":"Name ONE way a horse gets infected with anthrax.","answer":"Ingestion of bacteria spores (by grazing contaminated pastures), inhalation of bacteria, skin penetration (by biting flies or by open wounds exposed to infected soil or carcasses)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-11; HIH445-13; DET12"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1556","question":"Give ONE reason why anthrax bacteria can live in the soil for decades.","answer":"Low nutrient requirements; ability to survive temperature extremes  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH445-13"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1557","question":"Clostridia are deadly anerobic, spore-forming, toxin-producing bacteria that affect many species.  Name 3 types of Clostridium bacteria and give ONE example of a disease in horses caused by each.","answer":"C. tetani causes tetanus (lockjaw); C. botulinum causes botulism (Shaker Foal Syndrome, Forage Poisoning) and wound botulism; C. difficile causes diarrhea; C. perfringens causes foal septicemia and diarrhea (enterotoxemia or overeating disease)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-9,11,12,22; HSm340-1; HSm305-4; HIH640-1; HIH975-13; HIH445-5,6; FCH229,252"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1558","question":"Name ONE species of Clostridium that causes diarrhea in foals.","answer":"Clostridium difficile; Clostridium perfringens  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH975-13"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1559","question":"Name 3 ways horses can get botulism.","answer":"Ingesting bacteria or spores, ingesting preformed toxins, wounds contaminated by bacteria or spores  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH445-6; HSm365-11"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1560","question":"Wound botulism occurs when Clostridium botulinum contaminates a wound.  Name 3 types of wounds that increase the risk for wound botulism.","answer":"Puncture wounds, castration sites, injection abscesses, surgical sites, (umbilical hernias treated with clamps)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH445-8"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1561","question":"Name ONE way forage is processed that could increase the risk of botulism in horses.","answer":"Round hay bales, haylage, silage (FYI:  Horses can get botulism in 3 ways—ingestion of preformed toxin, ingestion of spores, or spores contaminating a wound.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH445-7,8"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1562","question":"Which bacterial disease is called Shaker Foal Syndrome when it affects foals?","answer":"Botulism (FYI:  Botulism is caused by Clostridium botulinum.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH445-8; HSm365-12"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1563","question":"Why do foals that have just started eating grass and hay get botulism?","answer":"Foals ingest the bacteria (spores) from the soil (which produces toxins in the foal's intestinal tract)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH445-7"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1564","question":"Why is botulism in foals sometimes called \"Shaker Foal Syndrome\"?","answer":"Because foals shake (have muscle tremors) [FYI:  Foals may ingest the deadly Clostridium botulinum bacteria, spores, or toxins when the first start eating hay or grass.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH445-8; HSm365-12"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1565","question":"Botulism is a deadly disease in horses that may cause death by respiratory failure in 1 – 2 days.  Name 3 signs or symptoms of botulism in horses.","answer":"Weakness, decreased muscle tone, muscle tremors, difficulty swallowing (dysphagia), drooling, nasal discharge, abnormal gait, difficulty standing, elephant-on-ball posture, dilated pupils, colic, difficulty breathing, pneumonia, collapse, recumbency  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH445-7,8; HSm365-11"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1566","question":"Which animal is considered the most sensitive to the tetanus toxin?","answer":"Horse  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH445-2"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1567","question":"What is a SLANG term for tetanus?","answer":"Lockjaw (FYI:  Trismus is the medical term for rigidity of the masseter muscles which causes “lockjaw”.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-4; HSm340-1; HIH445-4"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1568","question":"What system of the horse does tetanus affect?","answer":"Nervous system (specifically the central nervous system)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm340-1; HIH645-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1569","question":"What disease that affects the nervous system could follow a deep puncture wound?","answer":"Tetanus  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-4; HSm340-1; HIH445-2; HIH645-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1570","question":"Approximately how long does tetanus antitoxin give protection?","answer":"1 – 2 weeks or 7 – 14 days (accept any number within these ranges) [also accept up to 4 weeks from HIH445-3]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm340-2; HIH645-1; FCH168"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1571","question":"What SPECIFIC microorganism causes tetanus?","answer":"Clostridium tetani  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-4; HSm340-1; HIH445-2; HIH645-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1572","question":"What is the name for the disease caused by Clostridium tetani?","answer":"Tetanus (also accept lockjaw)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-4; HSm340-1; HIH445-2; HIH645-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1573","question":"Name 3 common wounds that serve as port of entry for tetanus.","answer":"Puncture wounds (hoof, etc.), lower limb wounds, castration wounds, lacerations (head or tail), contaminated surgical sites, injection abscesses, infected umbilical stump structures (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH445-2; HIH645-1; HSm305-4; HSm340-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1574","question":"How long after a wound is sustained are symptoms of tetanus likely to appear?","answer":"2 (two) days to 1 (one) month (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm340-1; HIH645-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1575","question":"Trismus is a symptom exhibited in a horse with tetanus.  The definition of trismus is the same as the common term for this disease.  What is trismus?","answer":"Lockjaw (FYI:  Trismus is spasm of the muscles of mastication.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-4; HSm340-1; HIH645-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1576","question":"What is the descriptive term of the stance of a horse with tetanus?","answer":"Sawhorse stance  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-4; HSm340-1; HSm365-9,22; HIH445-3"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1577","question":"Identify this disease: flashing or prolapse of the third eyelid, trismus or spasms of the masseter muscle, muscle stiffness, high mortality rate, and sawhorse stance.","answer":"Tetanus  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm340-1; HSm305-4; HIH445-3; HIH645-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1578","question":"Besides fever, depression, and anorexia or loss of appetite, name 4 signs or symptoms of tetanus.","answer":"Lockjaw, sawhorse stance, elevated tail carriage, protrusion of 3rd eyelid, flared nostrils, muscle rigidity, inability to eat, constant excitement, stiff gait, hypersensitivity, fast heartbeat, fast respiratory rate, difficulty breathing  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm340-1; HSm305-4; HIH645-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"jr bonus","number":"1579","question":"Besides fever, depression, and anorexia or loss of appetite, name 3 signs or symptoms of tetanus.","answer":"Lockjaw, sawhorse stance, elevated tail carriage, protrusion of 3rd eyelid, flared nostrils, muscle rigidity, inability to eat, constant excitement, stiff gait, hypersensitivity, fast heartbeat, fast respiratory rate, difficulty breathing  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm340-1; HSm305-4; HIH645-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1580","question":"Besides depression and anorexia or loss of appetite, name 3 signs or symptoms of Potomac Horse Fever.","answer":"Fever, laminitis, diarrhea (mild to profuse), colic (mild), dehydration, shock, darkened gums  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-5; HSm365-14; HIH455-11; HIH650-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1581","question":"What SPECIFIC microorganism causes Potomac Horse Fever?","answer":"Neorickettsia ristici (formerly called Ehrlichia risticii) [FYI: Rickettsia are obligate intracellular bacteria-like organisms that must live in the host’s cell to survive. Aquatic insects contain the parasite.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-5; HSm365-14,23; HIH445-11; HIH650-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1582","question":"Potomac Horse Fever is an infectious disease that can cause horses to have fever, diarrhea, colic, and laminitis.  How can Potomac Horse Fever be prevented?","answer":"Vaccination (FYI:  Vaccination might not always prevent the disease, but it may lessen the severity.  At risk horses should be vaccinated in early spring and/or mid-summer.  Horses that have contracted the disease may be immune for up to 2 years.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH445-11, 12"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1583","question":"What disease, first recognized in Maryland in 1979, is characterized by fever, laminitis, colic, and diarrhea?","answer":"Potomac Horse Fever  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-5; HSm365-14; HIH455-11; HIH650-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1584","question":"Name 3 treatments for Potomac Horse Fever.","answer":"Supportive care (IV fluids, anti-inflammatory medications); ice boots to prevent laminitis; antibiotics (Oxytetracycline) (FYI:  Antibiotics should be given early in the illness.  Symptoms quickly improve once antibiotics are started.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-14; HIH650-2"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1585","question":"What is the name of the bacterial infection that causes abscesses in the pectoral region, face, neck, and legs?  The lesions initially appear as small bumps.  House flies and stable flies may help spread this disease.","answer":"Pigeon fever (FYI:  Pigeon fever is caused by Corynebacterium pseudotuberculosis.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm355-7"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1586","question":"Equine Salmonellosis can cause profuse diarrhea in horses.  Name 3 complications of Equine Salmonellosis.","answer":"Dehydration, laminitis, septicemia, renal (kidney) failure, blood clots, disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC), hepatitis, pneumonia (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH660-2"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1587","question":"What is the most common clinical symptom of horses infected with Equine Salmonellosis?","answer":"Diarrhea (FYI:  Diarrhea is usually profuse, watery, and malodorous.  Color of feces may be from green to black.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH660-1; ES171"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1588","question":"Salmonella bacteria are difficult to eradicate or get rid of because they are very resistant and are adaptable to many environmental conditions.  Name 3 ways to prevent Salmonella infection is your horse.","answer":"Try to identify and remove the source of infection, isolate horses with diarrhea, use boot covers, boot dips, disposable gloves, wash hands, remove manure and contaminated bedding, clean stall with hot water or disinfectants  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH660-3,4; HIH975-13,14"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1589","question":"What bacteria is the most common cause of infectious enterocolitis in adult horses?","answer":"Salmonella (FYI:  There are more than 2,200 serotypes or strains of Salmonella that can affect horses.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH660-1; ES171"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1590","question":"Name 3 risk factors for Equine Salmonellosis.","answer":"Transportation, crowded conditions, abrupt change in diet, intense physical exercise, antimicrobial treatment, gastrointestinal tract disorders, surgery  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH660-1; ES171"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1591","question":"Besides fever, depression, and anorexia or loss of appetite, name 3 signs or symptoms of Equine Salmonellosis.","answer":"Profuse, watery diarrhea; foul-smelling diarrhea; blood in manure; dehydration; colic; tachycardia (fast heart rate); hypotension (low blood pressure); purple mucous membranes; no symptoms (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH660-2; HIH975-13,14; ES171"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1592","question":"Name ONE treatment for Equine Salmonellosis.","answer":"Symptomatic treatment or supportive care, fluids (oral or IV), fresh frozen plasma, hyperimmune serum, activated charcoal, bismuth salicylate (Pepto-Bismol), mineral oil, Banamine, NO STEROIDS, ANTIBIOTICS ARE CONTROVERSIAL, but are given  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH660-3; ES171"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"intermediate","number":"1593","question":"Besides depression and loss of appetite, name TWO signs of strangles in horses.","answer":"Fever (102 – 106); sore throat; swollen, hot lymph nodes; abscessed or draining lymph nodes; nasal discharge (cloudy and thick); pain with eating; stands with neck stretched out, increased respiratory rate; increased heart rate  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-5; HSm365-15; HIH445-12; HIH615-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1594","question":"Identify the following disease:  Purpura hemorrhagica is a serious complication. It’s seen in all ages of horses, but it’s mostly seen in horses ages 1 – 5 years of age. It’s caused by the bacterium Streptococcus equi.","answer":"Strangles; Equine Distemper (may accept Shipping Fever from FCH173) [FYI:  AAEP calls Shipping Fever a pulmonary disorder that occurs in animals that are shipped long distances.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-5; HSm365-15; HIH415-12; HIH615-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1595","question":"What bacteria causes strangles in horses?","answer":"Streptococcus equi  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-5; HSm365-15; HIH445-12; HIH615-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1596","question":"What is \"Bastard Strangles\"?","answer":"Form of strangles that spreads to other parts of the body (FYI:  Bastard Strangles can cause abscesses in the lungs, heart, liver, kidneys, spleen, brain, and internal lymph nodes.  Mortality or death rate is as high as 10%.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-15; HIH615-2"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1597","question":"Both purpura and petechiae can be seen with complications of strangles and are caused by leaky capillaries in the skin and mucous membranes.  What is the difference between purpura and petechiae?  (pronounced pee-TEE-kee-ee)","answer":"Purpura are large purple or red spots and petechia are small purple or red spots. (FYI:  In humans, purpura are 4 – 10 mm and petechiae are 1 – 3 mm.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-16; HIH445-12"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1598","question":"Name ONE feature of purpura hemorrhagica? (pronounced PURR-purr-ah him-oh-RAAJ-i-ca)","answer":"Serious complication of strangles; immune reaction that causes life-threatening vasculitis; causes hemorrhaging (bleeding), edema (swelling), purpura, petechiae, muscle inflammation, and heart muscle inflammation  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-16; HIH445-12"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1599","question":"Strangles is an infection mostly seen in young horses that causes fever and swollen lymph nodes.  Give ONE other name for strangles.","answer":"Equine Distemper; Streptoccous equi (may accept Shipping Fever from FCH173) [FYI:  AAEP calls Shipping Fever a pulmonary disorder that occurs in animals that are shipped long distances.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-5; HSm365-15; HIH445-5; HIH615-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1600","question":"Besides depression and anorexia or loss of appetite, name 3 signs or symptoms of strangles.","answer":"Fever (102 – 106); sore throat; swollen, hot lymph nodes;  abscessed or draining lymph nodes; nasal discharge (cloudy and thick); pain with eating; stands with neck stretched out, increased respiratory rate; increased heart rate  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-5; HSm365-15; HIH445-12; HIH615-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1601","question":"Give ONE name for the severely contagious bacterial infection that causes fever, sore throat, and abscessed lymph nodes under the jaw.","answer":"Strangles; Equine Distemper; Streptococcus equi (may accept Shipping Fever from FCH173) [FYI:  AAEP calls Shipping Fever a pulmonary disorder that occurs in animals that are shipped long distances.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-4; HSm365-15; HIH445-12; HIH615-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1602","question":"Strangles is a highly contagious infection that causes fever, sore throat, and swollen lymph nodes in horses.  Name ONE way strangles is spread.","answer":"Direct contact (touching other horses); aerosol (cough or nasal droplets); indirect contact (contact with infected secretions on tack or equipment)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-15; HIH445-12; HIH615-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1603","question":"Give ONE reason why the strangles vaccine should only be given to at-risk horses.","answer":"Can get purpura hemorrhagica; can get severe localized swelling and inflammation at the injection site; can’t give other IM vaccines at the same time as the nasal vaccine because the live bacteria can cause abscesses at injection sites  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-15; HIH445-13; HIH615-2"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1604","question":"Name 3 SYSTEMIC fungal diseases that affect horses.","answer":"Aspergillosis, blastomycosis, coccidiomycosis, histoplasmosis (Do NOT accept ringworm because it is not systemic or occurring throughout the body.)  <br/> <br/>ref:ES173"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1605","question":"Name TWO equine diseases that are caused by protozoa.","answer":"Giardia (Giardiasis), Equine Protozoal Myeloencephalitis (EPM), Equine Piroplasmosis (Babesiosis)  <br/> <br/>ref:ES174"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1606","question":"What infectious disease of horses is caused by the protozoan Sarcocystis neurona?","answer":"EPM or Equine Protozoal Myeloencephalitis (FYI:  The medication Marquis is used to treat EPM.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-6; HSm370-7; HIH670-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1607","question":"In reference to horse diseases, what do the initials EPM stand for?","answer":"Equine Protozoal Myeloencephalitis (FYI: EPM is an infection of the brain and spinal cord caused by the protozoan Sarcocystis neurona and Neospora hughesi.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-6; HSm370-7; HIH670-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1608","question":"What animal is the reservoir host for Sarcocystis neurona, the protozoan that causes EPM?","answer":"Opossum (FYI: EPM or Equine Protozoal Myeloencephalitis can also be caused by Neospora hughesi.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-6; HSm370-7; HIH670-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1609","question":"Name 3 signs or symptoms of EPM or Equine Protozoal Myeloencephalitis.","answer":"Weakness, ataxia (incoordination), head tilt, facial paralysis, facial asymmetry, dysphagia (difficulty swallowing), inability to rise, seizures, inability to rise, circling, muscle atrophy, lameness (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-6; HSm370-7; HIH670-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1610","question":"What is the COMMON name for the bacterial infection that causes the skin to crust and the hair to come off in clumps?  The skin underneath the crust is pink and irritated.  This condition is more common in hot and/or humid weather.","answer":"Rain rot or rain scald (accept either) [FYI:  The scientific name is dermatophilosis and it’s caused by the bacterium Dermatophilus congolensis.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm355-7; DET228"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1611","question":"What is another name for \"blood poisoning\"?","answer":"Septicemia or sepsis (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET33; DET241"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1612","question":"With septicemia, infection spreads throughout the horse’s body causing multi-organ problems.  How does this infection spread?","answer":"Through the bloodstream  <br/> <br/>ref:DET33; DET241"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1613","question":"“Navel ill” is a slang term for an infected umbilical stump that causes sepsis or systemic infection in foals.  Name 3 complications of sepsis in foals.","answer":"Septic arthritis, pneumonia, meningitis, diarrhea, ocular changes (accept any correct answers) [FYI:  Umbilical stumps should be treated with antiseptics such as 0.5% Chlorhexadine solution several times a day for 3 days to prevent infection.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH970-5; HIH975-3"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1614","question":"Name 3 signs of a LOCALIZED infection of the umbilical stump of a newborn foal.","answer":"Swelling, heat, purulent discharge, evidence of pain on palpation of the stump (FYI:  A systemic infection or septicemia occurs when the infection gets into the bloodstream and spreads to different parts of the body.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH975-3"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1615","question":"What is the general term for inflammation of the skin?","answer":"Dermatitis  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm355-3; DET79"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1616","question":"Give ONE term used to describe a bacterial or fungal infection of the skin on the heel or back of the pastern.","answer":"Grease heel, greasy heel, scratches, mud fever, or pastern dermatitis  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm355-7,8; DET124; DET183; DET240"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1617","question":"What is the condition known as grease heel or scratches?","answer":"Inflammation or infection of the skin on the back of the heel or pastern (also called mud fever, greasy heel, pastern dermatitis)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm355-7,8; DET124; DET183; DET240"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"intermediate","number":"1618","question":"What is an acute infection?","answer":"Infection where symptoms appear quickly (also accept any infection that lasts a short time)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm370-5; DET3; FCH380; HSc47"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"intermediate","number":"1619","question":"In reference to infectious diseases, what is a \"carrier\"?","answer":"Animal who carries and transmits a disease (who may or may not show any symptoms for the disease) [FYI:  Animals can also be carriers of genetic diseases.]  <br/> <br/>ref:DET49; HSc48"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"intermediate","number":"1620","question":"What is a chronic infection?","answer":"Infection that lasts a long time  <br/> <br/>ref:DET56; FCH385; HSc47"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"intermediate","number":"1621","question":"What is the general term for a disease that is communicable or transmissible from one individual to another?","answer":"Contagious  <br/> <br/>ref:DET69; FCH385"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"intermediate","number":"1622","question":"What is a contagious disease?","answer":"One that may be transmitted from one animal to another by direct or indirect contact  <br/> <br/>ref:DET69; ES167; FCH385"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"intermediate","number":"1623","question":"A reservoir host is an animal in which a virus lives before it causes disease in other animals.  Name ONE of the most common types of animals which serve as reservoir hosts.","answer":"Birds, rodents, reptiles  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-5; HSm320-5; HIH625-1; HIH455-5; ES169"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1624","question":"What is a dead end or terminal host?","answer":"Host from which infectious agents are not transmissible  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-5; HIH665-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"intermediate","number":"1625","question":"What is the term for the time period between exposure to an infection and the onset of clinical signs?","answer":"Incubation period  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-10; HSm665-1; DET151; FCH393"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"intermediate","number":"1626","question":"Define incubation period.","answer":"Period between exposure and first signs or symptoms of an infectious disease  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-10; HSm665-1; DET151; FCH393"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1627","question":"What is the term for the type of disease that is caused by pathogenic microorganisms such as bacteria, viruses, and fungi?","answer":"Infectious disease  <br/> <br/>ref:DET151; ES167; FCH393"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"intermediate","number":"1628","question":"What is an insect vector?","answer":"Insect that carries and transmits disease-causing organisms  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH445-4; DET281; ES169"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1629","question":"Name TWO important factors that determine whether a disease-causing organism will produce disease in an exposed animal.","answer":"Virulence (strength of the microorganism), animal's resistance, dose or amount of the microorganism, environmental stress  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH630-1; DET283; HSc47"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1630","question":"Disease-causing organisms vary greatly in their ability to produce disease.  What is the term used when the ability to produce disease is great?","answer":"Virulent  <br/> <br/>ref:DET283; HSc47"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1631","question":"What is a zoonotic disease?","answer":"Disease that is transmissible from animals to humans  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm355-8; HSm365-10,11; HIH445-4; HIH680-1; DET298"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1632","question":"Name TWO tick-borne diseases in horses.","answer":"Lyme Disease, tick bite paralysis, Colorado Tick Fever, Equine Piroplasmosis (Babesiosis), Anaplasmosis (EGE or Equine Granulocytic Ehrlichiosis), African horse fever  <br/> <br/>ref:Hsm320-5; HIH415-6,7; ES174,175"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1633","question":"Besides fever, depression, and anorexia or loss of appetite, name 3 signs or symptoms of Lyme Disease in horses.","answer":"Arthritis, dermatitis, uveitis, lameness, sweating, difficulty swallowing (dysphagia), glazed eyes, head tilt, tail paralysis, wandering aimlessly (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH655-1,2"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1634","question":"Name the disease carried by deer ticks that's caused by the bacterium Borrelia burgdorferi.","answer":"Lyme disease (also accept Borreliosis)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH655-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1635","question":"What is the COMMON name for Borreliosis?","answer":"Lyme disease (FYI: Lyme disease is caused by the bacterium Borrelia burgdorferi.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH655-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1636","question":"What is the vector for Lyme disease?","answer":"Ticks (specifically Ixodes ticks such as deer ticks (Eastern black-legged; also called bear ticks) and Western blacklegged ticks)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm320-5; HIH415-7; HIH655-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1637","question":"2-part question:  What is Equine Piroplasmosis and how is it transmitted?","answer":"Equine protozoal infectious disease; transmitted by ticks (Tropical Horse Tick)  <br/> <br/>ref:ES174; DET213; HSm320-5; HIH415-7"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1638","question":"Name TWO tick species that cause Tick Bite Paralysis.","answer":"Rocky Mountain Wood Tick and American Dog Tick (FYI:  Both produce a salivary neurotoxin that can cause paralysis in horses.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm320-5; HIH415-7"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1639","question":"Name ONE encephalomyelitis virus that both horses and humans can contract through infected mosquitoes.","answer":"EEE, WEE, VEE, West Nile, St. Louis (FYI:  Humans can also get Rabies, Anthrax, Lyme disease, Brucellosis, Leptospirosis, Ehrlichiosis (Anaplasmosis), Salmonellosis, and Giardiasis.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-10; HIH625-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1640","question":"Besides fever, depression, and anorexia or loss of appetite, name 3 signs or symptoms of Sleeping Sickness or Equine Encephalomyelitis.","answer":"Weakness, incoordination, irregular gait, seizures, hanging head low, head pressing, unable to swallow, circling, staggering, paralysis, lying down (recumbency), stupor, tongue may hang out, drooping lower lip, swollen eyelids, stiffness  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-4; HSm365-10; HIH445-4; ES177"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1641","question":"Name 4 types of equine encephalomyelitis that are transmitted by mosquitoes.","answer":"Eastern, Western, Venezuelan, West Nile (FYI:  Rabies causes encephalitis, but it’s not transmitted by mosquitoes.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-10"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"jr bonus","number":"1642","question":"Name 3 types of equine encephalomyelitis that are transmitted by mosquitoes.","answer":"Eastern, Western, Venezuelan, West Nile (FYI:  Rabies causes encephalitis, but it’s not transmitted by mosquitoes.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-10"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"intermediate","number":"1643","question":"What term means an inflammation of the brain?","answer":"Encephalitis (FYI: Encephalomyelitis means inflammation of the brain and spinal cord.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET91"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"intermediate","number":"1644","question":"What is encephalitis?","answer":"Inflammation of the brain (FYI:  Encephalomyelitis is inflammation of the brain and the myelin sheath of the spinal cord.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH625-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1645","question":"Where do mosquitoes contact Eastern, Western, and Venezuelan encephalomyelitis viruses?","answer":"From a wild host (birds) [FYI:  Rats, bats, and opossums may also serve as reservoir hosts for VEE.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-4; HSm320-5; HSm365-10; HIH625-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1646","question":"Which type of equine encephalomyelitis has the LOWEST mortality rate?","answer":"WEE (Western Equine Encephalomyelitis) [FYI:  The mortality or death rate of WEE is 50% in horses.  The mortality or death rate of EEE is 90% in horses.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH445-4"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1647","question":"Name ONE way to prevent Eastern, Western, and Venezuelan Encephalomyelitis.","answer":"Vaccination; use of insecticides; eliminate standing water; screen stalls (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH625-2"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1648","question":"Why are WEE, EEE, and VEE called \"sleeping sickness\"?","answer":"Infection causes profound depression or sleepiness.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-4; HSm365-10; HIH445-4"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1649","question":"What is the slang term for Eastern and Western Equine Encephalomyelitis?","answer":"Sleeping sickness  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-4; HIH445-4"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1650","question":"Which external parasite most commonly spreads equine encephalomyelitis?","answer":"Mosquitoes  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH445-4; HSm305-4; HSm365-10"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1651","question":"Viruses that cause Eastern, Western, and Venezuelan encephalomyelitis are arboviruses.  What is an arbovirus?","answer":"Virus transmitted by bloodsucking insects (arthropod borne virus)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH445-4; HIH625-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1652","question":"Equine Infectious Anemia viruses can only live in which animals?","answer":"Equines (horses and their close relatives like donkeys and mules)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH630-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1653","question":"What protein molecules does the Coggins test SPECIFICALLY check for in the horse’s blood?","answer":"Antibodies against the EIA virus  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH630-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1654","question":"What is the test for Equine Infectious Anemia?","answer":"Coggins test (FYI:  The \"gold standard\" test is the Coggins test which is an AGID (agar gel immunodiffusion) test.  ELISA (enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay) tests are also available.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET60; HSm365-17; HIH630-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1655","question":"The Coggins test is used to detect what disease?","answer":"Equine Infectious Anemia, EIA, or Swamp Fever (accept any)  <br/> <br/>ref:ES176; DET60; HSm365-17; HIH630-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1656","question":"A troublesome feature of Equine Infectious Anemia is that once a horse becomes infected, it’s infected for life.  Therefore, a Coggins positive horse is a threat to whom?","answer":"Other horses (FYI: Horses with EIA are either euthanized (put to sleep) or isolated at least 200 yards from other horses for life.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-17; HIH630-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1657","question":"Name ONE insect that transmits Equine Infectious Anemia to horses.","answer":"Horse flies, deerflies, biting flies, mosquitoes (ES176)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH630-1; ES176"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1658","question":"Give ONE other name for Equine Infectious Anemia.","answer":"EIA or swamp fever  <br/> <br/>ref:ES176; DET260; HSm365-17; HIH630-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"intermediate","number":"1659","question":"In reference to horse diseases, what do the initials EIA stand for? The Coggins test checks for this disease.","answer":"Equine Infectious Anemia (FYI:  DIC or Disseminated Intravascular Coagulopathy can be a complication of EIA and other diseases.  DIC can cause blood clots, hemorrhaging, and organ failure.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-17; HIH630-1; ES176"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1660","question":"Identify this disease: virus attacks red blood cells causing anemia and jaundice; no effective treatment or vaccine; once infected horse is a carrier for life; diagnosed by Coggins test.","answer":"Equine Infectious Anemia or EIA (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-17; HIH630-1; ES176"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1661","question":"EIA has 3 “stages”—acute, chronic, and inapparent.  What signs or symptoms do horses have in the “inapparent stage”?","answer":"No signs or symptoms (FYI:  Even with no clinical signs or symptoms, the horse will remain a carrier of the virus.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-17; HIH630-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1662","question":"Besides fever, depression, and anorexia or loss of appetite, name 3 signs, symptoms, or features of Equine Infectious Anemia.","answer":"No signs, weight loss, anemia, fatigue, swelling (edema), weak pulse, irregular heartbeat (arrhythmia), jaundice, enlarged spleen, once infected the animal is infected for life  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-17; HIH630-1; ES176"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1663","question":"Identify this virus:  can cause abortion in mares and death in foals; virus is also seen in swine; stallions can become long-term carriers.","answer":"EAV or Equine Arteritis Virus (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH620-1; HIH685-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1664","question":"In reference to horse diseases, what does EVA stand for?","answer":"Equine Viral Arteritis  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-13; HIH620-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1665","question":"Stallions from which TWO breeds are extremely likely to test positive for EVA or Equine Viral Arteritis?","answer":"Standardbreds and Warmbloods (especially Austrian Warmbloods)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH445-10,11"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1666","question":"Name ONE way to prevent outbreaks of EVA.","answer":"Identify carrier stallions; vaccinate stallions and teasers 3 – 4 weeks before breeding season; test broodmares; vaccinate broodmares 30 days before breeding to a carrier stallion; use management practices to prevent spread  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-13, 23; HIH445-10,11; HIH620-3,4"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1667","question":"Besides fever, depression, and anorexia or loss of appetite, name 3 signs, symptoms, or features of Equine Viral Arteritis.","answer":"Asymptomatic, swelling (edema or stocking up), nasal discharge, conjunctivitis, excessive tearing from the eyes, stiff gait, abortions, stallions can be carriers, can be transmitted via respiratory droplets or sexually  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-13; HIH445-10; HIH620-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1668","question":"Why should stallions and mares be tested for the presence of EVA antibodies BEFORE being vaccinated?","answer":"Because it's not possible to differentiate between vaccine-induced antibodies and those caused by an infection  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH445-11"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1669","question":"What sex of the horse can become a long-term carrier of Equine Viral Arteritis?","answer":"Male  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-13; HIH620-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1670","question":"What is one of the most common and fast-spreading respiratory infections in horses?","answer":"Influenza (flu)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-4; HSm365-14; HIH445-10"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1671","question":"Besides depression and anorexia or loss of appetite, name 3 signs,  symptoms, or features of influenza.","answer":"Fever (up to 106), cough (frequent, dry, harsh), nasal discharge, spreads rapidly through a group of horses  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-5; HSm365-14; HIH445-10; HIH605-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1672","question":"Give TWO signs, symptoms, or features of influenza.","answer":"Fever (up to 106), depression, loss of appetite, cough (frequent, dry, harsh), nasal discharge, spreads rapidly through a group of horses  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-5; HSm365-14; HIH445-10; HIH605-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1673","question":"How far can the influenza virus travel when an infected horse coughs?","answer":"35 yards  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-4"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1674","question":"Name ONE way influenza spreads rapidly through a group of horses.","answer":"By horses coughing, by moisture droplets traveling through the air, by contaminated surfaces  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-4; HSm365-14; HIH445-10; HIH605-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1675","question":"Rest is a primary treatment for horses with influenza.  How long should the horse be rested?","answer":"1 (one) week for each day of fever  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH445-10; HIH605-2"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1676","question":"Name ONE treatment for influenza.","answer":"Rest (one week for every day of fever); supportive care (IV fluids, control fever and discomfort, keep nasal passages clear); antibiotics only for secondary bacterial infections  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-14; HIH445-10; HIH605-2"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1677","question":"Name TWO equine influenza A viruses.","answer":"Equine 1 (H7N7) and Equine 2 (H3N8)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH445-9; HIH605-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1678","question":"Symptoms of rabies may be classified as “prodromal”, “dumb”, “furious”, and “paralytic”.  Name 3 signs or symptoms of the “furious” and “paralytic” phases of rabies.  (ACCEPT ANY CORRECT ANSWERS.)","answer":"ALTERED BEHAVIOR [aggressive, nervous, excited, hyper-aware, fearful, loss of fear, hyper-responsive (to sounds, touch)]; inability to swallow, drooling, dehydration, weakness, ataxia (uncoordinated gait), head pressing, blindness, lameness, colic  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-5; HSm365-10,22; HIH445-3; HIH680-1,2"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1679","question":"What disease of the nervous system is caused by a bite from an infected animal?","answer":"Rabies  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-5; HSm365-10; HIH445-3; HIH680-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1680","question":"Identify this disease: caused by a rhabdovirus, infects the nervous system, can be transmitted to any mammal, there’s no treatment, it’s fatal if the horse has not been previously vaccinated, and it’s transmitted by bites from infected animals.","answer":"Rabies  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-5; HSm365-10; HIH445-3; HIH680-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1681","question":"How is a diagnosis of rabies confirmed?","answer":"Postmortem examination of an animal's brain (necropsy)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-11; HIH445-3"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1682","question":"What mammal is considered to be the primary source of rabies in horses?","answer":"Skunk  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH680-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1683","question":"Name TWO wildlife species that serve as reservoir hosts for rabies.","answer":"Skunk, bat, fox, raccoon, coyote  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-5; HIH680-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1684","question":"How is rabies transmitted or spread?","answer":"Bite from infected animal  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-5; HSm365-10; HIH445-7,3"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1685","question":"It's estimated that what percent of horses have been infected with Equine Herpesvirus sometime within their lives?","answer":"90% – 100% (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH445-9"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1686","question":"What system of the horse does rhinopneumonitis affect?","answer":"Respiratory system  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-5; HSm365-13; HIH445-9; HIH610-1; HIH930-5"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1687","question":"Stable cough is the slang term for which viral equine disease?","answer":"Rhinopneumonitis  <br/> <br/>ref:DET253"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1688","question":"What virus causes rhinopneumonitis?","answer":"Equine Herpesvirus (EHV-4 and EHV-1)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-5; HSm365-13; HIH445-9; HIH610-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1689","question":"Abortions attributable to EHV-1 usually occur at what stage of gestation?","answer":"8 – 11 months (last trimester)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH610-1; ES178"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1690","question":"Equine Herpesvirus-1 causes rhinopneumonitis in horses. Name ONE other problem EHV-1 can cause.","answer":"Abortion in pregnant mares, birth of weak foals, or neurological disease  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-5; HSm365-13; HIH445-9; HIH610-1; HIH930-5"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1691","question":"For what SPECIFIC virus strain are pregnant mares vaccinated at 5, 7, and 9 months gestation to prevent abortion?","answer":"EHV-1 (Equine Herpesvirus 1)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-13; HIH445-14; HIH610-4; HIH930-5"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1692","question":"What are the TWO most common abortion-causing viral diseases in horses in the US?","answer":"Equine Herpesvirus (EHV-1) and Equine Viral Arteritis (EVA)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH930-4"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1693","question":"What is the most common cause of infectious abortions in mares?","answer":"Equine Herpesvirus-1 (EHV-1)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH930-5"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1694","question":"EHV-1 or Equine Herpesvirus 1 is known to cause abortions in pregnant mares, but it can also cause EHM or Equine Herpes Myeloencephalopathy.  Name ONE sign, symptom, or feature of EHM.","answer":"Neurological disease caused by EHV-1; can cause incoordination, paralysis, recumbency (FYI:  Outbreaks are usually associated with a mutated or neuropathic strain.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-5; HIH445-9; HIH610-1; HIH930-5"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1695","question":"How long can horses shed the EHV-1 virus?","answer":"Up to 21 days  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH445-9"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1696","question":"Besides depression and anorexia or loss of appetite, name 3 signs, symptoms, or features of rhinopneumonitis.","answer":"Fever, nasal discharge, cough, abortion (EHV-1), neurological problems (EHV-1)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-5; HSm365-13; HIH445-9; HIH610-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1697","question":"What are TWO primary reasons for the Equine Herpesvirus vaccination?","answer":"Prevention of abortion in pregnant mares; prevention of rhinopneumonitis  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-5; HSm365-13; HIH445-9; HIH610-1; HIH930-5"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1698","question":"What is the most common viral cause of foal diarrhea?","answer":"Rotavirus  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-15; HIH445-11"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1699","question":"Give 3 ways to help prevent rotavirus infections in foals.","answer":"Vaccinate pregnant mares (at 8, 9, and 10 months gestation), isolate sick foal, good hygiene (wash hands, use boot dip, wear disposable gloves and boots), good management practices (clean and disinfect stalls)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-15; HIH445-11,12"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1700","question":"Besides fever and depression, name 3 signs, symptoms, or features of rotavirus infections in foals.","answer":"Watery diarrhea, projectile diarrhea, lethargy, decreased suckling, anorexia (loss of appetite), dehydration, electrolyte imbalances, highly contagious  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-15; HIH445-12"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1701","question":"What is the incubation period for vesicular stomatitis?","answer":"2 – 8 days (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH685-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1702","question":"Vesicular stomatitis is a viral disease that results in the formation of vesicles in the mouth and on the lips, hooves, and teats.  What is a vesicle?","answer":"Fluid-filled sac or blister-like lesion (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH685-1; DET282"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1703","question":"Which disease has outward signs which are very similar to vesicular stomatitis?","answer":"Hoof and mouth disease (also accept foot and mouth disease) [FYI:  Horses do not get hoof and mouth disease.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH685-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1704","question":"What viral disease of horses causes blister-like lesions of the mouth, dental pad, tongue, lips, nostrils, hooves, and teats?","answer":"Vesicular stomatitis  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH685-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1705","question":"Which virus is the leading cause of arbovirus encephalitis in horses and humans in the US?","answer":"West Nile (FYI: An arbovirus is an arthropod borne virus.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH445-5"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1706","question":"The West Nile virus causes encephalitis which presents with neurological symptoms.  Name 3 diseases that may have similar symptoms.","answer":"EPM (Equine Protozoal Myeloencephalitis), EEE (Eastern Equine Encephalitis), WEE (Western Equine Encephalitis), VEE (Venezuelan Equine Encephalitis), rabies, botulism (FYI:  There are tests for West Nile that can be done on live and dead horses.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH665-2"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1707","question":"Since birds are the reservoir host for West Nile, finding a large number of dead ones can be a signal that the virus is present in the area.  Name 3 of the birds most often associated with West Nile.","answer":"Blue jays, crows, ravens, raptors (eagles, owls, hawks etc.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH665-2"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"intermediate","number":"1708","question":"Name ONE virus for which birds are the reservoir host.","answer":"West Nile, EEE, WEE, VEE  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-4,5; HSm320-5; HSm365-10; HIH445-4; HIH665-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1709","question":"What is the incubation period for West Nile disease?","answer":"5 – 15 days (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-10; HIH665-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1710","question":"Name ONE way to prevent West Nile disease in horses.","answer":"Vaccinate; keep horses stabled during peak mosquito activity (dusk and dawn); avoid leaving lights on in the barn; eliminate mosquito breeding grounds; prohibit birds from roosting near stables; clean water troughs; use insecticides  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH445-1; HIH665-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1711","question":"Many horses infected with West Nile will begin to improve how many days after displaying clinical signs?","answer":"3 – 7 days (accept any number within this range) [FYI:  Some horses may make a full recovery within 1 – 6 months.  Some horses will have continued neurological problems.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH445-5"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1712","question":"What is the recovery rate for horses infected with West Nile?","answer":"50% or higher (FYI:  Mortality or death rate is around 30%.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH665-1"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1713","question":"Besides fever, depression, and anorexia or loss of appetite, name 3 signs or symptoms of West Nile.","answer":"Weakness, incoordination (ataxia), paralysis, inability to swallow (dysphagia), head pressing, circling, aimless wandering, seizures, hyper-excitability, coma, behavioral changes, abnormal gait, muscle twitching, falling asleep during activities  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-5; HIH665-2"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1714","question":"Give ONE treatment for West Nile.","answer":"Treat the symptoms (rest, IV fluids, anti-inflammatories for fever and pain), pad the stall, use antibiotics only for secondary bacterial infections  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-10; HIH665-2"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"intermediate","number":"1715","question":"Name TWO health problems that can be created by moldy or dusty hay.","answer":"Colic, heaves, allergies  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH420-2; HIH740-8; HIH810-3"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1716","question":"Name 3 causes of slobbering or excessive salivation in horses.","answer":"Feeds (such as red clover, alsike clover), infectious diseases (such as rabies or vesicular stomatitis), diseases (choke, gastric ulcers), dental problems, copper bit mouthpieces, drugs, foreign bodies in mouth  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH349; HIH405-1; HIH425-2; HIH680-2; HIH685-1; HIH740-2; HIH975-11; HIH1100-10"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1717","question":"Identify the 3 diseases or conditions by the following stances or body positions: sawhorse stance; outstretched head and neck; and sitting dog stance.","answer":"Sawhorse stance is tetanus, outstretched head and neck is strangles or choke, and sitting dog stance is laminitis.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-4,5; HSm340-1; HSm365-2; HSm375-12; HIH445-3; HIH640-2; ES171-2; ES182"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1718","question":"What is the difference between hyperplasia and hypertrophy?","answer":"Hyperplasia is an increase in the number of cells; hypertrophy is an increase in the size of the cells.  <br/> <br/>ref:DET146-47"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1719","question":"What general term describes a disease of a muscle?","answer":"Myopathy (pronounced my-AHH-path-ee)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET186"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1720","question":"What is the MEDICAL term for an uncoordinated gait?","answer":"Ataxia [FYI:  Wobbler’s Syndrome or CMD (cervical spondilomyopathy) is seen in large dogs and horses and can cause ataxia.]  <br/> <br/>ref:DET17"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1721","question":"What is the difference between hemiparesis and hemiplegia? (pronounced hem-ee-pair-EE-sis and hem-ee-PLEEJ-ee-ah)","answer":"Hemiparesis is weakness on one side of the body; hemiplegia is paralysis on one side of the body.  <br/> <br/>ref:DET137"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1722","question":"What is the condition in which cerebrospinal fluid accumulates, causing the head to enlarge and the central nervous system to be abnormal?","answer":"Hydrocephalus (pronounced hie-droe-SEF-ah-lus)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET145"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1723","question":"Describe Wobbler's Syndrome.","answer":"Incoordination of the back legs (generally in growing horses) caused by compression of the cervical spinal cord  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH408"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1724","question":"Name 3 disorders of the horse that are affected by nutritional management.","answer":"Colic, laminitis, gastric ulcers (EGUS), Equine Metabolic Syndrome (EMS), Cushing’s disease, developmental orthopedic disease (DOD), hyperkalemic periodic paralysis (HYPP), exertional rhabdomyolysis (Tying Up), heaves (COPD)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm435-3-5; HIH795-1-4"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1725","question":"Give ONE common name for nutritional secondary hyperparathyroidism.","answer":"Big Head Disease, Miller's Disease, Bran Disease  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm430-3; DET28; ES135; FCH23; FCH382"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1726","question":"What causes Big Head Disease?","answer":"Excessive phosphorus and/or low calcium in the diet (FYI: Big Head Disease is also called Miller's Disease, Bran Disease, and nutritional secondary hyperparathyroidism.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm430-3; HIH725-1; DET28; ES135; FCH23; FCH382"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1727","question":"What causes horses to develop Big Head Disease, which is also called Miller’s Disease and Nutritional Secondary Hyperthyroidism?","answer":"Unbalanced calcium to phosphorus ratio (too much phosphorous compared to calcium in the horse’s diet) [FYI:  This disease was seen more commonly in the early 1900’s when working horses were fed a lot of wheat bran.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm430-3"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1728","question":"What is white muscle disease?","answer":"Disease of the muscles caused by deficiencies of selenium and/or Vitamin E (muscles become pale) [FYI:  White Muscle Disease is also called nutritional muscular dystrophy.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm430-11; HIH730-3"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1729","question":"In areas where the soil has low available selenium content, what disease can be prevalent in foals if the mares are fed homegrown feeds?","answer":"White muscle disease (FYI: White muscle disease is caused by low selenium and/or low Vitamin E.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm430-9; HIH730-3; HIH760-2; FCH31,32"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1730","question":"What is the SLANG term for a horse that bleeds from the lungs due to strenuous physical exertion?","answer":"Bleeder  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-6; HIH810-2; FCH382"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1731","question":"What is EIPH or Exercise Induced Pulmonary Hemorrhage?","answer":"Bleeding from the lungs during strenuous exercise (FYI:  EIPH is commonly seen in racehorses.  “Bleeder” is the slang term for the condition.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-6; HIH810-2; HIH850-3; HIH895-1; DET100"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1732","question":"What is epistaxis? (pronounced eh-pee-STAX-is)","answer":"Bleeding from the nose (FYI: It often occurs in EIPH or Exercise Induced Pulmonary Hemorrhage.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm430-12,13; DET98; FCH388"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1733","question":"What medication is commonly used to treat Exercise Induced Pulmonary Hemorrhage?","answer":"Lasix (also accept Salix or Furosemide)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-6; HIH810-2; HIH850-4"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1734","question":"The insertion of a fiber-optic endoscope into the horse’s bronchial tree to look for bleeding is used to diagnose what disease in horses?","answer":"EIPH (Exercise Induced Pulmonary Hemorrhage) [FYI:  An endoscope is an instrument used to examine the interior of hollow organs.]  <br/> <br/>ref:DET92"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1735","question":"What is the COMMON name of the respiratory disease, often of older horses, that causes coughing, nasal discharge, wheezing, and heaving of flanks?","answer":"Heaves (FYI: It’s also called COPD, Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease, RAO, or Recurrent Airway Obstruction.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-3; HSm380-6; HIH450-5; HIH810-3; HIH850-3; HIH895-1; HSc34"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1736","question":"What is a common respiratory disease of older horses?","answer":"Heaves (FYI: It’s also called COPD, Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease, RAO, or Recurrent Airway Obstruction.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-3; HSm380-6; HIH450-5; HIH810-3; HIH850-3; HIH895-1; HSc34"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1737","question":"Which respiratory disease is an allergic and inflammatory disorder that may develop after respiratory infections?","answer":"Heaves, COPD (Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease), or RAO (Recurrent Airway Obstruction) [accept any term or acronym]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-3; HSm380-6; HIH450-5; HIH810-3; HIH850-3; HIH895-1; HSc34"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1738","question":"Describe 3 management guidelines for decreasing a horse’s symptoms of heaves.","answer":"Leave horse on pasture, provide lots of fresh air, provide good ventilation, decrease dust, wet food, feed pelleted food, use dust-free bedding, spray down stall, use fans, adjust humidity, give medications (antihistamines, steroids, bronchodilators)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-3; HSm380-6; HIH450-5; HIH810-3; HIH850-3; HIH895-1; HSc34"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1739","question":"What is pleurisy?","answer":"Inflammation of the membranes surrounding the lungs (FYI: Pleurisy is often a complication of respiratory infections.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET214"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1740","question":"What is the term for inflammation of the membranes surrounding the lungs?","answer":"Pleurisy  <br/> <br/>ref:DET214"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1741","question":"What is the term for an infection localized in the lungs?","answer":"Pneumonia or pneumonitis (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET214-215"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1742","question":"What is the MEDICAL TERM for the condition characterized by excessive noises with breathing, especially during exercise?","answer":"Laryngeal hemiplegia (FYI:  Recurrent laryngeal hemiplegia is paralysis of a vocal cord, usually due to a damaged left recurrent laryngeal nerve.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-6; HIH810-3; HIH850-3"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1743","question":"What is the SLANG term for a horse that whistles or wheezes during exercise?","answer":"Roarer  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-6; HIH810-3; HIH850-3"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1744","question":"The vocal cords are two muscles that project across the lower part of the larynx.  Paralysis of one or both of the muscles results in a condition known as what?","answer":"Roaring (FYI: Roaring is called recurrent laryngeal hemiplegia.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-6; HIH810-3; HIH850-3"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1745","question":"Explain the unsoundness \"roaring\".","answer":"Whistling or wheezing when breathing (due to an obstruction of the larynx caused by partial paralysis)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-6; HIH810-3; HIH850-3"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1746","question":"Name 3 ways to manage rapidly growing foals to try to decrease the incidence of DOD or Developmental Orthopedic Disease.","answer":"Feed nursing foals and weanlings concentrates with 14% – 18% protein and adequate minerals; don’t let foals get obese; don’t let foals get excessively thin; feed yearlings concentrates with 12% – 14% protein with lesser concentration of minerals  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH765-1,2"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1747","question":"What is DOD or Developmental Orthopedic Disease in horses?","answer":"Group of musculoskeletal diseases affecting young growing horses (FYI:  The exact cause is unknown, but fast growth in young horses is a risk factor.  Genetic and environmental factors may be causes.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH795-3"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1748","question":"Restriction of exercise adversely impacts bone growth and development in young horses.  Without forcing foals to exercise which could lead to DOD or Developmental Orthopedic Disease, name ONE way foals can get adequate exercise.","answer":"Turning foals out in as large an area as possible for as long as possible (FYI:  24-hour turnout in a large paddock or pasture is ideal.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH765-1; FCH283"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1749","question":"DOD or Developmental Orthopedic Disease has several possible causes.  Name 3 factors that may predispose a growing animal to DOD.","answer":"Rapid growth, genetics, nutrition (mineral imbalances), exercise, trauma, obesity (FYI:  High protein diets are no longer considered a cause of DOD.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH765-1; FCH283"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1750","question":"DOD or Developmental Orthopedic disease is a multifactorial problem.  Name ONE problem associated with DOD.","answer":"Epiphysitis (enlarged, painful growth plates); osteochondrosis dessicans (defective bone and cartilage at the joint surface); flexure limb deformities; angular limb deformities; possible wobbler’s syndrome  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH765-1; FCH277"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1751","question":"In reference to skin conditions in horses, what is vitiligo?","answer":"Autoimmune condition that results in depigmentation of the skin  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-5; HSm110-5; HSm355-4"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1752","question":"Name 3 causes of skin and hair problems in horses.","answer":"Infections (bacteria, viruses, fungi), parasites (internal and external), tumors, trauma, sunlight (photosensitivity, skin cancers), genetics (HERDA), autoimmune (vitiligo), allergies, toxins, chemicals, irritants, nutritional deficiencies, plants  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm355-3-11; HIH465-2; HSm105-8"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1753","question":"What is a tumor of pigment-forming cells that's commonly seen in older gray horses?","answer":"Melanoma  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-8; HSm355-8,9"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1754","question":"Melanomas are abnormal growths of melanocytes resulting in tumor formation.  In HORSES, are most melanomas benign or malignant?","answer":"Benign (non-cancerous)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm355-8; FCH101"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1755","question":"What skin tumor is over 50% of skin tumors in horses?  It may appear smooth, round, and hairless or may look like a wart.","answer":"Sarcoid  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm355-9"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1756","question":"What is the name of a common skin condition of the horse that can resemble an ulcerated wart and may be caused by a virus?","answer":"Sarcoid  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm355-8,9; HIH465-2,3"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1757","question":"What is a sarcoid?","answer":"Type of skin tumor in horses (FYI: Sarcoids are benign tumors of horses that can recur and be invasive. They may be caused by viruses such as BPV or bovine papilloma virus, but the exact cause is unknown.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm355-8,9; HIH465-2,3"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1758","question":"Name ONE possible cause of sarcoids.","answer":"Virus (such as BPV or bovine papilloma virus); genetic component; exact cause is unknown [FYI: Sarcoids are benign tumors that can recur and be invasive.  Immunotherapy is a treatment unique to sarcoids in horses.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH465-3"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1759","question":"Name ONE area where sarcoids occur.","answer":"Eyelids, ears, head, legs, sheath  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm355-8,9; HIH465-2,3"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1760","question":"Sarcoids are common tumors of horses that are considered benign, but they are recurrent and invasive.  Name 3 treatments of sarcoids.","answer":"Immunotherapy (stimulating the immune system to cause tumor regression), surgical removal, chemotherapy, laser, freezing (cryotherapy), radiation, combination of these  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH465-2,3"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1761","question":"Name 3 of the categories of sarcoids.","answer":"Occult, verrucous, nodular, fibroblastic, mixed  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH465-3"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1762","question":"Identify this skin tumor of horses:  Skin may become raised, reddened, and ulcerated. Areas around the eyes and the tips of the ears are most commonly affected.  It’s seen on sun-exposed areas of light-colored horses.","answer":"Squamous cell carcinoma (pronounced SQUAY-muss) [FYI:  Use a dark, UV-protected fly mask on light-skinned horses year-round.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm355-8; HIH465-2"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1763","question":"Name TWO breeds that are predisposed to developing squamous cell carcinoma. (pronounced SQUAY-muss)","answer":"Appaloosa, Belgian, Paint (FYI: Squamous cell carcinoma is a type of skin cancer that develops on horses with large areas of white hair and pink skin, especially on the face.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm355-8; HIH465-2"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1764","question":"Name 3 treatments for a horse with squamous cell carcinoma. (pronounced SQUAY-muss)","answer":"Surgical removal, chemotherapy, laser, freezing (cryotherapy), radiation, combination of these  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm355-8; HIH465-2"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1765","question":"In reference to diseases, what does endemic mean?","answer":"Prevalent or very commonly found (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH930-5; DET91"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1766","question":"What is the study of the transmission and control of diseases?","answer":"Epidemiology  <br/> <br/>ref:DET97"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1767","question":"What does the term \"pathological\" mean?","answer":"Diseased condition  <br/> <br/>ref:DET206"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1768","question":"What is the term for a tumor that is not malignant?","answer":"Benign  <br/> <br/>ref:DET27"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1769","question":"What is another name for a benign fatty tumor?","answer":"Lipoma  <br/> <br/>ref:DET169"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1770","question":"Name 3 things you should INITIALLY do if your horse “ties up” or has acute sporadic exertional rhabdomyolysis.","answer":"Stop exercise, call vet, keep horse warm, check for dehydration, give pain medicine (Bute or Banamine), give sedative for anxiety (Ace), oral fluids, IV fluids (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH460-1,2; FCH211"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1771","question":"RER (recurrent exertional rhabdomyolysis) and PSSM are causes of chronic recurrent “tying up”.  Name TWO recommended dietary changes for these horses.","answer":"Decrease dietary sugar and starch; increase dietary fat; add rice bran (FYI:  There’s controversy on how much fat is needed in the diet.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm435-4; HIH460-4,5"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1772","question":"Name ONE genetic disease that can cause “tying up” or exertional rhabdomyolysis.","answer":"RER (Recurrent Exertional Rhabdomyolysis) and PSSM (Polysaccharide Storage Myopathy) [FYI:  RER is seen in Thoroughbreds, Standardbreds, and Arabians; PSSM is seen in QH’s, Warmbloods, and draft breeds.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm435-4; HIH460-3; HIH795-3"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1773","question":"Give 3 signs or symptoms of “tying up” or exertional rhabdomyolysis.","answer":"Reluctance to move; stiffness; tremors; firm, tender muscles over loin and croup; sweating (diaphoresis); rapid, shallow breathing (tachypnea); rapid heart rate (tachycardia); dark urine (myoglobinuria); males assume urinating posture  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH460-1,2"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1774","question":"What color urine can be a sign of exertional rhabdomyolysis or “tying up”?","answer":"Dark or coffee colored (FYI:  Breakdown of muscle tissue causes myoglobin to be released into the urine.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH425-2; HIH460-1,2"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1775","question":"What type of forage would be most appropriate for a horse with renal failure?","answer":"Grass forage (FYI:  Legume hays and beet pulp should be avoided because they're high in calcium; wheat bran should be avoided because it's high in phosphorous.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH450-4; HSm435-5; FCH296"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1776","question":"What part of the horse’s body is not functioning properly if the horse has renal failure?","answer":"Kidneys  <br/> <br/>ref:DET232; FCH401"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1777","question":"Name TWO nutrients that are required in lesser amounts in horses with chronic renal failure.","answer":"Protein, calcium, phosphorus  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH450-4; HSm435-5; FCH296"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1778","question":"Urinary calculi in horses are stones in the urinary tract that are most often made of calcium carbonate.  Name ONE dietary change that should be made in horses with recurrent urinary calculi.","answer":"Ensure adequate water intake; don’t feed excess calcium or phosphorous; avoid alfalfa and other feeds high in calcium; use soybean meal as a protein source instead of alfalfa; feed ammonium sulfate  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH450-4; FCH297"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1779","question":"What are urinary calculi?","answer":"Stones in the urinary tract (also called urolithiasis) [FYI:  Urinary calculi are less common in horses than in other animals.  The more often affect males because of their long urethras.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH450-4; FCH296,297; DET280"},
    {"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1780","question":"The color of a horse's urine can indicate health problems. Name 3 abnormal colors of urine and give ONE example of a disease associated with each abnormal color.","answer":"Red—bleeding in urinary tract; brownish green—jaundice or liver problems; dark brown or coffee colored—azoturia or tying up  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH425-2; HSm305-2"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1781","question":"What is a \"cutting horse\"?","answer":"Horse that's trained to separate one animal from the herd (horse used in a cutting class)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET76"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1782","question":"2-part question:  Where did the sport of cutting begin and where did the name come from?","answer":"On ranches (in the early 1800's); cows had to be separated or cut from the herd for branding, medical treatments, etc.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH180D-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1783","question":"What is the purpose of a cutting competition?","answer":"To show the ability of the horse to cut a cow from a herd and prevent it from returning to the herd  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH180D-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1784","question":"Which breed dominates cutting competitions?","answer":"Quarter Horse  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH180D-2"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1785","question":"In which equine sport does the rider \"drop\" the reins and allow the horse to work independent of any guidance?","answer":"Cutting  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH180D-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1786","question":"What specific equine competition has \"herd holders\"?","answer":"Cutting  <br/> <br/>ref:DET139"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1787","question":"During a cutting horse competition, when does the rider lift the reins and signal the horse to “quit the cow”?","answer":"When the cow turns away or gives up its efforts to return to the herd  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH180D-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1788","question":"What is the beginning score for a cutting horse entry?","answer":"70  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH180D-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"1789","question":"Name 3 things that cutting performances are judged on.","answer":"Challenges made by the cattle cut, horse's instinctive reactions, errors made by horse and/or rider (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH180D-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1790","question":"In reference to cutting, how long are horses and riders given to demonstrate their skills?","answer":"2 ½ minutes  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH180D-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1791","question":"What term refers both to a system of training horses and a competitive equestrian sport?","answer":"Dressage  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH181D-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1792","question":"Dressage has its roots in the classical horsemanship of what country?","answer":"Greece  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH181D-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1793","question":"Dressage has its roots in classical Greek horsemanship, but it was not recognized as an important equestrian pursuit until what era?","answer":"Renaissance  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH181D-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1794","question":"The term dressage comes from a French word meaning what?","answer":"Training  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH181D-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1795","question":"What do the initials USDF stand for?","answer":"United States Dressage Federation  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH181D-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1796","question":"Kur, a type of musical freestyle performance, can be seen in what TWO disciplines that originated in Europe.","answer":"Dressage and vaulting (FYI:  Reining has freestyle performances set to music, but reining originated in America.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET162; HSm185-5"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1797","question":"In reference to dressage, the popularity of dressage greatly increased with the addition of which competition?","answer":"Freestyle dressage  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH181D-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1798","question":"In equine competition, what is \"kur\"?","answer":"Musical freestyle ride in dressage  <br/> <br/>ref:DET162; HSm185-5"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1799","question":"In reference to dressage, what is the two-track exercise in which the horse moves forward and sideways at the same time?","answer":"Half pass  <br/> <br/>ref:DET128"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1800","question":"In reference to dressage, what is the movement in which the horse trots in a very cadenced, floating manner with a marked period of suspension?","answer":"Passage (pronounced puh-SAHJ)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET205"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1801","question":"In reference to dressage, what is the highly, collected trot in place with a prolonged period of suspension?","answer":"Piaffe (pronounced PEE-ahff)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET214"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1802","question":"In reference to dressage, describe the difference between the movements piaffe and passage. (pronounced PEE-ahff and puh-SAHJ)","answer":"Piaffe is a trot in place; passage (is a highly collected trot) with forward movement  <br/> <br/>ref:DET205,211"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1803","question":"In reference to dressage, describe the difference between the movements travers and renvers. (pronounced TRA-vair and RON-vair)","answer":"Travers is haunches in; renvers is haunches out (in reference to riding on the rail)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET232,274"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1804","question":"In reference to dressage, what is the correct term for a full turn on the haunches?","answer":"Volte (pronounced volt)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET284"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1805","question":"In reference to dressage, what is the term for the highly schooled movements in which the horse’s forelegs or the forelegs and hind legs are off the ground?","answer":"Airs above the ground  <br/> <br/>ref:DET5"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1806","question":"In reference to dressage, name ONE of the classical “airs above the ground” movements when all 4 feet are off the ground.","answer":"Ballotade, capriole, croupade  <br/> <br/>ref:DET22,48,73"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1807","question":"Airs above the ground refers to any of the dressage movements in which the horse's forelegs or both forelegs and hind legs are off the ground.  Which legs are off the ground when performing a capriole? (pronounced ca-pree-OLE)","answer":"Both fore and hind legs (FYI: Capriole means \"leap of the goat\".)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET48"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1808","question":"In reference to dressage, at what marker does the horse and rider enter the dressage arena?","answer":"A  <br/> <br/>ref:DET85 picture"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"1809","question":"Starting with the entry point and going clockwise, name the 8 letters of the small dressage ring.","answer":"A  K  E  H  C  M  B  F (FYI pneumonic:  All King Edwards' Horses Can Manage Big Fences; small dressage rings are 20 meters x 40 meters)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET85"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"intermediate","number":"1811","question":"Which type of walk in dressage would be completed with the horse on a \"long rein\"?  With this walk, the horse may lower and stretch out its head and neck.","answer":"Free walk  <br/> <br/>ref:TH113; DET114"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"1813","question":"Name 4 walks that might be called for in a dressage test.","answer":"Collected walk, medium walk, extended walk, free walk, working walk  <br/> <br/>ref:TH113; HH17"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1814","question":"In reference to driving, why are the tails of driving and working horses docked?","answer":"To prevent the tail from getting caught in the driving lines and harness  <br/> <br/>ref:DET83"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1815","question":"Name TWO types of bits used when driving horses.","answer":"Half-cheek snaffle, Liverpool bit, bar bit, plain snaffle (O ring, D ring, egg-butt, etc.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm155; HSm195-5"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1816","question":"In reference to tack, what are blinders or blinkers?","answer":"Solid pieces attached to the headstall alongside each eye so the horse can't see to the side without turning its head (keeps the horse looking forward)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET32; FCH382"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1817","question":"In reference to driving, what does the term \"open bridle\" mean?","answer":"Bridle without blinders or blinkers  <br/> <br/>ref:DET196"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1818","question":"What part of the harness helps the horse hold back the vehicle when there is no brake?","answer":"Breeching (also accept pole strap, thimbles, shaft cups)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET38"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1819","question":"What are the steel or wooden arms that are fitted to the collar of a harness?","answer":"Hames  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm155-10; DET129"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1820","question":"Terrets are rings on the harness of driving horses.  What passes through these rings?","answer":"Reins or lines  <br/> <br/>ref:DET265"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1821","question":"When driving a horse, the bearing rein is the rein opposite the direction of the desired movement. Which rein is the bearing rein when a draft horse is given the verbal cue of haw?","answer":"Right rein (FYI: Haw is a left turn; gee is a right turn.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET25; DET130"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1822","question":"In reference to driving, what is a jerk line?","answer":"Single rein fastened to the brake handle of a carriage and run through the driver’s hand to the bit of the lead horse  <br/> <br/>ref:DET157"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1823","question":"In driving, what are the parts of the harness that run from the collar to the singletree?","answer":"Traces  <br/> <br/>ref:DET272"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1824","question":"In reference to driving, what is the term for the cloth that's draped across the lap of passengers to keep them warm and dry when riding in a carriage?","answer":"Apron, rug, or lap robe (accept any)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET13; DET237"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1825","question":"What is the name for the metal rod on which the wheels of a carriage turn?","answer":"Axle  <br/> <br/>ref:DET19"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1826","question":"In reference to carriages, what is the \"box\"?","answer":"Driver's seat  <br/> <br/>ref:DET36"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1827","question":"English stagecoaches often were accompanied by a cockhorse that was ridden behind the coach.  What was the purpose of the cockhorse?","answer":"Cockhorse was hitched in front of the team when going up steep hills or heavy going  <br/> <br/>ref:DET60"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1828","question":"2-part question:  When driving a team, what are the verbal commands for turning and which direction are they for?","answer":"Gee is a right turn; haw is a left turn.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm195-6; DET119; DET130"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1829","question":"In reference to driving, where does the coachman sit on a hansom cab?","answer":"On a seat outside the body of the carriage behind the enclosed passenger seat  <br/> <br/>ref:DET130"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1830","question":"What term refers to the mounted horseman who rode on the outside of a stagecoach for protection from bandits?","answer":"Outrider  <br/> <br/>ref:DET198"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1831","question":"In reference to driving, what is the “teamster”?","answer":"Driver of draft horse hitches  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm195-6"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"1832","question":"Combined driving is considered a “triathlon” for driving horses.  Name the 3 phases of a combined driving competition.","answer":"Dressage, cross country or marathon, cones  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm195-3"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"1833","question":"Name 3 types of competitive driving.","answer":"Harness racing, combined driving (dressage, cross country/marathon, cones), horse shows (reinsmanship, obstacle driving, pleasure driving, fine harness, roadster pony), horse and pony pulls, plowing contests  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm195-2-4"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"1834","question":"When showing the Hackney Pony in harness classes, name 3 types of hitches used?","answer":"Single, pairs, and tandem  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH158B-2"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"1835","question":"When hitching horses one in front of the other, what are the correct terms for 2, 3, and 4 horse hitches?","answer":"2 is tandem, 3 is random, and 4 is quadrem.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm-7; DET225; DET229; DET263"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1836","question":"In reference to driving, what kind of hitch has two pairs of horses with one pair hitched in front of the other?","answer":"Four-in-hand, four up, or four-horse hitch (accept any)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm195-6; DET114"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"1837","question":"Name the 4 pairs of horses in an 8-horse hitch.","answer":"Leaders, swing team, body (point) team, wheelers  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm195-7; DET166; DET215; DET261; DET292"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1838","question":"In reference to driving, what term is used to describe the middle team in a 6-horse hitch?","answer":"Swing team (FYI:  Like the lead team, the swing team horses are smaller and more agile than the teams further back.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm195-7; DET261"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1839","question":"In reference to driving, what are “wheelers”?","answer":"Pair of horses closest to the wagon (FYI:  The wheel team horses are usually bigger and stronger.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm195-; DET261"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1840","question":"In reference to driving, describe a unicorn hitch.","answer":"Two horses hitched as a pair with a third horse hitched in front of them (pair of wheel horses with a single lead horse) [accept any reasonable wording]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm195-7; DET279"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1841","question":"In reference to driving, what term describes a hitch with two wheel horses and one lead horse?","answer":"Unicorn hitch  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm195-7; DET279"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1842","question":"In general, what is the main design difference between a cart and a carriage?","answer":"Cart has 2 wheels; carriage has 4 wheels.  <br/> <br/>ref:DET48, 49"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"jr bonus","number":"1843","question":"What are the 3 MAIN types of vehicles used in driving?","answer":"Cart, carriage, wagon (FYI:  Carts have two wheels; carriages and wagons have four wheels.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm195-5,6"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1844","question":"What is the term for a comprehensive test of both horse and rider consisting of the phases of dressage, cross country, and show jumping?","answer":"Combined training, eventing, or three-day eventing (accept any)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET62"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1845","question":"What 3 phases make up a three-day or combined training event?","answer":"Dressage, cross country jumping, and stadium or show jumping  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm190-10"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1846","question":"In reference to fox hunting, why is the scarlet livery worn by foxhunting staff commonly called “pinks”?","answer":"Famous British tailor named Pinque supposedly made the first coats  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm180-5; DET145"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"1847","question":"Rat catcher attire is only worn on very informal hunts.  Name 3 items of clothing included in rat catcher attire.","answer":"Brown or gray tweed coat; tan, buff, gray, or brown breeches; black or brown boots; white shirt with necktie; some allow the hunt’s polo shirt  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm180-5; DET229"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1848","question":"In reference to fox hunting, what is the person called who hunts the hounds and is in charge of the kennels?","answer":"Huntsman  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm180-3; DET145"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1849","question":"In reference to fox hunting, what do the initials MFH indicate when used after a person’s name?","answer":"Master of Fox Hounds  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm180-3; DET180"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1850","question":"In reference to fox hunting, what is a capping fee?","answer":"Fee paid by a visitor for a day of fox hunting  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm180-5; DET47"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1851","question":"In reference to fox hunting, what does the term “check” mean?","answer":"Temporary stop of the chase (FYI: Check may occur if the hounds lose the sent or if the pack and/or riders need to rest.) [UPDATED 2021]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm180-5; DET54"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1852","question":"In reference to fox hunting, what is the term for the bay of a hound?","answer":"Cry  <br/> <br/>ref:DET74"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1853","question":"In reference to fox hunting, what is a den?","answer":"Home of a fox  <br/> <br/>ref:DET79"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1854","question":"In reference to fox hunting, what is the term for the mounted followers of a fox hunt?","answer":"Field  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm180-1; DET107"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1855","question":"In reference to fox hunting, what does the term \"gone to ground\" mean?","answer":"Fox has taken refuge in the ground, drain, den, or other shelter.  <br/> <br/>ref:DET122"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1856","question":"Larking refers to unnecessarily jumping fences when participating in what equine activity?","answer":"Fox hunting  <br/> <br/>ref:DET164"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1857","question":"In reference to fox hunting, what is the cry of the hunt once the fox has been sighted?","answer":"Tally ho (also accept halloa or view halloo)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm180-1; HSm180-5; DET262"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1858","question":"What is gymkhana?","answer":"Games on horseback  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm165-2; HH40"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1859","question":"What is the term for games on horseback?","answer":"Gymkhana  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm165-2; HH40"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1860","question":"Scurry, potato race, speed barrels, flags, and pole bending are all activities seen at what type of equine event?","answer":"Gymkhana, games, or play day (accept any)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm165-4"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"intermediate","number":"1861","question":"What equipment is being described? This is used in speed-based events. The horse determines the “time” for this device. It has a clock that is “automatically” triggered when the horse starts the event and stops when the horse goes through the finish.","answer":"Automatic timer or electronic timer (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET18; HSm170-6"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"novice","number":"1862","question":"How many barrels are there in a cloverleaf barrel pattern?","answer":"3 (three) barrels  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm170-6"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1863","question":"What is the penalty for knocking over a barrel in barrel racing?","answer":"5-second penalty (FYI:  Each knocked over barrel adds an additional 5 seconds to the time.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm170-6"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1864","question":"How many poles are used in pole bending?","answer":"6 (six) poles  <br/> <br/>ref:DET215"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1865","question":"Which association was established to promote safe, knowledgeable riding instruction?","answer":"American Riding Instructors Association  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH193O-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"intermediate","number":"1866","question":"Name an English riding activity that a saddle seat rider does NOT usually participate in.","answer":"Jumping  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1867","question":"2-part question:  In most equestrian events, which side of an obstacle is indicated by a red flag and which side of an obstacle is indicated by a white flag?","answer":"Red flag is on the right side; white flag is on the left side.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm195-3; DET230; DET293"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1868","question":"You are completing a cross country race and are approaching a brush fence with a white flag on the right side of the obstacle.  What does this indicate?","answer":"You are approaching the fence from wrong direction (FYI: White flag should be on left side of the obstacle; right flag should be on the right side of the obstacle.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm195-3; DET293"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1869","question":"Name ONE time a rider should use the two-point position.","answer":"When jumping; when at the hand gallop (FYI:  Normal or full seat riding is called the three-point position.)  <br/> <br/>ref:PNW141"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1870","question":"What is another name for the jumping position?","answer":"Two-point position  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1871","question":"In reference to jumping, what TWO criteria determine the winner of an \"against the clock\" competition?","answer":"Rider with fastest time and the fewest faults  <br/> <br/>ref:DET4"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1872","question":"\"Against the clock\" is a term used in which equestrian discipline where the winner is determined by the fastest time and the fewest faults?","answer":"Show jumping or stadium jumping (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET4"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1873","question":"In reference to jumping, what term refers to the desirable arc a horse’s body makes as it goes over a jump?","answer":"Bascule  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm190-2,4; DET24"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1874","question":"In reference to jumping, what does the term bascule mean?","answer":"Desirable arc a horse’s body makes as it goes over a jump  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm190-2,4; DET24"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1875","question":"In reference to jumping, what is the term used when a horse rushes into a fence while jumping?","answer":"Charging  <br/> <br/>ref:DET54"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1876","question":"In reference to jumping, what does the term charging mean?","answer":"Rushing into a fence  <br/> <br/>ref:DET4"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1877","question":"In reference to jumping, what is meant when a competitor has a \"clear round\"?","answer":"Round is completed without jumping or time faults  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm190-9; DET58"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1878","question":"In reference to jumping, what is an element?","answer":"One jump in a combination  <br/> <br/>ref:DET150"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"intermediate","number":"1879","question":"What is the general term for a separation between rider and horse that necessitates remounting?","answer":"Fall  <br/> <br/>ref:DET103"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1880","question":"In regard to the horse, what designates a fall?","answer":"When both the shoulder and hip on the same side touch the ground  <br/> <br/>ref:DET103"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1881","question":"In reference to jumping, what term describes when the rail or top element of a jump is dislodged by the horse during a jump?","answer":"Knockdown (also accept rail down)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm190-9; DET161"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1882","question":"What is the term for a horse stopping in front of or passing a jump without jumping it?","answer":"Refusal  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm190-9; DET231"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"1883","question":"Identify each of these 4 jumps:  jump made of shrubs and brush with a clearly visible bar; drop jump that is a solid earthen ramp or wall; spread obstacle consisting of a sunken trough of water; obstacle that is wide rather than high.","answer":"Brush jump, bank jump, water jump, spread jump  <br/> <br/>ref:DET23; DET41; DET253; DET288"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1884","question":"In reference to jumping, what is the name for a drop jump that is a solid earthen ramp or wall?","answer":"Bank jump  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm190-8; DET23"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1885","question":"What are  cavalletti?","answer":"Raised jumps made of poles on the ground or poles on the ground which are properly spaced (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm190-8; DET52; HH43"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"1886","question":"What are 3 things that  cavalletti work teaches a horse?","answer":"Rhythm, balance, agility, lengthen stride, improve balance, loosen up muscles, strengthen muscles (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET52"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1887","question":"In reference to jumping, what type of jump has two fences set within 24 feet of each other?","answer":"In and out or combination jump (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm190-9; DET62"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1888","question":"In reference to jumping, what must the rider do when making a second attempt at a combination jump if a horse refuses the second element of a combination?","answer":"Take both jumps again  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm190-9; DET62"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1889","question":"In reference to jumping, what is an obstacle called when the wall or fence is set down in a ditch so as not to obstruct the horse’s view?","answer":"Ha-ha  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm190-8; DET128"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1890","question":"What is a spread jump?","answer":"Jump with width to it (such as an oxer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm190-9; DET253"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1891","question":"What is the umbrella organization for leaders or groups who work with youth and horses?","answer":"American Youth Horse Council  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH194O-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1892","question":"What is the name for the manager of an equestrian team who's responsible for making all the arrangements, both on and off the field, for a national team who's competing abroad?","answer":"Chef d'Equipe (chef de keep)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET55"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1893","question":"What Spanish term for roping classes is more commonly known as a favorite type of soda?","answer":"Colas  <br/> <br/>ref:DET61"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1894","question":"Freestyle patterns ridden to music are found in which TWO equestrian sports?","answer":"Dressage and reining  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH181D-1; HIH183D-2"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1895","question":"The Russian equestrian sport of kabakhi is ridden at a full gallop and includes what other type of sport?","answer":"Archery  <br/> <br/>ref:DET160"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1896","question":"In which type of competition do horses perform without personal contact from a rider or handler, as in circus acts?","answer":"Liberty classes  <br/> <br/>ref:DET168"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1897","question":"What is the term for the Australian game on horseback that is based on polo and lacrosse?","answer":"Polocrosse  <br/> <br/>ref:DET217"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1898","question":"Dressage is one of how many official Olympic equestrian sports?","answer":"3 (three) [FYI:  The 3 events are dressage, show jumping, and three-day eventing.  Reining is currently a demonstration sport only.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH181D-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"1899","question":"Name the 3 official Olympic equine sports.","answer":"Dressage; stadium or show jumping; three-day eventing, (FYI: Reining is currently a demonstration sport only with no medals.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH181D-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1900","question":"What organization is responsible for making the rules and regulations for the conduct of the equestrian sports in the Olympic Games?","answer":"FEI (Federation Equestre Internationale)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm185-1; DET105"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1901","question":"Name ONE way to restrain a pack horse.","answer":"Hobbles, picket line, highline (tie line between trees), tethering, corrals (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH27; PNW155"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1902","question":"Name TWO pieces of equipment that can be used to help stabilize a load on a pack horse.","answer":"Breeching, breast collar, croupier (crupper)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm160-2; HIH1125-2,3"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1903","question":"Which piece of equipment is used to keep a pack saddle from sliding backwards?","answer":"Breast collar  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm160-2; HIH1125-2"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1904","question":"The breast collar keeps the pack from sliding backwards.  Give ONE reason why this is important.","answer":"So the pack doesn’t slip back onto the horse's kidneys or lumbar region (accept any reasonable answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1125-3"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1905","question":"When a horse is carrying a pack load down a steep grade, what piece of rigging, other than the cinch, needs to be adjusted and pulled tighter?","answer":"Breeching  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm160-2; BEG118-1L"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1906","question":"What is the purpose of a pack saddle's breeching?","answer":"Prevents the saddle from sliding forward when going downhill  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm160-1; HIH1125-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1907","question":"When using a stock saddle for packing, what piece of equipment is used to keep the pack load centered?  This piece of equipment goes around the base of the horse’s tail and attaches to the saddle.","answer":"Croupier (crupper)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm160-2; HIH1125-3"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1908","question":"Name ONE purpose of a croupier (crupper) on a pack saddle.","answer":"To keep the pack load centered (FYI:  It can also help keep the saddle from sliding forward.  Croupiers are more suited for stock saddles.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm160-2; HIH1125-3"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1909","question":"Single, double, half, Arizona, and diamond are terms referring to what?","answer":"Pack hitches (also accept lash cinches)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1125-1; HSm160-3"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1910","question":"What is another name for a basket or barrel hitch?","answer":"Sling hitch  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm160-1; HIH1125-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1911","question":"Why is the “hitch” in packing important?","answer":"The hitch secures the balanced load to the pack animal (FYI:  The lash rope is tied with a \"hitch\" or kind of knot which secures the mantied load on the pack saddle.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm160-1; HIH1125-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"jr bonus","number":"1912","question":"Name 3 hitches used in packing.","answer":"Squaw hitch, half diamond, single diamond, double diamond, triple diamond, one-man diamond, box hitch, Arizona, square, sling, basket, barrel  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm160-3; HIH1125-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"1913","question":"Name 4 hitches used in packing.","answer":"Squaw hitch, half diamond, single diamond, double diamond, triple diamond, one-man diamond, box hitch, Arizona, square, sling, basket, barrel  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm160-3; HIH1125-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1914","question":"What is a half-inch rope of soft, twisted nylon 45 – 50 feet in length that's used to secure the entire load on a pack saddle?","answer":"Lash rope  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1125-5; HSm160-3"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1915","question":"In reference to packing, what is a lash rope used for?","answer":"To tie the load onto the pack saddle  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1125-5; HSm160-3"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1916","question":"What must be balanced and centered on a pack animal?","answer":"Load or pack  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1125-5; HSm160-3"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1917","question":"In reference to packing, what is a manta or mantee?","answer":"Canvas cover used to cover the load when packing  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm160-1; HIH1125-1,3"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1918","question":"In reference to packing, what does the term \"mantied\" mean?","answer":"Load is placed in a canvas cover.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm160-1; HIH1125-1,3"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1919","question":"A piece of canvas which is used to cover a pack load is called what?","answer":"Manta or mantee  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm160-1; HIH1125-1,3"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1920","question":"In reference to packing, what is a pannier?","answer":"Container used for carrying supplies while packing  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm160-2; HIH1125-2-5"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1921","question":"What is the name for the piece of equipment that's used to carry supplies on a pack trip?","answer":"Panniers  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm160-2; HIH1125-2-5"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"intermediate","number":"1922","question":"What item of pack equipment could contain shelves or double as a small table?","answer":"Panniers  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1125-3"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1923","question":"What is the purpose of a quarter strap in packing?","answer":"Reduce cinch sores  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1125-2 Picture"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1924","question":"Traditional pack saddles come in two styles.  Name them.","answer":"Crossbuck or sawbuck and Decker  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm160-2; HIH1125-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"1925","question":"Name 3 types of saddles that can be used in packing.","answer":"Decker, crossbuck or sawbuck, McClellan, Western or stock  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm160-1; HIH1125-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"intermediate","number":"1926","question":"When comparing crossbuck and Decker saddles, which is better suited to a sling load that's mantied?","answer":"Decker  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm160-1; HIH1125-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1927","question":"What type of pack saddle has a centerfire single cinch and is used with a half breed?","answer":"Decker  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm160-1; HIH1125-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1928","question":"How many cinches are on a Decker pack saddle?","answer":"1 (one) cinch  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm160-1; HIH1125-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1929","question":"Which pack saddle has a single cinch?","answer":"Decker  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm160-1; HIH1125-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1930","question":"2-part question:  In reference to packing, describe a half-breed and explain how it's used.","answer":"Heavy canvas pad with wooden bars at the bottom used over a Decker saddle; provides extra padding and holds the pack away from the animal's sides  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm160-1; HIH1125-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1931","question":"In reference to packing, what is the purpose of the half-breed?","answer":"To provide extra padding or to hold pack away from the animal's sides (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm160-1; HIH1125-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1932","question":"Why is a traditional McClellan saddle a reasonably effective packsaddle?","answer":"Lightweight; has plenty of rings and straps to tie things  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm160-1; HIH1125-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1933","question":"What is the use of a sawbuck saddle?","answer":"Packing  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm160-1; HIH1125-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1934","question":"On a sawbuck or crossbuck saddle, where is sheepskin lining added for more protection and comfort?","answer":"Blades  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm160-1; HIH1125-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1935","question":"Extra-long crossbucks are used for what purpose?","answer":"To hold the pack away from the animal's sides  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm160-1; HIH1125-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1936","question":"Which pack saddle has a double rigged cinch?","answer":"Crossbuck or sawbuck  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm160-1; HIH1125-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1937","question":"What type of rigging does a crossbuck or sawbuck saddle have?","answer":"Double rigging  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm160-1; HIH1125-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1938","question":"Over what TWO parts of a stock saddle would panniers fit?","answer":"Cantle and swells  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1125-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1939","question":"You do not have a crossbuck or Decker saddle available, but you want to go packing.  What other COMMONLY available saddle could you use with some modifications?","answer":"Western saddle (stock saddle)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm160-1; HIH1125-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1940","question":"Why is a horse or mule with little or no withers undesirable as a pack animal?","answer":"Because the pack saddle won’t fit well (which may cause sores)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm160-2; HIH1125-2"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1941","question":"2-part question:  In regard to withers, what type of conformation is undesirable in a pack horse and why?","answer":"Little or no withers allows the saddle to turn and rub or creates sores; withers that are too high are harder to fit and more prone to sores.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm160-2; HIH1125-2"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1942","question":"In choosing a pack horse, what kind of withers are best?","answer":"Medium high withers  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm160-2; HIH1125-2"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1943","question":"Polo matches are divided into 7 ½ minute periods called what?","answer":"Chukkers (chukkas)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET56; HH40"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1944","question":"What is possibly the oldest team equine sport?","answer":"Polo  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH182D-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1945","question":"What is the name of the game played by teams on horseback using mallets to hit a wooden ball?","answer":"Polo  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH182D-1; HH40"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"1946","question":"Name 3 programs offered by the United States Pony Club.","answer":"Dressage, stadium or show jumping, eventing (dressage, cross country jumping, and show jumping), mounted games, tetrathlon, know-down (quiz), fox hunting, polocrosse, vaulting  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH199O-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"intermediate","number":"1947","question":"What do the initials USPC stand for?","answer":"United States Pony Club  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH199O-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1948","question":"What historic events took place at Circus Maximus?","answer":"(Roman) chariot races  <br/> <br/>ref:DET57"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1949","question":"What is a race without jumps?","answer":"Flat race  <br/> <br/>ref:DET109; HH40"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"1950","question":"Name 3 different types of horse racing.","answer":"Flat, harness, steeplechase, chuckwagon, chariot, endurance (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm175-1; DET109,130,255"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"1951","question":"2-part question:  Explain the difference between harness racing and flat racing and name TWO breeds that participate in each.","answer":"Harness races are driving races (with sulkies).  Breeds are Standardbred, Trottingbred Pony, Russian Trotter, and Orlov.  Flat races are riding races (without jumps).  Breeds are Thoroughbreds, Quarter Horses, Appaloosas, Paints, and Arabians.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm175-1; DET130; DET109"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1952","question":"What is a flat race?","answer":"Race without jumps  <br/> <br/>ref:DET109; HH40"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1953","question":"Which breed excels in distance riding and is known for its great endurance?","answer":"Arabian  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-1; HIH153B-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"intermediate","number":"1954","question":"What is the distance of most endurance races?","answer":"25 – 100 miles (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm175-3"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1955","question":"The Tevis Cup is an endurance ride that takes place in California each year.  What famous route does this ride follow?","answer":"Pony Express route  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm175-3; DET266"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1956","question":"What is the name of the endurance competition that is ridden over the old Pony Express route from Lake Tahoe to Auburn, California?","answer":"Tevis Cup  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm175-3; DET266"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1957","question":"In reference to horse racing, what is the term used for administering an illegal drug to a horse to increase or decrease its speed or performance?","answer":"Doping  <br/> <br/>ref:DET84"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1958","question":"Administering drugs to a horse to improve or hinder his performance in a race or competition is known as doping.  Name 3 body fluids that may be tested to detect doping","answer":"Urine, saliva, blood  <br/> <br/>ref:DET84; DET227"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"novice","number":"1959","question":"What do you call the person who rides a horse in a race?","answer":"Jockey  <br/> <br/>ref:DET158"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1960","question":"In reference to horse racing, what is the term for when jockeys ride with one stirrup longer than the other to help keep their balance on sharp turns?","answer":"Acey-deucy  <br/> <br/>ref:DET2"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"intermediate","number":"1961","question":"Give ONE term used for a jockey in training.","answer":"Apprentice; bug boy  <br/> <br/>ref:DET14; DET42"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1962","question":"In reference to horse racing, what does the term \"blow a stirrup\" mean?","answer":"Lose a stirrup iron  <br/> <br/>ref:DET33"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1963","question":"In reference to horse racing, who chooses the colors of the jacket and cap worn by a jockey in the Kentucky Derby?","answer":"Horse's owners  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm175-7; DET245"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1964","question":"In reference to horse racing, what are the cap and jacket of a jockey called?","answer":"Silks  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm175-7; DET245"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1965","question":"When running a quarter mile, racing Quarter Horses have been clocked at up to what speed?","answer":"50 – 55 miles per hour (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm175-1; HSm380-2; ES83"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"novice","number":"1966","question":"Name ONE distance at which Quarter Horses race.","answer":"440 yards (also accept 1/4 or a quarter mile) [accept any number between 220 – 870 yards] {FYI:  Paints and Appaloosas race similar distances of 220 yards – 8 furlongs.}  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm175-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1967","question":"The Ruidoso Futurity, Rainbow Futurity, and All American Futurity make up the Triple Crown for what breed of racehorse?","answer":"Quarter Horse (FYI:  The Champion of Champions is another big QH race.  The only horse to win the QH Triple Crown was Special Effort.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm175-10"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1968","question":"The Little Brown Jug, Hambletonian, and Messenger Stakes are races for what breed of horses?","answer":"Standardbreds (FYI:  Trotting races are Hambletonian, Yonkers Trot, and Kentucky Futurity; pacing races are Cane Pace, Little Brown Jug, and Messenger Stakes.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm175-11"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1969","question":"In reference to harness racing, what is a \"free-legged\" pacer?","answer":"Pacer who races without hobbles  <br/> <br/>ref:DET114"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1970","question":"In reference to harness racing, what is the name of the light, two-wheeled racing rig?","answer":"Sulky  <br/> <br/>ref:DET259"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1971","question":"What is the primary difference between the horses that are raced in the Kentucky Derby and the Kentucky Oaks?","answer":"Kentucky Oaks is a race for fillies only (FYI: Both races are for 3-year-old Thoroughbreds.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm175-10; DET161"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1972","question":"The Breeders Cup is a race for what breed of horses?","answer":"Thoroughbreds (FYI:  Arabian races may also be held during Thoroughbred stakes races such as the Breeder’s Cup, Preakness, Kentucky Derby, etc.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm175-10"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1973","question":"At what age do Thoroughbred horses compete for the Triple Crown?","answer":"3 (three) years of age  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm175-10"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"jr bonus","number":"1974","question":"Name the 3 Thoroughbred races included in the Triple Crown.","answer":"Kentucky Derby, Preakness (Stakes), and Belmont (Stakes)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm175-10; DET274"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1975","question":"Name the 3 Thoroughbred races included in the Triple Crown.","answer":"Kentucky Derby, Preakness (Stakes), and Belmont (Stakes)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm175-10; DET274"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1976","question":"Collectively, the Kentucky Derby, Preakness Stakes, and Belmont Stakes are known as what?","answer":"Triple Crown  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm175-10; DET274"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1977","question":"Identify this Grade I Thoroughbred Stakes Race:  Secretariat still holds the record for the fastest time; winners are adorned with a blanket of white carnations; distance is 1 ½ miles; location is Belmont Park in Elmont, NY.","answer":"Belmont (FYI: Belmont is 1 ½ miles.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm175-10; DET27"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1978","question":"Identify this Grade I Thoroughbred Stakes Race:  distance is 1 ¼ mile; nickname is “Run for the Roses”; location is Churchill Downs; theme song is “My Old Kentucky Home”.","answer":"Kentucky Derby (FYI:  In 1875 Aristides was the first winner of the Kentucky Derby.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm175-10"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1979","question":"Identify this Grade I Thoroughbred Stakes Race:  held at Pimlico Race Course in Baltimore, MD; winners are adorned with a blanket of black-eyed susans; distance is 1 3/16 miles.","answer":"Preakness (Stakes)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm175-10; DET219"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"1980","question":"Name 3 Thoroughbred Triple Crown winners.","answer":"Sir Barton (1919), Gallant Fox (1930), Omaha (1935), War Admiral (1937), Whirlaway (1941), Count Fleet (1943), Assault (1946), Citation (1948), Secretariat (1973), Seattle Slew (1977), Affirmed (1978), American Pharoah (2015), Justify (2018)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm175-10"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1981","question":"2-part question:  In reference to horse racing, what is the difference between a Derby and a Futurity?","answer":"Derby is a race for 3-year-olds; futurity is a race for 2-year-olds.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm175-4"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1982","question":"In reference to Thoroughbred racing, what is an “allowance” race?","answer":"Races that have specific conditions that the horses must meet before they can compete.  (FYI:  Allowance Races are just below Stakes Races.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm175-4"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1983","question":"In reference to Thoroughbred racing, what is a \"claiming race\"?","answer":"Race in which every entered is for sale for a predetermined price. (FYI:  Horses are entered for a set price known as a “tag”. )  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm175-4; DET227"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1984","question":"What is done in handicapped races to try to equalize horses’ chances of winning?","answer":"Each horse is assigned a designated weight.  (FYI:  Weight is assigned based on age of horse, gender of horse, and horse’s past performances.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm175-4; DET129"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1985","question":"In reference to horse racing, what does the term \"maiden\" mean?","answer":"Horse that has never won a race  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm175-4; DET174"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1986","question":"In Thoroughbred racing, what is the SPECIFIC type of race for the highest level of competition?","answer":"Grade I Stakes Race  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm175-4"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1987","question":"In reference to horse racing, where did the name \"steeplechase\" come from?","answer":"In the late 1700's, races often went from one church to another. (FYI:  Current steeplechase jumps have a steel frame with plastic brush and a foam rubber roll on takeoff and are 54 inches tall.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET255"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1988","question":"In reference to horse racing, what is the name given to a race over natural or artificial obstacles such as fences, hedges, and water jumps?","answer":"Steeplechase (FYI:  Steeplechases get their name from races in the 1700’s that went from church to church. Current steeplechase jumps have a steel frame with plastic brush and a foam rubber roll on takeoff and are 54 inches tall.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm175-2; DET255"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1989","question":"In reference to horse racing, what is the type of wagering where the person placing the bet must pick the first and second finishers in exact order?","answer":"Exacta (FYI:  With straight wagers the person bets for the horse to win, place or show.  Quinella, Exacta, Trifecta, Superfecta, Daily Double, and Pick 3, 4, 5, and 6 are considered “exotic” wagers.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm175-9; DET100"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1990","question":"What is the term that dictates the type of betting at racetracks in the US?  It’s derived from French and means to “bet among ourselves”.","answer":"Pari-mutuel (FYI:  All bets of a particular type are placed together in a pool.  Taxes and fees are deducted, payoff odds are calculated, and the pool is split among the winning bets. The “Tote” or totalizator board displays the odds, results, etc.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm175-8; DET204"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1991","question":"In reference to horse racing, what term refers to two or more horses arriving simultaneously at the finish line?","answer":"Dead heat (Do NOT accept \"photo finish\" where one horse finishes slightly in front of the others.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET78"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1992","question":"What term refers to a horse that breaks through the starting gate prematurely?","answer":"False start  <br/> <br/>ref:DET104"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1993","question":"In reference to horse racing, how long is a furlong?","answer":"1/8 of a mile (220 yards or 102.17 meters)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm175-5; DET116"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1994","question":"You do the math…How many furlongs are in a 1½ mile race?","answer":"12 furlongs (FYI: 1 furlong equals 1/8th of a mile)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm175-5"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1995","question":"In reference to horse racing, what does the term \"also ran\" mean?","answer":"Any horse who ran, but didn't win, place, or show in the race  <br/> <br/>ref:DET7"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1996","question":"In horse racing, what are the terms for horses placing 1st, 2nd, and 3rd in a race?","answer":"Win, place, and show  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm175-9"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1997","question":"In reference to horse racing, what is the name for one's starting position?","answer":"Post position  <br/> <br/>ref:DET218"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1998","question":"In reference to horse racing, what is the official name for the prize money in a horse race?","answer":"Purse  <br/> <br/>ref:DET223"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"jr bonus","number":"1999","question":"Name 3 different racetrack surfaces used in the US.","answer":"Dirt, turf (grass), and synthetic  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm175-5"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2000","question":"In reference to horse racing, give TWO terms commonly used to describe the condition of the racetrack footing.","answer":"Fast, sloppy, muddy, heavy  <br/> <br/>ref:DET272"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2001","question":"In reference to horse racing, what is the term for the side of the track furthest from the winning post?","answer":"Backstretch  <br/> <br/>ref:DET21"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2002","question":"In reference to horse racing, what is the term for a racehorse that runs well on wet, sloppy tracks?","answer":"Mudder  <br/> <br/>ref:DET183"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2003","question":"Where are most working horses in the US found?","answer":"Cattle ranches  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH120-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2004","question":"What is another name for an auction ring?","answer":"Sale ring or bull pen (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET43"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2005","question":"In reference to ranching, what is the term for a cowboy whose job is to rescue cattle that have gotten trapped in mud or marshland?","answer":"Bog rider  <br/> <br/>ref:DET34"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2006","question":"In reference to ranching, what is the purpose of a boundary rider?","answer":"To ride the fences of the property and repair any problems  <br/> <br/>ref:DET36"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2007","question":"What is the term for a cowboy from the western US who follows the horsemanship techniques of the old California vaqueros?","answer":"Buckaroo  <br/> <br/>ref:DET41"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2008","question":"What do you call a man who herds and tends cattle?","answer":"Cowboy  <br/> <br/>ref:DET71"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2009","question":"What does the term \"fuzztail running\" mean?","answer":"Herding and catching wild horses  <br/> <br/>ref:DET116"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2010","question":"In reference to livestock, what is a knacker?","answer":"Person who buys animal carcasses or buys and slaughters unwanted livestock (FYI:  Renderers use animal parts to make needed items like pet food, Neatsfoot oil, etc.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET161"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"intermediate","number":"2011","question":"In reference to ranching, what is a maverick?","answer":"Unbranded stray  <br/> <br/>ref:DET176"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2012","question":"What is a vaquero?","answer":"Spanish term for cowboy  <br/> <br/>ref:DET281"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2013","question":"Reining is a judged event designed to show what?","answer":"Athletic ability of a ranch-type horse in the confines of the show arena (how willing a horse is guided through a series of maneuvers such as circles, spins, sliding stops, and rollbacks) [accept any reasonable explanation]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH183D-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"2014","question":"Name 4 things that are included in a reining pattern.","answer":"Large fast circles, small slow circles, flying lead changes, rollbacks, spins, sliding stops (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH183D-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"jr bonus","number":"2015","question":"Name 3 things that are included in a reining pattern.","answer":"Large fast circles, small slow circles, flying lead changes, rollbacks, spins, sliding stops (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH183D-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"intermediate","number":"2016","question":"In reference to reining, which hind foot should remain in place when completing a spin to the right?","answer":"Right hind foot  <br/> <br/>ref:DET213"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2017","question":"What is the term for reining maneuvers set to music?","answer":"Freestyle reining  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH183D-2"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2018","question":"What is freestyle reining?","answer":"Reining maneuvers set to music  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH183D-2"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2019","question":"What is the automatic beginning score for a reining pattern?","answer":"70  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH183D-1; HSm635-3,4"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2020","question":"You do the math…You are judging a reining class and have just finished scoring the last horse.  You have given this horse a total maneuver score of + 3 ½ (plus 3 ½) and total penalties of -5 (minus 5).  What would be the final score for this horse?","answer":"Final score 68 ½ (70+ 3 ½ -5=68 ½)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH183D-1; HSm635-3,4"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2021","question":"How is a reining pattern scored?","answer":"Starting score is 70; points are added or deducted for each maneuver.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH183D-1; HSm635-3,4"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2022","question":"Name TWO kinds of rodeo bronc riding.","answer":"Saddle bronc riding and bareback riding  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm170-4; DET23; DET40"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2023","question":"In reference to rodeo, name ONE event that has a rope barrier.","answer":"Calf roping (tie down roping), team roping (head and heeling), steer wrestling (bulldogging)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET24"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"2024","question":"Name 3 rodeo \"rough stock\" events.","answer":"Bareback riding, saddle bronc riding, and bull riding  <br/> <br/>ref:DET237"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2025","question":"For what event is an Association Saddle used?","answer":"Saddle bronc riding  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm170-7; DET17"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2026","question":"In reference to rodeo, what is another name for the activity described as “heading and heeling”?","answer":"Team roping  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm170-5; DET263"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2027","question":"Name ONE founding principle for High School Rodeo.","answer":"Encourage youth to stay in school; promote sportsmanship; encourage horsemanship; encourage character development through the sport of rodeo  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm170-6; HIH186D-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2028","question":"In reference to rodeo, what do the initials NHSRA stand for?","answer":"National High School Rodeo Association  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm170-6; HIH186D-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2029","question":"In reference to rodeo, what do the initials PRCA stand for?","answer":"Professional Rodeo Cowboys Association  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm170-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2030","question":"In reference to rodeo, what is the term for the box from which livestock are released into the arena in rodeo events?","answer":"Chute  <br/> <br/>ref:DET56"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2031","question":"In reference to rodeo, what is the slang term for the main office of a rodeo where excuses and grievances are aired?","answer":"Crying room  <br/> <br/>ref:DET74"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"intermediate","number":"2032","question":"What is the term for the wrap taken with a lariat around the horn of a Western saddle when roping?","answer":"Dally  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm170-5; DET77"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2033","question":"In reference to rodeo, what is the name for the prize money paid to the winners of each go-round of a competition?","answer":"Day money  <br/> <br/>ref:DET78"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2034","question":"In which equestrian sport would winning competitors receive \"day money\"?","answer":"Rodeo  <br/> <br/>ref:DET9"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2035","question":"In reference to rodeo, what is the term for the cowboy that rides on the side of the steer opposite the steer wrestler?","answer":"Hazer  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm170-5; DET130"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2036","question":"In reference to rodeo, what is the name for the person who helps the rider off the bronc when the ride is completed, pulls the flank strap off the bronc, and removes the bronc from the arena?","answer":"Pickup man  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm170-8; DET211"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2037","question":"In reference to calf roping, what is the name of the 6-foot length of rope used to tie the legs of the calf?","answer":"Pigging string  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm170-6; DET212"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2038","question":"Touching the saddle with a free hand is referred to by the slang term “pulling leather” and is a disqualification in what rodeo event?","answer":"Saddle bronc riding  <br/> <br/>ref:DET222"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2039","question":"What is a re-ride in rodeo?","answer":"Bronc or bull rider is given a second ride (in the same go-round)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm170-7; DET232"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2040","question":"Please fill in the blanks.  Be a good sport.  Win without_______ and lose without ________.","answer":"Win without bragging and lose without complaining. (accept any reasonable answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH43"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2041","question":"In reference to horse showing, what does AHSA stand for?","answer":"American Horse Show Association  <br/> <br/>ref:DET9"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2042","question":"When riding English, what does the phrase “addressing the reins” mean?","answer":"Correct procedure for picking up the reins when riding with a Pelham or double bridle.  <br/> <br/>ref:PNW138"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2043","question":"When riding in group classes on the rail, name ONE thing you can do to avoid bunching up.","answer":"Pass, cut corner, circle to get to a clear area (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH42; PNW119"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2044","question":"How should you change directions on the rail in a horse show?","answer":"Turn to the inside or away from the rail (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH24; PNW135"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"2045","question":"Name 3 pieces of optional personal appointments that can be used in Equitation over Fences.","answer":"Unroweled spurs, crops or bats, gloves  <br/> <br/>ref:HH25"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"2046","question":"Name 3 pieces of equipment that are GENERALLY not permitted in Hunter Hack.","answer":"Martingales of any type; flash or dropped nosebands; protective boots or wraps; draw reins; gag bits; Western bits; converters on Pelham bits; roweled spurs; hackamores or bitless bridles; colored saddle pads or pads embroidered with emblems or names  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm190-6"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"jr bonus","number":"2047","question":"A typical Hunter Hack class requires the horses to jump two fences.  Name 3 gaits that might be asked for in a Hunter Hack class.","answer":"Walk, trot, canter, hand gallop, stop, back (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm190-5; DET145"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"2048","question":"A typical Hunter Hack class requires the horses to jump two fences.  Name 4 gaits that might be asked for in a Hunter Hack class.","answer":"Walk, trot, canter, hand gallop, stop, back (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm190-5; DET145"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2049","question":"How far ahead of the class starting time should the judge post any required pattern?","answer":"At least one hour  <br/> <br/>ref:HH44"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"novice","number":"2050","question":"In open horse shows, what is USUALLY the penalty for NOT following the pattern?","answer":"Disqualification  <br/> <br/>ref:HH42; PNW145"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"novice","number":"2051","question":"Name ONE horse show class in which patterns are generally used.","answer":"Showmanship, Western Horsemanship or Equitation, Western Riding, Reining, English Equitation, Dressage, Trail, Jumping (Accept any correct answer.)  <br/> <br/>ref:PNW125,133,134,139, 142,144,150"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2052","question":"What do the following horse show classes have in common:  pole bending, dressage, and harness ponies?","answer":"They are all performance classes. (FYI:  Quality or conformation classes are judged on horses' conformation; performance classes are judged or timed on the horse's and rider's performance.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm635-3; HH40"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2053","question":"What personal equipment is PROHIBITIED in Showmanship classes?","answer":"Spurs  <br/> <br/>ref:HH44"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2054","question":"Explain how to back your horse in Showmanship.","answer":"Turn to face towards the rear of the horse with your right hand extended; walk forward beside the horse as it backs up. (Do NOT touch your horse with your hand.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH46; PNW124"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"intermediate","number":"2055","question":"When is a show stick acceptable for Showmanship classes?","answer":"When showing a draft horse  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-13; HH44"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"intermediate","number":"2056","question":"If the handler is wearing Hunt Seat attire in Showmanship, what tack should be on the horse?","answer":"English bridle (also accept plain leather halter)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH44"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2057","question":"When showing a horse in-hand with a Pelham or double bridle, with which rein do you lead the horse?","answer":"Lead with the curb rein. (FYI:  The snaffle rein should be placed over the horse’s neck.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH44"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2058","question":"Besides keeping your horse posed so that judge gets the best view, name ONE other thing you should do at all times during a Showmanship class.","answer":"Know where the judge is, know what's expected of you, know the pattern, know the quartering system or \"boxes\" (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH46; PNW127-128"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"novice","number":"2059","question":"In a show, what side should you generally be on when leading your horse?","answer":"Left side  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm205-3; HH45; PNW123"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"jr bonus","number":"2060","question":"Name 3 common elements in Showmanship patterns.","answer":"Walk, trot, pivot turn, back, set up for inspection (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:PNW123-128"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2061","question":"What is the term for a crisp, prompt 90 or 180 degree turn on the hindquarters in a Showmanship class?","answer":"Pivot turn  <br/> <br/>ref:DET213; HH46; PNW124"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2062","question":"Where are the dividing lines that define the quarter system of Showmanship?","answer":"Down the backbone of the horse and across the shoulders or withers  <br/> <br/>ref:PNW125"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"novice","number":"2063","question":"When turning a horse in Showmanship, in which direction do you GENERALLY turn?","answer":"To the right or away from you  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm205-3; HH46"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"2064","question":"Name 3 pieces of optional person appointments in Stock Seat Equitation.","answer":"Spurs, chaps, sweaters, vests, coats (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH24"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"jr bonus","number":"2065","question":"Name the 3 gaits performed in Western Pleasure.","answer":"Walk, jog, and lope  <br/> <br/>ref:HH24; PNW134"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"intermediate","number":"2066","question":"What is the term for the rider's personal attire and any equipment needed for showing?","answer":"Appointments  <br/> <br/>ref:DET14; HH20"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"intermediate","number":"2067","question":"In references to horse showing, what are appointments?","answer":"Clothing, equipment, and tack used in showing  <br/> <br/>ref:DET14; HH20"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2068","question":"What is the general name for a halter class in which coat color and pattern, NOT conformation, is a deciding factor?","answer":"Color class  <br/> <br/>ref:DET62"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2069","question":"A rider who stays far away from the arena corners and does not make good use of the full arena is said to be doing what?","answer":"Cutting corners  <br/> <br/>ref:DET76"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2070","question":"What does the term \"show in-hand\" mean?","answer":"Show at halter, show in showmanship, or show leading your horse instead of riding or driving (accept any)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET152"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"novice","number":"2071","question":"What do you call the official who ranks the horses at horse shows?","answer":"Judge  <br/> <br/>ref:DET158"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2072","question":"In reference to showing, what is a \"junior\" horse?","answer":"One that's 5 years of age or younger  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm135-5; DET159"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"intermediate","number":"2073","question":"Generally, in horse shows, when is a snaffle bit or bosal allowed?","answer":"When showing a young or junior horse (FYI:  Junior horses are 5 years of age or younger.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm135-5"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2074","question":"In which horse show class are young riders mounted and led by an adult handler?","answer":"Lead line  <br/> <br/>ref:DET166"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2075","question":"What term describes when the horse is required to stand still when the lead rope or reins are dropped on the ground?","answer":"Ground tie  <br/> <br/>ref:DET125"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2076","question":"What type of disposition should a therapeutic riding horse have?","answer":"Extremely gentle or tolerant  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH250-3"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"2077","question":"Name 3 things a therapy horse must learn to tolerate.","answer":"Wheelchairs, loading ramps, crutches, sudden noises, rider's lack of balance, inadvertent pressure by rider (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH250-3"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2078","question":"In reference to equine therapy, describe how hippotherapy provides benefits for a paralyzed rider.","answer":"Movement of the horse imparts movement of the rider's pelvis that closely resembles walking  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH250-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2079","question":"In reference to equine therapy, Sports Riding such as Special Olympics and trail riding is program designed to develop the rider’s what?","answer":"Rider's social skills  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH250-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"2080","question":"According to the Horse Industry Handbook, name 3 of the 4 methods used in therapeutic riding of providing treatment to individuals with disabilities.","answer":"Hippotherapy, rehabilitative, sports (Special Olympics, trail riding), developmental vaulting (UPDATED 2021)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH250-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2081","question":"According to the Horse Industry Handbook, what SPECIFIC type of therapeutic riding uses functional horsemanship skills to achieve therapeutic or educational goals such as improved speech or motor skills?","answer":"Rehabilitative (UPDATED 2021)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH250-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2082","question":"What is the common term for riding outside an arena for pleasure such as in fields, on roads, and on trails?","answer":"Trail riding  <br/> <br/>ref:DET273"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2083","question":"Name ONE type of trail ride.","answer":"Social or pleasure, competitive, endurance (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET273"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"2084","question":"Name 3 types of trail rides.","answer":"Social or pleasure, competitive, endurance (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET273"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2085","question":"What is the name of the person who looks after the horses on a trail ride?","answer":"Wrangler  <br/> <br/>ref:DET298"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"2086","question":"Explain the different ways vaulting was practiced during the early Roman times, Middle Ages, and Renaissance.","answer":"Early Romans vaulting was acrobatic displays on cantering horses;  Middle Ages knights practiced jumping onto horses; Renaissance was agility training for young nobles.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH185D-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2087","question":"Modern vaulting was developed in Germany in the 1940's as a way to do what?","answer":"Offer children an inexpensive way to participate in equestrian sports  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH185D-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2088","question":"How many vaulters may be on the horse at one time?","answer":"One, two, or three (accept any)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH185D-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"intermediate","number":"2089","question":"Name ONE thing vaulting is judged on.","answer":"Technique, performance, form, difficulty, balance, security, consideration of the horse, how well the horse and vaulter(s) work together, compulsory moves, freestyle routines, exercise scores of 0 – 10  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm185-5; HIH185D-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2090","question":"What discipline is defined as gymnastics on horseback?","answer":"Vaulting  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm185-1; HIH185D-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2091","question":"2-part question:  For an ideal team in vaulting there are bigger, stronger vaulters and some smaller vaulters.  What are the common terms for both of these types of vaulters?","answer":"Bases and flyers  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm185-5"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2092","question":"2-part question:  Vaulting is judged on teamwork and how well the human and equestrian athletes work together.  Similar to Olympic ice-skating competitions, the individual or teams will be scored on TWO different types of performance.  Name them.","answer":"Compulsory moves and freestyle routines  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm185-5; HIH185D-1"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2093","question":"In reference to vaulting, what is a longueur? (long-ER)","answer":"Person who controls the vaulting horse  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH185D-1"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2094","question":"The legs, hands, weight, and voice as used in controlling a horse are called what?","answer":"Aids (more specifically natural aids)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH21; DET5; PNW131"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2095","question":"What are the natural aids used for while riding your horse?","answer":"To control your horse (to tell your horse what you want him to do)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH21; DET5; DET188; PNW131"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"jr bonus","number":"2096","question":"Name 3 natural aids that are used to tell your horse what to do.","answer":"Voice,  legs, hands, weight, body, seat  <br/> <br/>ref:HH21; DET188; PNW131"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"novice","number":"2097","question":"Name TWO natural aids that are used to tell your horse what to do.","answer":"Voice,  legs, hands, weight, body, seat  <br/> <br/>ref:HH21; DET188; PNW131"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"hard","number":"2098","question":"Explain what is meant when a rider uses diagonal aids.","answer":"Rider uses opposite hands and legs  <br/> <br/>ref:DET80"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"medium","number":"2099","question":"Give ONE reason why it's important for a rider to stay deep in the saddle and to sit up straight.","answer":"So you don’t confuse the horse, throw the horse off balance, or fall off if the horse makes an unexpected move  <br/> <br/>ref:HH21; HIH1220-2"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"medium","number":"2100","question":"What is meant by the phrase “above the bit”?","answer":"Horse is carrying its head to high and is evading the bit making it difficult to control.  <br/> <br/>ref:DET26"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"medium","number":"2101","question":"A horse that moves forward with his head tucked into his chest is said to be what?","answer":"Behind the bit  <br/> <br/>ref:DET26"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"medium","number":"2102","question":"What is meant by the phrase \"behind the bit\"?","answer":"Horse evades the bit by over-flexing at the poll  <br/> <br/>ref:DET26"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"medium","number":"2103","question":"What is meant by the phrase \"on the bit\"?","answer":"When the horse has accepted contact with the bit (reacts to aids with a quiet, responsive manner)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET195"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"medium","number":"2104","question":"What is the term for one who rides horseback?","answer":"Equestrian  <br/> <br/>ref:DET98; HIH110-5"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"sr bonus","number":"2105","question":"Name 3 important general aspects of equitation.","answer":"Body position, hand position, leg position, seat, performing correctly at different gaits, performing pattern correctly (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm190-4; HH20,21; PNW131,133"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"sr bonus","number":"2106","question":"What are the 3 basic equitation or horsemanship styles?","answer":"Stock seat or Western, Hunt Seat, and Saddle Seat  <br/> <br/>ref:HH20; DET99"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2107","question":"When you get ready to mount safely, what do you do to control your horse?","answer":"Adjust reins and hold the horse steady (adjust the reins evenly with enough tension to feel the bit)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH20; PNW132"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"novice","number":"2108","question":"When mounting your horse, which foot goes into the stirrup first?","answer":"Left foot  <br/> <br/>ref:HH20; PNW132"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"novice","number":"2109","question":"On what side of the horse do you usually mount or get on?","answer":"Left side  <br/> <br/>ref:HH20; PNW132"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2110","question":"When mounting for Western Horsemanship, on what part of the saddle do you place the right hand?","answer":"Saddle horn  <br/> <br/>ref:HH23; PNW132"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2111","question":"Name ONE way to avoid getting your foot caught when dismounting.","answer":"Slide your left foot partially out of the stirrup before starting to dismount; lean across the saddle and take your left foot entirely out of the stirrup when dismounting (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:PNW130"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2112","question":"Which of the natural aids is used lightly to guide the horse's forehand?","answer":"Hands  <br/> <br/>ref:HH21"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"novice","number":"2113","question":"Constant, steady pulling on the reins can cause what problem?","answer":"Hard mouth or damage to the horse's mouth (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH21; HIH1220-2; PNW131"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2114","question":"Heavy hands can cause damage to what part of the horse?","answer":"Mouth (specifically the bars or interdental space)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH21; HIH1220-2; PNW131"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"jr bonus","number":"2115","question":"Light or good hands are important in riding so that the horse’s mouth doesn’t get injured.  Name 3 features of light or good hands.","answer":"As light a contact as possible with the horse’s mouth, quiet hands—no excessive movements, no jerking, relaxed fingers, give and take, avoid constant pulling (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:PNW129"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2116","question":"What part of the rider’s legs should be used as aids in equitation?","answer":"Calves (FYI:  Never raise your heel to signal the horse.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH25; PNW129"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"jr bonus","number":"2117","question":"Name 3 features of the correct position for riders’ legs in equitation.","answer":"Legs should be directly under the rider’s body, knees should be slightly bent, weight should be on the balls of the feet, toes should be up, heels should be down, toes should be parallel to horse or slightly turned out (accept any correct  <br/> <br/>ref:PNW129"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2119","question":"When riding, your legs are used to signal what?","answer":"Speed or direction of movement (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH21"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2120","question":"Ride with your weight on what part of your foot?","answer":"Ball of the foot (DON'T stick your feet too far into the stirrups or your feet could get \"hung up\".)  <br/> <br/>ref:PNW131"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"jr bonus","number":"2121","question":"Name 3 features of good body position for a rider in equitation.","answer":"Weight should be balanced in center of the saddle, shoulders should be straight and not rounded, rider should sit up straight and keep chin level, rider should be relaxed and supple, rider should be seated on “seat” bones (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:PNW129"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2122","question":"What is meant by the phrase \"sit tall in the saddle\"?","answer":"Sit up straight  <br/> <br/>ref:HH20"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2123","question":"What should a rider NEVER use for balance when learning to ride?","answer":"Reins  <br/> <br/>ref:HH21"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2124","question":"Name ONE thing that can happen if you get out of balance while riding.","answer":"You can fall off; you can throw your horse off balance; you can stiffen and lose the rhythm of motion with the horse.  <br/> <br/>ref:HH20"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"intermediate","number":"2125","question":"A “chair seat” is when a rider sits too far back in the saddle and has his or her legs too far forward.  Name ONE cause of a chair seat.","answer":"Rider sitting on their tail bone instead of their “seat bones” (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:PNW129"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"sr bonus","number":"2126","question":"Name 3 styles of English riding.","answer":"Hunt Seat, Saddle Seat, and Dressage  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-1"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"hard","number":"2127","question":"Which English rider sits in the saddle with a very sharp hip angle?","answer":"Jumping rider  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-1"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"hard","number":"2128","question":"2-part question:  The term \"perched\" refers to what type of English saddle and rider?","answer":"Close contact saddle; jumping rider  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-1"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2129","question":"What is the rising and descending of the rider in rhythm with the trot called?","answer":"Posting  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-2; PNW141"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"hard","number":"2130","question":"If the horse is traveling counterclockwise in the arena, what legs are moving forward when the rider rises for a correct diagonal?","answer":"Right front and left hind  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-2; PNW141"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2131","question":"In reference to horseback riding, what is posting?","answer":"Rising and descending of the rider in rhythm with the trot  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-2; PNW141"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"novice","number":"2132","question":"What term means to step a horse backwards?","answer":"Back  <br/> <br/>ref:HH23; DET20; PNW135"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2133","question":"When riding, how do you ask your horse to back?","answer":"Grip with your legs, hold the reins low, pull lightly, use your voice (accept any reasonable explanation)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH23; PNW135"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"intermediate","number":"2134","question":"A rein back is a movement signaled by the rider to the horse.  What does the horse do when this signal is given?","answer":"Back up  <br/> <br/>ref:DET231"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"intermediate","number":"2135","question":"In performing a correct rein back, how should the legs of the horse move?","answer":"In diagonal pairs (FYI:  The rein back is a two-beat maneuver where a horse backs with his legs in diagonal pairs.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET231"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"intermediate","number":"2136","question":"A pivot is a turn on the hindquarters. When performed correctly, which hind foot should remain more or less in place when completing a pivot clockwise?","answer":"Right hind foot  <br/> <br/>ref:DET213; PNW159"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"intermediate","number":"2137","question":"What motion is being described:  a galloping horse stops, lifts his forelegs, swings around 180 degrees, and starts galloping again in the same direction from which he came?","answer":"Rollback  <br/> <br/>ref:DET236; PNW160"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"intermediate","number":"2138","question":"What is a rollback?","answer":"When a galloping horse stops, lifts his forelegs, swings around 180 degrees and starts galloping again the in the direction from which he came (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET236; PNW160"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2139","question":"When riding, explain how you would get your horse to sidepass.","answer":"Hold the horse to prevent forward movement, rein in the direction you wish to move the forequarters, use outside leg to move the hindquarters (accept any reasonable explanation)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH23; PNW149"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2140","question":"What is the term for a turn on the front legs?","answer":"Turn on the forehand  <br/> <br/>ref:DET276; PNW150"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2141","question":"What is meant by the appropriate size horse and rider?","answer":"Not a small rider on large horse or vice versa  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH210-2"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2142","question":"What is the rein called that's PUSHED against the neck in the direction of the turn?","answer":"Bearing rein or neck rein (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET25; PNW158"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2143","question":"True neck reining is the response of your horse to what?","answer":"Pressure of the bearing rein against the neck  <br/> <br/>ref:DET189; PNW135; PNW158"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2144","question":"In reference to horseback riding, what is the bearing rein?","answer":"Rein pushed against the neck in the direction of the turn when neck reining  <br/> <br/>ref:DET25; PNW158"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"intermediate","number":"2145","question":"What is the term for the part of the reins that passes between the thumb and fingers and out the top of the hand?","answer":"Bight  <br/> <br/>ref:DET28; PNW132"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"medium","number":"2146","question":"What is the term for the method of holding single reins where the reins overlap in the rider's hands across the horse's back?","answer":"Cross reins  <br/> <br/>ref:DET73"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"medium","number":"2147","question":"What is \"plow reining\"?","answer":"Direct reining  <br/> <br/>ref:DET214"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2148","question":"When teaching a horse to neck rein, what is the rein called that PULLS in the direction of the turn?","answer":"Leading rein or direct rein (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET81; PNW135"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2149","question":"When using romal reins, should the bight or extra part of the reins be on the same side or opposite side of your reining hand?","answer":"Opposite side from the reining hand  <br/> <br/>ref:PNW132"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2150","question":"When riding with one hand using split reins, how many fingers can be between the reins in a Western Pleasure class?","answer":"1 (one) finger  <br/> <br/>ref:PNW132"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2151","question":"When riding with one hand using split reins, should the bight or extra part of the reins fall on the same side or the opposite side of the reining hand?","answer":"Same side as the reining hand  <br/> <br/>ref:PNW132"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2152","question":"When riding, when should you signal your horse for the stop?","answer":"When the horse's rear legs are moving forward under its body  <br/> <br/>ref:HH22"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"medium","number":"2153","question":"When a rider is riding side saddle they have both legs on the near side of the horse.  What term refers to riding with one leg on each side of the horse?","answer":"Astride  <br/> <br/>ref:DET17; HSm155-4,5"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2154","question":"In which riding style is the rider seated sideways?","answer":"Sidesaddle  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm155-4,5; HIH184D-1"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"novice","number":"2155","question":"What is the near side of the horse?","answer":"Left side  <br/> <br/>ref:DET188; HH20; PNW159"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"novice","number":"2156","question":"What is another name for the LEFT side of the horse?","answer":"Near side  <br/> <br/>ref:DET180; HH20; PNW159"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"novice","number":"2157","question":"What is another name for the RIGHT side of the horse?","answer":"Off side or far side (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm195-6"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"novice","number":"2158","question":"What is the off side of the horse?","answer":"Right side (also accept far side)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm195-6"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2159","question":"In reference to horseback riding, what is a \"passenger\"?","answer":"One who rides without control letting the horse go where it wants  <br/> <br/>ref:DET205; HH40"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2160","question":"One who rides a horse without control, letting the horse go as he wishes, is called what?","answer":"Passenger  <br/> <br/>ref:DET205; HH40"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2161","question":"What does it mean to \"pull leather\"?","answer":"Hold on to saddle with both hands when riding a bucking horse  <br/> <br/>ref:DET222; HH20"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2162","question":"What slang term is used when the rider holds on to the saddle with both hands while riding a bucking horse?","answer":"Pulling leather  <br/> <br/>ref:DET222; HH20"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2163","question":"In reference to horses, what is a \"rubberneck\"?","answer":"Horse with a very flexible neck (that may be hard to rein)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET237"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2164","question":"What is the term for a horse with a very flexible neck that may be hard to rein?","answer":"Rubberneck  <br/> <br/>ref:DET237"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2165","question":"In reference to horses, what is a stargazer?","answer":"Horse that holds his head high and his nose out  <br/> <br/>ref:DET254"},
    {"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2166","question":"What is the term for a horse that holds his head too high and his nose out?","answer":"Stargazer  <br/> <br/>ref:DET254"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2167","question":"What is required for all commercial feed products and is used as a method of communication between feed manufacturers and customers?","answer":"Labeling (also accept feed tags)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH745-1"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2168","question":"Name 4 things listed on a feed tag.","answer":"Product name, purpose statement, commercial feed class, guaranteed analysis, crude protein, crude fiber, crude fat, calcium, phosphorous, copper, zinc, selenium, Vitamin A, brand, manufacturer, weight, use directions, ingredients, caution statement  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH745-1,2"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2169","question":"Basically, what does a feed tag do?","answer":"Tells you what's inside the bag  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH745-1"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2170","question":"When looking at the feed tag for the concentrate you are currently feeding you notice the abbreviation GRAS.  What does GRAS indicate?","answer":"Generally Recognized as Safe (for animal consumption)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH391"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2171","question":"The US horse industry uses two types of feed management systems.  One is grazing full time.  What is the other?","answer":"Confined feeding (feeding hay or grain in a stall or paddock)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH365-1"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2172","question":"Hay should be fed in what?","answer":"Some type of feeder  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-11; HSm420-4; HSc51"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2173","question":"Give TWO reasons why a horse owner should take its horse's feed and water buckets with it when traveling.","answer":"Familiar containers reduce stress; reduces risk of disease from contaminated mangers or water tanks  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1150-2"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2174","question":"When do foals start trying to find other sources of feed such as grain, pasture, or hay?","answer":"After the first week of life  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH975-5"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2175","question":"How old should foals be when introduced to concentrates?","answer":"1 – 2 months (or as early as the foal shows interest)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH765-1; HIH975-5; HSm535-3"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2176","question":"What is the name of the structure that allows foals to eat grain or hay without interference from the mare?","answer":"Creep feeder  <br/> <br/>ref:DET72; HSm535-3; HIH765-2"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2177","question":"What is creep feeding?","answer":"Providing an area where the foal can eat without interference from the mare  <br/> <br/>ref:DET72; HSm535-3; HIH765-2"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2178","question":"Orphan foals have a very high dietary energy requirement and should be fed how often during the first 1 to 2 weeks of life?","answer":"Every 2 – 4 hours (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA69; FCH275"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2179","question":"The horse's digestive system was not designed to be fed large quantities of what type of feed?","answer":"Concentrates or grain (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH735-1"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2180","question":"What is the FIRST step in designing a workable feeding program?","answer":"Figuring out the nutrient requirements of the horse (FYI:  Nutrient requirements for horses are determined on their body weight, physiological status, and state of production.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc42; HIH735-1; HSm435-1"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"intermediate","number":"2181","question":"2-part question:  How should concentrate feeds be measured and explain why?","answer":"Measure by weight (not by volume); concentrates weigh different amounts (a coffee can of oats will weigh less than a coffee can of corn)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH735-1"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2182","question":"Name 3 things on which selection of feeds should be based.","answer":"Nutrient content (quality), cost, availability, acceptability to horse (palatability), convenience (of storing and feeding)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH745-5"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"2183","question":"Name 3 feeding guidelines.","answer":"Have water available, have salt available, feed at regular times, change feeds gradually, don't feed on the ground, don't overfeed, don't feed moldy hay, feed by weight not by volume, several small feedings are better than one big feeding  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH735-1,2; FCH Chapter 8; HSc51"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2184","question":"Name 5 feeding guidelines.","answer":"Have water available, have salt available, feed at regular times, change feeds gradually, don't feed on the ground, don't overfeed, don't feed moldy hay, feed by weight not by volume, several small feedings are better than one big feeding  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH735-1,2; FCH Chapter 8; HSc51"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2185","question":"What is the easiest way to determine if your horse's energy or calorie needs are being met?","answer":"Monitor body weight  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH790-1"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2186","question":"The amount fed should be adjusted as necessary to maintain what?","answer":"Optimal body weight or condition  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH186"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2187","question":"Name ONE thing that energy or calorie deficiency in mature animals causes.","answer":"Weight loss, poor reproduction, or poor athletic performance  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH4"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2188","question":"Name 3 contributing factors that result in obese horses.","answer":"Too much hay, too much concentrates, too much pasture, lack of exercise, metabolic diseases (Cushing’s, hypothyroidism), easy keepers, pecking order, overfeeding to mask undesirable traits, overfeeding in early pregnancy (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH790-1; FCH152"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2189","question":"Older horses may need some adjustments to their diet in order to maintain what?","answer":"Body condition or weight (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH770-2"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2190","question":"Just before winter, some may feed their older horses to achieve a body condition score greater than 5.  Why would this be helpful?","answer":"Horse has to use more energy in the cold weather.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH770-2"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2191","question":"Name 3 factors, other than feeding too little, that result in thin horses.","answer":"Parasites, lactating mares, hard work, poor teeth, pecking order (too much competition for food), malabsorption, hot, humid weather, disease, starvation (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH152; HIH405-1, 420-1, 450-2, 455, 790-3, 975-14"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2192","question":"When changing types of hay, how should you manage the change?","answer":"Mix the types together (for a period of approximately two weeks)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH735-2"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2193","question":"Describe ONE way you'd manage the change when switching horses from grass hay to lush pasture.","answer":"Turn them out for just a few hours a day at first, slowly increase the grazing time, feed hay before turning them out, use a grazing muzzle (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH735-2"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2194","question":"Why is it recommended to feed horses 2 – 3 times a day instead of once daily?","answer":"Horses have small stomachs; overeating can cause colic. (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH735-1; FCH151; HSm435-3"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2195","question":"Horses like to have a regular routine and are less likely to go off their feed or develop vices if fed how?","answer":"On a regular schedule  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH735-1"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2196","question":"How many acres of pasture per horse are needed to maintain pasture productivity?","answer":"2 – 3 acres per horse (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-1"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2197","question":"What percentage of its body weight should a horse consume in feed per day?","answer":"1% – 3% of its body weight (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-1; HSm405-2"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"intermediate","number":"2198","question":"You do the math...During the winter, most mature idle horses should receive 1.5 – 2% of their body weight in hay per day.  How many POUNDS of hay should be fed to a 1000-pound, mature idle horse?","answer":"15 – 20 pounds (accept any number within this range) [FYI:  A mature idle horse is one that is not growing, reproducing, or working.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH420-3; HIH740-10"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2199","question":"You do the math…You are feeding a weanling that weighs approximately 400 pounds.  If you are feeding twice a day and need to feed a total of 1% of the body weight, how many pounds would you feed for the morning feeding?","answer":"2 (two) pounds  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH765-2"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2200","question":"You do the math…A horse will eat approximately 2% of its body weight daily.  If a 1000-pound horse is only fed hay, how many pounds will he eat per day?","answer":"20 pounds  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-10"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2201","question":"You do the math…If a lactating broodmare should be fed 3% of her body weight in total feed each day, how much total feed should a mare that weighs 900 pounds receive in a day?","answer":"27 pounds of total feed intake (900 x 0.03=27)  <br/> <br/>ref:ES107"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2202","question":"Explain the difference between a balanced ration and a maintenance ration.","answer":"Balanced ration contains all digestible nutrients required; maintenance ration furnishes just enough of each required nutrient to maintain horse in current condition.  <br/> <br/>ref:DET22; DET174; HSc32"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2203","question":"What is the definition of a ration?","answer":"Entire amount of feed allowed an animal for a day  <br/> <br/>ref:DET229"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2204","question":"What is the term for a ration that supplies the proper amounts of all nutrients needed by the animal?","answer":"Balanced ration (also accept complete feed)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET22; FCH385"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2205","question":"What type of ration is designed to keep a horse in the same physical condition, not allowing weight gain or loss?","answer":"Maintenance ration  <br/> <br/>ref:DET174"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2206","question":"A horse is considered at maintenance if he is what?","answer":"Not working, not growing, not producing (not pregnant or lactating) [accept any]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH750-1; HSm435-2"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2207","question":"Based on research studies for the initial re-feeding of the starved horse, the best approach is feeding what type of feed?","answer":"High quality alfalfa hay (in frequent small feedings)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH785-3"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2208","question":"A single feeding of concentrates should NEVER exceed what amount?","answer":"5 (five) pounds or not more than 0.75% (3/4%) of the horse's body weight (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-11; HIH735-1"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2209","question":"Horsemen should feed by weight, not by what?","answer":"Volume  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH735-1; HSm405-2; HSc40"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2210","question":"Just because herbs are natural, doesn't necessarily mean they're safe.  Name 3 negative things about using them in the horse's diet.","answer":"Can cause toxicity, negative side effects, drug-like interaction with other components of diet; some contain prohibited substances; potential for some to be banned from various competitions  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH742-4"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2211","question":"Most studies to date have shown that herbal supplements don't enhance normal immune response, but may help with what?","answer":"Compromised immune system  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH742-4"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2212","question":"Why is eating grain less effective than eating hay for keeping a horse warm in winter?","answer":"One pound of hay produces more body heat than one pound of grain (FYI:  The heat of fermentation of fiber will help keep the horse warm)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH450-3; HSm305-7"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2213","question":"Give ONE reason why a horse may not have cleaned up his feed.","answer":"Overfed, something wrong with the feed, limited access to water, horse is sick, horse has teeth problems (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH735-1,2"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2214","question":"Name 3 herbs commonly fed to horses.","answer":"Devil’s claw, Echinacea, garlic, ginger, ginseng, valerian root, yucca (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH742-4"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2215","question":"How much free-choice salt will horses typically consume each day?","answer":"1 – 3 ounces (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH745-3"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2216","question":"How should sodium chloride or salt be fed in a horse's diet?","answer":"Free choice  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH745-3; HSm430-4; FCH25,26; HSc41"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2217","question":"Why should salt be offered free choice?","answer":"Horse will usually eat enough to meet its needs.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH745-3; HSm430-4; HSc41"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2218","question":"Although salt is usually fed free-choice, name ONE time salt may need to be added to a horse's ration.","answer":"With intense exercise; exercising in hot climates; in the winter when the horse may not drink enough water (accept any correct answer) [FYI:  Horses may lick sweat-contaminated objects if they're not getting enough sodium in their diet.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH725-2; FCH25; HSm430-4"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2219","question":"Name TWO types of salt blocks available for horses.","answer":"Plain, trace mineralized, iodized, added selenium, rock salt  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH226"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2220","question":"Besides water, horses on pasture not having access to commercial feeds should always have access to what?","answer":"Salt (or trace mineralized salt)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH750-2; HSm430-4; HSc41"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2221","question":"What is trace mineralized salt?","answer":"Salt that contains trace minerals  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH745-3; HSm410-4; HSc41"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2222","question":"What is the chemical name for salt?","answer":"Sodium chloride (NaCl)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm410-4; FCH25; HIH725-2"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2223","question":"What is \"lite salt\"?","answer":"½ sodium chloride and ½ potassium chloride  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-11; FCH201"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2224","question":"What is a biennial plant?","answer":"Plant that lasts for two years (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-3; HSm410-2; FCH382"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2225","question":"In reference to nutrition, what do the letters CF stand for?","answer":"Crude fiber (FYI:  The higher the crude fiber, the lower the digestible energy)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH745-3"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2226","question":"In reference to feeds, what is dry matter?","answer":"What's left in a feed after the water has been removed  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH387; HIH710-1; HSm410-1"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"intermediate","number":"2227","question":"What is an \"easy keeper\"?","answer":"Animal that doesn't need as much feed as others under similar conditions  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH388; HIH790-1"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"intermediate","number":"2228","question":"What is an animal called that's nutritionally unthrifty and that requires more feed than others?","answer":"Hard keeper  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH392"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2229","question":"Referring to feeds, what does the term \"tillering\" mean?","answer":"Plants in early stages of growth  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-1"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2230","question":"Explain the difference between an herbivore and a carnivore.","answer":"Herbivores eat plants; carnivores eat meat.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH705-1; FCH392"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2231","question":"What is the term for animals that prefer to eat plants?","answer":"Herbivore  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH705-1; FCH392; DET138"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2232","question":"What is an omnivore?","answer":"Animal that eats both plants and meat  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH705-1; FCH392"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2233","question":"In feeding management, what is the \"wicking effect\"?","answer":"Uptake of moisture from ground into a bale of hay  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm420-4"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2234","question":"Give 3 signs or symptoms of black walnut poisoning.","answer":"Laminitis, colic, stocking up (leg edema or swelling), decreased feed intake, depression, respiratory distress, death  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm425-6; FCH323"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2235","question":"What is the slang term for aimless wandering, circling, and apparent blindness caused by locoweed, moldy corn poisoning, or acute selenium toxicity?","answer":"Blind staggers  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH725-4; HSm430-9; FCH317; FCH329; FCH357"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2236","question":"Give ONE cause of blind staggers.","answer":"Moldy corn, locoweed, or selenium poisoning  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH725-4; HSm430-9; FCH317; FCH329; FCH357"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2237","question":"2-part question:  Blister beetle poisoning is more common when horses consume what type of hay and explain why?","answer":"Alfalfa or clover hay; the beetles are crushed during the hay making process so they remain in the baled hay  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-8; HSm320-6; FCH365"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2238","question":"What insect should you check your hay for?  These insects can harm the horse if eaten.","answer":"Blister beetles  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-8; HSm320-6; HSm415-3; FCH364"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2239","question":"What is the biggest danger associated with blister beetles?","answer":"Blister beetles secrete a toxic chemical (cantharidin) which can cause death if eaten, even if the blister beetles are dried.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-8; HSm320-6; HSm415-3; FCH364"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2240","question":"What is the toxin produced by blister beetles?","answer":"Cantharidin (pronounced can-THAIR-ih-din)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-8; HSm320-6; HSm415-3; FCH365"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2241","question":"Give ONE way you can reduce the likelihood of blister beetle infestation in hay you purchase.","answer":"Only buy hay from known sources; buy first cutting hay (which is seldom infested)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-8; HSm320-6; FCH366"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2242","question":"Why should you NOT feed cattle or poultry feed to horses?","answer":"Can contain antibiotics or other toxins that can poison horses (FYI:  Monensin (Rumensin) is an ionophore antibiotic given to cattle and poultry to increase feed efficiency.)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH361; HIH745-4"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2243","question":"Name ONE cattle feed additive that is extremely toxic to horses.","answer":"Ionophores (such as Monensin or Rumensin); growth promoters  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH361; HIH745-4"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2244","question":"Virtually all feed has some mold spores, but the presence of excessive mold can cause several problems if inhaled.  Name 3 of these problems.","answer":"Coughing, heaves, allergic reactions  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-8"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2245","question":"Name 3 health problems caused by mycotoxins.","answer":"Feed refusal, reproductive problems, neurological problems, immune system suppression, excess slobbering, photosensitivity, blood clotting problems (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH348"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2246","question":"Name 3 conditions that can cause mold in hay.","answer":"Improper baling (baling when moisture content is above 15%), improper storage (letting hay get wet; storing hay on the ground), moisture in hay, high heat, high humidity (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-5,6"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2247","question":"What is the most common group of toxins that result in feed-related poisoning?","answer":"Mycotoxins (FYI:  Mycotoxins are toxins produced by molds or fungi.)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH346"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2248","question":"Name 3 feeds that are often affected by mycotoxins.","answer":"Tall fescue, corn, red clover, peanuts, cottonseed (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH346,347"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2249","question":"In reference to toxins in feeds, what is a mycotoxin?","answer":"Toxin produced by a mold or fungus  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH346"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2250","question":"Corn infected with aflatoxins can cause damage to what organ of the horse's body?","answer":"Liver  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH360"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2251","question":"Name 3 signs or symptoms of “clover poisoning”.","answer":"Slobbers (red clover affected with fungus “black patch”); photosensitivity (alsike); liver damage (alsike); clotting problems (moldy sweet clover) [accept any correct answers]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-2-8; HSm425-5,6; FCH108"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2252","question":"Which type of clover can cause photosensitivity and liver damage?","answer":"Alsike clover (FYI:  Long-term exposure to alsike clover can cause \"big liver disease\".  Alsike clover can also cause \"slobbers\".)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-2,3; HSm425-6; FCH108"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2253","question":"What is the MAIN symptom of a horse that has grazed red clover that's affected with the fungus commonly known as \"black patch\"?","answer":"Excessive salivation or “slobbers” (FYI:  Black patch produces Slaframine.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-9; FCH108"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2254","question":"In reference to clover poisoning, what is dicoumarol?","answer":"Toxin found in moldy sweet clover (that affects Vitamin K levels and causes clotting problems)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm425-5; FCH51; DET80"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2255","question":"Sweet clover poisoning results in altered blood clotting, anemia, and a deficiency of which vitamin?","answer":"Vitamin K (FYI:  Dicoumarin is produced by moldy sweet clover which affects vitamin K levels.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm425-5; FCH51"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2256","question":"What disease is caused by a toxin-producing fungus found in contaminated corn that's consumed by horses?","answer":"Moldy corn poisoning, leukoencephalomalacia, or blind staggers (accept any)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH357"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2257","question":"Name ONE problem tall fescue can cause when used in pastures.","answer":"Prolonged gestation, abortion, decreased milk production, retained placenta, thickened placenta, dystocia (difficult birth), weak foals, slow growth in foals (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-4,8; HSm530-2; FCH347; HCH352"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2258","question":"Name 3 clinical signs associated with fescue toxicosis.","answer":"Prolonged gestation, abortion, decreased milk production, retained placenta, thickened placenta, dystocia (difficult birth), weak foals, slow growth in foals, dry gangrene (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-4,8; HSm530-2; FCH347; HCH352"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2259","question":"Fescue poisoning affects pregnant mares in the late stages of gestation.  What is the best and easiest way to rapidly relieve the effects of fescue toxicosis?","answer":"Remove mare from the infected fescue pasture or remove access to infected fescue hay (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-4,8; HSm530-2; FCH347; HCH352"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2260","question":"Which TWO general types of horses are affected by tall fescue poisoning?","answer":"Reproducing mares, stallions, and foals  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-4,8; HSm530-2; FCH347; HCH352"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2261","question":"What species of pasture grass contains a fungal endophyte that can cause problems in horses, especially pregnant mares?","answer":"Tall fescue (fescue)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-4,8; HSm530-2; FCH347; HCH352"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2262","question":"There are many plants that are non-toxic but are troublesome to horses.  Name 3.","answer":"Burs—sandbur, burdock; spines—spiny pigweed, Canada thistle, horse nettle, stinging nettle; nimblewill; common ragweed; awns—foxtail (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm425-3"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2263","question":"Horses are less likely to consume toxic plants if provided with what?","answer":"Enough hay or pasture (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH735-2; HSm425-4"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2264","question":"Name TWO measures which can be taken to help prevent plant poisoning in your horse.","answer":"Proper pasture management—don’t overgraze, get rid of noxious weeds, reseed pasture; feed clean hay; don't feed garden waste; don't enclose horses close to toxic plants; be able to recognize toxic plants  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH301; HSm425"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"intermediate","number":"2265","question":"Ornamental plants are decorative plants used in yards.  Name ONE ornamental plant that is poisonous to horses.","answer":"(Japanese) yew, foxglove, oleander, lily of the valley, wild jasmine, azalea (rhododendron species), larkspur, red maple tree, oak tree, horse chestnut tree (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm425-4-8; HIH741-3; FCH343,337,324"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2266","question":"Ornamental plants are decorative plants used in yards.  Name 3 ornamental plants that are poisonous to horses.","answer":"(Japanese) yew, foxglove, oleander, lily of the valley, wild jasmine, azalea (rhododendron species), larkspur, red maple tree, oak tree, horse chestnut tree (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm425-4-8; HIH741-3; FCH343,337,324"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2267","question":"What are the 3 major classifications of sudden death plants?","answer":"Alkaloid (yew, water hemlock, poison hemlock); cardiac glycoside (milkweed, foxglove, dogbane, oleander, lily of the valley); cyanogenic glycoside or cyanide (Johnson grass, arrow grass or root grass, elderberry, wild black cherry or chokecherry)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm425-7,8"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2268","question":"What do the following plants have in common:  yew, water hemlock, poison hemlock, and oleander?","answer":"They are very poisonous plants (that can cause sudden death in horses).  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm425-7-8; FCH334"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"2269","question":"Name 3 poisonous plants that can cause sudden death in horses.","answer":"Yew, water hemlock, poison hemlock, milkweed, foxglove, dogbane, oleander, lily of the valley, Johnson grass, arrow grass or root grass, elderberry, wild black cherry or chokecherry (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm425-7-8; FCH334"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2270","question":"Name 4 poisonous plants that can cause sudden death in horses.","answer":"Yew, water hemlock, poison hemlock, milkweed, foxglove, dogbane, oleander, lily of the valley, Johnson grass, arrow grass or root grass, elderberry, wild black cherry or chokecherry (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm425-7-8; FCH334"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2271","question":"Alkaloids are some of the deadliest poisons on the planet.  Name 3 plants that cause alkaloid poisoning in horses.","answer":"Yew, water hemlock, poison hemlock (European or spotted hemlock; unpalatable), death camas, larkspur, monkshood (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm425-7-8; FCH334"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2272","question":"It is rare that a horse is poisoned by a single mouthful of a toxic plant.  Name ONE plant that is an exception to this rule.","answer":"Water hemlock and (Japanese) yew (may also accept poison hemlock, oleander, foxglove, narrow-leafed milkweeds)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm425-4; FCH301, 334, 338, 341"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2273","question":"Water hemlock contains one of the most poisonous compounds known.  What is this compound?","answer":"Cicutoxin (pronounced SICK-you-tox-in)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm425-8; FCH342"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2274","question":"What type of sudden death poisoning would be the result of ingestion of water hemlock?","answer":"Alkaloid sudden death  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm425-8; FCH342"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2275","question":"Cardiac glycoside is one type of sudden death poisoning which causes heart arrythmias and cardiac arrest.  Name 3 plants that cause cardiac glycoside poisoning in horses.","answer":"Milkweed, foxglove, dogbane or Indian hemp, oleander, lily of the valley (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm425-7; FCH334"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2276","question":"Plant poisoning from consumption of milkweed causes what type of sudden death poisoning?","answer":"Cardiac sudden death  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm425-7; FCH337"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2277","question":"Other than death, give 3 symptoms of cyanide poisoning.","answer":"Cherry-red venous blood, rapid labored breathing, frothing at the mouth, dilated pupils, incoordination, muscle tremors, convulsions, dark red or cyanotic mucous membranes (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH336-37"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2278","question":"Name ONE poison that is found in Sorghum grasses such as Johnson and Sudan grasses.","answer":"Cyanide (prussic acid); nitrates (cause cystitis)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-3; HSm425-8; FCH321"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2279","question":"Cyanide or cyanogenic glycoside is one of the 3 types of sudden death poisonings.  Name 3 plants that can cause cyanide poisoning in horses.","answer":"Sorghum grasses (Johnson grass; Sudan grass, broom, or kafir corn); arrow, goose, or pod grass; elderberry; wild black cherry or chokecherry; serviceberry or Saskatoon berry; wild blue flax (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm425-8; FCH334,336,337"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2280","question":"Horses that eat the leaves of wild black cherry trees can get what kind of poisoning?","answer":"Cyanide poisoning  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm425-8"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2281","question":"What do the following trees have in common:  red maple, black walnut, oak, and wild black cherry?","answer":"They all can be poisonous to horses.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm425-4-8"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2282","question":"Name 3 poisonous TREES found in North America.","answer":"Red maple, oak (acorns), black walnut, chokecherry or wild black cherry, elderberry, horse chestnut or buckeye, black locust, black chestnut (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm425-5-8"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2283","question":"When are oak trees most toxic?","answer":"In the spring (FYI:  Leaves are green and flower buds are just opening.  Green acorns are more toxic than aged acorns.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm425-5; FCH304"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2284","question":"Tannins such as gallotanin cause colic, diarrhea, and red urine.  What toxic plant produces tannins?","answer":"Oak (FYI: The green leaves and green acorns are the most toxic parts.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm425-5; FCH303,304"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2285","question":"Name ONE part of the red maple tree that is toxic to horses.","answer":"Dry, wilted leaves; bark  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm425-5; FCH331"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2286","question":"At what stage are red maple leaves toxic to horses?","answer":"When they're wilted or dried (FYI:  Wilted or dried red maple leaves cause hemolytic anemia where red blood cells are destroyed.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm425-5; FCH331"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2287","question":"Name 3 effects of ingesting poisonous plants.","answer":"Excessive salivation (slobbering), colic, diarrhea, photosensitivity, liver disease, neurologic disease, lameness, muscle weakness, anemia, sudden death, birth defects (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm425-4; FCH Chapter 18"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2288","question":"Name ONE toxic plant that can cause anemia in horses.","answer":"Red maple, wild onions, moldy sweet clover (FYI: Wilted or dried red maple leaves cause hemolytic anemia where red blood cells are destroyed.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm425-5; FCH331"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2289","question":"Name 3 toxic plants that cause diarrhea is horses.","answer":"Buttercups (non-toxic when dried), buckeye or horse chestnut, pokeweed, oak, castor oil plant, Jimson weed, nightshade family of plants, rhododendron or azalea (non-toxic when dried)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm425-5"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2290","question":"Name ONE plant whose leaves cause colic and diarrhea when green, but become NON-TOXIC when dried.","answer":"Buttercups; azaleas (Rhododendron species)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm425-5,6; FCH306"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2291","question":"Poisonous plants that are classified as hepatotoxic primarily affect which organ?","answer":"Liver (FYI:  Alsike clover poisoning or “dew poisoning” can cause “big liver disease”.  Ragwort is also hepatotoxic.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm425-4"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2292","question":"Neurotoxic plants adversely affect the nervous system.  Name 3 neurotoxic plants.","answer":"Yellow star thistle, Russian knapweed, white snakeroot, bracken fern, horsetail (snake grass), locoweed (milkvetch), sagebrush, curly dock, Kentucky coffee tree, nightshade family (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm425-4-6"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2293","question":"Identify this poisonous plant:  It’s toxin is tremetol which causes “trembles” in horses and other livestock and “milk sickness” in people who drink milk from affected cows.  Tremetol is excreted in milk which poisons foals.","answer":"White Snakeroot  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH320; HSm425-6"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2294","question":"What is the main symptom of the poisoning that occurs when horses eat Yellow Star Thistle or Russian Knapweed?","answer":"Inability to take in or chew food (FYI: Poisoning is called \"chewing disease\" or nigropallidal encephalomalacia.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm425-6; FCH318"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2295","question":"What perennial weed has 5 bright yellow petals, 5 green sepals, and may cause colic, diarrhea, and photodermatitis?","answer":"St. John's Wort (FYI:  Alsike clover can also cause photodermatitis when eaten in large amounts.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm425-7; FCH306"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2296","question":"Name 3 plants that induce excessive salivation in the horse.","answer":"Red clover, foxtail, bearded barley, awns from wheat or rye, poison hemlock, water hemlock, death camas, Russian thistle, yellow star thistle, Canada thistle, white snakeroot, horse nettle, stinging nettle, azalea, bristle grass, buttercup, laurel  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH301; HSm425-3"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2297","question":"Name 3 COMMERCIAL feed classes.","answer":"Textured concentrates (sweet feed), processed concentrates (pelleted feed or extruded feed), complete feed, supplements (accept general or specific) [FYI:  Horse Science divides feed into 3 GENERAL categories—forages, concentrates, and mixed feeds.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH745-1"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"intermediate","number":"2300","question":"If fed without any other source of roughage, name ONE thing complete feeds may increase the risk of.","answer":"Colic, laminitis, gastric ulcers, vices (such as wood chewing)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH741-1"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2301","question":"What is a \"complete feed\"?","answer":"Combination of concentrates and forage in one product; one you don't have to feed hay with; one that provides all the horse's nutritional needs (accept any)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH741-1"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2302","question":"A complete feed contains all of the nutrients needed by the horse except for what TWO things?","answer":"Water and salt  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH385"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2303","question":"Give ONE reason why you'd use a complete feed.","answer":"When you have no hay available, when you have no pasture available, when you only have poor quality hay, when your horse has dental problems (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH741-1; HIH770-1,2"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"intermediate","number":"2304","question":"In which of the 3 main types of feed do grains and molasses fall?","answer":"Concentrates (FYI: The 3 main types of feeds are forages, concentrates, and mixed feeds.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc37"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2305","question":"Give 3 examples of concentrates.","answer":"Grain, molasses, byproduct feeds (beet pulp, rice bran, wheat bran), vitamin supplements, mineral supplements, protein supplements, energy supplements, fats  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc37"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2306","question":"Give 4 examples of byproduct feeds.","answer":"Beet pulp, rice bran, wheat bran, brewer's dried grains, corn gluten, corn distiller's dried grains  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH741-1-3; HSm410-3; HSc39"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2307","question":"Name TWO byproduct feeds that can be added to a horse's ration as additional sources of fiber.","answer":"Beet pulp; rice bran; wheat bran; brewer's dried grains  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH741-1-3; HSm410-3"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2308","question":"What feed has more digestible energy than hay and more bulk than grain?","answer":"Beet pulp  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm410-3"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2309","question":"Give ONE reason why horses are fed beet pulp.","answer":"Respiratory problems, heaves, thin horses, chronic colic, dental problems, exercise-related muscle problems (Tying Up), Equine Metabolic Syndrome (insulin resistance) [accept any correct answer]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm410-3"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2310","question":"Traditionally, what is done to beet pulp pellets before feeding them to horses?","answer":"They're soaked in water.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH741-2; FCH98"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2311","question":"Ideally horse feedstuffs should be fed by weight not by volume to ensure adequate nutrition.  How many pounds of dry beet pulp—beet pulp before it is soaked in water—can be fed per day to horses?\"","answer":"Up to 10 pounds per day  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH741-2"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2312","question":"What is typically used as a fat supplement, but is also a fair source of fiber?","answer":"Rice bran  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH741-2"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2313","question":"When feeding wheat bran as a supplement, how much can be fed per day?","answer":"1 (one) pound of wheat bran per day  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH741-3"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2314","question":"Give 3 benefits of feeding linseed meal or flaxseed to horses.","answer":"Gives glossy hair coat or “bloom”; softens stools to prevent impaction; has high level of Omega 3 fatty acids; treats allergic skin disease or “sweet itch”; used as a protein supplement; used to add fat and calories to the diet  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH85; HIH742-4,5; HIH715-3"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2315","question":"What feed additive is commonly used to reduce dust and to increase palatability of a feed?","answer":"Molasses (FYI:  Molasses is high in potassium so it should be avoided in horses with HYPP.)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH98; DET181; HSc40; HIH745-1"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"intermediate","number":"2316","question":"Give TWO reasons for using molasses in feeds.","answer":"Settles dust; increases palatability; used as a binder for pelleted feed; keeps supplements and other ingredients from sifting out of a loose grain mix  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH98; DET181; HSc40; HIH745-1"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"intermediate","number":"2317","question":"Molasses is added to feed to reduce dust and improve palatability.  Name the TWO plants that are the primary source of molasses fed to horses in the United States.","answer":"Sugar cane and sugar beets  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH98; DET181; HSc40"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2318","question":"Grain or concentrates should be what percent or less of a horse's total diet?","answer":"40% or less  <br/> <br/>ref:ES107"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2319","question":"Although wheat is high in digestible energy and protein, name 3 reasons why it’s not fed as often to horses as corn, oats, and barley.","answer":"High cost; small, hard kernels must be processed to be digested; low palatability; can form a dough ball in the horse's stomach  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH742-1; HSm410-3,5"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2320","question":"Regarding NUTRIENTS only, name 3 benefits of oats over corn and barley.","answer":"Oats are lower in digestible energy, higher in fiber, higher in fat, and higher in protein (FYI:  The lower digestible energy and higher fiber content of oats makes them safer to feed and more difficult to overfeed.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH742-1; HSm410-2; FCH39"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2321","question":"What advantage do cereal grains have over forage?","answer":"They are a more concentrated source of energy and nutrients.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH742-1"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2322","question":"Groats are grain kernels that have had what removed?","answer":"Hulls  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH391"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2323","question":"What is an oat groat?","answer":"Oat with the hull removed  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH391"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2324","question":"What is the name for the outer covering of grains?","answer":"Hull  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH393"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2325","question":"Name ONE grain that MUST be rolled or crimped before being fed to horses.","answer":"Barley, milo or sorghum, wheat  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm410-2,3; HSc40"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2326","question":"Name ONE thing that should be done to help foals, old horses, and horses with bad teeth digest grains.","answer":"Crack, crimp, roll, soak, steam, or extrude grain  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH76,77"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2327","question":"Give 3 ways grain is processed.","answer":"Grinding, roasting, crimping, dry rolling, steam rolling, cracking, steaming, extruded, popping, pelleting  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm410-3,4; FCH76,77"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2328","question":"What is the process of cracking grain by passing it through corrugated rollers called?","answer":"Crimping  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm410-4; FCH386"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2329","question":"In reference to feed processing, what is crimping?","answer":"Flattening and rippling grain (by running it through corrugated rollers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm410-4; FCH386"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2330","question":"Extruded feeds are half the weight of pelleted feeds because of what substance found in each pellet?","answer":"Air  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm410-4; FCH92"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"intermediate","number":"2331","question":"Which weighs less, a quart of pellets or a quart of extruded feed?","answer":"Extruded feed  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH92"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2332","question":"What is the primary benefit of extruded feed?","answer":"Improved digestibility  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH92"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2333","question":"Give 3 advantages of pelleted feeds.","answer":"Consistent product, decreased feed waste, less storage space, easier to store, easier to transport, reduced dust, better feed efficiency, beneficial for horses with poor teeth, less bulky  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm410-4; FCH92-94"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2334","question":"Name 3 disadvantages of pelleted feed.","answer":"Increased cost, rapid rate of eating can lead to choke, if roughage is not also fed it can lead to bad habits like wood chewing  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm410-4; FCH92-94"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2335","question":"Grains are processed in many ways.  What benefit does steam rolling have over dry rolling?","answer":"Decreases dust  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm410-4"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2336","question":"What is the most important factor to consider when storing grain?","answer":"Safe storage (protect the grain from moisture, pests, and horses)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH77; HSc51"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2337","question":"What is \"sweet feed\"?","answer":"Grain mix that's sweetened with molasses (accept any reasonable explanation)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH745-1; HSc41"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"2338","question":"Name 3 grains fed to horses.","answer":"Oats, corn, barley, wheat (usually as bran), rice (usually as bran), milo or sorghum, rye (unpalatable) [accept any correct answers]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH741; HSm410-2"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2339","question":"Name 4 grains fed to horses.","answer":"Oats, corn, barley, wheat (usually as bran), rice (usually as bran), milo or sorghum, rye (unpalatable) [accept any correct answers]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH741; HSm410-2"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2340","question":"2-part question:  When feeding barley to horses, in what form should it be fed and why?","answer":"Crimped or rolled; because it has a hard hull  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm410-2,3; HIH742-1"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2341","question":"What grain is being described?  It's the second most palatable grain for horses.  It's low in fiber and is high in digestible energy through its starch content.","answer":"Corn  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH742-1 HSm410-2,5; HSc40"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2342","question":"Give ONE reason why corn is considered a \"hot feed\".","answer":"Corn has a high energy content (lots of carbohydrates); it may make horses full of energy or high-strung (FYI:  Another meaning of a “hot feed” is one that produces a great deal of heat for its utilization, thus keeping the horse warm.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH755-1; HSm410-2; FCH393"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2343","question":"Which grain is more economical per unit of energy, oats or corn?","answer":"Corn  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm410-2; HSc40"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"novice","number":"2344","question":"What grain can be fed rolled, shelled, cracked, whole kernel, or on the cob?","answer":"Corn  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm410-2; HIH742-1; HSc40"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"2345","question":"Name 3 ways corn can be fed to horses.","answer":"Cracked, shelled, ground, rolled, crimped, whole kernel, whole ear or on the cob (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm410-2; HIH742-1; HSc40"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2346","question":"Name 4 ways corn can be fed to horses.","answer":"Cracked, shelled, ground, rolled, crimped, whole kernel, whole ear or on the cob (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm410-2; HIH742-1; HSc40"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2347","question":"Which of the following cereal grains fed to horses is LOWEST in crude protein:   barley, oats, corn, or wheat?","answer":"Corn  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm410-5"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2348","question":"What concentrate has the alternate name of sorghum?","answer":"Milo (FYI:  Milo has a small, hard kernel that needs to be processed and it's not palatable when fed alone.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH742-1; HSm410-3"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2349","question":"Name 3 advantages of feeding oats to your horse.","answer":"Difficult to overfeed, less likely to cause founder, most palatable of grains, soft kernel so processing not necessary, stores better, less likely to have mold or mycotoxins, not considered a hot feed  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH39; HIH742-1; HSm410-2"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2350","question":"Which concentrate is the MOST expensive in terms of cost per unit of nutrients?","answer":"Oats  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm410-2; HSc40; HIH742-1"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"novice","number":"2351","question":"What is the most popular grain fed to horses?","answer":"Oats  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH742-1; HSm410-2; HSc40"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2352","question":"Which of the following cereal grains fed to horses is HIGHEST in crude fiber:  barley, oats, corn, or wheat?","answer":"Oats  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm410-2; HIH742-1"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2353","question":"Rye grain is high in protein, but is typically not fed to horses for what reason?","answer":"Poor palatability  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-4; HSm410-3"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2354","question":"What is a calming supplement designed to do for a horse?","answer":"Quiet down a nervous or excited horse (Calm the horse.) [FYI:  Valerian root is found in many equine calming supplements.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH742-5"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2355","question":"Why is glucosamine commonly used as a supplement in animals and humans?","answer":"Glucosamine decreases the symptoms of arthritis.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH742-2"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2356","question":"Name ONE supplement that’s commonly used for arthritis in horses.","answer":"Glucosamine, chondroitin, hyaluronic acid, MSM (methyl-sulfonyl-methane)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH742-2"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2357","question":"Give TWO reasons why soybean meal is a popular supplement.","answer":"High in (high quality) protein; high in lysine; economical  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm410-3; FCH83,142"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2358","question":"Name ONE effect of an equine supplement that contains Valerian Root.","answer":"Calming effect, sedative effect, anti-spasmodic effect  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH742-4"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2359","question":"Give ONE advantage of feeding Zeolite to young horses.","answer":"Increases bone density; decreases exertion-induced bone injuries (FYI: Zeolite is a silicon-based supplement.)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH215"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2360","question":"What type of feed should be the start of any horse feeding program?","answer":"Forages (also accept hays or pastures which are types of forage)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm410-1; FCH63"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2361","question":"The terms roughages and forages are sometimes used interchangeably for foods that are high in fiber.  Give 3 examples of roughages that can be fed to horses.","answer":"Pasture, hay, silage, haylage, chaff, straw, beet pulp, cereal grain hulls, corn cobs  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm410-2; DET111; DET236; FCH402; HSc27"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2362","question":"Give ONE reason why grass clippings and/or garden refuse are NOT recommended for feeding horses.","answer":"Garden refuse may contain plants that are lethal to horses; lawn clippings ferment easily in warm weather or may contain endophytes which might be toxic  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH741-3"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"2364","question":"Name 3 types of GRASSES that horses eat. (ACCEPT ANY CORRECT ANSWERS)","answer":"Orchardgrass, Timothy, Kentucky bluegrass, tall fescue, smooth bromegrass, perennial ryegrass, annual ryegrass, reed canarygrass, Bahia, Bermuda, crabgrass, Teff, sorghum, Sudan, Johnson, pearl millet, browntop millet, wheatgrass, barnyard grass  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740; HSm410-2; HSm420-5-11; TH182-183"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2365","question":"Name 3 cool season grasses that horses eat.","answer":"Orchardgrass, Timothy, Kentucky bluegrass, tall fescue, smooth bromegrass, perennial ryegrass, annual ryegrass, reed canarygrass (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-4; HSm420-5-11"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2366","question":"Identify the following cool-season grass: nutritious, palatable, winter hardy, tolerates close grazing, and is an important forage in the central and northern eastern states. It’s named after a US state.","answer":"Kentucky bluegrass  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-4; HIH740-10; HSm410-2; HSm420-9"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2367","question":"Identify the following cool-season grass: leafy, rapid re-growth, does not tolerate close grazing, bunchy in growth habits, grown predominantly in the northeastern, midwestern, and northwestern US. Its name means a group of fruit trees.","answer":"Orchard grass  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-4; HIH740-10; HSm410-2"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2368","question":"Identify the following cool-season grass:  adaptable to a wide range of soils, tolerant of continuous grazing, excellent fall productivity, and is winter hardy.  It may contain endophytes which can cause dystocia, agalactia, and thickened placenta.","answer":"Tall fescue (fescue)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm410-2; HSm420-10; HIH740-9"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2369","question":"Is Timothy grass grown mainly for use as hay or for pasture?","answer":"Hay  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm410-2; HSm420-11; HIH740-9"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2370","question":"Identify the following cool-season grass:  highly palatable, winter hardy, slow regrowth, poor heat and drought tolerance, used for hay predominantly in the northeast and Midwest US.  It’s often fed to small animals like rabbits and guinea pigs.","answer":"Timothy  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-4"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2371","question":"Name 3 warm season grasses that horses eat.","answer":"Bahiagrass, Bermudagrass, crabgrass, Teff, sorghum, Sudan, sorghum-Sudan, Johnson, pearl millet, browntop millet, wheatgrass, barnyard grass, dallisgrass, nimblewill, St. Augustine, yellow foxtail (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-3; HSm420-5; FCH108"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2372","question":"Which grasses tend to be LOWER in nutritional value, warm season or cool season grasses?","answer":"Warm season grasses  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-8"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2373","question":"What warm-season, perennial, sod-forming grass is grown for both pasture and hay?","answer":"Bermuda grass  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm410-2; HSm420-6; HIH740-4; HIH740-10"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2374","question":"What warm season grass frequently invades Bermuda grass and tall fescue pastures and lawns?","answer":"Crabgrass  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-4"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2375","question":"Give ONE advantage of growing crabgrass in pastures with tall fescue.","answer":"Summer production is the highest at the time when fescue growth has slowed; dilutes toxins present in endophyte-infected tall fescue.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-3"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2376","question":"Name ONE warm season grass whose production is similar to that of sorghum and sorghum hybrids, but does not have the cystitis or prussic acid problems.","answer":"Pearl millet or browntop millet (FYI:  Cystitis is inflammation or infection of the urinary bladder.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-3"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2377","question":"2-part question: Name a warm season grass that's generally safe to feed as hay, but that's NOT recommended for use in pastures.  Explain why.","answer":"Sorghum, Sudan grass, or Johnson grass; can cause cystitis or cyanide (prussic acid) toxicity (FYI:  Cystitis is inflammation or infection of the urinary bladder.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-3"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2378","question":"Why is Teff safe to feed to horses with metabolic or digestive disorders?","answer":"Low in carbohydrates or sugars (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-9"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2379","question":"What is a summer annual grass that originated in Ethiopia where it's used primarily as a cereal crop?","answer":"Teff  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-9; HSm420-5"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2380","question":"What type of equine is more efficient in digesting fiber and therefore can be fed a diet that is higher in fiber?","answer":"Donkey  <br/> <br/>ref:ES146"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2381","question":"Name the TWO basic types of hay.","answer":"Grass and legume  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm410-1"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2382","question":"What is the most important winter feed for horses, hay or grain?","answer":"Hay  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH420-1; HSm305-7"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"intermediate","number":"2383","question":"What causes \"hay belly\"?","answer":"Horse eating more hay (extra bulk distends the intestinal tract)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH392"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2384","question":"What GENERAL type of pasture plants provides the greatest amount of nutrients and a longer grazing season?","answer":"Mixture of grasses and legumes  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc38; HSm415-2"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2385","question":"Give 3 possible causes for the lack of a sweet or pleasant smell in hay.","answer":"Over maturity, bleaching, old hay, mold, leaching  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm415-1"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2386","question":"Name 3 factors affecting the quality of hay.","answer":"Type (grass or legume), species, stage of maturity when cut, leafiness, weather conditions, harvest conditions, curing procedures, storage conditions, presence of weeds, presence of pests, presence of dust, presence of mold  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm415-1; HIH740-7,8"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2387","question":"What is the MOST ACCURATE method of assessing the nutrient makeup of hay?","answer":"Chemical analysis  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH114; HSm415-3; HIH750-1"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2388","question":"What instrument is used to take hay samples for nutrient content analysis?","answer":"Hay probe  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm415-3; FCH114"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2389","question":"You have just purchased a truckload of grass hay and would like to have it tested for nutrient analysis.  Explain how you'd do this.","answer":"Use a hay probe to take samples from at least 20 bales; mix samples together; send 1 quart of the mixture to the lab for analysis.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm415-3; FCH114"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2390","question":"What is a hay probe?","answer":"Instrument used for taking samples of hay for nutrient analysis  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm415-3"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2391","question":"What is the oldest and most common method of selecting hay?","answer":"Visual appraisal (by looking at it)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm415-3; HSc38"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2392","question":"Name TWO things to look for when selecting good hay.","answer":"Green color, fine stems, lots of leaves, no dust, no mold, no weeds, no bad odor, no poisonous plants, no blister beetles, no foreign objects, no rain damage (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm415-1; HIH740-7,8; HIH750-1"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"2393","question":"Name 3 qualities to look for when purchasing hay.","answer":"Green color, fine stems, lots of leaves, no dust, no mold, no weeds, no bad odor, no poisonous plants, no blister beetles, no foreign objects, no rain damage (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm415-1; HIH740-7,8; HIH750-1"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2394","question":"Name 4 qualities to look for when purchasing hay.","answer":"Green color, fine stems, lots of leaves, no dust, no mold, no weeds, no bad odor, no poisonous plants, no blister beetles, no foreign objects, no rain damage (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm415-1; HIH740-7,8; HIH750-1"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2395","question":"Name TWO components of the \"visual appraisal\" of hay other than just looking at the hay.","answer":"Feel and smell  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-7"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2396","question":"Describe the color of overly mature hay.","answer":"Pale yellow or brown (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm415-1; HSc38"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2397","question":"Hay with a bleached color indicates exposure to what?","answer":"Sunlight or rain (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-7"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2398","question":"As hay grows older, does it become more or less digestible?","answer":"Less digestible  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm415-2; HIH740-1; HSc38"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2399","question":"In reference to hay, what part of the plant is the LEAST digestible?","answer":"Stems  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm415-2; HIH740-1; HSc38"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2400","question":"Which general type of hay usually has the LEAST dust?","answer":"Grass hay  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm410; HSm420; HSc38"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2401","question":"What kind of hay tends to be the dustiest?","answer":"Legume hay (alfalfa)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc38"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2402","question":"If you have to feed your horse dusty hay, how can you reduce the dustiness before feeding?","answer":"Sprinkle it with water.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc38"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2403","question":"Name ONE problem that may occur if a hay rack is hung too high for the horse eating from it.","answer":"Hay may get into the horse's eyes; horse may inhale dust (which could lead to respiratory problems); horse may not get enough to eat. (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-12; FCH149"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2404","question":"To decrease the chances of hay getting into the horse's eyes or the horse inhaling dust, hay feeders for horses should be no higher than what part of the horse?","answer":"Shoulder level of the horse (also accept withers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-12; FCH149"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2405","question":"Give ONE reason why hay should be fed in a feeder.","answer":"To decrease ingestion of sand, dirt, or feces; to decrease parasite infestation  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-11; HSm420-4; HSc51"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2406","question":"Name 4 basic steps in making hay.","answer":"Growing, cutting, raking, drying, baling, storing (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-5-7"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"2407","question":"Name 3 basic steps in making hay.","answer":"Growing, cutting, raking, drying, baling, storing (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-5-7"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2408","question":"2-part question:  Hay should be baled at a maximum moisture content of 15% – 20%.   Give ONE reason why moisture content above this level and ONE reason why moisture content below this level could reduce the quality of the baled hay.","answer":"Above has potential for mold, increased heat production, decreased protein levels, and spontaneous combustion; below causes leaves to fall off during processing (which decreases the nutritional value and palatability).  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm415-1; HIH740-5"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2409","question":"What is the ideal percentage for the moisture content of hay when it is baled?","answer":"17% (accept any number within the 13% – 20% range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm415-1,2; HIH740-7; FCH65"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2410","question":"Hay that's been mowed, then rained on, can lose what percent of its nutritional value?","answer":"40% – 50% (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH65"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2411","question":"Give TWO characteristics of moldy hay.","answer":"Musty smell, color changes (white or black areas), dusty, unpalatable, damp, hot  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH445-8; HIH750-1; FCH69,70"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2412","question":"Give ONE reason why hay should NOT be baled if the moisture level is over 30%.","answer":"Hay will become moldy, hay will heat up, hay may spontaneously combust, hay will lose vitamins, hay will have decreased protein digestibility (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm415-2; HIH340-4; FCH65; HSc38"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2413","question":"Name 3 things that can happen when hay is baled with a moisture level of 30%.","answer":"Hay will become moldy, hay will heat up, hay may spontaneously combust, hay will lose vitamins, hay will have decreased protein digestibility (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm415-2; HIH340-4; FCH65; HSc38"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2414","question":"What happens to the total nutrient content of hay when it is over-cured and baled with a moisture content that is too low?","answer":"Nutrient content decreases (because the leaves shatter and fall off).  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm415-2; FCH65; HSc38"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"intermediate","number":"2415","question":"How long does hay usually take to dry after being cut?","answer":"3 – 5 days (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-6"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2416","question":"Give TWO reasons for spraying preservatives such as mold inhibitors or propionic acid on forage as its cut.","answer":"Reduces bacterial and fungal growth; allows farmer to bale at higher moisture content.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-7"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2417","question":"At what stage of growth is grass hay most easily digested by the horse?","answer":"Boot stage, pre-bloom stage, immature hay, or when seed heads begin to appear (accept any)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm415-1; HIH820-2; FCH68,69; HSc38"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2418","question":"Give TWO reasons why immature hay at the pre-bloom or boot stage is more desirable as horse feed than mature hay.","answer":"Most easily digested, highest leaf to stem ratio, highest nutrient value  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm415-1; HIH820-2; FCH68,69; HSc38"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2419","question":"Name 3 factors that influence when to cut hay.","answer":"Weather conditions, labor availability, equipment availability, if cut too early or too late plants may not re-grow well for the next cutting  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-6; HSm415-1"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2420","question":"Hay bought during the winter will often be high priced for what reason?","answer":"Demand is high; hay is hard to find, so prices are raised (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-6,7"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2421","question":"Many factors influence the supply and demand for hay and thus hay prices.  Name TWO supply factors and TWO demand factors","answer":"Supply—weather, species, preservation techniques, storage availability, fuel cost; demand—number of horses in region, perceived value of certain forage species, demand from other livestock species, weather  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-6,7; HSm225-5"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"intermediate","number":"2422","question":"Give ONE reason why hay prices fluctuate from year to year.","answer":"Weather during growing and processing, type of hay grown, how hay is stored, fuel costs, number of horses in region, demand from other livestock species, perceived value of forage type (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-6,7; HSm225-5"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"intermediate","number":"2423","question":"Older horses with dental problems may not be able to eat forage in the traditional form of hay and may need alternatives.  Name TWO of these alternatives.","answer":"Chopped hay, hay cubes (soak first), hay pellets, complete feeds  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH770-1,2"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2424","question":"What is the main objective when growing and processing hay?","answer":"Preserve nutrient and energy content  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-5"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2425","question":"Name 4 ways hay can be fed to horses other than loose or from bales.","answer":"Cubes, pellets, chopped, silage, haylage, compressed, wafers, extruded (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm410-2; HIH741-1,2; FCH66,67"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"2426","question":"Name 3 ways hay can be fed to horses other than loose or from bales.","answer":"Cubes, pellets, chopped, silage, haylage, compressed, wafers, extruded (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm410-2; HIH741-1,2; FCH66,67"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2427","question":"What are hay cubes?","answer":"Cubes of hay (hay that's been chopped, compressed, and formed into cubes)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH741-1"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2428","question":"Give ONE advantage of hay cubes.","answer":"Easy to transport, easy to store, more consistent product  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH741-1"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2429","question":"Give ONE disadvantage of feeding hay cubes.","answer":"Horse can develop vices such as wood chewing if no long stem forage is fed; potential for choke  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH741-1"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2430","question":"How many pounds of hay cubes can be fed to horses per day?","answer":"Up to 15 pounds per day  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH741-1"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2431","question":"Give ONE NUTRITIONAL advantage of feeding hay pellets instead of hay.","answer":"Increased digestibility; more consistent product with hay pellets  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH741-2"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2432","question":"If you store hay above stalls, how much space must be left between the hay and the walls for air passage?","answer":"At least 12 inches (1 foot)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-9; HSm210-1"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"novice","number":"2433","question":"Give ONE reason NOT to store hay above horse stalls.","answer":"Dust, mold, fire hazard, respiratory problems (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-9; HSm210-1"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2434","question":"\"Heavy\" bales of hay are often caused by too much moisture in the hay during the baling process.  Describe how storing \"heavy bales\" can start a fire.","answer":"Dampness or mold in heavy bales can cause hot spots that can lead to spontaneous combustion.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH340-1"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2435","question":"Name ONE important factor to consider when storing hay.","answer":"Protect hay from moisture; protect hay from sun.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-6; HIH740-12; HSm420-4"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2436","question":"Why should hay be stored off the ground?","answer":"So moisture from the ground won't spoil the bottom bales or so air can circulate (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-6; HSm420-4"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2437","question":"Name 3 things to consider when storing hay.","answer":"Store off the ground so ground moisture won't spoil bottom bales, allow for air circulation, protect from sunlight, protect from moisture, protect from vermin, protect from animals  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-6; HSm420-4"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2438","question":"Name 3 types of cereal grain used for hay.","answer":"Oats, beardless wheat, barley  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-10"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2439","question":"What does a legume contain that allows it to produce higher levels of energy and protein than grasses?","answer":"Bacteria (in the root nodules)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm420-2; INT202-1"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2440","question":"Give 3 considerations and/or potential hazards associated with feeding alfalfa pasture or hay.","answer":"Dust; mold; blister beetles; mycotoxins; caution in older horses; caution with kidney, liver, or metabolic problems; can cause development orthopedic disease (DOD), respiratory problems, colic, tying up, thumps, or mineral imbalances  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH64; FCH192; FCH214; FCH286; FCH365HSm"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2441","question":"Name 3 types of legumes that may be fed to horses.","answer":"Alfalfa, red clover, white clover, ladino clover, alsike, yellow (sweet) clover, crimson clover, birdsfoot trefoil, lespedeza, perennial peanut  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-2,3; HSm410-2; HSm415-2; FCH108"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2442","question":"What is the most common legume fed to horses?","answer":"Alfalfa (FYI:  Alfalfa, red clover, white clover, and alsike clover are cool-season legumes. Lespedeza is a warm-season legume  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-2; HSm420-5"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2443","question":"Give ONE reason why pure alfalfa pasture is NOT recommended for most horses.","answer":"Contains more protein than most horses require; contains more energy than most horses require; requires long rest periods between grazing  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-2; HSm420-5"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2444","question":"Which legume is more expensive than others and is also difficult to establish?","answer":"Birdsfoot trefoil  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-2"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2445","question":"Birdsfoot trefoil is a low-growing legume perennial that's commonly used by highway departments for what purpose?","answer":"Roadside seeding or erosion control (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-2"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2446","question":"Name 3 different varieties of clover that may be fed to horses.","answer":"Red, alsike, sweet (yellow), white, ladino (type of white clover), crimson  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-2,3; HSm410-2; HSm415-2; FCH108"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2447","question":"2-part question:  Give ONE advantage and ONE disadvantage of using red clover in pastures.","answer":"Advantages:  highly nutritious, deep rooted, grows where alfalfa won't grow, easy to establish; disadvantages:  only grows for two years, can cause photosensitivity, can cause slobbering, difficult to dry, doesn’t tolerate close grazing  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-10; HSm410-2; HSm420-9"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2448","question":"Red clover grows best in acidic, wet soils and is usually grown in areas where which other legume will not grow?","answer":"Alfalfa  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-2"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2449","question":"Which type of clover has low productivity, but it's commonly found in pre-packaged pasture mixes?","answer":"White clover (FYI:  White clover is nutritious, palatable, and is very competitive in pastures when conditions are cool and moist.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-2"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2450","question":"Perennial peanut hay is a good substitute for what other legume in tropical regions?","answer":"Alfalfa  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-10"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2451","question":"Are mineral and vitamin contents higher, lower, or equal in immature grasses and legumes than in mature plants?","answer":"Higher in immature plants  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm410-2; HSm415-1; HIH740-6; HIH820-2; FCH68; HSc38"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2452","question":"The amount of seed heads on grasses or the amount of flowers on legumes present at the time of harvest tells you what about the hay?","answer":"Stage of maturity  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm415-1; HIH740-6; HIH820-2; FCH68"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2453","question":"What is the most important factor affecting the nutrient content of grasses and legumes?","answer":"Stage of maturity at harvest  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm410-2; HSm415-1; HIH740-6; HIH820-2; FCH68; HSc37"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2454","question":"How is plant maturity of GRASS hay visually determined?","answer":"Amount of seed heads present at time of harvest  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm415-1; HIH740-6; HIH820-2; FCH68"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2455","question":"Which type of forage should be harvested at the “boot” stage?","answer":"Grasses (FYI:  Boot or early head stage is when the grass the seed heads are just beginning to show through the sheath.  Legumes should be harvested at the pre-bloom, bud, or vegetative stage just prior to flowering.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm415-1; HIH740-6; HIH820-2; FCH68"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2456","question":"How is the plant maturity of LEGUME hay visually determined?","answer":"By the amount of flowers present at time of harvest  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm415-1; HIH740-6; HIH820-2; FCH68"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2457","question":"Which type of forage should be harvested at the pre-bloom stage?","answer":"Legumes (FYI:  The pre-bloom, bud, or vegetative stage is just prior to flowering.  Grasses should be harvested at the boot or early head stage when seed heads are beginning to show through the sheath.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm415-1; HIH740-6; HIH820-2; FCH68"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2458","question":"As forages mature and the percentage of lignin and structural carbohydrates increases, what happens to the digestibility of the forage?","answer":"Digestibility decreases as forage matures. (FYI:  For every 1% increase in lignin, the digestibility of forage dry matter decreases 3% – 4%.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm415-1; HIH740-8; FCH68"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2459","question":"What happens to the lignin content as hay matures?","answer":"Lignin content increases as hay matures. (FYI: Lignin, like cellulose, is a complex compound found in the cell walls of plants.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm415-1; HIH740-8; FCH68"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2460","question":"Give 3 advantages of a grass-legume pasture.","answer":"Increased productivity (they mature at different times), increased nutritional value of forage, pure alfalfa pasture often has too much protein, horses prefer mixed types of grass, legumes add nitrogen to the soil  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-8; HIH735-3"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2461","question":"Do horses prefer pastures of mixed grass types or a single type?","answer":"Mixed types  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH735-3"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2462","question":"What physical part of hay contains the highest level of carbohydrates and proteins?","answer":"Leaves  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-1; HSm410; HSm420"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2463","question":"Fiber is necessary in horse diets to ensure the normal functioning of what body system?","answer":"Digestive system  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH745-3"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2464","question":"Which cutting of hay will usually have the HIGHEST fiber content?","answer":"First cutting  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-7"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"intermediate","number":"2465","question":"What is the GENERAL term for plant material that’s high in fiber that’s fed to horses and livestock?","answer":"Forages (also accept roughage)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET110; HSc36"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2466","question":"Name 3 things that a good quality legume hay is higher in than a good quality grass hay.","answer":"Energy, protein, minerals (calcium), vitamins (vitamin A, beta carotene, vitamin B, vitamin E), soluble carbohydrates (nitrogen-free extract) [PHOSPHOROUS WAS REMOVED AS A CORRECT ANSWER]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm410-1; FCH64; HSc36"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2467","question":"Name TWO nutrients that are higher in legumes than in grasses.","answer":"Protein, calcium, vitamins (A and B, such as riboflavin), other minerals (such as potassium, magnesium, copper, zinc, iron, and cobalt), and energy (PHOSPHOROUS WAS REMOVED AS A CORRECT ANSWER)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm415-1; HSm410-1; HIH740-2,7, 11; HIH745-3; HIH795-3; HIH730-1; HIH735-3; HSc37"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2468","question":"Which hay would have a higher calcium content, Timothy or clover?","answer":"Clover  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm415-1; HSm410-1; HIH740-2,7, 11; HIH745-3; HIH795-3; HIH730-1; HIH735-3; HSc37"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2469","question":"Which forage has a higher calcium content, legumes or grasses?","answer":"Legumes  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm415-1; HSm410-1; HIH740-2,7, 11; HIH745-3; HIH795-3; HIH730-1; HIH735-3; HSc37"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2470","question":"What type of hay will provide the horse with the greatest amount of crude protein?","answer":"Alfalfa  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-7; HSm410-1FCH419-420 tables"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2471","question":"If hay is rained on before baling, it will lose some nutrients, especially carbohydrates.  However, good quality, rained on hay can benefit horses that are sensitive to what?","answer":"Forage sugar content  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-7"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2472","question":"What is the percentage of water in pasture forages?","answer":"65% – 90% (accept any number within this range) [FYI:  Percentage is 75% – 90% in new growth grasses in the spring; just prior to cutting, moisture content is 65% – 85%.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm410-1; HIH740-6; HSc36"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2473","question":"The horse is an animal that developed grazing on grasslands.  Its digestive tract was therefore designed to do what?","answer":"Handle frequent, small feedings of forage  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm435-3; HIH735-1"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2474","question":"If forage is good, approximately how long do free-ranging horses graze per day?","answer":"12 hours per day (accept any number between 10 – 17 hours per day)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-3; HIH735-2; HIH740-11"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2475","question":"Horses spend what percent of their time grazing at night?","answer":"20% – 50% (accept any number within range) [FYI:  Horses graze more at night during the summer.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH735-2"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2476","question":"Name 3 things that influence grazing time for horses on pastures.","answer":"Age, gender, breed, grouping, time of day, season, grass species, environmental conditions (rainfall, wind, temperature, relative humidity, snowfall)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH735-2"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2477","question":"Horses on pasture will spend 10 – 17 hours per day doing what?","answer":"Grazing  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH735-2; HIH740-11; HSm305-3"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2478","question":"How does the relative humidity affect the length of grazing time?","answer":"Higher humidity results in longer grazing times. (FYI:  High rainfall, high wind, and high temperature, decrease grazing time; cold weather increases grazing time; snow decreases grazing time.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH735-2"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2479","question":"According to the Horse Industry Handbook, tell which grazes longer per day for each of the 3 following pairs:  stallions or mares, Thoroughbreds or Arabians, and individuals or herds.","answer":"Mares, Arabians, herds  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH745-5"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"intermediate","number":"2480","question":"In order to decrease the risk of laminitis, colic, diarrhea, and stable vices, forage should be what percent of the horse's diet?","answer":"At least 50% (FYI:  Newer source says at least 70%.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-1; FCH196"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2481","question":"Why is leafiness in hay an important guide to feeding value?","answer":"Most of the nutrients are found in the leaves  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc38; HIH740-1; HSm415-1"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2482","question":"What is meant by the term \"forage quality\"?","answer":"Nutritional quality of forages (characteristics affecting the consumption and nutrition quality)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm415-1"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2483","question":"Name TWO methods of determining forage quality.","answer":"Visual appraisal, chemical analysis, near infrared reflectance spectroscopy  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm415-3"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2484","question":"Good quality silage, haylage, or ensiled forage should not exceed what percent of a horse’s daily forage ration?","answer":"50% (FYI:  Silage, haylage, and ensiled grass are forages that are harvested at higher moisture contents and are stored under anaerobic conditions.)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH80"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2485","question":"What is the term for forage that's been fermented and stored in anaerobic conditions?","answer":"Silage or haylage (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm410-2"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2486","question":"Straw should NOT be considered as a source of nutrition for horses other than for supplemental use as what?","answer":"Source of fiber or \"chew factor\" (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH741-2"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2487","question":"2-part question:  Explain the difference between straw and cereal grain forage and tell what each is used for.","answer":"Straw is what's left of the plant after the seed heads have been removed; straw is used as bedding; cereal grain forages are plants such as oats that've been harvested with the seeds still attached; cereal grain forages are used as hay.  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH95"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2488","question":"Horses will usually drink enough water during the winter if water is maintained at what temperature?","answer":"45 – 68 degrees (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH710-1; HSm305-7"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2489","question":"When allowed to choose between a bucket and an automatic watering system, which one do most horses prefer?","answer":"Bucket  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH710-2"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2490","question":"What does hyper-hydration mean?","answer":"Excess water consumption  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH710-2"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2491","question":"How much water does the average 1000-pound horse drink each day?","answer":"10 gallons (accept any number between 5 – 12 gallons)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH710-1; HIH420-2; HSm305-7; ES116; HSc32; PNW63"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2492","question":"Lactating mares may increase their water intake over their maintenance requirement by what amount in order to meet lactation demands?","answer":"2 – 3 times maintenance requirement  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH710-1"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2493","question":"By the age of two months, most foals are drinking how much water per day?","answer":"Up to one gallon  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH710-2"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2494","question":"How many times do most horses drink per day?","answer":"2 – 8 times per day (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH710-2"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2495","question":"Name 3 DISADVANTAGES of an automatic waterer.","answer":"Expense, can freeze (if not installed properly), can malfunction (check water supply daily), hard to monitor water intake, hard to restrict water intake, horse can get caught in some designs, can shock horse, need to be cleaned and disinfected  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-5; HIH415-3"},
    {"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2496","question":"Name ONE way a bucket that's used for watering a horse should be managed to prevent infectious diseases.","answer":"Should be emptied at least once a day, should be cleaned every 2 – 3 days, should be cleaned daily if there's an illness in the barn  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-5"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2497","question":"Which abnormal way of going is worse, inward or outward movement of the front legs?","answer":"Inward movement (because legs can interfere)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-3; HIH230-5; CAHA39; HH12"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"jr bonus","number":"2498","question":"In reference to gaits, name 3 abnormal ways of going.","answer":"Paddling or winging out; dishing or winging in; winding, rope walking, or plaiting; rolling; trappy; pounding; cross firing; forging; interfering; pointing; scalping; speedy cutting; limping  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-2,3; HIH230-5; CAHA39; HH13"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"sr bonus","number":"2499","question":"In reference to gaits, name 4 abnormal ways of going.","answer":"Paddling or winging out; dishing or winging in; winding, rope walking, or plaiting; rolling; trappy; pounding; cross firing; forging; interfering; pointing; scalping; speedy cutting; limping  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-2,3; HIH230-5; CAHA39; HH13"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"medium","number":"2500","question":"In reference to horses, what is a \"daisy cutter\"?","answer":"Horse that skims the surface of the ground at the trot (doesn't bend legs much)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET77"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2501","question":"How will a splay footed horse travel?","answer":"Dish or wing in  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-3; HIH230-5; CAHA39; HH12"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2502","question":"What conformation fault does a horse have if he dishes or wings in when he travels?","answer":"Splay foot or toe out (also accept base wide)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-3; HIH230-5; CAHA39; HH12"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"intermediate","number":"2503","question":"What is the term used to describe a noticeable pause in the flight of the foot as though the stride were completed before the foot reaches the ground?","answer":"Dwelling (also accept floating)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH13; HIH174B-1"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"intermediate","number":"2504","question":"What is the term used when a horse's action is difficult to perform and is painfully excessive?","answer":"Labored action  <br/> <br/>ref:HH17; DET163"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"intermediate","number":"2505","question":"In reference to gaits, what is \"labored action\"?","answer":"When a horse has to work hard to move (horse's action is difficult to perform and is painfully excessive) [accept any reasonable wording]  <br/> <br/>ref:HH17; DET163"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"sr bonus","number":"2506","question":"Name 3 causes of lameness that are NOT related to the feet or lower legs.","answer":"Neck pain, withers pain, shoulder pain, hip pain, stifle pain, inherited, trauma, infection, metabolic, neurological  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-3"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2507","question":"What is the term used when a pigeon-toed horse throws the front feet outward while traveling?","answer":"Paddling  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-3; HIH230-5; CAHA39; HH13"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2508","question":"In reference to gaits, what is paddling?","answer":"Throwing the front feet outward while traveling  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-3; HIH230-5; CAHA39; HH13"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2509","question":"What is the term for striking the ground hard in the stride?","answer":"Pounding  <br/> <br/>ref:DET219; HH18"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2510","question":"In reference to gaits, what is pounding?","answer":"Striking the ground hard in the stride  <br/> <br/>ref:DET219; HH18"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"intermediate","number":"2511","question":"In reference to abnormal ways of going, what is rolling?","answer":"Excessive lateral shoulder motion (FYI:  Rolling is movement like the motion of a bulldog walking.  It’s seen in horses with protruding shoulders.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET236; HH13,18"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"intermediate","number":"2512","question":"What is the term for excessive lateral shoulder motion that’s seen in horses with protruding shoulders?","answer":"Rolling  <br/> <br/>ref:DET236; HH13,18"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"medium","number":"2513","question":"2-part question:  In reference to way of going, what is plaiting and what type of conformation results in this way of travel?","answer":"Forefeet travel inward to land in front of one another; occurs in base narrow, toed-out horses  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-3; CAHA39; HH13"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2514","question":"What is the term used when describing a winding or twisting of the striding leg around in front of the supporting leg which results in contact like that of a rope walking artist?","answer":"Rope walking, winding, or plaiting (accept any)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-3; CAHA39; HH13"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"intermediate","number":"2515","question":"What is the term for a pacer that rolls its body sideways as it paces?","answer":"Sidewheeler  <br/> <br/>ref:DET245; HH18"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2516","question":"In reference to gaits, what does the term \"trappy\" mean?","answer":"Short, quick, choppy stride  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-4; HH13"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2517","question":"A trappy stride is most commonly seen in horses with what TWO conformation defects?","answer":"Straight shoulders and short, steep pasterns  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-4; HH13"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2518","question":"What is the term used for a short, quick, choppy stride?","answer":"Trappy  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-4; HH13"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2519","question":"Winging out is an exaggerated paddling seen in high stepping horses.  Name ONE breed that might wing out.","answer":"Saddlebred, Hackney, Morgan  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-3; DET294"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2520","question":"What is the term for the exaggerated paddling that is seen in high-stepping horses such as Saddlebreds?","answer":"Winging or winging out (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-3; DET294"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2521","question":"Why do working ranch horses need to have gaits that are comfortable for the rider and are easy on the horse?","answer":"Both work long days (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:ES83"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2522","question":"What is the term used to describe the rhythmic, pattern of movements of a horse's feet and legs?","answer":"Gaits  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-1; HH17"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"medium","number":"2523","question":"Give TWO reasons why horse owners should have a working understanding of a horse’s gaits.","answer":"To detect lameness, to train a performance horse, to be able to use a horse for a specific purpose  <br/> <br/>ref:HH17"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"jr bonus","number":"2524","question":"Give another name for each of the following gaits: trot, lope, slow gait, and rack.","answer":"Trot is jog, lope is canter, slow gait is stepping pace, and rack is singlefoot.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm135-3; HSm380-2; HH18"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"jr bonus","number":"2525","question":"Name 3 gaits that have 4 beats.","answer":"Walk, gallop or run, slow gait or stepping pace, rack or singlefoot, running walk, amble, paso, tolt, racking walk (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm135-3,4; HSm380-2; HH Chapter 4"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"sr bonus","number":"2526","question":"Name 5 gaits that have 4 beats.","answer":"Walk, gallop or run, slow gait or stepping pace, rack or singlefoot, running walk, amble, paso, tolt, racking walk (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm135-3,4; HSm380-2; HH Chapter 4"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"intermediate","number":"2527","question":"Name TWO gaits—other than the walk, trot, canter, gallop, or back—that may be natural gaits to some breeds.","answer":"Pace, running walk, slow gait (stepping pace), rack (singlefoot), fox trot, paso, tolt, flying pace (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:ES81,82; HIH166B-1, 169B-1, 172B-1; HSm135-4; HH17"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"hard","number":"2528","question":"In reference to gaits, describe the flying pace.","answer":"Fast, 2 beat lateral gait (FYI:  The flying pace is an Icelandic horse’s racing gait.  It has a period of suspension between footfalls.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm135-4"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"hard","number":"2529","question":"Describe the fox trot gait.","answer":"4 beat diagonal gait (where the hind foot hits the ground an instant before the diagonal forefoot; head usually nods; walking in front and trotting in back)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH161B-1; HSm135-4"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"medium","number":"2530","question":"What is the name of the gait described as walking in front and trotting behind?","answer":"Fox trot  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH161B-1; HSm135-4"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"hard","number":"2531","question":"2-part question:  Identify this gait and name the breed.  The gait starts out as a simple trot, but the hind diagonal foot comes down before the front foot making it a 4-beat gait.","answer":"Gait is the fox trot; breed is the Missouri Fox Trotter.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH161B-1; HSm135-4"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"jr bonus","number":"2532","question":"What are the 3 gaits of the Missouri Fox Trotter?","answer":"Walk, fox trot, and canter  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm135-4"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"hard","number":"2533","question":"Describe the paso gait.","answer":"4-beat lateral gait (a broken pace)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-4; HSm135-3"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"sr bonus","number":"2534","question":"What are the 3 speeds of the paso gait?","answer":"Paso fino, paso corto, and paso largo  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-4; HSm135-3"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"hard","number":"2535","question":"2-part question:  What is “termino” and in which breed is it seen?","answer":"Forelegs roll towards the outside as the horse strides forward (like the arm motion of a swimmer); seen in the Peruvian Paso  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm135-3"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"intermediate","number":"2536","question":"What 2 gaits does a 5-gaited horse perform that a 3-gaited horse does NOT perform?","answer":"Slow gait (stepping pace) and rack (singlefoot)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm135-3; HH40"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"sr bonus","number":"2537","question":"Name the 5 gaits performed by a 5-gaited horse.","answer":"Walk, trot, canter, slow gait or stepping pace, and rack or singlefoot  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm135-3; HH40"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2538","question":"What is the name for the fast, flashy, 4-beat gait that's sometimes referred to as the singlefoot?","answer":"Rack  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-3; DET228; HH18; HH40"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2539","question":"What is the 5th gait of the American Saddle Horse?","answer":"Rack or singlefoot (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-3; DET228; HH18; HH40"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2540","question":"Which fast, 4-beat artificial gait of the horse is easy on the rider, but is extremely tiring for the horse?","answer":"Rack or singlefoot (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:ES81"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2541","question":"How many beats are in the gait referred to as the stepping pace?","answer":"4 (four) beats  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm135-3"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2542","question":"In reference to Saddlebreds, what is another name for the slow gait?","answer":"Stepping pace  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm135-3; ES81"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"hard","number":"2543","question":"In reference to gaits, describe the tolt.","answer":"4 beat lateral ambling gait that can be performed at different speeds.  (FYI:  The tolt is performed by Icelandic horses.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm135-4"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"jr bonus","number":"2544","question":"Name the 3 gaits of the Tennessee Walking Horse.","answer":"Walk (flat walk), running walk, and canter (rocking chair canter)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH172B-1; HSm115-2"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2545","question":"What is furniture-sounding term used to describe the canter of the Tennessee Walking Horse?","answer":"Rocking chair canter  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH172B-1; HSm115-2"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"medium","number":"2546","question":"What is the footfall sequence for the running walk, starting with the left front foot?","answer":"Left front; right rear; right front; left rear  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH172B-1"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2547","question":"What is the name for a fast, 4-beat ground-covering walk of the Tennessee Walking Horse?","answer":"Running walk  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm115-1; HIH152-1; HH"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"medium","number":"2548","question":"2-part question: The Plantation Gait is a smooth, ground-covering gait that made the Tennessee Walking Horse popular in the South. What is the proper name for this gait and how many beats does it have?","answer":"Running walk; 4 beats  <br/> <br/>ref:DET214; ES81"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"jr bonus","number":"2549","question":"Name 3 gaits that are natural to MOST breeds.","answer":"Walk, trot or jog, canter or lope, gallop or run, back  <br/> <br/>ref:ES69-70"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"sr bonus","number":"2550","question":"Name 5 gaits that are natural to MOST breeds.","answer":"Walk, trot or jog, canter or lope, gallop or run, back  <br/> <br/>ref:ES69-70"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"medium","number":"2551","question":"How many beats are there in the horse's gait when backing?","answer":"2 (two) beats  <br/> <br/>ref:ES79"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2552","question":"What gait is an easy, rhythmical, 3-beat gait?","answer":"Canter or lope (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-2; HH17-20"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2553","question":"How many beats are in the canter?","answer":"3 (three) beats  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-2; HH17-20"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2554","question":"In reference to gaits, what is a lead?","answer":"Independently moving or leading front leg in a canter or gallop (FYI:  The leading leg is the LAST foot to hit the ground in a canter or gallop.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-2; DET166; ES74; HH17-20"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2555","question":"At the canter or lope, what do you call the independently moving front leg?","answer":"Lead  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-2; DET166; ES74; HH17-20"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2556","question":"When a horse is cantering in a counterclockwise direction in a riding arena, which lead is considered the correct one?","answer":"Left lead  <br/> <br/>ref:ES75-76; PNW134"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2557","question":"What is the collected canter exhibited in Western classes called?","answer":"Lope  <br/> <br/>ref:DET172; HH18,22; PNW134"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2558","question":"With which foot does a horse START a right lead canter?","answer":"Left hind  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-2; ES75 diagram; HH18"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2559","question":"When on the left lead, which leg or legs are on the ground for the SECOND BEAT of the canter?","answer":"Left rear and right front (FYI: 1st beat is right hind, 2nd beat is left hind and right front, and 3rd beat is left front)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-2; HH18"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2560","question":"What is the LAST foot to hit the ground in the canter when on the right lead?","answer":"Right front  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-2; HH18"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"novice","number":"2561","question":"What is another name for the gallop?","answer":"Run  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-2; DET237-238; HH19; ES76"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"medium","number":"2562","question":"What is the difference between a full gallop as run by a racehorse and a hand gallop?","answer":"Full gallop is a 4-beat gait; hand gallop is a 3-beat gait and is more of an extended canter.  <br/> <br/>ref:DET117; DET129"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2563","question":"How many beats are there in a gallop?","answer":"4 (four) beats  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-2; HH19; DET117"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2564","question":"At a gallop on a right lead, what is the next foot to hit the ground after the right front?","answer":"Left hind  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-2; HH19; ES77"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2565","question":"Beginning with the contact of the left hind foot with the ground, explain the footfall sequence of a horse on the right lead at the gallop.","answer":"Left hind, right hind, left front, and right front  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-2; HH19; ES77"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2566","question":"Which gait is a two-beat lateral gait?","answer":"Pace  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-2; HH19; ES81"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2567","question":"In reference to gaits, describe the pace.","answer":"Two-beat gait lateral gait (legs move in lateral pairs; front and hind legs on the same side start and stop at the same time)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-2; HH19; ES81"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2568","question":"The \"base of support\" of any gait means what legs are on the ground supporting the horse.  What is the base of support for the pace?","answer":"Two lateral legs (two legs on the same side are on the ground at once)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH19"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2569","question":"Which gait is a rapid, two-beat diagonal gait?","answer":"Trot  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-2; HH18; ES72"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2570","question":"In reference to gaits, describe the trot.","answer":"Two-beat diagonal gait (front foot and opposite hind foot start and stop at the same time)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-2; HH18; ES72"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2571","question":"Which gait is faster, the trot or the pace?","answer":"Pace  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm175-2"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2572","question":"What is the difference between a trot and a pace?","answer":"Trot is a two-beat DIAGONAL gait; pace is a two-beat LATERAL gait.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-2; HH18-19"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2573","question":"The \"base of support\" of any gait means what legs are on the ground supporting the horse.  What is the base of support for the trot?","answer":"Two diagonal legs  <br/> <br/>ref:ES72; HH18"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"intermediate","number":"2574","question":"What is the term for the lengthening of the trot stride without an increase in tempo?","answer":"Extended trot  <br/> <br/>ref:TH115; DET101"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"intermediate","number":"2575","question":"What is an extended trot?","answer":"Lengthening of the stride without an increase in tempo or speed  <br/> <br/>ref:TH115; DET101"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"novice","number":"2576","question":"What is another name for the slow trot seen in Western classes?","answer":"Jog  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-2; HH18,21"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2577","question":"Which natural gait is the slowest 4 beat gait with each foot striking the ground independently from the other 3 feet?","answer":"Walk  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-2; HH17; DET286"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"novice","number":"2578","question":"Which gait is the slowest gait and is common to all breeds of horses?","answer":"Walk (FYI:  Speed of the walk is 3 – 4 miles per hour.)  <br/> <br/>ref:ES70; HH17; DET286"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2579","question":"The \"base of support\" of any gait means what legs are on the ground supporting the horse.  What kind of base of support does the horse have at the walk?","answer":"Triangular (3 legs are on the ground at once)  <br/> <br/>ref:ES70; HH17"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2580","question":"What movement is important for opening gates?","answer":"Sidepass, sidestep, or traverse (accept any)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH23"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"intermediate","number":"2581","question":"Name this movement:  The horse steps laterally with both forequarters and hindquarters moving together with a crossover step.  There is no forward or backward movement.","answer":"Sidepass, traverse, or sidestep (accept any)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET245; DET274; HH18"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2582","question":"In reference to gaits, describe a sidepass.","answer":"Sideways movement without forward or backward movement  <br/> <br/>ref:DET245; DET274; HH18"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"sr bonus","number":"2583","question":"Interference is a general term to describe the horse's legs hitting each other when moving.  Name 4 types of interference.","answer":"Forging, scalping, cross firing, speedy cutting, shin hitting, hock hitting, overreaching (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-3; HH13"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"medium","number":"2584","question":"2-part question:  Name TWO striding leg interferences where the toe of the forefoot hits the hind leg and describe where on the hind leg the striking occurs.","answer":"Hock hitting the front toe hits the hock; scalping the front toe hits the hind coronet; shin hitting the front toe hits the hind cannon (on the same side); speedy cutting the front toe hits the hind pastern or fetlock (on same side).  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-3"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"jr bonus","number":"2585","question":"Interference is a general term to describe the horse's legs hitting each other when moving.  Name 3 types of interference.","answer":"Forging, scalping, cross firing, speedy cutting, shin hitting, hock hitting, overreaching (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-3; HH13"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"medium","number":"2586","question":"In reference to supporting leg interference, explain the difference between brushing and striking.","answer":"Brushing is slight contact between the legs; striking is harder contact between legs that may result in an open wound.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-2"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"intermediate","number":"2587","question":"What is the term for the striding leg interference—often seen in pacers—where the inside fore foot and the outside hind foot strike in the air as the stride of the hind leg is ending and the stride of the foreleg is beginning?","answer":"Cross-firing  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-3; DET73; HH13"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"intermediate","number":"2588","question":"In reference to striding leg interference, what is cross-firing?","answer":"When the inside fore foot and the outside hind foot strike each other (FYI:  The feet strike in the air as the stride of the hind leg is ending and the stride of the foreleg is beginning.  It’s commonly seen in pacers.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-3; DET73; HH13"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"medium","number":"2589","question":"What is the GENERAL term for the striking of the inside of one leg with the hoof or skin of the opposite leg?","answer":"Interfering (FYI:  This can occur anywhere from the coronet to the knee or hock.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-2; DET153"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"medium","number":"2590","question":"In reference to gaits, what is the term for striking the inside of one leg with the hoof or skin of the opposite leg?","answer":"Interfering or interference (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-2; DET153"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2591","question":"What is the term for when the toe of the HIND foot hits the sole or shoe of the fore foot?","answer":"Forging (FYI:  This usually occurs at the trot and may make a characteristic clicking sound.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-3; HH13"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2592","question":"In reference to gaits, what is forging?","answer":"Striking the forefoot with the toe of the hindfoot (on the same side) [FYI:  This usually occurs at the trot and may make a characteristic clicking sound.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-3; HH13"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"intermediate","number":"2593","question":"What term is commonly used for forging at the walk where the toe of the HIND foot grabs the heel of the fore foot?","answer":"Overreaching  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-3"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"intermediate","number":"2594","question":"What is the term for when the toe of the FRONT foot hits the area of the hock on the hind leg?","answer":"Hock hitting  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-3"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"intermediate","number":"2595","question":"In reference to gaits, what is hock hitting?","answer":"When the toe of the FRONT foot hits the area of the hock on the hind leg  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-3"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2596","question":"What is the term for when the toe of the FRONT foot strikes the coronet or hairline of the hind leg?","answer":"Scalping  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-3; HH13"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2597","question":"In reference to gaits, what is scalping?","answer":"Toe of the front foot hits the hairline or coronet of the hind leg (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-3; HH13"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"intermediate","number":"2598","question":"What is the term for when the toe of the FRONT foot hits the cannon bone of the hind leg?","answer":"Shin hitting  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-3"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"intermediate","number":"2599","question":"In reference to gaits, what is shin hitting?","answer":"When the toe of the FRONT foot hits the cannon bone of the hind leg  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-3"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"intermediate","number":"2600","question":"What is the term for when the toe of the FRONT foot hits the fetlock of the hind leg?  This type of interference usually occurs at fast gaits.","answer":"Speedy cutting  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-3; HH13"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"intermediate","number":"2601","question":"In reference to gaits, what is speedy cutting?","answer":"When the toe of the FRONT foot hits the fetlock of the hind leg (FYI:  It’s usually seen at fast gaits.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-3; HH13"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"hard","number":"2602","question":"What are the TWO major general types of leg interference that can occur in horses?","answer":"Striding leg and supporting leg interference (FYI:  In striding leg interference, a moving leg contacts another moving leg.  In supporting leg interference, a moving leg contacts a supporting leg.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-2"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"intermediate","number":"2603","question":"What is the speed of the canter?","answer":"10 – 17 miles per hour (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-3"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"intermediate","number":"2604","question":"What is the speed of the gallop?","answer":"30 – 50 miles per hour (accept any number within this range) [FYI:  Racing Quarter Horses have been clocked up to 55 miles per hour during sprints!]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-2"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"intermediate","number":"2605","question":"What is the speed of the running walk?","answer":"7 – 10 miles per hour (accept any answer within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH172B-1; HH18"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"intermediate","number":"2606","question":"The trot is the most energy efficient of the gaits.  What is the speed of the trot?","answer":"8 – 10 miles per hour (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-2"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"intermediate","number":"2607","question":"The walk is the horse's slowest gait.  What is the average speed of the horse's walk?","answer":"3 – 4 miles per hour (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-2; ES70"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"medium","number":"2608","question":"What is the term for the moment in a horse's stride between landing and takeoff?","answer":"Breakover [FYI:  Breakover is when the heel starts to lift off the ground (heel lift), tipping the foot forward to lift off at the toe (toe pivot).]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-1"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2609","question":"In reference to gaits, describe the term “stride”.","answer":"Distance from imprint to imprint of the same hoof. (FYI:  A step is the distance between imprints of two front hooves or two hind hooves.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-1; HH18; FCH405"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2610","question":"What is the term for the distance from imprint to imprint of the same hoof?","answer":"Stride (FYI:  A step is the distance between imprints of two front hooves or two hind hooves.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-1; HH18; FCH405"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"sr bonus","number":"2611","question":"Name 3 important features of the stride.","answer":"Balance, directness (trueness), height (action), length, rapidity, regularity  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-1; HH19"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"hard","number":"2612","question":"In reference to foot action, what is meant by the term \"height\"?","answer":"Amount of elevation in the stride  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-1; HH18"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"medium","number":"2613","question":"What is the Thoroughbred's average length of stride at the gallop?","answer":"21 – 23 feet (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:ES78"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"hard","number":"2614","question":"At the gallop, Secretariat had a stride of what length?","answer":"29 feet  <br/> <br/>ref:ES76"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"medium","number":"2615","question":"Name 3 phases of the horse's stride.","answer":"Weight-bearing phase:  landing, loading, stance, and breakover; swing phase (non-weight bearing phase)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-1"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"medium","number":"2616","question":"In relation to stride, name TWO things that determine a horse's speed.","answer":"Stride length, stride frequency (rapidity), overlap time (amount of time the hoof is on the ground versus the time the hoof is off the ground)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-1"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2617","question":"What makes it possible for a horse to do a flying lead change?","answer":"Brief period of suspension (when all 4 legs are off the ground)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-2; HH19"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"medium","number":"2618","question":"Referring to gaits, what is the period of suspension?","answer":"Period when all 4 feet are off the ground  <br/> <br/>ref:DET260; HSm380-2; HH18"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2619","question":"In reference to horses, what is action?","answer":"How a horse moves its feet and legs at the walk, trot, canter, etc.  <br/> <br/>ref:DET3; HSm120-2,3; HH12"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"intermediate","number":"2620","question":"Your horse is being ridden at a controlled and correct gait.  The hocks are well under him and he is ridden well up to his bit with his neck flexed and his jaw relaxed.  What is the correct term for the appearance of this horse?","answer":"Collected  <br/> <br/>ref:DET61; PNW93; HH17"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"intermediate","number":"2621","question":"What is a counter canter?","answer":"Balanced canter on one lead while the horse is traveling in the opposite direction (intentionally cantering a horse on the opposite lead from the direction it's traveling)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET70; PNW135; PNW158"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2622","question":"What is the term for a balanced canter on one lead while the horse is traveling in the opposite direction?","answer":"Counter canter  <br/> <br/>ref:DET70; PNW135; PNW158"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2623","question":"What term would be used to describe a horse that's cantering on one lead in front and a different lead in the rear?","answer":"Disunited canter, cross firing, or cross canter (accept any)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET82; HH18"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2624","question":"What is the expression used for a horse's gaits when the rider's reaction is pleasant and enjoyable?","answer":"Easy gaited  <br/> <br/>ref:DET88; HH17"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"hard","number":"2625","question":"Generally speaking, when it's said that a horse is \"engaged\", what does this mean?","answer":"Horse is using its hindquarters for impulsion.  <br/> <br/>ref:DET93"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"medium","number":"2626","question":"In reference to gaits, what is four-beating?","answer":"4-beat canter instead of a 3-beat canter (lopes with front legs and trots with hind legs)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET114"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"intermediate","number":"2627","question":"In reference to gaits, explain free going.","answer":"Free forward movement (when the horse moves forward freely in a smooth, collected manner without pain or difficulty) [accept any reasonable wording]  <br/> <br/>ref:DET114; HH17"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"intermediate","number":"2628","question":"What is the expression used when a horse's gaits are executed in a smooth, collected manner and its action is not excessive or labored?","answer":"Free going  <br/> <br/>ref:DET114; HH17"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"intermediate","number":"2629","question":"What is the term for changing from one gait to another?","answer":"Transition  <br/> <br/>ref:DET273; HSm380-2"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2630","question":"What is meant by the term \"way of going\"?","answer":"How a horse moves, travels, or tracks at different gaits (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm145-3; HSm380-1; HSm385-1"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"medium","number":"2631","question":"What term is used to refer to the nature of movement in the horse?","answer":"Way of going or action (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm145-3; HSm380-1; HSm385-1"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"easy","number":"2632","question":"What is the study of how characteristics are passed from parents to offspring?","answer":"Genetics (FYI:  Gregor Mendel is known as the “father of modern genetics”.  He was a scientist and friar in the 1800’s who studied pea plants.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm505-1; HSc18"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"intermediate","number":"2633","question":"Define heredity.","answer":"Passing of traits from parents to offspring (FYI:  Genetics is the study of heredity or how characteristics are passed from parents to offspring.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET139"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2634","question":"In reference to genetics, what does diploid mean?","answer":"Chromosomes are in pairs. (FYI:  The number of sets of chromosomes contained within a cell is defined as its ploidy which is determined by the type of cell division that a cell goes through.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm310-2; ES87"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2635","question":"In reference to genetics, what does haploid mean?","answer":"Chromosomes are single, NOT in pairs. (FYI:  Somatic or body cells are diploid. Their cell division is mitosis.  Gametes or sex cells are haploid.  Their cell division is meiosis.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm310-2; ES87"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2636","question":"What is the COMMON term for deoxyribonucleic acid?","answer":"DNA  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm510-1; DET79; ES87"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2637","question":"Genes are made up of complex molecules of what?","answer":"DNA (deoxyribonucleic acid)  <br/> <br/>ref:ES87"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"easy","number":"2638","question":"If a gene has the ability to mask the genetic makeup of the other gene in the pair, is it dominant or recessive?","answer":"Dominant  <br/> <br/>ref:ES90; DET83; HIH1060-1; HSm505-3; HSc19"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"easy","number":"2639","question":"If a gene CANNOT mask the genetic makeup of the other gene in a pair, is it dominant or recessive?","answer":"Recessive  <br/> <br/>ref:ES90; DET230; HIH1060-1; HSm505-3; HSc19"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2640","question":"In genetics, what does the term \"codominance\" mean?","answer":"When two alleles are equally dominant (FYI:  An example of codominance would be the AB blood type.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1020-2"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2641","question":"Give ONE example of partial dominance where the dominant gene is not fully expressed.","answer":"Dilution of color (such as cream dilutions in palominos and buckskins)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1040-2,3"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2642","question":"In genetics, what does the term “partial dominance” mean?","answer":"Gene action that results in an intermediate state between the two alleles (Example:   A single dominant cream gene doesn’t make a chestnut a cremello.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1020-2,3"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2643","question":"The cream gene is a partially dominant gene which does what when combined with other color genes?","answer":"Lightens or dilutes the color  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1040-2; HSm510-3"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"easy","number":"2644","question":"What are the basic units of inheritance?","answer":"Genes (Do NOT accept genetics which is the study of heredity.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm505-1; HSc18"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2645","question":"In reference to genetics, what are alleles? (pronounced ah-LEELS)","answer":"Paired genes (that are located at the same physical location on a chromosome) [FYI:  Alleles may or may not be identical.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1080-2; HIH1020-1; HSm505-2,3; ES90; DET6"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2646","question":"In reference to genetics, what is the locus?","answer":"Specific location of a gene on a chromosome (FYI:  Plural is loci.)  <br/> <br/>ref:ES90; HIH1020-1; HSm505-2,3"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"intermediate","number":"2647","question":"What does genotype mean?","answer":"Genetic makeup  <br/> <br/>ref:ES91; DET119; HSm505-2; HIH1020-2; HSc20"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"intermediate","number":"2648","question":"What is the difference between genotype and phenotype?","answer":"Genotype is the genetic makeup; phenotype is the outward appearance.  <br/> <br/>ref:ES91; DET119; DET211; HSm505-2; HIH1020-2; HSc20"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"intermediate","number":"2649","question":"What does phenotype mean?","answer":"Outward appearance of an animal  <br/> <br/>ref:ES91; DET211; HIH1080-2; HSm505-2; HSc20"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"intermediate","number":"2650","question":"If paired genes are NOT identical, are they homozygous or heterozygous?","answer":"Heterozygous  <br/> <br/>ref:ES90,91; DET139,141; HIH1020-2; HSm505-3"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"intermediate","number":"2651","question":"If paired genes are the same, are they homozygous or heterozygous?","answer":"Homozygous  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1020-2; HSm505-3"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2652","question":"What is the name of the special procedure used to visualize or examine chromosomes under a microscope?","answer":"Karyotyping (pronounced CARE-ee-oh-type-ing)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1060-1; ES94"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2653","question":"Where is the cytoplasm located in a cell?","answer":"Between the nucleus and the cell wall  <br/> <br/>ref:DET76; HIH1020-1 Figure 1"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"intermediate","number":"2654","question":"What is the nucleus of a cell?","answer":"Dense center of a cell that contains the genetic material  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc23; ES86; HIH1020-1; HSm505-4; HSm510-1"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"intermediate","number":"2655","question":"What is the dense center of a cell that contains the genetic material?","answer":"Nucleus  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc23; ES86; HIH1020-1; HSm505-4; HSm510-1"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2656","question":"What is a Punnett square?","answer":"Diagram that’s used to predict the outcomes of matings (way of determining what percentage of offspring of a mating will have which genes of the parents)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm510-9,12; H3-10"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"easy","number":"2657","question":"In the inheritance of sex or gender in the horse, what are the chances for the foal to be male?","answer":"50 – 50 (half may be male)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1060-1; HSm505-1; HSc21"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2658","question":"If a sperm carrying the X chromosome fertilizes the egg, what sex will the foal be?","answer":"Female  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1060-1; HSm505-1; HSc21"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"intermediate","number":"2659","question":"What is the general term for the X and Y chromosomes?","answer":"Sex chromosomes  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1060-1; HSm505-1; HSc21"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"intermediate","number":"2660","question":"What is the sex genotype for a mare?","answer":"XX  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1060-1; HSm505-1; HSc21"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"intermediate","number":"2661","question":"What is the sex genotype of a stallion?","answer":"XY  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1060-1; HSm505-1; HSc21"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2662","question":"What is the proper name for a mature sex cell?","answer":"Gamete  <br/> <br/>ref:DET118; HSm505-2; ES92; HIH1020-2"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"intermediate","number":"2663","question":"In what type of cells do chromosomes exist as singles, NOT as pairs?","answer":"Sex cells, egg and sperm, gametes, or haploid cells (accept any)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm505-1; HIH1020-1"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"sr bonus","number":"2664","question":"Define 3 of the following terms:  outcrossing, crossbreeding, inbreeding, and linebreeding.","answer":"Outcrossing—mating unrelated animals; crossbreeding—mating animals of different breeds; inbreeding—mating closely related animals; linebreeding—form of inbreeding that tries to concentrate the inheritance of one family line  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1080-1; DET73"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2665","question":"What is the term for the type of inbreeding that's aimed at trying to maintain a close relationship with a particular animal?","answer":"Linebreeding  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1080-1"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2666","question":"What is inbreeding?","answer":"Breeding closely related animals  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1080-1; DET150"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2667","question":"What does the term \"nicking\" mean?","answer":"When the offspring has more superior qualities than expected by their pedigree  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1080-1"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2668","question":"What is outcrossing?","answer":"Mating animals that are members of the same breed, but which show no relationship close up in the pedigree.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1080-1; DET198"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2669","question":"What is a chromosome?","answer":"Long, thread-like structure in the nucleus of a cell that contains genetic material  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm505-1; HIH1020-1; HSc18; DET56"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"intermediate","number":"2670","question":"How many chromosomes are responsible for the sex of a foal?","answer":"2 chromosomes (one pair)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1060-1; HSm505-1; HSc21"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"easy","number":"2671","question":"How many PAIRS of chromosomes do horses have?","answer":"32 pairs of chromosomes  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm505-1; HIH1020-1; ES88; Hsc18"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"intermediate","number":"2672","question":"How many chromosomes does the sperm of a stallion or an egg of a mare contain?","answer":"32 SINGLE chromosomes (Do NOT accept 32 pairs.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm505-2; HIH1020-1; HSc19"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2673","question":"How many chromosomes does a donkey have?","answer":"62 chromosomes  <br/> <br/>ref:ES20; HSc21"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2674","question":"How many chromosomes do mules and hinnies have?","answer":"63 chromosomes (FYI: Horses have 64; donkeys have 62.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc21"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"intermediate","number":"2675","question":"2-part question:  Are chromosome pairs always identical?  Explain your answer.","answer":"No.  Males have XY sex chromosomes and females have XX chromosomes.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1060-1; HSm505-1; HSc21"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"sr bonus","number":"2676","question":"Name 3 coat colors whose base color is black with a dilution or modification.","answer":"Bay and seal brown (agouti), buckskin (single cream bay), perlino (double cream bay), classic dun (dun bay), grulla (dun black), smoky black (single cream black), smoky cream (double cream black), red roan (bay), blue roan (black), gray  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105; HSm510"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"sr bonus","number":"2677","question":"Genetically, name 3 ways a BLACK coat color be modified.","answer":"Dilutions, spotting, graying, roaning, agouti gene (bay)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1040; HSm510"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2678","question":"Are the genes for coat color separate or combined with the gene loci for occurrence and pattern of white hairs on the body?","answer":"Separate  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1040"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2679","question":"In reference to coat color genetics, what color modifier do the letters A/a represent?","answer":"Agouti gene (FYI: Agouti gene controls the distribution of black on bay horses to the points only.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm510-2; ES95"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2680","question":"What gene must be present to produce the color bay?","answer":"Dominant agouti gene (agouti gene)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm510-2; ES95"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2681","question":"What does the agouti gene do?","answer":"Restricts the black coloring to the points of the horse (mane, tail, lower legs, and ear rims)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm510-2; ES95"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2682","question":"Genetically, what is the difference between a buckskin and a “classic” or \"coyote\" dun?","answer":"Buckskin is a cream dilution of bay; classic or coyote dun is a dun dilution of bay.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1040-2; HSm510-4"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2683","question":"What does dilution of color mean?","answer":"Lessening the intensity of the color  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm510-3; DET81"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2684","question":"2-part question:  What color results from a single cream dilution of bay and what color results from a double cream dilution of bay?","answer":"Single cream dilution of bay is buckskin; double cream dilution of bay is perlino.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-11; HSm510-3,4; HIH1040-2"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2685","question":"Genetically speaking, what is a buckskin?","answer":"(Single) cream dilution of bay  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-11; HSm510-3,4; HIH1040-2"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2686","question":"What color is a single cream dilution of bay?","answer":"Buckskin  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-11; HSm510-3,4; HIH1040-2"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2687","question":"The cremello color is a result of a double cream dilution of what base color?","answer":"Chestnut  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-11; HSm510-3; HIH1040-2"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2688","question":"A double cream dilution of chestnut results in what color?","answer":"Cremello  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-11; HSm510-3; HIH1040-2"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"sr bonus","number":"2689","question":"If a palomino mare were mated to a palomino stallion, what percentage of foals would be what color?","answer":"50% palomino, 25% cremello, and 25% chestnut  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-11; HSm510-3; HIH1040-2"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2690","question":"The palomino color is a single cream dilution of what base color?","answer":"Chestnut  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-11; HSm510-3; HIH1040-2"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2691","question":"You are planning to breed your chestnut mare and would love her to produce a palomino foal.  In order to guarantee a foal of this color, what color stallion should she be bred to?","answer":"Cremello (Since cremellos have two dominant cream genes, the cremello stallion would pass one cream gene to the foal and the mare would pass two recessive extension genes to the foal to make a palomino—single cream dilution of chestnut.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-11; HSm510-3; HIH1040-2"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2692","question":"What color is a single cream dilution of chestnut?","answer":"Palomino  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-11; HSm510-3; HIH1040-2"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2693","question":"The perlino color is a double cream dilution of what base color?","answer":"Bay  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-11; HSm510-3; HIH1040-2"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2694","question":"Which one of the following modifications of black does NOT have black points:  bay, seal brown, buckskin, dun, grulla, or perlino?","answer":"Perlino  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-11; HSm510-3; HIH1040-2"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"sr bonus","number":"2695","question":"Name the 3 colors that result from dun dilutions of black, bay, and chestnut.","answer":"Grulla is a dun dilution of black, dun (classic, coyote, or zebra) is a dun dilution of bay, and red dun is a dun dilution of chestnut.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105; HSm510; HIH1040-2"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"intermediate","number":"2696","question":"Grulla is a dun dilution of what basic coat color?","answer":"Black  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-9; HSm510-4; HIH1040-2"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"intermediate","number":"2697","question":"What color is a dun dilution of black?","answer":"Grulla  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-9; HSm510-4; HIH1040-2"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"intermediate","number":"2698","question":"What color is a dun dilution of chestnut?","answer":"Red dun  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-9; HSm510-4; HIH1040-2"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2699","question":"What is the base color of a red silver horse?","answer":"Bay (FYI: Red silver is a silver dapple dilution of bay.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-10; HIH1040-2"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"sr bonus","number":"2700","question":"What color would be the result of the silver dapple gene on the following 3 colors:  black, bay, and chestnut?","answer":"Black is silver dapple (also called blue silver, black silver, or taffy), bay is red silver, and chestnut is chestnut (FYI:  Silver dapple gene only affects black areas.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm105-10; HIH1040-2"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2701","question":"In reference to coat color genetics, what genes must a chestnut horse have?","answer":"2 (two) recessive Extension genes (ee)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1040-1; ES94-95; HSm510-2"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2702","question":"If you breed a heterozygous black stallion to a heterozygous black mare, what percentage of the foals may be red?","answer":"25%  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1040-1; ES94-95; HSm510-2"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"easy","number":"2703","question":"Which coat color is dominant, black or chestnut?","answer":"Black (FYI:  Black and red (chestnut) are controlled by the Extension gene.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1040-1; ES94; HSm510-2,3"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2704","question":"What TWO base colors are determined by the Extension gene?","answer":"Black and red (chestnut) [FYI: Bay is an agouti modification of black.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1040-1; ES94-95; HSm510-2"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"easy","number":"2705","question":"What color is recessive to black and bay?","answer":"Chestnut  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1040-1; ES94-95; HSm510-2"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2706","question":"Name TWO genotypes of a black horse.","answer":"EE, Ee, aaEE, aaEe  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1040-1; ES94-95; HSm510-2"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2707","question":"In reference to coat color genetics, what is the Extension gene?","answer":"Gene that regulates black and red coloring (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1040-1; ES94-95; HSm510-2"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"easy","number":"2708","question":"If a chestnut is mated to a chestnut, what color or colors can be produced?","answer":"Only chestnut (FYI: Chestnut is recessive to black.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1040-1; ES94; HSm510-2"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2709","question":"2-part question:  What colors of foals would a chestnut mare produce when mated with a homozygous black stallion and when mated with a heterozygous black stallion?","answer":"When mated with a homozygous black stallion, ALL of the foals would be black; when mated with a heterozygous black stallion, half of the foals would be black and half would be chestnut.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1040-1; ES94-95; HSm510-2"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2710","question":"The gene for what color is located at the G locus?","answer":"Gray  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1040-3"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"intermediate","number":"2711","question":"What color foal will a homozygous gray produce?","answer":"Gray (FYI: Gray is dominant to other colors.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1040-3; HSm510-7"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2712","question":"In equine color genetics, what do the letters “TO” refer to?","answer":"Tobiano (FYI:  Recessive “to” results in no spots.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1040-3; HSm310-8"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"easy","number":"2713","question":"Which color can cover up or mask the colored areas of a horse?","answer":"White  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1040-1"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2714","question":"What does the term \"congenital\" mean?","answer":"Abnormal condition that an animal possesses at birth  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1060-4; HSc18"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2715","question":"What is the term for an abnormal condition that an animal possesses at birth?","answer":"Congenital  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1060-4; HSc18"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"intermediate","number":"2716","question":"What is a genetic disease?","answer":"Disease that can be passed on to offspring (and may be the result of a genetic mutation)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1060-1; HSm505-9"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"sr bonus","number":"2717","question":"Name 3 genetic diseases in horses.","answer":"SCID (combined immunodeficiency), HYPP, HERDA, PSSM, GBED, OLWS (overo lethal white syndrome), malignant hyperthermia, hemophilia, JEB, aniridia (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:ES98-102; HIH1060; HSm105-3,5; HSm505"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2718","question":"Aniridia is a genetic disorder in which the iris of the eye is absent.  This occurs primarily in which horse breed?","answer":"Belgian  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm505-8; ES100"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2719","question":"CID or Combined Immunodeficiency is an inherited disease of which breed?","answer":"Arabian or part Arab (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1060-4,5; HIH1095-2; HIH1060-2,4; HSm505-5; ES99"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2720","question":"What term is used to describe the genetic disease characterized by the failure of the immune system to form?","answer":"Combined Immunodeficiency (CID) or Severe Combined Immunodeficiency (SCID) [FYI: CID is commonly seen in Arabians.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1060-4,5; HIH1095-2; HIH1060-2,4; HSm505-5; ES99"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2721","question":"What sensory deficit is often present in horses with the splashed white color pattern?","answer":"Deafness  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm510-5; ES50"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2722","question":"HERDA or HC is an inherited disorder that causes what?","answer":"Causes skin to be very stretchable, fragile, and/or vulnerable to trauma (accept any)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH675-1,2; HSm505-7"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2723","question":"Identify the following disease that primarily affects Quarter Horses:  superficial and deep layers of the skin separate resulting in \"stretchy\" skin that's easily damaged or torn.","answer":"HERDA (Hereditary Equine Regional Dermal Asthenia) or HC (Hyperelastosis Cutis) [accept any]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH675-1,2; HSm505-7"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2724","question":"Which Quarter Horse sire has been linked to the disorder HERDA?","answer":"Poco Bueno  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH675-2; HSm505-7"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2725","question":"This disease results in “stretchy” skin due to separation of the superficial and deep layers of the skin. What breed is affected by HERDA or HC?","answer":"Quarter Horse (FYI:  HERDA stands for Hereditary Regional Dermal Asthenia.  HC stands for Hyperelastosis Cutis.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH675-1,2; HSm505-7"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2726","question":"Which breed of horse carries the genetic disease HYPP?","answer":"Quarter Horse  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH725-3, 795-3, 1060-6, 1095-1; HSm430-6, 435-4, 505-6-8; ES98, 136"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2727","question":"HYPP or Hyperkalemic Periodic Paralysis is a genetic disease of Quarter Horses who are descendants of the stallion Impressive.  Name ONE way HYPP is diagnosed.","answer":"Genetic blood test; clinical signs and elevated blood potassium levels [FYI: There’s a 5-panel test that checks for the following genetic diseases—HYPP, PSSM, HERDA, GBED, and MH (malignant hyperthermia).]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1060-6; HSm505-6"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2728","question":"A horse with what genetic disease would benefit from a diet that is low in potassium?","answer":"HYPP or Hyperkalemic Periodic Paralysis (also accept PIPP or Potassium Induced Periodic Paralysis)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1060-6; FCH298; HSm430-6; HSm435-4; HSm505-6"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2729","question":"HYPP is found in which Quarter Horse line?","answer":"Impressive  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH795-3; HIH1095-1; HSm430-6; ES136; FCH297"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2730","question":"What causes foals with Overo Lethal White Syndrome to die?","answer":"Failure of nerves in the gastrointestinal tract to develop which causes colic (FYI: Condition is called ileocolonic aganglionosis.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1060-6,7; HIH1095-2; HSm505-6"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2731","question":"What genetic disease is associated with the frame overo pattern?","answer":"Lethal White Foal Syndrome or OLWS (Overo Lethal White Syndrome) [accept either]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1040-3; HIH1095-1; HSm505-6"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2732","question":"Which lethal genetic defect can result from mating two overo Paint horses?","answer":"Lethal White Foal Syndrome or OLWS (Overo Lethal White Syndrome) [accept either]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1060-6; HSm105-3; HSm505-6"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2733","question":"What do the initials OLWS refer to?","answer":"Overo Lethal White Syndrome  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH975-4, 1040-3, 1095-1; HSm505-6, 510-5; ES49, 98"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2734","question":"What does the abbreviation PSSM indicate?","answer":"Polysaccharide Storage Myopathy (FYI: PSSM is a genetic disease of horses such as Quarter Horses that can cause \"tying up\".)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH460-4; HSm435-4; HSm505-6-8; ES101"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2735","question":"2-part question:  If a mare is a carrier for an X-linked genetic disease, what percent of her male foals will be affected with the disease and what percent of her female foals will be carriers?","answer":"50% males will be affected and 50% of females will be carriers  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1060-3,6; HSm505-5; ES99"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2736","question":"Give ONE example of a sex-linked trait in horses.","answer":"Hemophilia  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1060-3,6; HSm505-5; ES99"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2737","question":"What sex-linked disease results in a deficiency of clotting factor VIII (8)?","answer":"Hemophilia (Hemophilia A)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1060-3,6; HSm505-5; ES99"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2738","question":"Are male or female horses primarily affected by genetic diseases that have an X-linked mode of inheritance?","answer":"Male horses  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1060-3,6; HSm505-5; ES99"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2739","question":"On what chromosome is the gene for hemophilia found?","answer":"X chromosome  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1060-3,6; HSm505-5; ES99"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2740","question":"Which chromosome carries the genes for most sex-linked traits?","answer":"X chromosome  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1060-3,6; HSm505-5; ES99"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2741","question":"Name the TWO types of cell division.","answer":"Mitosis and meiosis (pronounced my-TOE-sis and my-OH-sis)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm505-2; HIH980-3; ES88; HSc19"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2742","question":"Explain how mitosis differs from meiosis. (pronounced my-TOE-sis and my-OH-sis)","answer":"Mitosis is normal cell division where each daughter cell receives an identical copy of the original chromosome pairs; meiosis is sex cell division where each daughter cell only receives half of each chromosome pair (haploid number of chromosomes)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm505-2; HIH980-3; ES88; HSc19"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2743","question":"What is the term for sex cell division?","answer":"Meiosis (pronounced my-OH-sis)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm505-2; HIH980-3; ES88; HSc19"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2744","question":"What is the term for normal or somatic cell division?","answer":"Mitosis (pronounced my-TOE-sis)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm505-2; ES88; HSc19"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"sr bonus","number":"2745","question":"2-part question:  What is the difference between qualitative and quantitative genetic actions?","answer":"Qualitative genetic action—trait is influenced by 1 – 3 pairs of genes; quantitative genetic action—trait is influenced by a number of genes  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1020-1; HIH1080-2; HSm505-3"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"sr bonus","number":"2746","question":"In traits affected by qualitative gene action there are 3 primary types of gene action that affect the trait.  Name them.","answer":"Dominance, co-dominance, and partial dominance  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1020-1; HSm505-3"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2747","question":"In what type of gene action are several genes required to produce a trait?","answer":"Quantitative  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1020-1; HIH1080-2; HSm505-3"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2748","question":"2-part question:  What is a quantitative trait and give ONE example?","answer":"Trait influenced by many genes; examples are speed, cow sense, and  jumping ability (accept any)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1020-1; HIH1080-2; HSm505-3"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2749","question":"What does the term “quantitative gene action” mean?","answer":"Trait is controlled by several genes.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1020-3; HSm505-3"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"sr bonus","number":"2750","question":"Name 3 things, other than genetic makeup, that may affect a horse's potential.","answer":"Care, feeding, training, injuries, interaction with other horses (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1020-1; HIH1070-1; HSm505-1"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"sr bonus","number":"2751","question":"Name 3 things that should be considered when selecting breeding stock.","answer":"Conformation, breeding or pedigree, individual performance records, progeny records, disposition, size (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1090"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"intermediate","number":"2752","question":"Although a horse may have the genetic potential to be large, fast or intelligent, 30 – 50% of the trait is due to what?","answer":"Environmental factors (such as feed, care, training and injuries)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1070-1"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"intermediate","number":"2753","question":"Name TWO factors that determine how well a horse will do in a particular discipline such as horse racing.","answer":"Heredity; environment (nutrition, exercise, training, health) [accept any correct answers]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1020-1; HSm505-1"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2754","question":"What is gene mapping?","answer":"Determining and recording the identities and positions of genes  <br/> <br/>ref:ES85"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2755","question":"What is heritability estimate?","answer":"Percentage of the horse’s expressed trait that is due to genetics (probability of that trait being passed from one generation to the next)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1070-1; HSm505-4"},
    {"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2756","question":"Justin Morgan was the foundation sire for the Morgan breed. His ability to pass his breed type on to his offspring regardless of the type of mare he was bred to would be referred to by what genetics term?","answer":"Prepotent or prepotency (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET220"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"easy","number":"2757","question":"How can bathing your horse dull his coat?","answer":"Removes the skin's natural oils  <br/> <br/>ref:HH38; FCH179; PNW70"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"2758","question":"How can you remove caked mud and manure from the hoof wall?","answer":"Wash with water and use a stiff brush or use a hoof brush (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH37"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"2759","question":"Give TWO times you should groom a horse that you are exercising.","answer":"Both before and after the workout  <br/> <br/>ref:HH35"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"2760","question":"Ideally, how often should horses be groomed?","answer":"Daily  <br/> <br/>ref:HH35"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"2761","question":"What practice most helps the appearance of the horse's coat?","answer":"Frequent, thorough grooming  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH180"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"jr bonus","number":"2762","question":"When brushing a horse, what are the LAST 3 parts to be brushed?","answer":"Head, mane, and tail  <br/> <br/>ref:HH37"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"sr bonus","number":"2763","question":"Name 3 benefits of grooming your horse.","answer":"Improves appearance, cleans hair and skin, brings out natural oils in skin, prevents skin problems, looks for skin problems, massages muscles, increases circulation, removes dirt and external parasites, improves muscle condition  <br/> <br/>ref:HH35; PNW69"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"2764","question":"When using a body brush or dandy brush, in what direction should the hair be brushed?","answer":"In the direction of its natural lay (in the direction it grows)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH37"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"2765","question":"Give ONE way to avoid a dull, sun-bleached appearance to your horse's coat.","answer":"Keep him stabled during the sunniest part of the day or only turn him out to pasture in the early morning or late evening (FYI:  Sun bleaching is most dramatic on black, but it can occur on any color.  UV light causes hair to lose pigment.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH38; HSm110-4"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"2766","question":"Why is it recommended to groom a horse thoroughly before saddling?","answer":"Removes dirt or burrs that might cause sores; you may find new sores (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:PNW69"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"2767","question":"Why should you brush the horse's belly in the area of the saddle cinch?","answer":"To remove dirt that might chafe the horse or cause sores (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:PNW69"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"jr bonus","number":"2768","question":"Name 3 important steps in grooming a horse.","answer":"Use curry comb on non-bony parts of body, use stiff brush, use body brush, use face brush, comb mane and tail, clean feet, use grooming cloth, groom before and after riding, cool horse out after exercise  <br/> <br/>ref:HH36-38; PNW69"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"2769","question":"If you body clip your horse, how can you keep him warm in cold weather?","answer":"Blanket him or keep him in a stable (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH38"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"2770","question":"What does it mean to body clip a horse?","answer":"Clip the horse's body  <br/> <br/>ref:DET34; PNW73,74"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"jr bonus","number":"2771","question":"Name 3 areas of the Western stock horse that are usually clipped for a show.","answer":"Muzzle, under the chin, under the jaw, bridle path, ears, long hairs around the eyes, below the knees and hocks (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH39; PNW71"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"easy","number":"2772","question":"Give ONE reason why horse's legs should be clipped a couple of weeks before a show.","answer":"To avoid clipper lines or contrasting colors (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH39; PNW71"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"intermediate","number":"2773","question":"Give ONE reason why the hair around the fetlocks of horses is sometimes clipped.","answer":"To give the legs a neater or cleaner appearance; breed preference; owner preference; treatment or prevention of skin problems such as scratches  <br/> <br/>ref:HH30; PNW73,74"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"medium","number":"2774","question":"When clipping a horse during the winter, why is it advisable to leave an unclipped area for the saddle blanket?","answer":"To protect the horse's back (from abrasions)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH39"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"easy","number":"2775","question":"To obtain a neat look, which way should clippers be run, against the hair or with the natural lay?","answer":"With the natural lay  <br/> <br/>ref:HH30; PNW71"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"sr bonus","number":"2776","question":"Name 3 types of clips used in grooming horses.","answer":"Blanket clip, trace clip, body clip, hunter clip  <br/> <br/>ref:DET950; DET30; DET144-145; DET34; PNW73,74"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"hard","number":"2777","question":"When a horse has a blanket clip, which parts of the horse are NOT clipped?","answer":"Head, neck, and legs (FYI: With a blanket clip, only the blanket area is clipped.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET30; PNW73,74"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"hard","number":"2778","question":"Clipping along the belly, under the neck, and above the thigh is known as what type of body clip?","answer":"Trace clip  <br/> <br/>ref:DET950; PNW73,74"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"2779","question":"In reference to horses, what is docking?","answer":"Cutting the bones of the tail to shorten it  <br/> <br/>ref:HH40; DET83"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"2780","question":"What term is used for the cutting of the bones of the tail in order to shorten the tail?","answer":"Docking (docked)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH40; DET83"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"sr bonus","number":"2781","question":"Name 3 effects of hand rubbing your horse.","answer":"Brings out the bloom or shine, stimulates circulation, massages tired muscles, feels good to the horse, helps you bond with your horse (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH38"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"medium","number":"2782","question":"Describe how to pluck or pull a mane.","answer":"Begin on underside of mane with the longest hairs. Grasp a few strands of hair close to the roots and jerk sharply removing hair and roots.  <br/> <br/>ref:HH39; PNW74"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"easy","number":"2783","question":"What is meant by \"picking out\" a mane or tail?","answer":"Separating the hairs with your fingers to keep them from tangling  <br/> <br/>ref:HH38"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"2784","question":"When braiding a horse's mane and tail, how many sections should be worked with at one time?","answer":"3 (three) sections  <br/> <br/>ref:HH30; PNW75,76"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"2785","question":"How long an area is clipped for the bridle path?","answer":"1 ½  – 8  inches depending on the breed and style of riding (accept any number within this range) [also accept the length of the ear]  <br/> <br/>ref:DET39; HH39; PNW71,72"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"2786","question":"What is the name for the section of mane at the poll that's trimmed or clipped to allow space for a halter or bridle to rest?","answer":"Bridle path  <br/> <br/>ref:DET39; HH39; PNW71,72"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"2787","question":"In reference to grooming, what is a \"bridle path\"?","answer":"Clipped area behind the ears where the crownpiece of the bridle goes  <br/> <br/>ref:DET39; HH39; PNW71,72"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"medium","number":"2788","question":"Why do some gaited saddle horses have their bridle paths trimmed 6 – 7 inches down the neck?","answer":"To make the horse's neck look longer and finer through the throatlatch  <br/> <br/>ref:HH39; PNW71,72"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"medium","number":"2789","question":"What determines the style of the mane and tail of a horse that's being exhibited?","answer":"Breed of horse and/or what type of classes it’s being shown in  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-12; PNW72"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"medium","number":"2790","question":"How are the manes and tails of Arabians prepared for a show?","answer":"Washed and left full  <br/> <br/>ref:HH38"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"intermediate","number":"2791","question":"Describe TWO ways a draft horse may be decorated for a show.","answer":"Manes may be “rolled” (braided); manes may be left loose; tail may be braided, knotted, and or put in a bun; flowers or bows may be tied along the crest; undocked tails may be French-braided  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-13; HH44"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"medium","number":"2792","question":"How are Fjord’s manes usually clipped?","answer":"Cut into a crescent (to emphasize the well-muscled and crested neck)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-10,11"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"medium","number":"2793","question":"How are many saddle seat breeds decorated for show?","answer":"Ribbon braid in forelock and single mane braid  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm135-5"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"easy","number":"2794","question":"How long is a hogged mane?","answer":"3 (three) inches or less  <br/> <br/>ref:DET141; HH35"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"easy","number":"2795","question":"In reference to grooming, what is roached?","answer":"Mane shaved off or cut short  <br/> <br/>ref:DET235; HH35"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"easy","number":"2796","question":"In reference to grooming, what does the term \"hogged\" mean?","answer":"Mane that's cut short or shaved off  <br/> <br/>ref:DET141; HH35"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"easy","number":"2797","question":"In reference to grooming, what is a banged tail?","answer":"Hair cut straight off below the dock or bony part of the tail  <br/> <br/>ref:DET23; HH35; PNW74"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"medium","number":"2798","question":"How far down are un-docked tails of draft horses French braided for a show?","answer":"To the end of the tail bones  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-2; HH39; PNW76"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"medium","number":"2799","question":"How are the tails of Hackney Ponies groomed for Harness Pony classes versus Cob Tail classes?","answer":"Long tail in Harness Pony classes; cob tail (docked tail) in Cob Tail classes (FYI:  Pleasure Ponies may have docked or long tails.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm120-3"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"easy","number":"2800","question":"What do you call a tail that's been shortened or thinned by pulling?","answer":"Pulled tail  <br/> <br/>ref:HH35; PNW72,74"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"easy","number":"2801","question":"Although not used as much today as in the past, what is the preferred method by which you thin a horse's tail?","answer":"Pulling (FYI:  In the 60's and 70's, stock horses' tails were often pulled and shortened to the height of the hocks.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH35; PNW72,74"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"easy","number":"2802","question":"What is a rat-tailed horse?","answer":"Horse having little hair in its tail (can be seen in Appaloosas)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH7; ES51"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"easy","number":"2803","question":"When applying a wrap to a horse's tail, why is it important not to pull the wrap too tight?","answer":"You can cut off circulation to the tail  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1150-3; HSm220-4"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"intermediate","number":"2804","question":"What is the term that refers to hair that's clean and glossy, denoting a healthy appearance?","answer":"Bloom  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH382; HH35"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"medium","number":"2805","question":"In reference to horses, what is meant by the term \"bloom\"?","answer":"Glossy, healthy looking hair coat (luster or shine to coat)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH382; HH35"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"easy","number":"2806","question":"In reference to horses, give ONE meaning of the term \"curry\".","answer":"Rubber or metal grooming tool; to rub down or groom a horse  <br/> <br/>ref:DET75; HH38"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"2807","question":"What do you call a person who cleans and brushes horses?","answer":"Groom  <br/> <br/>ref:DET125; HH35"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"jr bonus","number":"2808","question":"Name 3 grooming tools and give their purposes.","answer":"Curry comb removes deep dirt, dandy or stiff brush removes dirt, body brush removes dust and brings out oils, face brush brushes the face, mane and tail comb combs the mane and tail, and hoof pick cleans the hooves.  <br/> <br/>ref:HH35-59; PNW69-75"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"2809","question":"Name 3 grooming tools.","answer":"Currycomb, dandy or stiff brush, body or soft brush, face brush, mane and tail comb, hoof pick, grooming cloth, sweat scraper, clippers (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH35-59; PNW69-75"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"2810","question":"Give ONE use of a grooming cloth.","answer":"Polish coat; dry off wet horse; wipe around eyes, nostrils, lips, dock, and sheath  <br/> <br/>ref:HH36,38; PNW70"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"sr bonus","number":"2811","question":"Name 3 uses of a grooming cloth.","answer":"Polish coat; dry off wet horse; wipe around eyes, nostrils, lips, dock, and sheath  <br/> <br/>ref:HH36,38; PNW70"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"2812","question":"What motion is most effective when using a currycomb?","answer":"Circular motion  <br/> <br/>ref:HH37; PNW70DET75; HH37; PNW70"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"2813","question":"What grooming tool is used in a circular motion to loosen hair and dirt?","answer":"Currycomb  <br/> <br/>ref:DET75; HH37; PNW70"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"2814","question":"How do you clean the currycomb when grooming?","answer":"Hit it on something hard or pull the hair out (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH37"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"2815","question":"In grooming a horse, where is the currycomb NEVER used?","answer":"Over the bony areas (head and lower legs)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH37; PNW70"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"easy","number":"2816","question":"What is a rubber currycomb used for?","answer":"To remove deep dirt, loose hair, saddle marks, or mud (accept any)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET75; HH37; PNW70"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"easy","number":"2817","question":"What is the only reason to use a metal currycomb?","answer":"To remove thick, dry mud or heavy, loose hair  <br/> <br/>ref:HH35"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"2818","question":"Why should you NOT use a currycomb on your horse's face or legs?","answer":"You might hurt him (FYI:  Skin is thin and there's less muscle to protect the horse from injury.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH35,37"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"2819","question":"What is the name for the soft brush with fine bristles that's used to give your horse a finishing touch?","answer":"Body brush, soft brush, or finishing brush (accept any)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET34; HH35,38; PNW70"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"2820","question":"Name ONE function of the body or soft brush.","answer":"Removes the last particles of dust; brings out natural oils  <br/> <br/>ref:DET34; HH35,38; PNW70"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"2821","question":"What type of brush is best for sensitive areas of the face and legs?","answer":"Soft brush (also accept face brush or body brush)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET34; HH35,38; PNW70"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"2822","question":"Give ONE name for the grooming tool that is a hard-bristled brush and is used to remove excess hair and loose dirt.","answer":"Dandy brush; stiff brush  <br/> <br/>ref:DET77; HH35-37"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"easy","number":"2823","question":"What type strokes will remove the most dirt when using a stiff or dandy brush?","answer":"Short, strong strokes with an outward motion away from the body  <br/> <br/>ref:DET77; HH35-37"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"easy","number":"2824","question":"2-part question:  What is a dandy brush and what is it used for?","answer":"Stiff brush; used to remove loose hair and dirt  <br/> <br/>ref:DET77; HH35-37"},
    {"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"2825","question":"What grooming aid is used to remove excess water after washing your horse?","answer":"Sweat scraper  <br/> <br/>ref:DET260; HH37,38; PNW70"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"2826","question":"Name ONE thing that can happen if a leg bandage is applied with too much tension.","answer":"Can cut off blood supply; can damage tissues (such as tendons)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1160-1,2"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"2827","question":"What is the key to applying a good bandage?","answer":"Practice  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1160-1"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2828","question":"Why should leg bandages be wrapped in a spiral fashion from front to back?","answer":"To decrease damage of tendons, nerves, and blood vessels (to decrease the risk of uneven tension on the back of the leg)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1160-2"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"2829","question":"What type scissors are best for cutting hair away from a wound?","answer":"Blunt end ones (bandage scissors)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-6"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2830","question":"Most medically indicated bandages have how many layers?","answer":"3 (three) layers  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1160-1"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"2831","question":"Name ONE material used for each of the 3 bandage layers.","answer":"Primary or contact layer—Telfa or non-stick pad, release pad, gauze pad; secondary layer—sheet cotton, roll cotton, quilted leg wraps; outer or tertiary layer—vet wrap, Elasticon  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1160-1"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"2832","question":"Why should you NOT use cotton or material with loose fibers to wrap a wound?","answer":"Sticks to wound  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-4; HIH1160-1"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2833","question":"Give ONE purpose of the secondary bandage layer.","answer":"Absorbs fluids from wound; provides padding  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1160-1"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"2834","question":"Give ONE purpose of the outer bandage layer.","answer":"Holds other layers in place; keeps other layers clean  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1160-1; HSm355-9"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2835","question":"Give ONE reason why you would use a COLD poultice on your horse.","answer":"Decreases inflammation, decreases swelling, decreases pain, decreases heat (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-6"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2836","question":"Give ONE reason why you would use a HOT poultice on your horse.","answer":"Increases blood supply to area, draws out infection, encourages abscess to open (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-6; HSm375-7"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"2837","question":"Give 3 uses for a poultice.","answer":"Increases blood supply to the area, draws out infection, encourages abscess to open, decreases inflammation, decreases swelling, decreases pain, decreases heat (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-6; HIH540-2"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"2838","question":"Name 3 general types of bandages.","answer":"Support, shipping, first aid (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1160-1"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"2839","question":"Give 3 purposes of bandages for horses.","answer":"Support; keep wound clean; protect from infection, dirt, or insects; protect from further trauma; absorb drainage; travel protection; immobilization; control bleeding; reduce swelling; keeps medication on wound (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1160-1; HIH440-4"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"2840","question":"Name ONE purpose of a pressure bandage.","answer":"Control bleeding; decrease swelling; used with antibiotic/steroid ointment to prevent proud flesh  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1160-1; HIH440-2,4"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2841","question":"What is the correct term for a thick, multi-layered bandage that includes wood or metal splints and is used to restrain and support an injured leg?","answer":"Robert Jones bandage  <br/> <br/>ref:DET235"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2842","question":"A method of assessing a horse's body condition by visually appraising or physically feeling fat cover in several areas is called what?","answer":"Body condition scoring  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH451-8"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"intermediate","number":"2843","question":"A horse's body fat can be estimated by using the BCS method of evaluation.  What do the initials BCS stand for?","answer":"Body condition scoring (FYI: BCS is determined by observing and feeling the fat cover over 6 body sites—neck, withers, back, tail head,  ribs at mid-barrel, and behind the shoulders at the fore-rib.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH790-1; HSm305-3; HSm405-2; HSm530-1"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"2844","question":"When determining body condition in the winter, it's easy to be misled by what?","answer":"Horse's winter coat or long hair (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH420-1"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"2845","question":"In reference to “Body Condition Score”, name 3 of the body sites that are evaluated.","answer":"Neck, withers, back, tail head, ribs at mid-barrel, and behind the shoulder the at fore-rib  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH790-1; HSm305-3; HSm405-2; HSm530-1"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"2846","question":"What is the ideal body condition score for most horses?","answer":"4 – 6 (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH790-1; HSm305-9"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2847","question":"Give the body condition score for this horse:  slight fat cover over the ribs, but the ribs are easily seen; hook bones appear rounded, but are visible; tail head is prominent; withers, shoulders, and neck are accentuated.","answer":"Body Condition Score of 3 (three)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-9; HIH425-3; HIH780-2"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2848","question":"Give the body condition score of this horse:  topline is level; ribs can be felt, but not seen.","answer":"Body Condition Score of 5 (five)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-9; HIH425-3; HIH780-2"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2849","question":"Give the body condition score for this horse:  prominent crease down the back; ribs are difficult to feel; fat around the tail head is soft; area behind the shoulder is filled; neck is thickened; fat is deposited along the withers and inner buttocks.","answer":"Body Condition Score of 8 (eight)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-9; HIH425-3; HIH780-2"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2850","question":"Name TWO things that would affect a horse’s body condition or degree of fat covering.","answer":"Diet, amount of exercise, pregnancy, lactation, weather changes, parasites, dental problems, overall health, feeding practices, availability of food (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH425-2; HSm305-3"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2851","question":"Racehorses and endurance horses are sometimes maintained at a BCS score of less than 5, yet they are healthy.  Why would you NOT want to maintain a highly competitive horse at a higher BCS score?","answer":"Horse would be carrying extra, unnecessary weight  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH755-1"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"2852","question":"A horse with a body condition score of 9 would be considered to be what?","answer":"Obese (very fat)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-3; HSm530-1"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2853","question":"How many POUNDS can an obese horse safely lose in one month?","answer":"50 pounds  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH790-3"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"2854","question":"Name ONE reason, other than being overfed, that horses or ponies might get fat.","answer":"High grain diet, unlimited pasture, lack of exercise, easy keepers, dominant horse in herd, Cushing's disease (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH790-1"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"2855","question":"Give 3 reasons, other than being overfed, that horses or ponies might get fat.","answer":"Lack of exercise, easy keepers, dominant horse in herd, hypothyroidism, Cushing's disease (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH790-1"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"novice","number":"2856","question":"Name ONE thing you can do to help your horse lose weight.","answer":"Increase exercise or decrease calories  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH790-1"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"2857","question":"Name 3 health problems that can be caused by overfeeding horses.","answer":"Weight gain, laminitis or founder, colic, infertility, hyperlipidemia, heat stress, respiratory problems (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc45"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2858","question":"How much time is generally required to get a starved horse back to normal body weight?","answer":"3 – 5 months (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH785-3"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"intermediate","number":"2859","question":"Name ONE cause of starvation in horses.","answer":"Unintentional neglect, intentional neglect, abandoned, ignorance of horse care, economic hardship of owner (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH785-1"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2860","question":"When a horse loses more than 50% of his body weight, what is the prognosis for recovery?","answer":"Very poor prognosis  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH785-2"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2861","question":"What does the term \"emaciated\" mean?","answer":"Extremely thin (Body Condition Score of less than 3)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET90; FCH338"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2862","question":"What is the best approach for rehabilitating a starved horse?","answer":"Feed small, frequent meals of high-quality alfalfa for the first 10 days, then increase hay amounts slowly to free choice.  Grain is not recommended until horse is near normal weight.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH785-3; HSm435-4"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"jr bonus","number":"2863","question":"Name 3 ways to determine a horse's weight.","answer":"Livestock scales, weight tape, visual estimation (guessing), body weight equation (FYI:  Body Weight Equation, height in inches x body length in inches, sum of those divided by 330 = body weight.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH775-1; HSm405-2"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"2864","question":"How is a tape used to estimate the weight of a horse?","answer":"Measure the horse's heart girth with a marked weight tape  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH775-1; HSm405-2"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"2865","question":"What is the MOST ACCURATE way to weigh your horse?","answer":"Scales  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH775-1"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"2866","question":"Give ONE reason why you should know your horse's weight.","answer":"So you know how much to feed your horse; so you know how much wormer to give your horse; so you know how much medicine to give your horse  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH710-2"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"2867","question":"What is the MOST COMMON way to estimate your horse's weight?","answer":"Weight tape (also accept visual estimation or guessing)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH775-1; HSm405-2"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2868","question":"In reference to animal health, what is biosecurity?","answer":"Keeping biological or living things from being infected from agents that can cause disease (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:ES193-195; HIH475-1; HSm205-6; PNW31"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"2869","question":"Name 3 ways horse owners can help prevent infectious diseases in horses.","answer":"Vaccinate, avoid sick animals, isolate sick animals, isolate new animals, keep barn clean, wash hands, disinfect boots, provide boot dip, disposable boots, clean trailer, disinfect trailer, don’t re-use needles, use fly/tick spray  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH475-1; ES170-180; HSc45,46"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"jr bonus","number":"2870","question":"Name 3 things you should do to keep your horse in year-round good health.","answer":"Feed properly, provide clean water, exercise it regularly, provide shelter, take care of its feet, vaccinate, deworm (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH120-2,3; HSc45,46"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"2871","question":"Name 5 things you should do to keep your horse in year-round good health.","answer":"Feed properly, provide clean water, exercise it regularly, provide shelter, take care of its feet, vaccinate, deworm (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH120-2,3; HSc45,46"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"2872","question":"Name 3 paths of physiological water loss from a horse’s body.","answer":"Urine, sweat, feces, and respiration  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH425-2; HSm305-2; FCH245"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"2873","question":"What is dehydration?","answer":"Condition of the body where more water is lost than is taken in (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET78"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"2874","question":"What is the term for the condition in which water is lost from the body faster than it's taken in?","answer":"Dehydration  <br/> <br/>ref:DET78"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"2875","question":"Under NORMAL conditions, what's the best way to replenish your horse's electrolytes?","answer":"Provide a salt or mineral block  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH860-3; HSm430-4"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"intermediate","number":"2876","question":"In which bodily fluid is the greatest amount of electrolytes lost?","answer":"Sweat  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH820-2; HSm430-4"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"2877","question":"Give ONE way to prevent dehydration in a horse.","answer":"Provide plenty of fresh clean water; encourage horse to drink; monitor how much horse is drinking; mask the taste of “strange” water; provide electrolytes (salt); soak food (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1150"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"2878","question":"Skin pliability is a test for what?","answer":"Dehydration  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-2; HIH425-2; FCH200"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"2879","question":"Measurements of ALL of the horse's vital signs are important in assessing the health of a horse.  Describe how the skin pliability or pinch test is used to check for dehydration.","answer":"Pull the skin back; if the skin quickly flaps back into place, the horse is not dehydrated.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-2; HIH950-6"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2880","question":"Give ONE other name for the medication referred to as “Ace”.","answer":"Acetylpromazine; acepromazine  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm370-6; HIH460-2; HIH640-1; DET2"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2881","question":"Give ONE reason why the drug Acepromazine may be used.","answer":"Tranquilizer (relieve anxiety); vasodilation (increase blood flow); laminitis (FYI:  Acepromazine is also called acetylpromazine.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm370-6; HIH460-2; HIH640-1; DET2"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"2882","question":"2-part question:  Name 3 types of injections and identify the location where they're given.","answer":"SubQ (subcutaneous)—under the skin; IM (intramuscular)—in the muscle; IV (intravenous)—into a vein; intradermal—into the skin; intra-articular—into a joint  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-7,8; HIH445-11; FCH405; FCH393,394; DET258; DET154,155"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2883","question":"What is the name for the syringe-like device used to give large pills to horses?","answer":"Balling gun  <br/> <br/>ref:DET22"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2884","question":"What is a bolus?","answer":"Rounded mass of food or medicine given orally (FYI:  A \"bolus\" of an IV medication can also be given.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET34"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2885","question":"What does the term \"drenching\" a horse mean?","answer":"Giving liquid medication to the horse by pouring it down its throat from a bottle  <br/> <br/>ref:DET85"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2886","question":"What is the term for a liquid introduced into the intestine by way of the anus?","answer":"Enema  <br/> <br/>ref:DET92"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2887","question":"Where is a subcutaneous shot administered?","answer":"Under the skin  <br/> <br/>ref:DET258; FCH405; HSm355-2"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2888","question":"How is a sublingual medication given?","answer":"Under the tongue  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-7; DET259"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2889","question":"What is the general term for a drug that causes the air passages of the lungs to widen?","answer":"Bronchodilator  <br/> <br/>ref:DET40"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2890","question":"Identify this medication:  used to treat severe asthma or anaphylactic reactions; causes contraction of the capillaries and arteries by stimulating the sympathetic nervous system; causes an increase in the heart rate.","answer":"Adrenalin or epinephrine (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET4"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2891","question":"What is immunotherapy?","answer":"Stimulating the immune system as a treatment for tumors or allergies  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH465-3; FCH292"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2892","question":"Give ONE purpose of a correct use of a steroid medication.","answer":"Control inflammation, suppress allergic reaction, heaves or COPD, hives  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm370-4; DET255"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2893","question":"What is the term for a chemical substance that inhibits or destroys bacteria or other microorganisms and is used primarily in the treatment of infectious diseases?","answer":"Antibiotic  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm370-1; FCH381; DET12"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2894","question":"An antibiotic is used to control what type of infections?","answer":"Bacterial infections (FYI: Antibiotics are also used to treat some protozoal infections; antibiotics do NOT treat viral infections.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm370-1; FCH381; DET12"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2895","question":"What is the difference between a broad spectrum and a narrow spectrum antibiotic?","answer":"Broad spectrum antibiotic is effective against a wide range of bacteria; narrow spectrum antibiotic is effective against only a few types or a single type of bacteria.  <br/> <br/>ref:DET40; DET187"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2897","question":"What type of drug increases the excretion of urine after administration?","answer":"Diuretic (an example is Lasix)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-6; FCH387"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2898","question":"What does the drug Lasix treat in racehorses?","answer":"Exercise Induced Pulmonary Hemorrhage (bleeders)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-6; HIH810-2"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2899","question":"What is the term for a liquid medication that is applied to the horse’s legs after exercise to prevent swelling and to reduce soreness?","answer":"Brace, liniment, or astringent (accept any)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET36; DET169; DET17"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2900","question":"What is an astringent?","answer":"Drug that causes constriction of tissues and/or decreases secretions (examples are tannic acid, alum, and zinc oxide)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET17"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"2901","question":"Name ONE thing an anti-inflammatory drug does.","answer":"Decreases inflammation, reduces pain, reduces swelling, and decreases fever (antipyretic) [FYI: Bute and Banamine are NSAID’s or non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs used in horses.]  <br/> <br/>ref:DET12; HIH440-4; HSm370-3"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2902","question":"What type of medications are Flunixin (floo-NIX-in) meglumine (MEG-glue-mean), Ketoprofen (kee-toe-PRO-fen), and Phenylbutazone (feen-ill-BUTE-ah-zone)?","answer":"NSAID's (non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH640-2; HIH435a-3; HSm370-3"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2903","question":"What is the expected effect of an antipyretic medication?","answer":"Fever reduction  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-6; DET13"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2904","question":"What is the COMMON name for the drug Phenylbutazone?","answer":"Bute  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm370-3; DET211"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2905","question":"What is the chemical name for the anti-inflammatory drug Bute?","answer":"Phenylbutazone  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm370-3; DET211"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2906","question":"Give TWO medical properties or uses for Dimethyl Sulfoxide or DMSO.","answer":"Anti-inflammatory; antibacterial; analgesic  <br/> <br/>ref:DET81; HIH640-2"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2907","question":"What is the correct term for the medication referred to as DMSO?","answer":"Dimethyl sulfoxide [FYI:  DMSO can be used orally, topically, or through an IV as an anti-inflammatory, antibacterial, or analgesic (pain killer).]  <br/> <br/>ref:DET81; HIH640-2"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2908","question":"What term describes a preparation that contains no medication and is administered in order to simulate treatment such as in a research study?","answer":"Placebo  <br/> <br/>ref:DET221"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2909","question":"There are no specific treatments for some poisonings, but horses are usually given activated charcoal and a saline laxative by nasogastric tube.  What is the reason for giving these medications?","answer":"To prevent further absorption of the toxin (FYI: Activated charcoal binds with the toxin and the saline laxative speeds up the passage of toxins through the digestive tract.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET3; FCH339"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2910","question":"What is the name of the medication that's used to counteract a poison?","answer":"Antidote  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-6; DET12"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2911","question":"What is the use of a prophylactic medication?","answer":"To prevent illness or disease  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm365-6; DET221"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2912","question":"A soluble-fiber, bulk agent such as psyllium would be administered to a horse with diarrhea that is a result of what type of ingestion?","answer":"Sand ingestion (FYI:  Sand Clear is a brand name of psyllium for horses.  Metamucil is a brand name of psyllium for humans.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH435a-5; FCH293,294"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2913","question":"What is silver nitrate?","answer":"Medication used to stop bleeding (also used as an antiseptic)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-2"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2914","question":"What substance can be applied topically to control bleeding?","answer":"Silver nitrate  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-2"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2915","question":"What term describes an accumulation of abnormally large amounts of fluid in the horse's body tissue?","answer":"Edema (FYI: Stocking up is edema of the lower legs.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH620-1; FCH405; DET89"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2916","question":"What does the slang term \"stocking up\" mean?","answer":"Swelling of the lower legs of the horse (FYI: When horses stand still for long periods, fluid can accumulate below the knees and hocks.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH620-1; FCH405; DET257"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"2917","question":"Name 3 symptoms common to horses who have survived an electric shock.","answer":"Dazed, unconscious, abnormal breathing, abnormal pulse, dilated or constricted eyes, convulsions, paralysis (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-4,5"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"2918","question":"Name ONE cause of electric shock in horses.","answer":"Lightning, contact with overhead wires, contact with wire fencing, chewing through wires, contact with other sources of electric current (especially if the ground is wet)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-4,5"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2919","question":"What is the correct medical term used to describe the humane or painless death of an animal through the action of a person, usually a veterinarian?","answer":"Euthanasia  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH470-1; DET100"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"2920","question":"What are the only 3 acceptable methods of euthanasia for a horse?","answer":"Overdose of barbiturates, gunshot, and captive bolt  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH470-1"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2921","question":"2-part question:  Give ONE advantage and ONE disadvantage of using a barbiturate overdose for euthanasia.","answer":"Advantages—speed of action, minimal discomfort for horse; disadvantages—requires IV, so horse must be restrained (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH470-1"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"2922","question":"How often should horses be ridden or turned out to exercise?","answer":"At least once daily  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH420-3"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"2923","question":"Name 3 problems that can occur when working an out of condition horse.","answer":"Laminitis or founder, heat exhaustion, exhaustion, heart attack, stroke, lameness, tying up, muscle soreness (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH410-1"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2924","question":"Give TWO ways to increase exercise for horses with chronic lameness.","answer":"Turn out into large paddock or pasture, provide companion, locate feed and water sources far apart, hand walk, swimming (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH790-2"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"2925","question":"Give ONE result of NOT exercising your horse.","answer":"Weight gain, lameness, stiffness, colic, stable vices, nervousness, loss of cardiovascular fitness, loss of muscle tone, stocking up (swelling) [accept any correct answer]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH420-3"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"2926","question":"Name 3 things that can happen if horses are confined and can't exercise.","answer":"Weight gain, lameness, stiffness, colic, stable vices, nervousness, loss of cardiovascular fitness, loss of muscle tone, stocking up (swelling) [accept any correct answers]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH420-3; HSc46"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"2927","question":"All eye injuries should be treated as what?","answer":"Emergencies; call the vet!  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-6"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"2928","question":"2-part question:  All corneal ulcers should be considered emergencies.  Describe the difference between a simple and a complicated corneal ulcer and give the main treatments for each.","answer":"Simple is superficial and is not infected; treat with topical antibiotics and pain medications; complicated is deep and is infected; treat with antibiotics and pain medications plus it may require surgery.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH465-3"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2929","question":"What is a corneal ulcer?","answer":"Ulcer of the cornea (also accept abrasion or tear) [FYI: Corneal ulcers are caused by trauma and may lead to infection and blindness.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH465-3"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2930","question":"Why are ointments less effective in warm weather?","answer":"Heat will cause the ointment to melt (and to escape from wound or bandage).  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-5"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"2931","question":"Give ONE reason for keeping your horse's first aid supplies in a small waterproof box.","answer":"Supplies stay clean and dry; box can be taken with the horse when it travels from home.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-5"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"jr bonus","number":"2932","question":"Name 3 items found in an equine first aid kit. (ACCEPT ANY CORRECT ANSWERS.)","answer":"Thermometer, stethoscope, vet info, gloves, weight tape, medicines—Bute, Banamine, syringes, needles; wound care—scissors, antiseptic cleanser, antibiotic ointment, bandage materials (non-stick, cotton, vet wrap, Elasticon, duct tape, etc.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-5,6; HIH1150-2; HSm220-3; HSm365-4,5"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"2933","question":"Name 5 items found in an equine first aid kit. (ACCEPT ANY CORRECT ANSWERS.)","answer":"Thermometer, stethoscope, vet info, gloves, weight tape, medicines—Bute, Banamine, syringes, needles; wound care—scissors, antiseptic cleanser, antibiotic ointment, bandage materials (non-stick, cotton, vet wrap, Elasticon, duct tape, etc.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-5,6; HIH1150-2; HSm220-3; HSm365-4,5"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2934","question":"What is the term for removal of foreign material and damaged or dead tissue from a wound?","answer":"Debridement (pronounced de-BRIDE-ment or de-BREED-ment)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm375-2; DET78"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2935","question":"What is the vet doing if he's lavaging your horse's wound? (pronounced luh-VAH-zching)","answer":"Washing the wound with a stream of fluid  <br/> <br/>ref:DET165"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2936","question":"What is the name of the aluminum or wooden device worn around the neck of a horse to prevent it from chewing at sores, blankets, or bandages?","answer":"Neck cradle or cradle (Do NOT accept cribbing collar.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1160-3; DET72"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2937","question":"What is the difference between a simple and a compound or open fracture?","answer":"Compound fracture or open fracture breaks the skin (FYI:  With a comminuted fracture, the bone is broken in several places.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET63"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2938","question":"Fractured limbs in horses are a medical emergency and, unfortunately, still have a poor prognosis.  Name ONE way to immobilize a suspected fracture below the knees and hocks until the vet arrives.","answer":"Wrap a thick layer of towels around the leg and secure with tape; reinforce with 4 to 6-inch PVC pipe; reinforce with fiberglass casting tape  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-6; HIH1160-2"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"2939","question":"Hyperthermia, heat exhaustion, heat cramps, and heat stroke are caused by over-heating in horses.  Name 3 causes of heat-related illnesses in horses.","answer":"Hot weather, high humidity, poor stable ventilation, prolonged exposure to direct sunlight, overwork, transportation, obesity, genetic (malignant hyperthermia) [accept any correct answers]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH410-1,2; HSm305-6"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"jr bonus","number":"2940","question":"Name 3 things you can do for an overheated horse.","answer":"Call vet, spray horse with a hose, sponge horse down, put horse in the shade, use fans, put ice on the horse, give horse a few swallows of water (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH410-1,2"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"novice","number":"2941","question":"Name ONE way to cool out a horse besides walking it.","answer":"Spray horse with a hose, sponge horse down, put horse in the shade, use fans, put ice on the horse, give horse a few swallows of water (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH410-1,2"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"2942","question":"Horses with heat-related illnesses need replacement of body salts or electrolytes.  Name ONE way to replace a horse’s electrolytes.","answer":"Free choice; adding electrolyte mixes to grain; IV fluids [FYI:  Electrolyte Mix Recipe:  3 parts lite salt (potassium chloride) and 1 part limestone; give 2 ounces daily (after consulting your vet)]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH410-2; HSm305-6"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"2943","question":"Name ONE important difference between heat stroke and heat exhaustion.","answer":"Heat stroke is more serious; horses with heat exhaustion respond to cooling efforts; horse with heat exhaustion should not be depressed; horse with heat exhaustion should be willing to drink; horse with heat exhaustion should have good gut sounds  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH410-1; HSm305-6"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2944","question":"How soon should a horse with heat exhaustion respond to cooling efforts?","answer":"10 – 15 minutes (FYI: Horse will continue to appear very tired, but it should be willing to eat and drink.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH410-1"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2945","question":"The heat stress index is the sum of the ambient temperature and the percent relative humidity.  At what heat stress index level does the efficiency of the cooling mechanism BEGIN to decrease?","answer":"130 or higher (FYI:  At 150, the cooling efficiency is greatly reduced.  180 or higher could cause death.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH410-1; HSm305-6"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"2946","question":"Heat stroke or sunstroke is much more serious than heat exhaustion.  At first the horse may refuse to work, become depressed, not drink, and have poor gut sounds, but symptoms can rapidly progress.  Name 3 other signs of heat stroke in horses.","answer":"Weakness, incoordination (ataxia), high temperatures that don’t respond to cooling efforts, fast heart rate (tachycardia), fast respiratory rate (tachypnea), hot dry skin (anhidrosis), delirium, convulsions, collapse  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH410-1"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"2947","question":"What is the MAIN way a horse cools itself?","answer":"By sweating (FYI:  Sweating is evaporative cooling.  Radiation, conduction, convection, and respiratory evaporative cooling are other means of heat dissipation.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH860-1"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"intermediate","number":"2948","question":"What mammal, other than the horse, cools itself primarily by sweating?","answer":"Man  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH860-1"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"2949","question":"Name 4 signs of inflammation.","answer":"Heat, pain, swelling, and redness  <br/> <br/>ref:DET151"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2950","question":"What part of the horse is inflamed with desmitis?","answer":"Ligament  <br/> <br/>ref:DET79; FCH387"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2951","question":"What is an inflammation of the endometrium called? (pronounced in-doe-MEE-tree-um)","answer":"Endometritis (pronounced in-doe-mee-TRITE-is)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET92; FCH388"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2952","question":"What is the general term for inflammation of a tendon?","answer":"Tendonitis  <br/> <br/>ref:DET265; FCH406"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"2953","question":"Besides vital signs, name 3 things to consider when evaluating the health of a horse.","answer":"Body condition score, weight, skin and coat condition, skin pliability (check for dehydration), behavior (alert, content, “acting right\"), feeding habits, hoof condition, movement, lameness, flexibility, soreness, body fluids (urine, feces)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH425-1; HSm305-1"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2954","question":"What is an adhesion?","answer":"When structures that normally move freely from each other stick together  <br/> <br/>ref:DET4; HIH435a-3"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2955","question":"What is anhidrosis?","answer":"Inability to sweat (FYI:  Horses with heat stroke may develop anhidrosis causing their skin to be hot and dry.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET11; FCH211"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"2956","question":"Why is it necessary to know the normal parameters for your horse's vital signs and behavior?","answer":"So you'll know when something's wrong  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH425-1; HSm305-1"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2957","question":"What term refers to a horse that's fallen or is lying down too close to a wall or fence to get up without assistance?","answer":"Cast  <br/> <br/>ref:DET51"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2958","question":"What is the term for the lodgment of a foreign particle, such as a blood clot or air bubble, in the circulatory system?","answer":"Embolism (FYI:  A thrombus is a blood clot that remains attached to the point of formation in a blood vessel and causes obstruction.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc56; DET91"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2959","question":"What is necrosis?","answer":"Death of cells or body tissue while the animal is still alive  <br/> <br/>ref:DET189; FCH397"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2960","question":"What is an excessive reaction of the skin to sunlight called?","answer":"Photosensitivity (FYI: Crusting and peeling occur in areas of white or little hair. Photosensitivity is caused by the ingestion of toxins or by liver failure.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm355-4; FCH399"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2961","question":"What is a pre-purchase exam?","answer":"Exam made by a veterinarian to determine the overall soundness and health of a horse prior to sale.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH130-1; HIH210-5; HSm145-2"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2962","question":"What is the term meaning the prospect of recovery from an injury or disease?","answer":"Prognosis  <br/> <br/>ref:DET221; FCH400"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2963","question":"What is a spasm?","answer":"Sudden involuntary contractions of a muscle or group of muscles  <br/> <br/>ref:DET251; FCH394"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2964","question":"What is the term for the involuntary spasmodic muscle contractions that produce heat in cold weather?","answer":"Shivering (FYI:  Shivering can also occur with fright, stress, excitement, fever, or illness.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET243; HSm360-1"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2965","question":"Name ONE advantage of using swimming as a means for exercising a horse recovering from an injury.","answer":"Helps horse maintain cardiovascular fitness; doesn’t put unwanted stress on legs.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH851-9,10"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"intermediate","number":"2966","question":"What is the term for the condition of a horse that is healthy, active, and vigorous?","answer":"Thrifty  <br/> <br/>ref:HH9; DET267"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"novice","number":"2967","question":"Who is trained and skilled in the treatment of diseases and injuries of animals?","answer":"Veterinarian  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc45-46"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2968","question":"You do the math…Approximately 75 percent of a horse's total bodyweight is made up of water.  If your horse weighs 1000 pounds, how much of this total weight is water?","answer":"750 pounds (1000 x 0.75 = 750)  <br/> <br/>ref:ES115"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"2969","question":"Shock is a life-threatening emergency that results in altered vital signs, decreased level of consciousness, and collapse.  Name 3 causes of shock.","answer":"Trauma, blood loss, anaphylaxis (severe allergy), heatstroke, toxins, drugs, infections, heart failure, neurogenic, head injury (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH403; DET244; HIH650-1"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"2970","question":"When an animal goes into “shock”, blood is pulled away from the peripheral circulation to the internal vital organs.  Name 3 changes in vital signs that might indicate shock.","answer":"Weak, rapid pulse; decreased blood pressure (hypotension); shallow, rapid breathing; slowed breathing; capillary refill time of over 3 seconds; pale mucous membranes (poor blood perfusion); blue mucous membranes (lack of oxygen); cool, clammy skin  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH403; DET244; HSm305-2; ES163"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2971","question":"What is the term used for a diagnosis based on signs or symptoms?","answer":"Clinical diagnosis  <br/> <br/>ref:DET59; HIH645-1"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2972","question":"What is an ECG or electrocardiogram?","answer":"Tracing of the electrical activity of the heart  <br/> <br/>ref:DET90"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"2973","question":"In reference to horse health, what is the purpose of a flexion test?","answer":"To determine the flexibility of a joint (FYI:  With the flexion test, a joint is flexed for 30 – 60 seconds, then the horse is jogged to check for lameness.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET110; HSm145-3"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2974","question":"In reference to medical tests, what is the hematocrit?","answer":"Percent of red blood cells in the blood  <br/> <br/>ref:DET137; FCH392"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2975","question":"What is the term for the passage of a tube into either the trachea or the esophagus?","answer":"Intubation (pronounced in-tube-AY-shun) [FYI:  Nasogastric intubation or the insertion of a NG or “stomach tube” is used in the diagnosis and treatment of colic.]  <br/> <br/>ref:DET155; HIH435a-4"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2976","question":"What is the name of the procedure where anesthetic injections are given to numb certain areas to help diagnose the location of lameness?","answer":"Nerve block (FYI:  Nerve blocks are also used as local anesthesia for surgeries.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET32; DET189; HIH540-3; HSm365-1"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2977","question":"One important part of a pre-ride check is to check for back or loin soreness?  How is this evaluated?","answer":"Use thumb and forefinger on each side of withers to apply gentle pressure; move fingers down the back; if the horse is sore; it will drop its back away from the pressure in that area.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH851-3,4"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2978","question":"What TWO internal body parts are associated with the condition called \"thumps\"?","answer":"Diaphragm and heart (FYI: Thumps is synchronous diaphragmatic flutter. It's often caused by electrolyte imbalances and may be seen in horses in endurance races.)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH213"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2979","question":"Give ONE name for the movements of the flank in sync with the heartbeat that often indicate an electrolyte imbalance.","answer":"Thumps or synchronous diaphragmatic flutter  <br/> <br/>ref:DET268; HIH430-6; HSm430-16"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2980","question":"Why should horses be vaccinated about one month prior to going to a new equine facility?","answer":"So they have time to produce an adequate amount of antibodies prior to exposure (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH445-1"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2981","question":"What is a vaccination or vaccine?","answer":"Substance that artificially stimulates immunity (the production of antibodies) in an animal (without giving the animal the disease)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET281; HIH445-1; HSm365-9"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"2982","question":"Who should you consult to develop an immunization plan to prevent infectious diseases in your horse?","answer":"Vet  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc46"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2983","question":"The American Veterinary Medical Association (AVMA) divides vaccinations into TWO categories.  What are they?","answer":"Core and risk-based vaccines  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH445-2; HSm305-7,8; HSm365-9"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2984","question":"SPECIFICALLY, what is the name of the immune-stimulating product that's made from killed or live attenuated BACTERIA?","answer":"Bacterin (FYI: Bacterin is a type of vaccine.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET20; HSc47"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2985","question":"What is a bacterin vaccine?","answer":"Type of vaccine made of killed bacteria (or live attenuated bacteria)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET20; HSc47"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"intermediate","number":"2986","question":"Medically speaking, what is a \"booster\"?","answer":"Second or subsequent dose of a vaccine  <br/> <br/>ref:DET35; HSm305-8"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2987","question":"According to the AVMA, what is the term for vaccinations that protect from diseases that are endemic to a region, that pose a potential public health significance, are required by law, are highly infectious, and/or pose a risk of severe disease?","answer":"Core vaccines (FYI:  Tetanus, West Nile, EEE, WEE, and Rabies are core vaccines.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH445-2; HSm305-7; HSm365-9"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"2988","question":"The AAEP and AVMA divide vaccinations into two groups, core and risk based.  Name 3 diseases in the AVMA’s \"core\" group.","answer":"Tetanus, West Nile, EEE (Eastern Equine Encephalomyelitis), WEE (Western Equine Encephalomyelitis), rabies  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH445-2; HSm305-7; HSm365-9,10"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2989","question":"What is the difference between Tetanus antitoxin and Tetanus toxoid vaccine?","answer":"Tetanus antitoxin gives immediate, short-term protection. (It’s given when the immunization status of the animal is unknown or is not up to date). Tetanus toxoid gives long term protection. (Tetanus toxoid should be given annually.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH445-3; HSm340-2"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2990","question":"What is the correct name of the vaccine used in horses for prolonged protection against Tetanus?","answer":"Tetanus toxoid (FYI: Tetanus antitoxin only provides temporary protection.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH445-3; HSm340-2; DET266"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"2991","question":"At least how many doses of a vaccine are initially needed to get an adequate immune response?","answer":"2 (two) doses  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-8"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2992","question":"By what age should Tetanus, WEE, EEE, and West Nile vaccines be given to a foal from an UNVACCINATED mare?","answer":"By 1 – 4 months (accept any number within this range) (FYI:  Foals from unvaccinated mares get a 3-dose series with 1st doses at 1 – 4 months and then at 4-week intervals.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH445-7; HSm340-2,3"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"2993","question":"By what age should Tetanus, WEE, EEE, and West Nile vaccines be given to a foal from a previously vaccinated mare?","answer":"By 4 – 6 months in foals from vaccinated mares (1st dose at 4 – 6 months, 2nd dose at 10 – 12 months, then annually)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH445-7; HSm340-2,3"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"2994","question":"Name 3 vaccinations that a foal should receive by 6 months of age.","answer":"Core vaccines—tetanus, EEE, WEE, West Nile, rabies; risk-based vaccines—rhinopneumonitis, influenza; [FYI:  May get other risk-based vaccines—botulism, Potomac Horse Fever, strangles, Equine Viral Arteritis (given to males 6 – 12 months of age)]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH445-7,16; HSm340-3"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"2995","question":"Pregnant mares should be vaccinated for tetanus, WEE, EEE, West Nile, and influenza how long before foaling in order to build antibodies that'll be transferred to the foal?","answer":"4 – 6 weeks before foaling (FYI:  EHV-1 should be given at 5, 7, and 9 months of gestation to prevent abortions.  Rotavirus vaccines can be given at 8 months gestation with 2nd and 3rd doses given at 4-week intervals.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH445-6,14,15; HSm340-2"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2996","question":"Foals born to dams who were not vaccinated for tetanus and have insufficient absorption of colostral antibodies, can be given what at birth to prevent tetanus?","answer":"Tetanus antitoxin (FYI:  Three doses of tetanus toxoid vaccination is recommended starting at 1 – 4 months, given at 4-week intervals.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH645-2; HSm340-3"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"novice","number":"2997","question":"How often should horses be immunized for Tetanus, Eastern, and Western Encephalomyelitis?","answer":"Once a year  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH445-2,5,6; HIH415-2"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"2998","question":"Name 3 diseases whose vaccinations are considered in the AVMA's “risk-based” group.","answer":"Rhinopneumonitis (Equine Herpes Virus), influenza, strangles, botulism, equine viral arteritis (EVA), Potomac Horse Fever, rotaviral diarrhea, anthrax, leptospirosis  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH445-2; HSm305-7,8; HSm365-11-16"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"2999","question":"Why is the anthrax vaccine not readily available in the US?","answer":"Anthrax is not very common (has only occurred in certain areas of the country)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH445-13"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3000","question":"Who developed an anthrax vaccine in 1881?","answer":"Louis Pasteur  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH445-13"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3001","question":"Why should other injectable vaccines NOT be given at the same time as the INTRANASAL strangles vaccine?","answer":"Live bacteria in the intranasal strangles vaccine can cause abscesses at the injection sites.  (FYI:  The IM or intramuscular strangles vaccine often causes local irritation.  BOTH vaccine types can cause purpura hemorrhagica.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH445-12; HSm365-16"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"jr bonus","number":"3002","question":"Name 3 immunizations that may be given to horses annually.","answer":"Tetanus, West Nile, EEE (Easter Equine Encephalomyelitis), WEE (Western Equine Encephalomyelitis), rabies, EVA (Equine Viral Arteritis), anthrax, botulism; rhino (EHV), flu, strangles, PHF (Potomac Horse Fever) can be given annually to semi-annually  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH445-4,6,11, 14,15"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"3003","question":"Name 5 immunizations that may be given to horses annually.","answer":"Tetanus, West Nile, EEE (Easter Equine Encephalomyelitis), WEE (Western Equine Encephalomyelitis), rabies, EVA (Equine Viral Arteritis), anthrax, botulism; rhino (EHV), flu, strangles, PHF (Potomac Horse Fever) can be given annually to semi-annually  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH445-4,6,11, 14,15"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3004","question":"In reference to horse health, what does TPR stand for?","answer":"Temperature, pulse, and respiration  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH425-1"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"jr bonus","number":"3005","question":"Vital signs are very important parts of the health assessment of the horse.  Name 3 vital signs of the horse.","answer":"Temperature, pulse, respiration, capillary refill time, mucous membrane color, skin pliability  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH425-1,2; HSm305-1"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"3006","question":"Vital signs are very important parts of the health assessment of the horse.  Name 5 vital signs of the horse.","answer":"Temperature, pulse, respiration, capillary refill time, mucous membrane color, skin pliability  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH425-1,2; HSm305-1"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3007","question":"Name ONE condition that a CRT or capillary refill time of longer than 3 seconds may indicate.","answer":"Dehydration, shock, poor blood perfusion  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH425-1,2; HSm305-2"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3008","question":"How do you test capillary refill time?","answer":"Press your thumb on the horse's gums for a few seconds and then remove pressure; gum should return to a normal pink color within 1 – 2 seconds.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH425-1,2; HSm305-2"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3009","question":"What is the term for a respiratory rate that's higher than the heart rate?","answer":"Inversion  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH425-1; HSm305-1"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3010","question":"Inversion means the respiratory rate is higher than the heart rate.  Why is this significant?","answer":"Inversion can indicate a serious condition that needs immediate attention.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH425-1; HSm305-1"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"3011","question":"Name 3 things you’d check when examining the mucous membranes of a horse.","answer":"Color, moistness, capillary refill time, odor  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH425-1,2; HSm305-1"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"3012","question":"Mucous membranes are evaluated as one of the vital signs of the horse.  Name 4 places on the horse’s body that mucous membranes can be found.","answer":"Inner surface of eyelids, inside nostrils, inner surface of lips, gums, inner surface of vulva, inner surface of rectum  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-1; HIH425-1; DET183"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"3013","question":"Name ONE medical condition associated with each of the following mucous membrane colors—pale, blue, yellow.","answer":"Pale mucous membranes can mean anemia or shock; blue mucous membranes (cyanotic) means deficiency of oxygen; yellow mucous membranes is a sign of jaundice from liver disease. (FYI:  Cyanide poisoning can cause “cherry red” mucous membranes.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-1"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3014","question":"Examining the mucous membranes is an important way to check if your horse is healthy.  Name ONE normal appearance of the horse’s gums or mucous membranes.","answer":"Pink, moist, bright  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH425-1; HSm305-1"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3015","question":"Name ONE area on the horse that the DIGITAL pulse can be palpated.","answer":"Back side of the lower leg above the fetlock, over the fetlock, or down the pastern (FYI:  The digital pulses of the medial and lateral digital arteries are normally hard to feel, but they’re “bounding” with laminitis and a hoof abscess.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-1; ES163; CAHA62"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"3016","question":"Name 3 places horse’s pulses are USUALLY palpated or felt using the fingers.","answer":"Under the jaw (facial artery), below the eye (transverse facial artery), on the hind leg in the groove on the cannon (lateral dorsal metatarsal artery), digital arteries  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA62; ES160"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3017","question":"Name ONE thing that can cause an elevated heart rate in a horse.","answer":"Exercise, fever, illness (infections, colic), pain (tying up), stress, fear, excitement, outside temperature, humidity, wind, precipitation, time of day, age, sex, medications, toxins (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-1; HIH790-2,830-2,460-2,410-1,370; PNW26,27,28,55,56,79"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"jr bonus","number":"3018","question":"Name 3 factors that affect the horse's heart rate.","answer":"Exercise, fever, illness (infections, colic), pain (tying up), stress, fear, excitement, outside temperature, humidity, wind, precipitation, time of day, age, sex, medications, toxins (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-1; HIH790-2,830-2,460-2,410-1,370; PNW26,27,28,55,56,79"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"3019","question":"Name 5 factors that affect the horse's heart rate.","answer":"Exercise, fever, illness (infections, colic), pain (tying up), stress, fear, excitement, outside temperature, humidity, wind, precipitation, time of day, age, sex, medications, toxins (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-1; HIH790-2,830-2,460-2,410-1,370; PNW26,27,28,55,56,79"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3020","question":"How high can a horse’s heart rate be during a prolonged gallop?","answer":"200 – 250 beats per minute (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH851-4; HSm380-4"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3021","question":"What is the normal heart rate of an ADULT horse at rest?","answer":"35 beats per minute (accept any number between 28 – 45 beats per minute)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-1; HSm350-2; HSm380-4; HIH850-4; HIH851-3; ES155; CAHA62; DET223"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3022","question":"What is the normal heart rate for a FOAL during the first week of life?","answer":"80 beats per minute (accept any number between 60 – 120 beats per minute depending on the age of the foal)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm535-2; HIH975-1; ES155"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3023","question":"What is the normal respiration rate for an ADULT horse?","answer":"10 breaths per minute (accept any number between 8 – 16 breaths per minute)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-1; HIH425-1; HIH851-3; ES155"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3024","question":"What is the normal respiratory rate of a FOAL?","answer":"30 breaths per minute (accept any number between 20 – 40 breaths per minute)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm535-2; HIH975-1; ES155"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"3025","question":"Name 3 factors that can cause temperature variations in the individual horse.","answer":"Age, sex, time of day, ambient temperature, humidity, wind, precipitation, exercise, illness, disease, level of activity, stress, poor ventilation, prolonged exposure to direct sunlight, overwork, transport, obesity (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-1; HIH410-1; HIH425-1"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3026","question":"What is the normal temperature of an ADULT horse?","answer":"101 degrees (accept any number between 99 – 101.5 degrees)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-1; HIH425-1; HIH440-6; ES155"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3027","question":"What is the normal temperature for a NEWBORN FOAL?","answer":"101 degrees (accept any number between 98 – 102 degrees)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm535-2; HIH975-1"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3028","question":"With what instrument is the temperature of a horse taken?","answer":"Thermometer  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-6; ES156"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3029","question":"What does the prefix “carcino” mean?","answer":"Cancer (FYI:  A carcinoma is a cancerous tumor. An adenocarcinoma is a cancerous tumor of glandular tissue.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm310-3"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3030","question":"What does the suffix “emia” describe?","answer":"A blood condition (FYI:  Anemia literally means without or lacking blood, but it’s used medically to describe a condition of low red blood cell counts.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm310-4"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3031","question":"2-part question:  What do the prefixes “erythro” and “leuko” mean?","answer":"Red; white (FYI:  An erythrocyte is a red blood cell and a leukocyte is a white blood cell.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm310-5"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3032","question":"2-part question:  What do the prefixes “hypo” and “hyper” mean?","answer":"Hypo means under or deficient; hyper means above or excessive. (accept any reasonable wording) [FYI:  Hypothyroidism is too little thyroid hormones and hyperthyroidism is too much thyroid hormones.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm310-5"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3033","question":"What does the suffix “itis” mean?","answer":"Inflammation (FYI:  Tendonitis is inflammation of a tendon.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm310-4"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3034","question":"What does the suffix “oma” mean?","answer":"Tumor (FYI:  A lipoma is a fatty tumor.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm310-4"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"3035","question":"3-part question:  Describe what the prefixes “peri”, “inter”, and “intra” mean.","answer":"\"Peri\" means around, \"inter\" means between, and \"intra\" means within.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm310-4"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"3036","question":"Name 3 common conditions or management practices that can result in injury to the horse.","answer":"Barns, stalls, fences, or gates either too small, not designed properly, or in poor repair; improper building materials; uncapped steel posts; sharp edges on waterers, etc. (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-6"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"jr bonus","number":"3037","question":"Name 3 common causes of horse wounds.","answer":"Kicks, bites, falls, colliding with objects, trauma, lacerations from fencing (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-1; HSm365-3"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3038","question":"What is the term for a localized collection of pus in the body tissue which is often accompanied by swelling and inflammation?","answer":"Abscess  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm355-4; FCH380; DET1"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3039","question":"What is the FIRST step in treating an abscess?","answer":"Open the abscess so it can drain  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH540a; HSm230-8"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"3040","question":"Name 3 types of closed wounds.","answer":"Contusion, hematoma, sprain, torn muscle, torn ligament, torn tendon, torn cartilage (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-4"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"intermediate","number":"3041","question":"What type of wound results from blunt force trauma and causes bleeding, bruising, and swelling without breaking the skin?","answer":"Contusion  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-4; DET68"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"intermediate","number":"3042","question":"A contusion is an area of injured tissue where the skin has not been broken.  Name ONE treatment for a contusion.","answer":"Ice packs or cold hosing, compression or leg wrap, rest; later may apply heat to encourage absorption of excess fluid  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-4"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3043","question":"2-part question:  What is a hematoma and what causes it?","answer":"Abnormal collection of blood in body tissues; caused by trauma or by blood vessel injury  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-4; DET137"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3044","question":"Your horse has been kicked by another horse and has a contusion.  The trauma is sufficient to break blood vessels, resulting in an abnormal collection of blood in the body tissue.  What is this called?","answer":"Hematoma  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-4"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3045","question":"What is the difference between a closed wound and an open wound?","answer":"Skin is intact with a closed wound; skin is broken with an open wound.  (FYI:  Examples of closed wounds are contusions and bruises.  Examples of open wounds are lacerations and abrasions.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-2,4"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"3046","question":"Name 3 tissues of the horse that can be damaged in open wounds.","answer":"Skin, muscle, nerves, blood vessels, tendons, bones, internal organs  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH410-1"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"3047","question":"Name 4 types of open wounds.","answer":"Incisions, lacerations, punctures, abrasions, penetrating wounds, avulsions  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-1; HSm365-3"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"jr bonus","number":"3048","question":"Name 3 types of open wounds.","answer":"Incisions, lacerations, punctures, abrasions, penetrating wounds, avulsions  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-1; HSm365-3"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"intermediate","number":"3049","question":"What term describes the type of wound caused by a rope burn or by poorly fitted tack?","answer":"Abrasion (FYI: Abrasions are scrapes.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-2; HSm365-3"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3050","question":"What is the SLANG term for an open sore that forms just behind a horse’s elbow?","answer":"Girth gall (also accept abrasion or saddle sore)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET117"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"intermediate","number":"3051","question":"What is an abrasion?","answer":"Scrape (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-2; HSm365-3; DET1"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3052","question":"Galls are sores caused by tack such as girths, saddles, or harnesses.  Name ONE result if galls are left untreated.","answer":"They may cause open sores, infections, or scarring which results in white spots on the coat  <br/> <br/>ref:DET117"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3053","question":"What is the best way to control bleeding of a leg wound?","answer":"Apply pressure (or apply a pressure bandage)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-2; HSm365-3"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3054","question":"Which is more serious, cutting an artery or a vein?","answer":"Artery  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-2; HSm365-3"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3055","question":"If blood is spurting from a wound, is an artery or vein cut?","answer":"Artery  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-2; HSm365-3"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3056","question":"Your horse has been injured and is bleeding.  How would you know if an artery was cut?","answer":"Bright red blood would be spurting from the wound  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-2; HSm355-9"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"jr bonus","number":"3057","question":"An open wound is a wound where the skin has been broken.  Name 3 steps in treating a SIMPLE open wound in your horse.","answer":"Call vet if needed; CONTROL BLEEDING; hose wound; clip hairs around wound if possible; clean wound with mild antiseptic; bandage wound; debride wound (by vet); suture (by vet) [accept any correct answers]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm355-9; HIH440-2"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3058","question":"What does hemorrhaging mean?","answer":"Uncontrolled bleeding  <br/> <br/>ref:DET138"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3059","question":"What is the best way to INITIALLY clean a large wound that's contaminated with dirt?","answer":"Hose it with water  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-2"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3060","question":"Give ONE reason why the hair around a wound should be clipped.","answer":"So you can get a better look at the wound; so hair doesn't get into the wound; so the wound is easier to clean; so the wound is easier to treat  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-2"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3061","question":"After hosing a wound, what should you do next if the wound is not bleeding heavily?","answer":"Clean the wound with a mild antiseptic  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-2"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3062","question":"Name TWO benefits of hosing a leg wound with cold water.","answer":"Cleans wound, decreases swelling, decreases pain, controls bleeding  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-2,4"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3063","question":"In reference to a wound, what is meant by the term \"golden period\"?","answer":"Elapsed time from injury to closure (after which, suturing a wound would do little good)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-3; HSm355-9"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3064","question":"You are the veterinarian on call and are examining a horse that sustained a laceration to the front lower leg sometime in the past 12 hours.  There is no active bleeding from the wound.  What would be the main reason to NOT suture the wound?","answer":"Suturing this long after the injury may increase the risk of infection.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-3; HSm355-9"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"intermediate","number":"3065","question":"What is the term for an open wound that is usually man-made and that has clean, straight edges?","answer":"Incised wound or incision (accept either) [FYI:  An incision is usually a cut made by a surgeon's scalpel, but it can be a wound caused by a knife or piece of glass.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-1; HSm365-3; DET150"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"intermediate","number":"3066","question":"In reference to wounds, what is an incision?","answer":"An open wound or cut with clean, straight edges (FYI:  An incision is usually a cut made by a surgeon's scalpel, but it can be a wound caused by a knife or piece of glass.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-1; HSm365-3; DET150"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"intermediate","number":"3067","question":"What is a laceration?","answer":"Jagged tear in the skin (wound with torn, irregular edges)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-1; HSm365-3; DET163"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"intermediate","number":"3068","question":"Which type of open wound has torn and irregular edges?","answer":"Laceration  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-1; HSm365-3; DET163"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"intermediate","number":"3069","question":"What SPECIFIC type of open wound is often caused by barbed wire?","answer":"Laceration (FYI:  Lacerations are cuts with jagged edges; incisions are cuts with straight edges.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-1; HSm365-3; DET163"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3070","question":"2-part question:  What is a penetrating wound and how should it be treated?","answer":"Wound that penetrates a body cavity or organ; treat as an EMERGENCY—call the vet and cover the wound with sterile gauze.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-1,2; HSm365-3"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3071","question":"What is a puncture wound?","answer":"Deep wound that has a small skin opening (accept any reasonable explanation)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-1; HSm365-3; DET223"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3072","question":"Name ONE serious complication of puncture wounds.","answer":"Infections (such as tetanus); damage to vital structures  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-1; HSm365-3; HSm340-1"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"intermediate","number":"3073","question":"Why must drainage be established and encouraged with simple puncture wounds?","answer":"So the wound can heal properly (FYI:  Puncture wounds should heal from the inside out.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-1; HIH455-3"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3074","question":"What type of wound would a nail cause?","answer":"Puncture wound  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-1; HSm365-3; DET223"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3075","question":"Name ONE way to keep a puncture wound open while it's healing.","answer":"Soak in warm water and Epsom salts; use a poultice  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-1; HIH455-3"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3076","question":"Horses with puncture wounds should receive what vaccination if it’s been 6 months or more since their last shot?","answer":"Tetanus shot (FYI:  If a horse hasn’t been vaccinated or if its vaccination status is unknown, then it should receive BOTH Tetanus toxoid and Tetanus antitoxin.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-1; HSm365-3"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3077","question":"What is proud flesh?","answer":"Excess granulation tissue (FYI:  The best treatment is surgical removal or debridement of proud flesh.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-3,4; HSm355-11; DET222"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"3078","question":"Name 3 risk factors for the development of proud flesh.","answer":"Lower leg injuries (where there’s little muscle), injuries in areas where there’s a lot of movement, injuries around joints, infected tissues, wounds left open to heal, limited intact healthy skin to cover the wound  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-3,4; HSm355-11"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3079","question":"Name ONE common complication in the healing of lower leg wounds.","answer":"Proud flesh; infection (FYI: Proud flesh is excess granulation tissue.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH440-3,4; HSm355-11"},
    {"category":"History","level":"sr bonus","number":"3080","question":"Name 3 parts to the scientific classification of animals.  Hint:  The pneumonic is King Phillip Cried “Oh, For Goodness Sakes”.","answer":"Kingdom, Phylum, Class, Order, Family, Genus, Species  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm140-1,2; ES15"},
    {"category":"History","level":"easy","number":"3081","question":"Warm blooded animals that give milk and have hair fall into what zoological CLASS?","answer":"Mammalia (mammals) [FYI:  Mammals are warm-blooded vertebrates that have hair or fur, usually give birth to live young, and produce milk to nourish their young.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm140-2; ES15"},
    {"category":"History","level":"hard","number":"3082","question":"In the zoological classification, what FAMILY includes the horse?","answer":"Equidae  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm140-2; ES15"},
    {"category":"History","level":"medium","number":"3083","question":"What GENUS includes horses, zebras, and asses?","answer":"Equus (pronounced EK-wuss)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm140-2; ES15; DET99"},
    {"category":"History","level":"intermediate","number":"3084","question":"In the zoological classification, to what KINGDOM does the horse belong?","answer":"Animalia (animals)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm140-1; ES15"},
    {"category":"History","level":"hard","number":"3085","question":"In the zoological classification, to what ORDER does the horse belong?","answer":"Perissodactyla (FYI:  Perissodactyla contains non-ruminant, odd-toed ungulates (hooved animals).  Cows, etc. are in the order Artiodactyla which are ruminant, even-toed ungulates.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm140-2; ES15"},
    {"category":"History","level":"hard","number":"3086","question":"In the zoological classification, to what PHYLUM does the horse belong?","answer":"Chordata (FYI: Members have a notochord which is a flexible rod-shaped cord composed of cartilage-like material.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm140-1; ES15"},
    {"category":"History","level":"hard","number":"3087","question":"In the zoological classification, to what SUBPHYLUM does the horse belong?","answer":"Vertebrates (FYI:  Vertebrates possess a backbone and are in the phylum Chordata.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm140-1; ES15"},
    {"category":"History","level":"medium","number":"3088","question":"What is the GENUS and SPECIES of horse?","answer":"Equus caballus (EK-wuss cah-BALL-us)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm140-2; ES15"},
    {"category":"History","level":"medium","number":"3089","question":"Horses were domesticated in Western Europe no later than what year?","answer":"1000 BC  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm130-4"},
    {"category":"History","level":"easy","number":"3090","question":"Name ONE continent where horses were first domesticated.","answer":"Asia; Europe  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm130-4,8"},
    {"category":"History","level":"intermediate","number":"3091","question":"Although the precise date of domestication of the horse remains unknown, what serves as the first record of man's dependence on the horse?  These records date back to the most ancient of times.","answer":"Cave paintings  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm130-4"},
    {"category":"History","level":"easy","number":"3092","question":"What proof do we have of what ancient horses were like?","answer":"Fossils  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm140-1 pictures"},
    {"category":"History","level":"jr bonus","number":"3093","question":"Name 3 stages of evolution of the horse.","answer":"Eohippus, Mesohippus, Miohippus, Parahippus, Merychippus, Pliohippus, Plessipus, and Equus  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm140-2-4; ES9"},
    {"category":"History","level":"sr bonus","number":"3094","question":"Name 5 stages of evolution of the horse.","answer":"Eohippus, Mesohippus, Miohippus, Parahippus, Merychippus, Pliohippus, Plessipus, and Equus  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm140-2-4; ES9"},
    {"category":"History","level":"easy","number":"3095","question":"How tall was Eohippus?","answer":"12 inches (accept any answer from 10 inches to 20 inches) [FYI: Eohippus or “dawn horse” had 4 toes on the front feet and 3 toes on the back feet.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm140-2; ES9; Hsc4"},
    {"category":"History","level":"easy","number":"3096","question":"2-part question:  How many toes did Eohippus have on his front feet and how many toes did he have on his back feet?","answer":"4 toes on the front feet; 3 toes on the back feet  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm140-2; ES9; Hsc4"},
    {"category":"History","level":"easy","number":"3097","question":"What does Eohippus mean?","answer":"Dawn horse  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm140-2; HSc4"},
    {"category":"History","level":"easy","number":"3098","question":"What was the original ancestor of the modern horse?","answer":"Eohippus  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm140-2; HSc4"},
    {"category":"History","level":"medium","number":"3099","question":"What type of environment was Eohippus most suited for?","answer":"Forested environment (may also accept swampy environment)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm140-2; HSc4"},
    {"category":"History","level":"easy","number":"3100","question":"What was the final stage of the development of the horse?","answer":"Equus  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm140-4; ES10; HSc4"},
    {"category":"History","level":"easy","number":"3101","question":"How many toes did Merychippus have?","answer":"3 (three) on each foot (FYI: Only the middle toe touched the ground.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm140-3; ES9"},
    {"category":"History","level":"easy","number":"3102","question":"How tall was Merychippus?","answer":"Size of a Shetland Pony, 10 hands, or 40 inches (accept any)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm140-3; ES9"},
    {"category":"History","level":"easy","number":"3103","question":"How tall was Mesohippus?","answer":"24 inches (FYI: Mesohippus or \"middle horse\" had 3 toes on the front feet and 3 toes on the back feet.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm140-2; HSc4"},
    {"category":"History","level":"easy","number":"3104","question":"How many toes did Mesohippus have?","answer":"3 (three) on each foot (FYI: Middle toe was the largest.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm140-2; ES9"},
    {"category":"History","level":"easy","number":"3105","question":"What is the second stage in the horse's evolution?","answer":"Mesohippus  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm140-2; HSc4"},
    {"category":"History","level":"easy","number":"3106","question":"What does Mesohippus mean?","answer":"Middle horse  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc5"},
    {"category":"History","level":"easy","number":"3107","question":"Which toe of Mesohippus was largest?","answer":"Middle toe  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm140-2; ES9; HSc4"},
    {"category":"History","level":"intermediate","number":"3108","question":"Describe the difference between the front legs of Mesohippus and Merychippus.","answer":"On Mesohippus all 3 toes touched the ground; on Merychippus only the middle toe touched the ground.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm140-2; ES9"},
    {"category":"History","level":"hard","number":"3109","question":"Name TWO horse ancestors that lived between Mesohippus and Merychippus","answer":"Miohippus and Parahippus  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm140-3"},
    {"category":"History","level":"easy","number":"3110","question":"Which horse ancestor was the first to have only one toe on each foot?","answer":"Pliohippus  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm140-3; ES9"},
    {"category":"History","level":"easy","number":"3111","question":"How tall was Pliohippus?","answer":"Size of a pony or 12 hands (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm130-3; ES9"},
    {"category":"History","level":"medium","number":"3112","question":"2-part question:  When did horses return to North America and who brought them?","answer":"16th century (1500’s); Spaniards  <br/> <br/>ref:HsC5; HSm130-6"},
    {"category":"History","level":"easy","number":"3113","question":"Geologists suggest our modern horse began his history how long ago?","answer":"58 million years ago (accept any number between 55 – 60 million)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc4; ES5"},
    {"category":"History","level":"medium","number":"3114","question":"Which individual is credited with bringing the first spotted horses to North America?","answer":"Cortez  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH163B-1"},
    {"category":"History","level":"easy","number":"3115","question":"When Equus died out in North America, how did some of the population survive?","answer":"Crossed a land bridge between North America and Asia (between Alaska and Russia)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm130-8; ES7; ES4,5"},
    {"category":"History","level":"sr bonus","number":"3116","question":"Give 3 reasons that are thought to be the cause of the horse's extinction in North and South America during the Pleistocene epoch.","answer":"Disease, depletion of food sources, insects, early human intervention, sudden climate change, parasites, failure to adapt to environment, used as a source of food for humans (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm140-4"},
    {"category":"History","level":"hard","number":"3117","question":"Name ONE important event in the history of the horse that occurred during the Pleistocene epoch.","answer":"Equus, the final stage of the horse, developed; horses became extinct in North America; Equus crossed the land bridge to Europe and Asia.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm130-8"},
    {"category":"History","level":"medium","number":"3118","question":"During what time period did Equus migrate over the land bridges to Asia?","answer":"Ice Age (FYI: about 1 million years ago)  <br/> <br/>ref:HsC4; HSm125-1"},
    {"category":"History","level":"medium","number":"3119","question":"What was the significance of the Bering Strait in the evolution of horses?","answer":"It's the area where the horse's ancestors crossed the land bridge to migrate to Asia and Europe.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm130-8; ES7; HSc5"},
    {"category":"History","level":"easy","number":"3120","question":"On what continent did Equus originate?","answer":"North America (FYI:  First horse ancestors developed on what is now the Great Plains of the United States.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc4; ES5"},
    {"category":"History","level":"sr bonus","number":"3121","question":"Name 3 other animals that became extinct from North America about the same time as the horse (during the Pleistocene epoch).","answer":"Rhinoceros, saber-toothed tiger, mastodon, camel, elephant  <br/> <br/>ref:ES8"},
    {"category":"History","level":"easy","number":"3122","question":"How did horses return to North America during the 1500's?","answer":"Spanish explorers  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc5; HSm130-6; ES10,14"},
    {"category":"History","level":"easy","number":"3123","question":"What animal has played a significant role in warfare since ancient times?","answer":"Horse  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc4; HSm125-1"},
    {"category":"History","level":"easy","number":"3124","question":"Name ONE of the horse's greatest contributions to human history.","answer":"Use in war, transportation, draft animal, pack animal, food source, pleasure, recreation, sports, showing, rodeo, agriculture (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc4; HSm125-1"},
    {"category":"History","level":"jr bonus","number":"3125","question":"Name 3 ways horses have been used throughout history.","answer":"Use in war, transportation, draft animal, pack animal, food source, pleasure, recreation, sports, showing, rodeo, agriculture (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc4; HSm125-1"},
    {"category":"History","level":"sr bonus","number":"3126","question":"Name 4 ways horses have been used throughout history.","answer":"Use in war, transportation, draft animal, pack animal, food source, pleasure, recreation, sports, showing, rodeo, agriculture (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc4; HSm125-1"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3127","question":"Name 3 desirable characteristics of a horse's hoof.","answer":"Hard wall; no rings; pliable coronet; no heat; pulses same in both feet—not bounding; pliable, intact frog; no foul odor; no discharge; thick, firm sole; uniform thickness of white line; no discoloration of white line; no corns or bruises  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-2"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3128","question":"What is the foundation of a horse?","answer":"His feet  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH505-1"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3129","question":"Name 3 things a horse's foot was designed to do.","answer":"Support weight, resist wear, absorb shock, provide traction, conduct moisture, assist in pumping blood, replenish itself  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH505-1; HSm230-1; HSc48"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"jr bonus","number":"3130","question":"Name 3 parts of the horse's foot.","answer":"Wall, white line, sole, frog, apex of frog, cleft or sulcus of frog, bars, collateral grooves, sulci, commissures of frog, toe, quarter, heel, heel bulbs, buttress of heels, periople, seat of corn (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH525-1; HSm230-1; HSc48"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3131","question":"Name 5 parts of the horse's foot.","answer":"Wall, white line, sole, frog, apex of frog, cleft or sulcus of frog, bars, collateral grooves, sulci, commissures of frog, toe, quarter, heel, heel bulbs, buttress of heels, periople, seat of corn (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH525-1; HSm230-1; HSc48"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3132","question":"What is the name for the portions of the hoof wall that are turned inward at the heels and run parallel to the sides of the frog?","answer":"Bars  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH525-1; HH48; DET24; CAHA24"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3133","question":"Name 3 parts of the hoof which furnish nutrition to the hoof.","answer":"Perioplic corium, coronary corium, laminar corium, sole corium, frog corium  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA25"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3134","question":"The digital cushion fills the area between the frog and what tendon?","answer":"Deep digital flexor tendon (also accept deep flexor tendon)  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA27"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3135","question":"What is the fibro-elastic, fatty cushion in the foot that acts as a shock absorber?","answer":"Digital or plantar cushion (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH505-4; HH48; DET81"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3136","question":"What is the PRIMARY purpose of the digital cushion?","answer":"Shock absorption (FYI:  The secondary purpose of the digital cushion is to assist in blood circulation.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH505-4; HH48; DET81"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3137","question":"Name TWO functions of the digital cushion.","answer":"Shock absorption; helps with circulation of blood  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH505-4; HH48; DET81"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3138","question":"What is the shape of the digital cushion?","answer":"Wedge-shaped  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH505-4"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3139","question":"What term describes the point of the frog towards the toe?","answer":"Apex of the frog (also accept point of the frog)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH525-1; DET13; CAHA24; HH48"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3140","question":"What is the name for the soft, spongy, wedge-shaped part of the horse’s foot?","answer":"Frog  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH525-1; HSm230-1; DET115; HH48"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3141","question":"What part of a horse's foot provides traction and absorbs shock?","answer":"Frog  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH525-1; HSm230-1; DET115; HH48"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3142","question":"What is the average hoof growth rate per month?","answer":"3/8 inch (accept any number within the range of ¼ – ½ inch or 0.5 – 1 cm)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH505-6; HSm230-1; CAHA25; HH47"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3143","question":"How long does it take the hoof to grow out from the coronet to the ground at the toe?","answer":"9 – 12 months (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH505-6 Figure 6"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3144","question":"Which grows FASTER, the front hooves or the back hooves?","answer":"Front hooves  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH505-6"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3145","question":"Horses' hooves grow at different rates of speed.  Which hooves grow SLOWER?","answer":"Hind hooves  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH505-6"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3146","question":"Name 3 things that affect hoof growth.","answer":"Temperature, age, front vs. hind hooves, exercise, nutrition, genetics, heart rate, moisture, massage of the coronary band, irritation or injury to sensitive structures, individual differences (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH505-6; HSm230-1"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3147","question":"What part of the horse's foot grows the FASTEST?","answer":"Toe  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH505-6"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3148","question":"Horse's hooves grow faster in what GENERAL temperature?","answer":"Warm temperature  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH505-6"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3149","question":"What is the soft, fleshy part of a horse's heel called?","answer":"Bulb  <br/> <br/>ref:DET42; HSm230-1; CAHA24; HH48"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3150","question":"What structure transfers the horse's weight from the bony structure to the hoof wall?","answer":"Laminae  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH505-1; HSm230-1"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3151","question":"What is the term for the tiny, folded, accordion-like, interlocking projections that connect the coffin bone to the hoof wall?","answer":"Laminae (FYI:  There are sensitive and insensitive laminae.  Sensitive laminae contain nerves and blood vessels.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH455-1; HSm230-1; DET163"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3152","question":"What part of the horse's foot contains the GREATEST amount of moisture?","answer":"Frog  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH505-7"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3153","question":"What in the horse's feet helps to maintain their flexibility or elasticity?","answer":"Moisture  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH505-7"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3154","question":"What part of the horse's foot contains the LEAST amount of moisture?","answer":"Wall  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH505-7"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3155","question":"What is the moisture content of the following parts of the hoof:  wall, sole, and frog?","answer":"Wall—25%; sole—33%; frog—50%  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH505-7"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3156","question":"What is nature's hoof conditioner?","answer":"Water  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH505-7"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3157","question":"Hoof moisture has been shown to have a direct effect on hoof quality.  Where does the moisture come from that helps maintain hooves’ flexibility?","answer":"Water within the body or foot; water in the environment (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH505-6"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3158","question":"What is the varnish-like layer of the hoof called?","answer":"Periople  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH505-7; DET208; CAHA24"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3159","question":"Specifically, what part of the foot produces the periople?","answer":"Perioplic corium (pronounced pair-ee-OH-plic CORE-ee-um)  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA25"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3160","question":"Describe the difference between the sensitive and insensitive structures of the hoof.","answer":"Sensitive areas contain nerves and blood vessels; insensitive areas do NOT contain nerves and blood vessels.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH505-1,2"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3161","question":"Name TWO differences in the shape of the front feet and the hind feet.","answer":"Front feet are rounder and are naturally flat; hind feet are narrower, more pointed, and are naturally concave.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH535-3; HSm230-4; CAHA24"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3162","question":"What is the diameter of an average adult light horse's foot?","answer":"4 – 6 inches (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-4"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3163","question":"What is the primary function of the sole?","answer":"Protection (of the coffin bone)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH505-2; HSm230-1"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3164","question":"What part of the foot covers the large area between the white line, frog, and bars?","answer":"Sole  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH505-1; HSm230-1; DET250; CAHA24; HH48"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3165","question":"What part of the hoof should NOT bear weight?","answer":"Sole  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm230-1; HIH525-1"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3166","question":"Give ONE name for the two grooves that separate the sole from the frog.","answer":"Collateral grooves, commissures, sulci  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH525-1; HSm230-1; DET62,259; HH48"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3167","question":"2-part question:  What part of the foot is most important to clean properly? Give ONE reason why this area is important to clean.","answer":"Deep depressions between the bar and the frog (commissures, sulci, or collateral grooves); it's the area most likely to have rocks, dirt, and manure; it's the area where thrush is most likely to start.  <br/> <br/>ref:HH47; HSm375-1; HIH540-1"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3168","question":"What is the function of the commissure in the hoof?","answer":"Gives elasticity to the foot (FYI:  Commissures, collateral grooves, or sulci are the deep depressions between the frog and the bars.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET62"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3169","question":"Which area of the wall of a horse's hoof is the thickest?","answer":"Toe  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH505-4"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3170","question":"Why is the hoof wall harder at the toe than at the quarters?","answer":"Toe is further from the coronary band and is therefore more keratinized.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH505-4"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3171","question":"Where is the GREATEST point of wear on a horse's hoof?","answer":"Toe or breakover point (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH505-4"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3172","question":"What happens when the large venous plexuses within the hoof are compressed?","answer":"Blood is pumped back up the leg.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH505-5"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3173","question":"What part of the normal, ideal hoof supports the primary weight of the horse?","answer":"Wall  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH505-4; HSm230-1"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3174","question":"What is the term for the hard, outside part of the hoof?","answer":"Wall  <br/> <br/>ref:DET287; HIH505-1; HSm230-1"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3175","question":"Where is the white line located?","answer":"Between the wall and the sole  <br/> <br/>ref:DET293; CAHA24; HIH525-1; HSm230-1; HH48"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3176","question":"What part of the foot separates the wall and the sole?","answer":"White line  <br/> <br/>ref:DET293; CAHA24; HIH525-1; HSm230-1; HH48"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3177","question":"Timeline…You are a farrier and are demonstrating how to remove a shoe and trim the hoof.  What is the correct order to use the following 5 farrier tools when accomplishing this task:  nippers, hoof knife, clinch cutter, rasp, pull offs?","answer":"Clinch cutter, pull offs, hoof knife, nippers, rasp  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH530; HIH535; HSm230-2-4; HH47-48"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3178","question":"Name 5 basic tools used in trimming or shoeing horses.","answer":"Hoof pick, nippers, rasp, hoof knife, rounding hammer, driving hammer, clincher, clinch cutter, pull offs (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH530; HIH535; HSm230-2-4; HH47-48"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"jr bonus","number":"3179","question":"Name 3 basic tools used in trimming or shoeing horses.","answer":"Hoof pick, nippers, rasp, hoof knife, rounding hammer, driving hammer, clincher, clinch cutter, pull offs (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH530; HIH535; HSm230-2-4; HH47-48"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3180","question":"What is the \"farrier's workbench\"?","answer":"Anvil  <br/> <br/>ref:DET13; HIH530-3; HSm230-3"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"novice","number":"3181","question":"Give ONE purpose of a horseshoer's leather apron.","answer":"Protects the shoer's legs from cuts, nails, or tools; protects against heat when working at the forge; provides barrier between horse and farrier for dirt and moisture; holds small tools  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH530-1; HSm230-2; DET14"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3182","question":"The part of the horseshoe nail that's bent over after being nailed through the hoof is called what?","answer":"Clinch  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm230-7; HIH530-3"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3183","question":"Why should the clinches be cut or straightened before pulling off the shoe?","answer":"To prevent tearing or chipping the hoof wall  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH535-2"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3184","question":"What are the TWO main parts of a clinch cutter?","answer":"Blade and point  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH530-1; HSm230-2"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3185","question":"Which farrier tool is used to cut and/or raise clinches?","answer":"Clinch cutter  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH530-1; HSm230-2"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3186","question":"What is the name of the tool that farriers use to bend over the end of a horseshoe nail?","answer":"Clincher or clinching tong (can also use a clinch block and a driving hammer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH530-3; HSm230-3"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3187","question":"A clinch block can be used to turn the head of the nail to start the clinch.  If your horse objects to this procedure, what other tool could be used to turn the clinch?","answer":"Clinchers or clinching tongs  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH530-3; HSm230-3"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3188","question":"Identify the 3 general types of clinchers or clinching tongs.","answer":"Saddle horse, gooseneck, and draft horse  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH530-3; HSm230-3"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3190","question":"Which farrier's hammer is heavier, rounding or driving?","answer":"Rounding hammer (FYI: A rounding hammer weighs 2 – 2½ pounds; a driving hammer weighs less than a pound.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH530-2; HSm230-3,4"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3191","question":"2-part question:  What are the TWO basic types of hammers used by farriers and how are they used?","answer":"Rounding hammer is used for making and shaping shoes; driving hammer is used for driving nails and finishing clinches. (FYI:  Claws of the driving hammer can be used for wringing off the old nails.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH530-2,4; HSm230-3"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3192","question":"Give ONE purpose of the farrier's driving hammer.","answer":"Driving nails or finishing clinches (FYI:  Claws of the driving hammer can be used for wringing off the old nails.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH530-2; HSm230-3"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3193","question":"What type of farrier's hammer is used for making and shaping shoes?","answer":"Rounding hammer or turning hammer (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH530-4; HSm230-3"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3194","question":"What farrier tool is used for cutting hot metal?","answer":"Hardy  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm230-3,4; DET130"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3195","question":"In reference to farrier tools, what is a hardy?","answer":"Tool used by farrier to cut hot metal  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm230-3,4; DET130"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3196","question":"What piece of equipment is used by a farrier to determine the angle of the hoof?","answer":"Hoof gauge  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH530-2; HSm230-2; DET142"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3197","question":"Give ONE purpose of a hoof gauge.","answer":"Measure the hoof angle; measure the toe length  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH530-2; HSm230-2; DET142"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3198","question":"What does the farrier remove from the hoof when trimming the hoof with a hoof knife?","answer":"Excess dead tissue from the horse’s frog and sole  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH530-2; HSm230-3; DET142"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3199","question":"Name 3 uses of a hoof knife.","answer":"Pare away dead sole, trim ragged frog, relieve pressure on corns or cracks, remove foreign bodies from the hoof (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH530-2; HSm230-3; DET142"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"novice","number":"3200","question":"What is the safest direction to use a hoof pick?","answer":"Heel to toe or away from you (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH530-2; HH47; PNW71"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"novice","number":"3201","question":"What is the name for the piece of equipment that's used to clean out a horse's foot?","answer":"Hoof pick  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH530-1; HSm230-2; DET143"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"novice","number":"3202","question":"Why should a hoof pick be used from heel to toe?","answer":"Safety! If used the opposite way, it could slip and gouge the handler or the horse.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH530-2; HH47; PNW71"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3203","question":"What is the pincher-like instrument that's used to squeeze the hooves to find a sore spot or cause of lameness?","answer":"Hoof testers  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH530-3; HSm230-2; DET143"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3204","question":"What is the purpose of hoof testers?","answer":"To identify or locate problems in the hoof (or areas of soreness)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH530-3; HSm230-2; DET143"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3205","question":"Name the farrier's tool that's used to remove excess hoof wall.","answer":"Nippers  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH530-1; HSm230-3; DET190"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3206","question":"In reference to hoof care, what are nippers used for?","answer":"Trim the hoof wall  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH530-1; HSm230-3; DET190"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3207","question":"What is a pritchel used for?","answer":"Make or enlarge nail holes in a horseshoe (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH530-4; HSm230-3"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3208","question":"What farrier tool is used to make or enlarge nail holes in horseshoes?","answer":"Pritchel  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH530-4; HSm230-3"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3209","question":"What is the difference in USE between nippers and pull offs?","answer":"Nippers are used to trim the hoof; pull offs are used to remove shoes. (FYI:  Pull offs can also be used to remove nails, nail stubs, and improperly driven nails.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH530-1; HSm230-2"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3210","question":"You reach into your toolbox looking for nippers and grab what looks like nippers, but they have knobs on the ends of the handles.  What tool do you have?","answer":"Pull offs  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH530-1; HSm230-2"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3211","question":"Nippers and pull offs look similar.  Describe how you can quickly tell one from another.","answer":"Pull offs have knobs on the end of the handles.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH530-1; HSm230-2"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3212","question":"When removing a shoe from a horse, describe 3 steps in how the pull-offs are used.","answer":"Put jaws under one heel of shoe; pull down towards toe and in towards center of hoof; support toe with your knee; work gradually towards the toe, first on one branch of the shoe, then on the other; continue until shoe works loose from foot.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH535-2; HSM230-4"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3213","question":"When removing a shoe, why should you pull down on the pull offs instead of pulling them from side to side?","answer":"So you don't injury the leg (don't twist the foot, pull a tendon, or injure the joints of the lower leg)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH535-2"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3214","question":"After a farrier's rasp has become too dull for rasping hooves, what can the farrier use it for?","answer":"As a clinching or finishing rasp  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH530-2; HSm230-3"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3215","question":"What tool is used to file the hoof wall and level the bearing surface of the hoof after it has been trimmed by the nippers?","answer":"Rasp  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH530-2; HSm230-3"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3216","question":"A satisfactory trimming job can be accomplished with a hoof knife, nippers, and what else?","answer":"Rasp  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm230-2; HIH535-3,4"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"jr bonus","number":"3217","question":"Name 3 important points in the care of a horse's foot.","answer":"Keep them clean (to prevent thrush), remove rocks (to prevent bruises), keep them trimmed properly, prevent the hoof from drying out, give good nutrition, exercise, keep on appropriate ground surfaces (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc47; HIH525"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"intermediate","number":"3218","question":"How does exercise help keep horse's feet healthy?","answer":"By helping to circulate blood (which brings essential nutrients to the hoof)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH525-2"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"intermediate","number":"3219","question":"Why should horses that are turned out for the winter be left unshod?","answer":"Helps keep snow and ice from accumulating in the hooves (FYI:  Barefoot hooves will stay short by natural wear in rocky terrain.  Removing shoes allows the heels to spread naturally and strengthens the frog.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH525-2; PNW45"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3220","question":"Referring to horses, define the term \"barefoot\".","answer":"Horse has no shoes (is unshod).  <br/> <br/>ref:DET 23; HSm230-5; PNW45"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"novice","number":"3221","question":"Give ONE reason for cleaning out a horse's foot.","answer":"Clean out dirt and rocks; check for injuries; check for thrush or other diseases; check for loose shoes; check for missing nails; check for abnormal growth, uneven wear, cracks, splitting, dryness (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH535-2; HSm375; HH47; PNW32,71"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3222","question":"Referring to horse's feet, what does \"picking out\" mean?","answer":"Cleaning out a horse's hoof  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH525-2; PNW44"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3223","question":"Name 4 things you should look for when inspecting the horse's hoof.","answer":"Rocks and other debris, puncture wounds, bruises, diseases, loose shoes, loose or missing horseshoe nails, abnormal growth, uneven wear, cracks, splitting, too dry (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH535; HSm375; HH47; PNW32,71"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3224","question":"How do you pick up a front foot?","answer":"Stand beside the shoulder, facing the rear; run your hand down the back of the leg to just above fetlock; grasp the fetlock area and pick up the foot; you can pinch the tendon or push the shoulder away to help. (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH37; PNW71"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3225","question":"Explain how to pick up a horse's hind foot.","answer":"Stand to the side of the horse facing its tail.  Put your hand on its hindquarters and run your hand down its leg to its fetlock.  Ask the horse to pick up its foot.  If needed, pinch the tendon or lean into the horse.  (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH37; PNW71"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3226","question":"Name ONE thing snow or ice accumulating in hooves can cause.","answer":"Pain or discomfort; unstable footing; tendon strain  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH525-2"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3227","question":"Give TWO names for a person who trims or shoes horses' hooves.","answer":"Farrier, blacksmith, horseshoer, shoer  <br/> <br/>ref:DET104; DET29; PNW156"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3228","question":"What product can you use on your horse during FLY SEASON, to help your horse stand still and cooperate with the farrier and vet","answer":"Fly spray (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-14"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3229","question":"Give ONE reason why you should work with your foal's feet.","answer":"Get him used to being handled while he's young, he's easier to control when he's young, he will grow up knowing he won't be hurt  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH525-2-4"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3230","question":"Careless trimming of a foal's feet can cause what?","answer":"Injury (strained tendons or lameness)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH48"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3231","question":"Why should young foal's feet be trimmed monthly?","answer":"So his feet and legs can grow as straight as possible  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH525-3"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3232","question":"Name 3 shoeing practices that may contribute to the development of corns.","answer":"Shoe too small, leaving shoe on too long, trimming heel too low  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH540-2; HSm375-5,6; HH48"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3233","question":"What is the term used to describe when a nail is being driven too close to the white line?","answer":"Quicking  (also accept “hot nail”)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm230-1; DET226"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3234","question":"In reference to shoeing, what is meant by the term re-set?","answer":"Farrier uses the same set of shoes for a second time  <br/> <br/>ref:DET232; HH49"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3235","question":"What is the term for the type of shoeing job when the farrier uses the same set of shoes for a second time?","answer":"Re-set or re-shod (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET232; HH49"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3236","question":"Name 3 things that can happen if you leave a shoe on too long.","answer":"Shoes can become loose or fall off, shoes can become thin, foot can get bruised or punctured, tendons and ligaments can become strained, hooves can grow out of proportion. (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH48"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3237","question":"2-part question:  When holding a horse for the farrier, on which side should you stand and why?","answer":"Same side as the farrier; if the horse acts up, you can pull its head toward you and the horse's body will move away from the farrier.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH525-3 Figure 1"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3238","question":"What are the TWO types of balance to consider when trimming the hoof?","answer":"Heel to toe (front to back) and medial to lateral (side to side)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH510-1"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3239","question":"Why should the bars be trimmed level with the sole?","answer":"So the bars won't be broken or torn on rocks  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH535-3"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3240","question":"Name ONE common fault corrected by trimming.","answer":"Splay foot, pigeon toe, quarter crack, cocked ankle, contracted heels (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH49; CAHA39"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3241","question":"Name 3 common faults corrected by trimming.","answer":"Splay foot, pigeon toe, quarter crack, cocked ankle, contracted heels (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH49; CAHA39"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3242","question":"A base narrow horse will wear its feet unevenly.  What part of the foot needs to be rasped more in order to bring the foot level?","answer":"Inside wall  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA39"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3243","question":"The condition of foals’ limbs should be assessed soon after birth.  It is important to treat limb deviations before what happens?","answer":"Before the growth plates close  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH525-3"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"intermediate","number":"3244","question":"By lowering the inside hoof wall, the farrier is correcting what problem?","answer":"Pigeon toe (toe in)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH49"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"intermediate","number":"3245","question":"Trimming more off the inner half of the hoof will help correct which conformation fault?","answer":"Pigeon toe or toed-in (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH49"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3246","question":"Trimming more off the outer half of the hoof will help correct which conformation fault?","answer":"Splay foot or toed-out (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH49"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3247","question":"Name ONE thing that may happen if the hoof is not trimmed and it grows too long.","answer":"Hoof wall may crack, hoof wall may break off, or hoof won't wear evenly. (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH47"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3248","question":"How often should horse's hooves be trimmed or shod?","answer":"Every 2 – 8 weeks (accept any number within this range) [FYI:  Trimming frequency depends on growth and changes of horse’s hoof, hoof’s influence on horse’s performance, wear, changes in horse (seasonal or medical), and owner’s preference.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH535-1; HIH525-2; HIH540-1; HSm230-2; HH49"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3249","question":"Name 3 factors that determine how often horse’s hooves need to be trimmed or shod.","answer":"Growth and changes in the horse’s hoof; influence of hoof length, angle, and balance on the horse’s performance; wear on the shoe or hoof; seasonal changes; changes for medical reasons; owner’s preference  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH535-1; HIH540-1; HSm230-2"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3250","question":"A normal, healthy mature horse without foot problems often has its feet trimmed every 6 weeks.  How often should FOALS' feet be trimmed?","answer":"Once a month, every 30 days, or every 4 weeks (accept any)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH525-3"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3251","question":"Why should you NEVER rasp the walls of the hoof?","answer":"Removes the periople or outer varnish layer (which causes the hoof to dry out).  <br/> <br/>ref:HH47"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"intermediate","number":"3252","question":"How much sole should be trimmed from a horse that's stabled?","answer":"Only enough to remove the dead tissue  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH535-3"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3253","question":"2-part question:  When trimming a horse that's going to be ridden on rocky ground and/or roads, what part of the foot should NOT be trimmed and why?","answer":"Sole; because it protects the foot  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH535-2"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3254","question":"What is an infection that penetrates the white line and abscesses at the coronet?","answer":"Gravel or sub-solar abscess (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH455-4; HSm375-7; DET124"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3255","question":"In relation to horses' hooves, what is \"gravel\"?","answer":"Infection that penetrates the white line and abscesses at the coronet (subsolar abscess)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH455-4; HSm375-7; DET124"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3256","question":"In relation to horses' hooves, what is another name for gravel?","answer":"Sub-solar abscess  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH455-4"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3257","question":"Name 3 causes of gravel or sub-solar abscess.","answer":"Puncture, bruising, trauma, dirt or bacteria getting in through cracks in white line or wall, wet footing  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH455-4; HSm375-6"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3258","question":"Name ONE common location of a hoof abscess.","answer":"Sole; white line  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH540-2"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3259","question":"What is quittor?","answer":"Inflammation of the lateral cartilages which can cause subcoronary abscesses (wound at the rear quarter of the hoof that discharges pus above the coronet)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH455-4,5; DET226"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3260","question":"Chronic inflammation and swelling of the lateral cartilages resulting in intermittent sub-coronary abscesses is called what?","answer":"Quittor  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH455-4,5; DET226"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3261","question":"Sidebones are a condition associated with ossification of the collateral cartilages.  What term refers to the condition that occurs when the collateral cartilages become infected?","answer":"Quittor  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH455-4"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3262","question":"Name ONE type of hoof problem that causes drainage at the coronet and severe lameness.","answer":"Quittor; gravel (subsolar abscess)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH455-4,5"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3263","question":"What is the MOST COMMON cause of quittor?","answer":"Injury to the coronary band (over the area of the lateral cartilages) [FYI:  Other causes of quittor are penetrating wounds of the sole, wire cuts, or bruises.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH455-5"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3264","question":"Name 3 steps in treating an abscessed foot.","answer":"Open abscess (remove as little tissue as possible); drain abscess; soak foot (in Epsom salts); use antiseptic or germicide; use hot, moist poultice (Animalintex); pack; x-ray puncture wounds; Tetanus shot; protect hoof with shoe, pad, or bandages  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH540-2; HSm375-7; HIH455-3,4"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3265","question":"Name ONE thing you can do to encourage drainage of a hoof abscess.","answer":"Soak the foot (in Epsom salts, etc.); use hot, moist poultice (Animalintex); pack the hoof (FYI:  Other treatments include applying a germicide, giving a Tetanus booster, and protecting the foot with a bandage, boot, or shoe and pad.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH540-2; HSm375-7; HIH455-3,4"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3266","question":"What is the term for the condition where a horse's foot may become smaller at the ground level than at the top of the foot?","answer":"Contracted heels  <br/> <br/>ref:DET67,68; HH49"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3267","question":"A narrow, shrunken frog and heels that are pulled together are signs of what?","answer":"Contracted heels  <br/> <br/>ref:DET67,68; HH49"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3268","question":"What are contracted heels?","answer":"Heels of the hoof are too close together (FYI: Hoof may become narrower, frog may shrink, and horse may develop navicular.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET67,68; HH49"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3269","question":"In referring to the hoof, what can happen if there isn't any frog pressure or contact with the ground?","answer":"Contracted heels may develop.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH505-4"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3270","question":"Give 3 causes of contracted heels.","answer":"Improper trimming or shoeing, lack of frog pressure, lack of weight bearing, lack of moisture in the hoof, leaving shoes on too long, genetics, faulty conformation, uneven weight distribution (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET67,68; HIH505-4"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3271","question":"Name ONE cause of contracted heels.","answer":"Improper trimming or shoeing, leaving shoes on too long, lack of frog pressure, lack of moisture in hoof, genetics, faulty conformation, uneven weight distribution (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET67,68; HIH505-4"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3272","question":"What is a specific type of sole bruise occurring in the heel area?","answer":"Corn  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH455-2,3; HIH540-2; HSm230-5,6; DET68"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3273","question":"In reference to a horse's hoof, where are corns found?","answer":"Heel area of the sole  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH455-2,3; HIH540-2; HSm230-5,6; DET68"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3274","question":"Name ONE common cause of corns in the horse.","answer":"Improper trimming (trimming the heel too long); improper shoeing (using too small a shoe that doesn’t extend back to the heel); leaving shoes on too long; trauma; horses with flat, thin soles (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH455-2,3; HIH540-2; HSm230-5,6; DET68"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3275","question":"What is a sand crack?","answer":"Crack in the hoof wall (FYI:  Toe cracks occur at the toe; quarter cracks occur at the quarter or on the side of the hoof where the wall is thin; heel cracks occur at the heel.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH540-2; HSm230-7; DET239"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3276","question":"Why are quarter cracks more common than toe cracks?","answer":"Wall of the hoof is thinner at the quarter.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH455-4"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3277","question":"Name ONE cause of a sand crack or a crack in the hoof wall.","answer":"Uneven weight bearing, irregular hoof growth, wire cuts, excessive hoof length, dry conditions, dry hooves, thin-walled hooves, injury to the coronary band (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH540-2; HIH455-4"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3278","question":"Name 3 causes of cracks in the hoof wall.","answer":"Uneven weight bearing, irregular hoof growth, wire cuts, excessive hoof length, dry conditions, dry hooves, thin-walled hooves, injury to the coronary band (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH540-2; HIH455-4"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"intermediate","number":"3279","question":"The edges of cracks in the hoof wall will NOT grow back together; therefore, healthy hoof wall must grow out to eliminate the crack.  Name ONE thing that will help stabilize a quarter crack while the hoof wall is growing out.","answer":"Hold cracks together with some type of material; fill in cracks; keep the toe shortened; keep the hoof moist; file a notch across the top of cracks that go from the bottom up (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH49; HIH455-4; HIH540-3; HSm375-7-9; HSm230-7,8"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3280","question":"2-part question:  Will the edges of a crack in the hoof wall grow back together or repair itself if the hoof wall is supported and immobilized?   Explain why.","answer":"No; the hoof wall must grow out to eliminate the crack  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH540-2"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3281","question":"Name 3 different variations of a hoof crack.","answer":"Sand crack, toe crack, full thickness toe crack, quarter crack, horizontal crack, crack that extends partway down from coronary band, crack that extends partway up from ground level, crack that extends full length of wall  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm375-7-9; HIH540-2,3"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3282","question":"What are outward distortions of the hoof called?","answer":"Flares (FYI:  Flares are also called wings.  The removal of outward distortions is called shaping or dressing the hoof.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH535-4"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3283","question":"Referring to hooves, what is meant by the term “flare”?","answer":"Outward distortions of the wall (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH535-4"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3284","question":"Which farrier tool would be used to correct a flare?","answer":"Rasp  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH530-2; HSm230-3"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3285","question":"A darkened or moist area on the sole is usually an indication of what?","answer":"Puncture wound (also accept sole bruise or abscess)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH455-3"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3286","question":"What is the name of the condition of the hoof where there is a separation of the sensitive and insensitive laminae at the white line in the toe area?","answer":"Seedy toe (also accept white line disease)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET241; FCH402"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3287","question":"What is seedy toe?","answer":"Separation of the sole from the hoof wall near the toe (separation of the sensitive and insensitive laminae at the white line in the toe area)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET241; FCH402"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3288","question":"Thrush is a black, strong smelling infection of the hoof that causes destruction of the frog. Is it caused by aerobic or anaerobic bacteria?","answer":"Anaerobic bacteria (FYI:  HSm375-1 has Fusarium necrophorum as the causative bacteria, but it should be Fusobacterium necrophorum.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH540-1; HSm375-1,2; ES183"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3289","question":"What is thrush?","answer":"Infection of the frog (FYI: Thrush is an infection of the frog caused by the anaerobic bacterium that usually involves the central sulcus of the frog.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH540-1; HSm375-1,2; ES183"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3290","question":"Name the following disease: caused by anaerobic bacteria, usually is a result of wet or unsanitary conditions, signs include crumbly frog, black sulci, and a pungent odor.","answer":"Thrush  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH540-1; HSm375-1,2; ES183"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3291","question":"What disease of the hoof causes black discoloration and a strong-smelling odor?","answer":"Thrush (FYI: Thrush is an infection of the frog caused by the anaerobic bacterium that usually involves the central sulcus of the frog.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH540-1; HSm375-1,2; ES183"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3292","question":"Name ONE way to treat thrush.","answer":"Keep hooves clean, remove affected tissue, treat with anti-thrush medication (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH540-1; HSm375-1,2; ES183"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3293","question":"What is white line disease?","answer":"Infection in the white line that causes separation of the sole and the wall (also called seedy toe) [FYI:  White line disease or seedy toe can be caused by bacteria, hoof digesting fungi, or a combination of both.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HH540-1; HSm375-2"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3294","question":"Regarding horses' feet, what is one of the best-known quotations in the horse world?","answer":"\"No foot, no horse\"  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH505-1; HSm375-1"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"jr bonus","number":"3295","question":"Name 3 reasons to shoe a horse.","answer":"Protection; traction; correction—of conformation faults, abnormal gait, or faulty hoof structure or growth; therapeutic—ease pain of diseased or injured hoof (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH535-5; HSm230-5; HH48-49"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3296","question":"Give ONE reason for shoeing your horse.","answer":"Protection; traction; correction of conformation fault, abnormal gait, or faulty hoof structure or growth; therapeutic—ease pain of diseased or injured hoof (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH535-5; HSm230-5; HH48-49"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3297","question":"Name 4 reasons to shoe a horse.","answer":"Protection; traction; correction—of conformation faults, abnormal gait, or faulty hoof structure or growth; therapeutic—ease pain of diseased or injured hoof (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH535-5; HSm230-5; HH48-49"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"jr bonus","number":"3298","question":"Name 3 steps in shoeing a horse.","answer":"Observe the horse, cut the clinches, pull off the old shoe, trim the hoof wall, trim the frog and sole, shape the shoe, nail the shoe on, clinch the nails, rasp  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH535; HSm230"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3299","question":"Name 5 steps in shoeing a horse.","answer":"Observe the horse, cut the clinches, pull off the old shoe, trim the hoof wall, trim the frog and sole, shape the shoe, nail the shoe on, clinch the nails, rasp  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH535; HSm230"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3300","question":"Referring to horseshoeing, what is balance?","answer":"Equal weight distribution (around the center of gravity on the horse's leg)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH510-1; HSm230-6"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3301","question":"What is corrective shoeing?","answer":"Shoeing to correct the stance or gait of a horse  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH515-1; HSm230-5"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3302","question":"What is therapeutic shoeing?","answer":"Shoeing to treat a medical condition of the foot or leg (FYI:  Therapeutic shoeing is called surgical shoeing or pathological shoeing in the UK.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH515-2; HSm230-5"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3303","question":"Name 3 corrective or therapeutic horseshoes, modifications, or devices.","answer":"Bar, egg bar; heart bar; Patten shoe; hospital plate; glue-on; square toe; extension; rocker toe, rolled toe, or set toe; wedge heels; pads; Chadwick spring; trailer; clip  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm230-7-9; HIH515-1-5"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3304","question":"What type shoe can be used to protect the foot while a corn is healing?","answer":"Bar shoe  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH540-2; HSm375-6"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3305","question":"Give ONE reason why a horse might wear a bar shoe.","answer":"Bar shoe—corns; egg bar shoe—navicular disease, underrun heels; heart bar shoe--laminitis, quarter cracks, heel cracks (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH515-4; HIH540; HSm230-7; HSm375"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3306","question":"Name ONE type of shoe that's used to support a hoof with navicular syndrome.","answer":"Egg bar shoe; bar shoe with heel support; rocker toe  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH515-4; HSm230-7,9"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3307","question":"Give ONE purpose of an egg bar shoe.","answer":"Supports the rear portion of the hoof, used for navicular, used for under-run heels  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH515-4; HSm230-7"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3308","question":"Heart bar shoes are used temporarily to treat hoof problems such as laminitis.  Heart bar shoes transfer weight from the hoof wall to what structure of the hoof?","answer":"Frog  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH515-4; HSm230-7"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3309","question":"What type of horseshoe may be used on horses with laminitis to transfer weight from the wall of the hoof to the frog?","answer":"Heart bar shoe  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH515-4; HSm230-7"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3310","question":"What is the name of the V-shaped device that is fitted to the bottom of the foot that keeps constant pressure on the heels?","answer":"Chadwick spring  <br/> <br/>ref:DET53"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3311","question":"The Chadwick Spring provides constant outward pressure on the bars of the hoof and would be used for what hoof problem?","answer":"Contracted heels  <br/> <br/>ref:DET53"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3312","question":"What type of horseshoes can be used on a horse that temporarily needs shoe protection without damaging the foot with horseshoe nails?","answer":"Glue-on shoes (FYI:  Glue-on shoes are especially useful on very young foals with thin, fragile hoof walls.  They are also used on thin-walled, weak-footed horses that temporarily need protection until the hoof grows out.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH515-5; HSm230-8,9"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3313","question":"In horseshoeing, what are pads used for?","answer":"To protect the bottom of the foot  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH515-5; HSm230-10"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3314","question":"What is the term for a specialized type of horseshoe pad that can be removed to treat or apply medicine to the hoof and can then be re-attached?","answer":"Hospital plate  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH515-5; HSm230-8"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3315","question":"When would a hospital plate be used on a shoe?","answer":"When the foot is abscessed or when the sole has an injury (accept either) [FYI: Hospital plates are easy to remove so you can apply medication to foot bottom; hospital plates also keep out debris.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH515-5; HSm230-8"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3316","question":"What is the name of the type of shoe that's used to elevate the heels of a horse that's confined to stall rest?","answer":"Patten shoe (FYI:  The patten shoe takes tension off a torn or sprained deep digital flexor tendon.  A rocker toe may be used in conjunction with a patten shoe.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH515-5; HSm230-8"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3317","question":"What type of horseshoe is desirable to use on young horses to ease breakover and reduce the risk of forging?  This type of shoe may be used in conjunction with an egg bar to alleviate tension on the deep digital flexor tendon.","answer":"Rocker toe (FYI:  Rocker toe, rolled toe, or set toe shoes help horses suffering from limb deformities, posterior heel lameness, navicular disease, and stumbling.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH515-4; HIH525-4; HSm230-9"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3318","question":"Why would a rocker toe horseshoe be used on a healthy young horse?","answer":"To reduce the risk of forging or overreaching (which is a common problem of young horses in training)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH515-4; HIH525-4; HSm230-9"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3319","question":"What type of horseshoe is used mostly on the hind feet to stabilize the breakover of the foot?","answer":"Square toed shoe  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH515-3; HSm230-9"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3320","question":"How many years have horseshoes been protecting horse's feet?","answer":"More than 2000 years  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH505-1"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3321","question":"Handmade shoes are still used extensively by farriers doing corrective or therapeutic shoeing.  Name 3 advantages of handmade shoes.","answer":"Can be made specifically for an individual foot problem; more secure nailing; less interference with natural hoof function; can be made in variety of widths, thicknesses and styles of bar stock; farrier has high level of skill and craftsmanship  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH515-2; HSm230-5"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3322","question":"Name ONE way to tell the difference between a front and hind shoe if your farrier asks you to hand him a front shoe.","answer":"Front shoes are rounder; front shoes are wider at the heel; hind shoes are narrower.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH505-5"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3323","question":"What is the first rule to remember in fitting a shoe to a horse's foot?","answer":"Shape the shoe to fit the foot.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH515-1; HSm230-6"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3324","question":"2-part question:  Give ONE advantage and ONE disadvantage of aluminum shoes.","answer":"Advantage:  lightweight, cause less fatigue, keeps feet closer to the ground, allows for a freer longer stride, improves fold in jumping horses; disadvantage:  wears out more quickly than steel  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH515-4; HSm230-8"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3325","question":"Aluminum horseshoes have the advantage over steel horseshoes of being lighter in weight, but have what disadvantage compared to a steel shoe?","answer":"Aluminum shoes wear faster.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH515-4; HSm230-8"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3326","question":"What alloy can be added to horseshoes to increase traction and life of the shoe?","answer":"Borium (FYI:  Borium or drill tech is tungsten carbide, is expensive, and is used on regionally in America.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH515-4; DET35"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3327","question":"What metal alloy used in horseshoes maintains the light weight of aluminum, but has the durability of steel?","answer":"Titanium  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH515-4"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3328","question":"Where on a horseshoe are calks found?","answer":"Ground surface of the shoe (usually at the heels and/or toes)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH515-4; HSm230-9; DET45"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3329","question":"What is the purpose of adding stickers or mud calks to the heel of racing plates?","answer":"Increase traction (on a muddy racetrack)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH515-4; HSm230-9; DET45"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"intermediate","number":"3330","question":"Why might calks and studs be added to horseshoes?","answer":"To increase traction  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH515-4; HSm230-9; DET45"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"intermediate","number":"3331","question":"What is a thin metal projection on the outside of a shoe that lies against the hoof to give it support?","answer":"Clip (FYI:  Toe clips are placed on the front center of the shoe and are usually used on front shoes but may be used on hind shoes of draft horses.  Side clips are placed between the 1st and 2nd nail holes, usually on hind shoes.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH515-2; HSm230-6"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3332","question":"What type of shoe modification is used to take the stress off nails and to stabilize the shoe?","answer":"Clips (FYI:  Toe clips are placed on the front center of the shoe and are usually used on front shoes but may be used on hind shoes of draft horses.  Side clips are placed between the 1st and 2nd nail holes, usually on hind shoes.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH515-2; HSm230-6"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"intermediate","number":"3333","question":"What are toe clips?","answer":"Metal projections on the outside front of a shoe (FYI: Clips help hold the shoe on and take stress off the nails.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH515-2; HSm230-6"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3334","question":"Give ONE purpose of clips on horseshoes.","answer":"To take stress off the nails, to stabilize the shoe on the hoof, to help hold the shoe more securely on thin-walled hooves  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH515-2; HSm230-6"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3335","question":"What is the name for a removable traction device for horseshoes?","answer":"Studs (FYI: Studs are usually screwed into the shoe; caulks are usually forged into the shoe.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH515-4; HSm230-9"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3336","question":"In racehorses, why are traction devices such as toe grabs not being used by trainers as commonly as they used to be?","answer":"They produce too many injuries.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH515-4; HSm230-9; DET270"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3337","question":"A thin protrusion of metal on the GROUND SURFACE of the toe of a racing plate is known as what shoe alteration?","answer":"Toe grab (also accept toe grip)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH515-4; HSm230-9; DET270"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3338","question":"Referring to horseshoes, what is a \"trailer\"?","answer":"Horseshoe heel that extends ½ inch or more beyond the horse's heel. (FYI:  Trailers are used on hind shoes.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET272"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3339","question":"How far above the horseshoe should horseshoe nails exit the hoof?","answer":"¾ – 1 inch or 20 – 25 mm (accept any number within these ranges)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH535-5; HSm230-6"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3340","question":"How many nail holes are there in most ready-made horseshoes?","answer":"8 (eight)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH515-1 Figure 1"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3341","question":"What is the purpose of beveling on a horseshoe nail?","answer":"Directs the point of the nail to come out the side of the hoof wall instead of going straight into the hoof  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm230-6; HIH535-5"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3342","question":"Horseshoe nails have a shank that is flat on one side and the other side is concave.  When driving a nail, the nail should be started with which side facing the OUTSIDE of the hoof?","answer":"Flat side should be outside. (FYI:  The checked pattern or trademark on the beveled head of the nail should face the center of the foot.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH535-5; HSm230-6"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3343","question":"Name 3 parts of a horseshoe nail.","answer":"Head, bevel of the head, neck, bevel, blade or shank, inner face, outer face, bevel of point, point  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm230-11,14"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3344","question":"What SPECIFIC part of the horseshoe nail prevents the nail from pulling through the shoe?","answer":"Nail head (FYI:  Clinches prevent the nails from being pulled out of the hoof wall.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm230-11,14"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3345","question":"A horseshoe nail has two sizes of heads, regular and city head.  Which is smaller?","answer":"City head  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm230-11"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3346","question":"What type of horseshoe nail is used to increase traction on icy surfaces?","answer":"Frost head nail  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm230-11"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3347","question":"Name 3 types of horseshoe nails.","answer":"Regular head, city head, countersunk, frost head  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm230-11"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3348","question":"Fullering, web, and branch are parts of what?","answer":"Horseshoe  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH515-1 Figure 1"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3349","question":"What is the width and thickness of the metal in the horseshoe called?","answer":"Web  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH515-1 Figure 1"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3350","question":"How does the thickness of the hoof wall determine the web or width of a horseshoe?","answer":"Web should be TWICE the thickness of the hoof wall.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH535-5; HSm230-5"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3351","question":"2-part question:  Name TWO types of shoes used specifically for the FRONT feet and give their purposes.","answer":"Half round shoes are used in harness racing or reining; weighted shoes enhance the action of gaited horses.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH515-3; HSm230-7,9"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3352","question":"Name 3 types of horseshoes that are used for specific equine activities.","answer":"Racing plates, sliding plates, polo shoes, half-round shoes (harness racing), weighted shoes (gaited horses) [accept any correct answers]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH515; HSm230"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3353","question":"2-part question:  Name TWO types of shoes used specifically for the HIND feet and give their purposes.","answer":"Sliding plates help horses perform a sliding stop; square toe shoes stabilize the breakover point; weighted shoes are used on the hind feet when teaching a horse to rack.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH515-3; HSm230-8,9"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3354","question":"Name 3 things that influence horseshoe style.","answer":"Type of activity horse does, type of terrain horse is worked on, integrity of hoof (how good hoof is), size of horse, weight of horse (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH535-5; HSm230-5"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3355","question":"Give ONE reason why hoof boots are used on horses.","answer":"Replace a lost shoe, treat a foot by placing medication in the boot, protect the hoof from further injury, keep the hoof clean, traction (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET142"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3356","question":"Describe a concave, rim, or fullered horseshoe.","answer":"Shoe that has fullering or creasing all the way around the shoe.  (FYI:  The fullering of these shoes fills with dirt which helps increase traction.  Mud, snow, and other debris falls out of the shoe easier as the horse moves.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH515-4; HSm230-9"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3357","question":"Give ONE reason for using half-round shoes.","answer":"Harness racing (trotters), reining, young horses in training (FYI:  Half-round shoes are used on the front feet.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH515-3; HIH525-4; HSm230-7"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3358","question":"What is the term for the most commonly used manufactured, pre-formed horseshoes?","answer":"Keg shoes  <br/> <br/>ref:DET160"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3359","question":"What is a keg shoe?","answer":"Pre-sized, ready-made shoe (manufactured, pre-formed shoe)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET160"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3360","question":"In general appearance, how does a mule’s shoe differ from a horse’s shoe?","answer":"Mule shoe is narrower.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH515-3 figure 4"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3361","question":"What is the name for a type of shoe where the inside rim on the web is raised above the outside rim?","answer":"Polo shoe (FYI:  The raised inside rim increases traction and prevents sliding.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH515-3 figure 4"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3362","question":"Racing plates are generally made from what type of metal?","answer":"Aluminum  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH515-4; HSm230-8"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3363","question":"Aluminum shoes are most commonly used in what equine sport?","answer":"Racing (FYI:  Aluminum shoes are 1/3 the weight of steel shoes.  They are also used on the front feet of reining horses, western pleasure horses, and jumping horses.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH515-4; HSm230-8"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3364","question":"Name the type of keg shoe that is made of aluminum and is used on racehorses.","answer":"Racing plates (also accept plates)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH515-4; HSm230-8"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3365","question":"Sliding plate horseshoes will be found on the rear hooves of a horse performing in what kind of competition?","answer":"Reining  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH515-3; HSm230-8"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3366","question":"What kind of shoes would be found on the hind feet of a horse in a reining competition?","answer":"Sliding plates (sliders)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH515-3; HSm230-8"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3367","question":"Specifically, how does the weight of aluminum shoes compare to the weight of steel shoes?","answer":"Aluminum shoes are 1/3 the weight of steel shoes of the same size and type.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH515-4; HSm230-8"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3369","question":"Give ONE reason how a farrier chooses the proper weight of shoe for a horse.","answer":"Shoe should be of the minimum weight necessary to last between shoeing intervals (the lightest weight the horse can wear); shoe should encourage the action desired (FYI:  Heavier shoes are used on gaited horses to achieve higher action.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH515-1; HSm230-5"},
    {"category":"Horse Judging","level":"easy","number":"3370","question":"How many classes are youth USUALLY required to judge in a Horse Judging competition?","answer":"4 – 8 classes (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm635-5"},
    {"category":"Horse Judging","level":"easy","number":"3371","question":"How many horses are in a Horse Judging competition?","answer":"4 (four) [FYI:  In “quality” or halter classes, horses are numbered 1 – 4 from left to right.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm635-5"},
    {"category":"Horse Judging","level":"easy","number":"3372","question":"What is the name of the competition where contestants evaluate quality and performance classes of 4 horses and then explain why they placed the class as they did?","answer":"Horse Judging  <br/> <br/>ref:HH15; HSm635; HSm640"},
    {"category":"Horse Judging","level":"easy","number":"3373","question":"Give ONE way competitors can improve their Horse Judging skills.","answer":"Practice (by watching real classes), learn from more experienced judgers, get more info on judging (from books or internet)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm635-6"},
    {"category":"Horse Judging","level":"easy","number":"3374","question":"In Horse Judging, name ONE difference between quality or conformation classes and performance classes.","answer":"Conformation classes are judged on the horse’s conformation; performance classes are judged on the performance of the horse and/or handler or rider.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm635-2,3"},
    {"category":"Horse Judging","level":"intermediate","number":"3375","question":"In horse judging competitions, what are the TWO BASIC types of classes judged by competitors?","answer":"Halter, quality, or conformation classes (accept any) and performance classes  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm635-2,3"},
    {"category":"Horse Judging","level":"easy","number":"3376","question":"In Horse Judging, what is the difference between pleasure classes and equitation classes?","answer":"Pleasure classes are mainly judged on the horse; equitation classes are mainly judged on the rider.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm635-3; PNW159; PNW158; HH40DET99; DET214"},
    {"category":"Horse Judging","level":"easy","number":"3377","question":"In judging a quality or conformation class, what is the single most important characteristic in equine selection?","answer":"Balance (FYI:  The slope of the shoulder is critical to balance.  When the slope of the shoulder changes, other angles and ratios change which can cause a hard stride and other problems.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-2"},
    {"category":"Horse Judging","level":"jr bonus","number":"3378","question":"Name 3 things halter quality horses are judged on.","answer":"Balance, structural correctness, structural smoothness, muscling, symmetry, action or way of going, type, conformation, soundness, quality, breed characteristics, sex characteristics (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm635; HSm640; DET129; HH8-13"},
    {"category":"Horse Judging","level":"sr bonus","number":"3379","question":"Name 4 things halter quality horses are judged on.","answer":"Balance, structural correctness, structural smoothness, muscling, symmetry, action or way of going, type, conformation, soundness, quality, breed characteristics, sex characteristics (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm635; HSm640; DET129; HH8-13"},
    {"category":"Horse Judging","level":"easy","number":"3380","question":"When determining the quality of a horse's conformation, to what do you compare it?","answer":"Breed standard (ideal horse for the breed as set up by the breed association)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-1; HSm385-1"},
    {"category":"Horse Judging","level":"intermediate","number":"3381","question":"A horse that does not fit the general description of a breed type is said to be what?","answer":"Off type  <br/> <br/>ref:HH9"},
    {"category":"Horse Judging","level":"easy","number":"3382","question":"Name TWO things to look for when judging a horse at the walk or trot.","answer":"Stride should be straight, true, elastic, smooth, long, well-coordinated, no lameness, no abnormal ways of going, no interference (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH12,14; HSm385-1"},
    {"category":"Horse Judging","level":"jr bonus","number":"3383","question":"In horse judging quality or confirmation classes, horses are viewed several ways to assess confirmation, way of going, etc.  Name 3 ways horses are viewed in a quality or confirmation class.","answer":"Left side view, front view, right side view, hind view, at the walk, at the trot  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-1; HSm385-1; HH14"},
    {"category":"Horse Judging","level":"sr bonus","number":"3384","question":"In horse judging quality or confirmation classes, horses are viewed several ways to assess confirmation, way of going, etc.  Name 4 ways horses are viewed in a quality or confirmation class.","answer":"Left side view, front view, right side view, hind view, at the walk, at the trot  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH220-1; HSm385-1; HH14"},
    {"category":"Horse Judging","level":"jr bonus","number":"3385","question":"Name 3 ways competitors can be successful in judging performances classes.","answer":"Know the judging criteria for the class, know the rules for the class, know how to score the class (i.e. Reining), know the patterns (if indicated), take good notes, study, practice (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm635-6"},
    {"category":"Horse Judging","level":"intermediate","number":"3386","question":"In some performance classes, each maneuver is scored from 0 – 10.  Name ONE class that is scored this way.","answer":"Dressage (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm635-3"},
    {"category":"Horse Judging","level":"easy","number":"3387","question":"Many performance classes start with a score of 70 and points are added and deducted for each maneuver.  Name ONE class that is scored this way.","answer":"Reining, Cutting, Trail, Horsemanship (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm635-3,4"},
    {"category":"Horse Judging","level":"jr bonus","number":"3388","question":"When judging English Pleasure, name 3 reasons for point deductions.","answer":"Breaking gaits, inconsistent gaits, incorrect gaits, wrong leads, excessive speed or slowness, fighting the bit, throwing the head, not backing, poor manners, swishing the tail, unsafe behaviors (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:PNW142"},
    {"category":"Horse Judging","level":"jr bonus","number":"3389","question":"Name 3 things English Pleasure is judged on.","answer":"Suitability to purpose (Hunt Seat), gaits, head carriage, performance, ability to give a pleasurable ride, style, manners (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:PNW142"},
    {"category":"Horse Judging","level":"jr bonus","number":"3390","question":"When judging Showmanship besides starting on the wrong side of the cone and breaking pattern—which in a horse show would normally result in disqualification—name 3 things that would cause point deductions from exhibitors.","answer":"Horse not traveling straight, horse not setting up straight, horse resting a foot, gelding “letting down”, horse not pivoting correctly, exhibitor not changing sides, exhibitor changing hands, exhibitor touching horse (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:PNW125,126"},
    {"category":"Horse Judging","level":"jr bonus","number":"3391","question":"When judging Western Pleasure, name 3 reasons for point deductions.","answer":"Breaking gaits, inconsistent gaits, incorrect gaits, wrong leads, excessive speed, fighting the bit, throwing the head, not backing, poor manners, swishing the tail, unsafe behaviors (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:PNW134"},
    {"category":"Horse Judging","level":"jr bonus","number":"3392","question":"Name 3 things Western Pleasure is judged on.","answer":"Horse’s manners, performance, suitability to give a pleasurable ride, gaits, way of going, head position (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:PNW134"},
    {"category":"Horse Judging","level":"easy","number":"3393","question":"In Horse Judging, what is the maximum time for giving oral reasons?","answer":"2 (two) minutes  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm640-7"},
    {"category":"Horse Judging","level":"easy","number":"3394","question":"At what distance should you stand from an oral reasons judge while delivering a set of oral reasons?","answer":"8 feet (accept any number within the 6 – 10 feet range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm640-6; HH15"},
    {"category":"Horse Judging","level":"easy","number":"3395","question":"Where should your hands be while you're delivering a set of oral reasons?","answer":"Behind your back  <br/> <br/>ref:HH15"},
    {"category":"Horse Judging","level":"easy","number":"3396","question":"In reference to horse judging, what determines how easy your oral reasons are to follow?","answer":"How you organize them (FYI: Oral reasons should have an introduction, comparisons of top, middle, and bottom pairs, and a conclusion.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm640-4"},
    {"category":"Horse Judging","level":"medium","number":"3397","question":"How is the phrase “I fault” used in horse judging oral reasons?","answer":"Negative quality of the top horse in a pair  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm640-5"},
    {"category":"Horse Judging","level":"medium","number":"3398","question":"How is the phrase “I grant” used in horse judging oral reasons?","answer":"Positive quality of the bottom horse in a pair  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm640-5"},
    {"category":"Horse Judging","level":"jr bonus","number":"3399","question":"Name 3 important points in giving a good set of oral reasons in horse judging.","answer":"Take notes during class, have a mental picture of class, use correct terms, organize reasons—intro, use of pairs, conclusion, practice (preferably without notes), accuracy, delivery—appearance, posture, voice, eye contact (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm640"},
    {"category":"Horse Judging","level":"easy","number":"3400","question":"What is the MAIN purpose of giving oral reasons in Horse Judging?","answer":"To explain to the judge why you placed the class the way you did  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm640-1"},
    {"category":"Horse Judging","level":"novice","number":"3401","question":"When is the best time to take notes in a judging class?","answer":"When the class is in front of you (FYI:  To take notes, many divide their paper into 4 quadrants and list each horse in a quadrant.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm640-2"},
    {"category":"Horse Judging","level":"easy","number":"3402","question":"What is USUALLY considered a perfect score for a Horse Judging class placement?","answer":"50 points  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm635-5"},
    {"category":"Horse Judging","level":"medium","number":"3403","question":"When being judged in horse show classes, what is the difference between the American system and the Danish system of judging?","answer":"American system ranks each entry from most desirable to least desirable; Danish system judges all exhibitors against a standard.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm635-3"},
    {"category":"Horse Judging","level":"medium","number":"3404","question":"What is the term that’s used to calculate deductions due to placing errors in Horse Judging?","answer":"Cuts (FYI:  There will be 3 “cuts” per class—between the 1st pair, the 2nd pair, and the 3rd pair.  Cuts range from 1 – 7.  The bigger the cut, the bigger the differences in the horses in the pair.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm635-5"},
    {"category":"Horse Judging","level":"easy","number":"3405","question":"Which type of class is judged on the rider?","answer":"Equitation or horsemanship (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm190-4; PNW156"},
    {"category":"Horse Judging","level":"sr bonus","number":"3406","question":"Name 3 things Working Hunter horses are judged on.","answer":"Performance, manners, hunting pace, style of jumping, way of going, suitability for use in the hunting field, form, ability to negotiate a course safely, faults earned on the course.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm190-4; DET145"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"easy","number":"3407","question":"In general, how many years of an equine's life are equal to one year of a human's life?","answer":"3 (three) years (FYI: In young horses the ratio is 1:3.5 years.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH450-1"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"easy","number":"3408","question":"You do the math…If one horse year is equal to three human years, how old is a 20-year-old mare in human years?","answer":"60 years old (FYI:  In young horses the ratio is 1:3.5 years.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH450-1"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"medium","number":"3409","question":"Give TWO reasons why horses live longer today than in the past.","answer":"Horses aren't worked as hard; horses generally receive better care.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH450-1"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"sr bonus","number":"3410","question":"Give 4 signs of old age in the horse.","answer":"Gray hairs, deep depressions above the eyes, swayback, drooping lower lip, weight loss, thin hooves, arthritis, coarser hair coat, teeth changes—angle of incidence, Galvayne’s groove, shape of teeth (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH450-6"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"jr bonus","number":"3411","question":"Give 3 signs of old age in the horse.","answer":"Gray hairs, deep depressions above the eyes, swayback, drooping lower lip, weight loss, thin hooves, arthritis, coarser hair coat, teeth changes—angle of incidence, Galvayne’s groove, shape of teeth (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH450-6"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"easy","number":"3412","question":"What is the term for the service when a boarding stable takes care of all your horse's needs?","answer":"Full board  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH110-3; HSm145-1"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"easy","number":"3413","question":"What is meant by the term \"full board\"?","answer":"Stable where your horse is kept will take care of all your horse's needs.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH110-3; HSm145-1"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"medium","number":"3414","question":"To be considered a business rather than a hobby by the IRS, how many years must a horse business make a profit?","answer":"2 out of every 7 years  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1360-1"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"sr bonus","number":"3415","question":"Name 3 types of equine-related contracts.","answer":"Breeding contracts, sales contracts, boarding, equine leases, training agreements, hauling agreements, liability waivers, sales agency agreements, partnership agreements, syndication agreements (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1355"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"medium","number":"3416","question":"Referring to leasing a horse, what is the difference between a lessor and a lessee?","answer":"Lessor is the one who owns the horse; lessee is the one who's leasing the horse.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1355-1"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"medium","number":"3417","question":"In reference to equine business, what does the Latin expression \"caveat emptor\" mean? (pronounced CAV-ee-aht EMP-tor)","answer":"Let the buyer beware  <br/> <br/>ref:DET52"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"sr bonus","number":"3418","question":"Name 3 equine-related careers where workers do NOT work hands-on with live horses.","answer":"Cooperative Extension, Department of Agriculture, breed association, horse council, announcer, feed industry, show organizer, equine insurance, equine lawyer, tack store, judge, barn builder, equine appraiser (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm650"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"jr bonus","number":"3419","question":"Name 3 equine-relate careers which require contact with horses.","answer":"Vet, vet tech, farrier, dentist, chiropractor, (other medical personnel), trainer, jockey, groom, exercise person, outrider, ranching, riding instructor, stable manager, therapeutic riding, mounted police officer (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm650"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"easy","number":"3420","question":"Other than the purchase price of a horse, name TWO expenses of horse ownership.","answer":"Feed, board, vet care, hoof care, tack, training, lessons, transportation, leasing (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH110-3; HSm150"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"jr bonus","number":"3421","question":"Horse ownership is very expensive.  Other than the purchase price of a horse, name 4 expenses of horse ownership.","answer":"Feed, board, vet care, hoof care, tack, training, lessons, transportation, leasing (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH110-3; HSm150"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"jr bonus","number":"3422","question":"Accurate identification of horses is important for medical records, showing or racing, or for finding lost or stolen horses.  Name 3 ways a specific horse can be identified.","answer":"Sex, breed, color, markings, coat patterns or spots, height, weight (may vary), blemishes (scars, muscular dimples or defects), whorls (cowlicks), brands, lip tattoo, microchips, chestnut patterns (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-7-9"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"sr bonus","number":"3423","question":"Accurate identification of horses is important for medical records, showing or racing, or for finding lost or stolen horses.  Name 5 ways a specific horse can be identified.","answer":"Sex, breed, color, markings, coat patterns or spots, height, weight (may vary), blemishes (scars, muscular dimples or defects), whorls (cowlicks), brands, lip tattoo, microchips, chestnut patterns (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-7-9"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"easy","number":"3424","question":"Name TWO types of brands or human-made marks of identification in horses.","answer":"Hot brand, freeze brand, lip tattoo, microchip  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-7,8"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"easy","number":"3425","question":"What is a brand?","answer":"Mark of identification  <br/> <br/>ref:DET37"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"medium","number":"3426","question":"How does freeze branding a gray horse differ from freeze branding a chestnut horse?","answer":"New hair growth after freeze branding comes in white.  When branding a gray horse, the iron is applied long enough to kill the root so the hair won't grow back.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-8"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"easy","number":"3427","question":"What is the name of the branding method that uses extreme cold rather than heat?","answer":"Freeze branding (FYI:  The branding iron is dipped in liquid nitrogen and is usually applied long enough to kill the pigment in the skin which causes white discoloration.  In gray horses, the brand is applied long enough to kill the hair follicles.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-8"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"easy","number":"3428","question":"What is one of the oldest methods of marking horses for identification?","answer":"Hot branding  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-7"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"jr bonus","number":"3429","question":"Name 3 areas on a horse that are branded.","answer":"Cheek, neck (Mustangs, Arabians), shoulder, hip  <br/> <br/>ref:DET37"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"easy","number":"3430","question":"Where is a Thoroughbred racehorse tattooed?","answer":"Inside of the upper lip  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-8"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"jr bonus","number":"3431","question":"Name 3 pieces of information that should be listed on a horse’s bill of sale.","answer":"Name of horse (registered name), breed, registration number, age (date of birth), sex, color, markings, buyer, seller, signatures, purchase date, purchase price, special details of purchase, other identifying info (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1355-2"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"hard","number":"3432","question":"Most equine insurance policies require you to do what if your horse is injured, ill, or lame?","answer":"Immediately notify the company  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1340-5"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"hard","number":"3433","question":"What type of insurance provides coverage for when someone or something is injured on your property or by your horse?  The insurance company will investigate the claim, hire a lawyer to represent you, and pay settlements as covered by the policy.","answer":"Liability insurance  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1340-1"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"sr bonus","number":"3434","question":"Name 3 US states that do NOT have Equine Activity Liability Laws.","answer":"California, Maryland, Nevada, and New York (FYI:  Even if your state has an equine activity liability law, you should still have liability insurance.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1340-4"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"hard","number":"3435","question":"What type of insurance offers coverage in the event that an insured horse suffers from a physical condition that makes it totally and permanently unable to fulfill its intended use?","answer":"Loss of use insurance (FYI:  Loss of use policies may only pay 50% – 60% of the face value of the mortality insurance policy.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1340-3"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"hard","number":"3436","question":"What type of insurance covers the costs of illness-related veterinary expenses, diagnostic tests, and non-surgical care?  This type of insurance does NOT cover routine expenses like vaccinations, Coggins tests, etc.","answer":"Equine major medical insurance (FYI:  Some policies will cover up to $7,500 and may include colic surgery.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1340-3"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"hard","number":"3437","question":"What type of insurance policy is pays the owner if an insured horse dies from illness, injury, disease, or accident?","answer":"Mortality insurance (FYI:  Full mortality covers almost all causes of death.  Specified peril only covers death from certain causes.  Mortality insurance may also cover if the horse is stolen.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1340-3"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"intermediate","number":"3438","question":"You do the math…A horse that is 66 inches tall would be considered to be how many hands tall?","answer":"16.2 hands tall (66 divided by 4 = 16.5 which would 16.2 hands)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET129"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"intermediate","number":"3439","question":"You do the math...In inches, how tall is a 16-hand horse?","answer":"64 inches (16 x 4 = 64)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET129"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"novice","number":"3440","question":"Referring to horses, what is a hand?","answer":"Measurement of height (1 hand equals 4 inches)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET129"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"easy","number":"3441","question":"When did the horse and pony program become part of the 4-H organization?","answer":"1960's  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH190O-1"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"easy","number":"3442","question":"What is the oldest, non-formal youth development organization in the US?","answer":"4-H  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH190O-1"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"medium","number":"3443","question":"2-part question:  How and why was the Cooperative Extension Service established?","answer":"By the Smith-Lever Act in 1914 as a way to distribute new research information to the states  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH130-1"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"medium","number":"3444","question":"What do the initials AHC stand for?","answer":"American Horse Council  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH130-1"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"sr bonus","number":"3445","question":"Name 3 things that should be considered in order to select the most appropriate horse for your needs and desires.","answer":"Age of rider and/or horse, experience of rider and/or horse, temperament, intended use, cost, breed, horse and rider combination, management experience, color, registered or grade (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH210; HSm145"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"sr bonus","number":"3446","question":"If you are thinking of buying a horse, what are 3 things you should consider in deciding whether or not be become a horse owner?","answer":"Expensive to buy, expensive to take care of, time for feeding and care, time for riding and training, you may need to pass up other activities, knowledge of caring for a horse (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH210-6"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"sr bonus","number":"3447","question":"Name 3 questions you should ask the owner before buying a horse.","answer":"Why selling, health problems, unsoundness, vices; how it gets along with other animals, previous use, training, specific cues, temperament, health care history, idiosyncrasies, behavioral problems (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH210-5; HSm145"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"novice","number":"3448","question":"What GENERAL age of horses is preferred for novice or first-time owners?","answer":"Older horses  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH210-1"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"easy","number":"3449","question":"In choosing a horse or pony for a young child, what is more important than the animal's size?","answer":"Disposition or temperament (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH110-2"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"sr bonus","number":"3450","question":"What are 3 advantages to leasing a horse?","answer":"May satisfy desire to ride and costs less than owning, good way to determine if interest is serious before buying, good way to see if horse is compatible or what you expected, allows you to gain experience that will help you manage your own horse better  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH110-2; HSm145-1"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"sr bonus","number":"3451","question":"Name 3 life skills that children may develop as a result of horse ownership.","answer":"Responsibility, time management, money management, teamwork, self-confidence, sportsmanship, self-discipline, social skills, healthy competitive nature, greater coordination, greater strength, greater agility (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH110-4"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"hard","number":"3452","question":"In reference to horses, what does syndicate mean?","answer":"Horse is owned by a group of people who each own shares in it.  <br/> <br/>ref:DET61"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"hard","number":"3453","question":"REM or deep sleep occurs only when horses are in what position?","answer":"Lying down with their muzzles touching the ground  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH181"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"intermediate","number":"3454","question":"Referring to horses, what is a \"cavy\"?  (CAVE-ee)","answer":"Collection of horses  <br/> <br/>ref:DET52; HSc4"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"hard","number":"3455","question":"What term refers to the mythological creature that had a head, torso, and arms of a man and the body and legs of a horse?","answer":"Centaur  <br/> <br/>ref:DET52"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"sr bonus","number":"3456","question":"Cob or cobby are terms used in the horse industry.  Give 3 examples of how you might use these terms.","answer":"Cob-tailed—docked tail; cob-tail class—type of Hackney Pony class; cob—type of horse (short, heavyweight hunter); COB—form of feed (corn, oats, barley mix); cobby—horse that’s closely coupled and stoutly built  <br/> <br/>ref:DET60; HIH175B1; HIH350-2"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"intermediate","number":"3457","question":"What is the term that means \"of or pertaining to the horse\"?","answer":"Equine  <br/> <br/>ref:DET98"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"intermediate","number":"3458","question":"In reference to horses, give TWO definitions of forging.","answer":"Shaping of iron at the forge; striking the forefoot with the hindfoot  <br/> <br/>ref:DET112"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"easy","number":"3459","question":"Give TWO definitions of the term \"hack”.","answer":"Horse ridden to a hunt meet, a riding horse for hire, a pleasure ride  <br/> <br/>ref:DET127; FCH10"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"hard","number":"3460","question":"What does the slang term “hat rack” mean when used in describing a horse?","answer":"Emaciated or very thin horse (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET130"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"hard","number":"3461","question":"What does the term \"hippophile\" describe?","answer":"Horse lover  <br/> <br/>ref:DET140"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"medium","number":"3462","question":"The horse has no equal as a draft animal. Even today, tractors, automobiles, and trucks are rated in what manner reflecting on the horse?","answer":"They are compared in terms of horsepower.  <br/> <br/>ref:DET143"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"hard","number":"3463","question":"What does the term “Indian broke” mean?","answer":"Horse is trained to be mounted from either side.  <br/> <br/>ref:DET151"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"easy","number":"3464","question":"What are TWO meanings of the term \"jockey\"?","answer":"Person who rides racehorses; small flaps on each side of the saddle  <br/> <br/>ref:DET158"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"easy","number":"3465","question":"In reference to the horse world, give TWO definitions of the term \"maiden\".","answer":"Mare that’s never been bred; horse that's never won a race  <br/> <br/>ref:DET174"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"intermediate","number":"3466","question":"A collection of saddle horses at a roundup from which horses are chosen to be used for the day is called what?","answer":"Remuda (pronounced ray MYOU-dah or ray-MOO-dah)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET232; HH40"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"medium","number":"3467","question":"What is it called when a horse is ridden to his absolute limit so that he's exhausted and is unable to go farther?","answer":"“Riding him into the ground”  <br/> <br/>ref:DET234"},
    {"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"easy","number":"3468","question":"Give TWO definitions of the term throatlatch.","answer":"Part of the horse—space between the jaw and the neck; part of the bridle—strap that goes around the horse's throatlatch area (and keeps the bridle from slipping over the horse's head)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET267; HH8; HH28"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3469","question":"Name ONE disease that has been linked to excessive free radicals or a deficiency of key antioxidants.","answer":"Equine motor neuron disease (EMND), chronic rheumatic disease, degenerative joint or bone disease  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH730-3"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3470","question":"Name ONE function of an antioxidant.","answer":"Helps decrease the negative effects of free radicals; decreases susceptibility to oxidative stress and damage  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm430-9"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3471","question":"Antioxidants decrease the negative effect of free radicals on body cells.  Give TWO examples of antioxidants.","answer":"Selenium, vitamin E, vitamin A, vitamin C, enzymes, nutrient derivatives  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm430-9"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"intermediate","number":"3472","question":"What is the major nutritional function of carbohydrates?","answer":"Energy  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH715-1; HSm410-1; HSc33"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3473","question":"Give ONE example of monosaccharides or simple carbohydrates.","answer":"Glucose, fructose, galactose, xylose (FYI: Examples of disaccharides are sucrose and lactose. Examples of polysaccharides are starches and fructans.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH715-1; FCH16"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3474","question":"What is the difference between a structural carbohydrate and a non-structural carbohydrate?","answer":"Structural carbohydrates are polysaccharides that make up the fiber components of plants. Nonstructural carbohydrates act as storage forms of carbohydrates in plants.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH715-1,2; FCH16"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3475","question":"What nutrient is primarily stored in the horse's body as glycogen?","answer":"Carbohydrates (specifically glucose)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET122; FCH391; HSc33"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3476","question":"In reference to equine nutrition, what is glycogen?","answer":"Storage form of glucose (FYI: Glucose is stored in the liver, kidneys, and muscles as glycogen.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET122; FCH391; HSc33"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3477","question":"What happens to excess simple sugars when the glycogen storage capacity of the liver, kidneys, and muscles are full?","answer":"Stored as fat  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH17; ES146"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3478","question":"In reference to equine nutrition, what is oxidative phosphorylation?","answer":"Aerobic breakdown of carbohydrates, fats, and proteins into energy (ATP)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH850-1"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3479","question":"In reference to equine nutrition, what is glycolysis?","answer":"Anaerobic breakdown of  glucose or glycogen into lactic acid  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH850-1"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"intermediate","number":"3480","question":"Name TWO time periods when the energy requirements for a broodmare increase.","answer":"Last 1/3 of pregnancy (last trimester); while lactating  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH760-1; FCH411"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3481","question":"Nutritional energy is measured in what scientific term?","answer":"Calories (also accept kilocalories or joules) [FYI:  A calorie is defined as the amount of energy needed to raise the temperature of one (1) gram of water, one (1) degree Celsius.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH715-3; FCH9"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3482","question":"Horses are only able to convert what percent of available chemical energy in food to mechanical energy or work?","answer":"20 – 25% (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH715-3"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3483","question":"Which has more digestible energy per pound, Timothy hay or oats?","answer":"Oats  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm410-4,5"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3484","question":"Explain the difference between digestible energy (DE) and net energy (NE).","answer":"DE is the amount of energy in a feed that is available for absorption (gross energy minus energy lost in feces); NE is the amount of energy in a feed that can be used by the horse (gross energy minus energy lost in feces, urine, and digestion).  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH715-3; FCH9"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3485","question":"Give ONE reason why a horse's digestible energy or calorie needs may increase.","answer":"Exercise, fever, illness, parasites, growing, reproducing, outside temperature (temperature extremes), humidity (wet weather) [accept any correct answer]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH715-1; FCH9-10"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"jr bonus","number":"3486","question":"Give 3 reasons why a horse’s digestible energy or calorie needs may increase.","answer":"Exercise, fever, illness, parasites, growing, reproducing, outside temperature (temperature extremes), humidity (wet weather) [accept any correct answers]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH715-1; FCH9-10"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3487","question":"A deficit of what TWO nutrients can cause fatigue or exhaustion?","answer":"Energy, water, electrolytes  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH214"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3488","question":"Give ONE reason why hay can't supply all the energy needs for a hard-working horse.","answer":"Energy concentration of hay is lower than that of grain; horse can't eat enough hay to meet the increased energy needs  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH820-1"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"intermediate","number":"3489","question":"At room temperature what is the PHYSICAL difference between fats and oils?","answer":"Fats are solids and oils are liquids.  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH18"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3490","question":"Name 3 benefits of adding fat to the equine diet.","answer":"Growth, performance, stamina, body weight, helps reproductive function, helps milk production, reduces gut fill, helps skin and coat (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:ES148"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3491","question":"What is the most commonly used fat source in horse diets?","answer":"Vegetable oil (such as corn oil)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm410-3; HIH741-3"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3492","question":"In the past, horse diets were formulated at 6% – 7% fat, but now some diets have up to what percent fat?","answer":"15%  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH760-2"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3493","question":"Which is safer to feed to meet an athletic horse's energy needs, fat or grain?","answer":"Fat  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH755-2"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3494","question":"Proper use of what nutrient in the horse's diet increases the time before fatigue sets in during exercise or conditioning?","answer":"Fat  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH851-7"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3495","question":"Compared to proteins and carbohydrates, fats contain what percent more digestible energy on a per pound basis?","answer":"2.25%  (FYI: Fats have 9 calories/gram; proteins and carbohydrates have 4 calories/gram.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH715-3; HSm410-3; HSc33"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3496","question":"Which nutrient has the HIGHEST energy density?","answer":"Fat (FYI: Fats have 9 calories/gram; proteins and carbohydrates have 4 calories/gram)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH715-3; HSm410-3; HSc33"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3497","question":"Name ONE thing omega 3 fatty acids can do in the horse’s body.","answer":"Enhance the coat, skin, and hooves; help with allergic skin conditions such as “sweet itch”; soften the stool (prevent impaction); make the coat glossy (gives \"bloom\")  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH742-5"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3498","question":"What source of omega 3 fatty acids provides a significant improvement in \"sweet itch\" or other allergic skin conditions when added to the horse's diet?","answer":"Flaxseed (also called linseed)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH742-5; FCH85"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3499","question":"Name 3 benefits of feeding flaxseed to horses.","answer":"Makes coat glossy (gives “bloom”), softens stools (prevents impaction), treats allergic skin disease (“sweet itch”), enhances coat, skin, and hooves  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH742-5; FCH85"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3500","question":"Fiber is made of what specific type of nutrient?","answer":"Complex carbohydrates (such as cellulose)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc33"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3501","question":"When reading a feed tag, which figure on the guaranteed analysis is the best indicator of a feed's energy content?","answer":"Crude fiber (FYI:  Feeds with higher fiber content have less digestible energy.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH745-2,3"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3502","question":"2-part question:  When reading a feed tag, what is the best indicator of energy content and why?","answer":"Fiber content (crude fiber); as fiber content increases, energy content decreases  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH745-2,3"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3503","question":"Fibrous feedstuffs are broken down into volatile fatty acids.  What percent of the horse's energy needs do these acids provide?","answer":"80%  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH705-2"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3504","question":"The large intestine of the horse has microbes which break down fibrous feedstuffs into what substances that are used as energy sources?","answer":"Volatile Fatty Acids (VFA) [FYI:  VFA's may provide up to 80% of the horse's energy needs.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH705-2; HSm405-2; HSc30,31"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3505","question":"Compared to cow’s milk, name 3 nutrients that have LOWER concentrations in mare’s milk.","answer":"Fat, protein, zinc, total solids or dry matter (also accept ash which is total minerals) [FYI:  Mare’s milk is HIGHER in water, carbohydrates such as lactose, calcium, and copper.]  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH274"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3506","question":"In mare's milk, which is higher, milk fat or lactose?","answer":"Lactose (FYI:  Milk fat is 1.4% to 1.8%.  Lactose is 6.2% to 6.5%.)  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA69"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3507","question":"Compared to cow’s milk, name 3 nutrients that have HIGHER concentrations in mare’s milk.","answer":"Water, carbohydrates (lactose), calcium, copper (FYI:  Mare’s milk is LOWER in fat, protein, zinc, and total solids or dry matter.)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH274"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3508","question":"Name ONE thing that minerals influence about other nutrients.","answer":"Absorption, metabolism, excretion of other nutrients  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH725-1"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3509","question":"Name 3 minerals that are essential in adult horses’ diets.","answer":"Calcium, phosphorus, sodium, chloride, potassium, magnesium, sulfur, cobalt, copper, iodine, iron, manganese, selenium, zinc  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm430; FCH20"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3510","question":"At what TWO stages of a horse’s life are calcium needs the greatest?","answer":"Growing animals and lactating mares  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH725-1"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3511","question":"Give TWO examples of minerals.","answer":"Macro-mineral examples: sodium, chloride, calcium, phosphorus, magnesium, potassium, sulfur; micro-mineral examples: iron, copper, zinc, manganese, iodine, selenium, cobalt, fluorine, molybdenum, chromium, silicon  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH725; HSm430"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3512","question":"Iron, copper, and phosphorus are examples of which kind of nutrient?","answer":"Minerals (Do NOT accept micro-minerals because phosphorus is a macro-mineral.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH725; HSm430"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3513","question":"Name 3 minerals that are needed in the diet of rapidly growing foals to help prevent DOD or developmental orthopedic disease.","answer":"Calcium, phosphorus, copper, zinc  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH765-1"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3514","question":"Name 5 MACRO minerals.","answer":"Calcium, phosphorus, sodium, chloride, potassium, magnesium, sulfur  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH725; HSm430-2"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3515","question":"What is a MACRO mineral?","answer":"Mineral that is needed in larger amounts.  (FYI:  Macrominerals are measured in percentage or grams per kilogram.  Microminerals are measured in parts per million or milligrams per kilogram.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH725-1-3; HSm430-2; FCH395"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"jr bonus","number":"3516","question":"Name 3 MACRO minerals.","answer":"Calcium, phosphorus, sodium, chloride, potassium, magnesium, sulfur  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH725; HSm430-2"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3517","question":"Approximately what percent of body calcium is contained in the bones and teeth?","answer":"99%  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH20"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3518","question":"Name 3 functions of calcium in the horse's body.","answer":"Bone or teeth formation, muscle contraction, blood clotting, enzyme action, cell membrane function, temperature regulation, neuromuscular function (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH20; DET45; HSm430-2"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3519","question":"Which mineral aids in muscle contraction, blood clotting, enzyme activation, and bone formation?","answer":"Calcium  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH20; DET45; HSm430-2"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3520","question":"What is a readily available storage location in the body for calcium?","answer":"Skeleton (bones)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH725-1; HSm430-2"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3521","question":"What should the calcium to phosphorus ratio be for horse feeds?","answer":"2 to 1 (accept any ratio within the 1 to 1 to 6 to 1 ratios) [FYI:  The calcium to phosphorus ratio should never be inverted--more phosphorus than calcium.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH750-2; HSm430-2; FCH22"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3522","question":"Phosphorus should NEVER exceed the amount of what mineral in the horse's diet?","answer":"Calcium  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH725-2; HSm430-3"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3523","question":"Steamed bone meal, limestone, and dicalcium phosphate are the most common sources of what TWO minerals?","answer":"Calcium and phosphorus  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm430-4"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3524","question":"What TWO minerals are necessary for proper bone and teeth formation?","answer":"Calcium and phosphorus (also accept magnesium)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH725-1,2; HSm430-2; FCH20"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3525","question":"Give ONE result of having an inverted calcium to phosphorus ratio in a horse's ration.","answer":"Impaired calcium absorption; skeletal abnormalities (such as \"Big Head\" disease)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH725-2; HSm430-3"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3526","question":"What effect does excess dietary phosphorus have on calcium?","answer":"Interferes with calcium absorption (FYI:  Horses with too much phosphorus in the diet can get \"Big Head\" disease.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH725-2; HSm430-3"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3527","question":"Electrolytes are minerals that dissolve in water and are essential for many chemical processes in the body.  Name TWO important electrolytes that are lost in sweat.","answer":"Sodium, chloride, and potassium (FYI:  Electrolytes carry an electric charge and affect the amount of water in the body.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm430-4-6; FCH388"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3528","question":"Name 3 electrolytes that are essential for maintaining fluid balance, nerve and muscle function, and acid-base balance.","answer":"Sodium, chloride, potassium  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH820-2; HSm430-4-6"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3529","question":"Name 3 electrolytes lost in sweat.","answer":"Sodium, chloride, potassium, calcium, magnesium  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm430-4"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3530","question":"Name ONE circumstance when magnesium requirements are high.","answer":"Lactating mares; exercising horses; growing horses  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH725-2; HSm430-4"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3531","question":"Give 3 results of too little magnesium in a horse's diet.","answer":"Nervousness, muscle tremors, muscle cramps, muscle spasms, fatigue, weakness, arrhythmias, increased respiratory rate (tachypnea), ataxia, potential for collapse, death (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH725-2; HSm430-4"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3532","question":"60% of the magnesium in a horse's body is found where?","answer":"Skeleton (bones and teeth)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH725-2"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3533","question":"A mare that has hyperkalemia has an abnormally high level of what electrolyte in her blood?","answer":"Potassium (FYI:  The chemical symbol for potassium is K for Kalium.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm430-6; DET146"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3534","question":"Give TWO signs or symptoms of sodium deficiency.","answer":"Decreased skin turgor, desire to lick sweat-contaminated objects, lowered water intake, loss of appetite (anorexia) [accept any correct answers]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH725-2; HSm430-5"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3535","question":"Sodium plays an important role in the function of which body system of the horse?","answer":"Nervous system  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH725-2"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3536","question":"Name ONE electrolyte that is involved in the maintenance of the acid-base balance and osmotic regulation of body fluids.","answer":"Sodium; chloride  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH725-2; FCH25"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3537","question":"Give 3 signs or symptoms of “salt poisoning”.","answer":"Colic, diarrhea, frequent urination (polyuria), weakness, staggering, paralysis of the hind limbs, excessive thirst (polydipsia) [accept any correct answers]  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH26"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3538","question":"Sweating and lactation are two physiological functions that will increase the free choice consumption of what mineral supplement?","answer":"Salt (sodium chloride)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH27; HSm430-4"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3539","question":"Chloride in the horse's diet is usually accompanied by which other mineral?","answer":"Sodium  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH725-2; HSm430-5"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3540","question":"What TWO minerals are necessary in a horse's diet for the regulation of all body fluids, maintenance of acid-base balance, and the conduction of electrical impulses in nerves and muscles?","answer":"Sodium and chloride  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH25"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3541","question":"Name TWO physiological functions that will increase the natural intake of salt in a horse's diet.","answer":"Sweating and lactation  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH27"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3542","question":"In some animals, chronic consumption of excess sulfur may cause a secondary deficiency of what mineral?","answer":"Copper (FYI:  Acute sulfur toxicity can result in lack of energy, colic, and eventually death.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH725-3; HSm430-6"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3543","question":"Name ONE thing sulfur is necessary for in the horse.","answer":"Production of proteins and enzymes; carbohydrate metabolism; helps insulin function properly (FYI:  Sulfur is found in some amino acids (methionine and cysteine), B-vitamins, heparin, insulin, and chondroitin sulfate.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH725-3; HSm430-6"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3544","question":"What medical condition can iron deficiency cause?","answer":"Anemia (FYI:  Anemia is when the body lacks enough red blood cells or hemoglobin to transport oxygen in the blood.  There are other causes of anemia besides iron deficiency.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH725-4; HSm430-8; DET155"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3545","question":"What are trace or micro minerals?","answer":"Minerals that are required in smaller amounts (FYI:  Macrominerals are measured in percentage or grams per kilogram.  Microminerals are measured in parts per million or milligrams per kilogram.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH725-1; HSm430-2"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3546","question":"Name 3 of the TRACE minerals in trace mineralized salt.","answer":"Zinc, manganese, iron, copper, cobalt, iodine, selenium  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH26"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3547","question":"Name 5 MICRO or trace minerals.","answer":"Copper, zinc, iron, manganese, iodine, selenium, cobalt, fluorine, molybdenum, chromium, silicon  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH725; HSm430-2"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"jr bonus","number":"3548","question":"Name 3 MICRO or trace minerals.","answer":"Copper, zinc, iron, manganese, iodine, selenium, cobalt, fluorine, molybdenum, chromium, silicon  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH725; HSm430-2"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3549","question":"What micromineral is essential for the synthesis of vitamin B12?","answer":"Cobalt (FYI: Vitamin B12 is cobalamin and is synthesized in the hindgut by microbes.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH725-3; HSm430-6"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3550","question":"The Great Lakes basin, Rocky Mountains, Northern Great Plains, upper Mississippi Valley, and Pacific Coast regions are all deficient in iodine.  Name ONE condition that may be caused by this deficiency.","answer":"Hypothyroidism; goiter (also accept cretinism and myxedema which are forms of hypothyroidism)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH34"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3551","question":"What mineral is necessary for proper function of the thyroid gland?","answer":"Iodine (FYI:  Thyroid hormones T3 and T4 (thyroxine) are triiodothyronine and tetraiodothyronine, compounds that contain iodine.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH725-3; HSm430-7; ES138"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3552","question":"What is the primary cause of iron deficiency?","answer":"Blood loss (from parasites or trauma)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH38"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3553","question":"The largest percentage of which mineral is found in the hemoglobin in the horse’s body?","answer":"Iron (FYI:  Iron is found in hemoglobin in the blood, myoglobin in the muscles, ferritin, hemosiderin, and transferrin.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH725-4; HSm430-8; FCH38; DET185"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"intermediate","number":"3554","question":"Which mineral is necessary in the blood to carry oxygen to the body's cells?","answer":"Iron (FYI:  Iron is part of the hemoglobin in red blood cells and it helps attach oxygen to the red blood cell for transport in the body.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH725-4; HSm430-2"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3555","question":"Give 3 signs of selenium toxicity.","answer":"Blind staggers, colic, hair loss (especially from mane and tail), rough hair coat, change in hooves, horizontal hoof cracks, lameness, garlic-odor halitosis, muscle tremors, respiratory problems, death (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH725-4; HSm430-9"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3556","question":"Name TWO states in the US that have excessively selenium-rich soils due to native plants.","answer":"California, Colorado, Idaho, Montana, Oregon, South Dakota, Utah, Wyoming  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH325"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3557","question":"What mineral imbalance results in the condition commonly referred to as “bobtail disease\"?","answer":"Excess selenium (FYI:  Bobtail disease, also called \"alkali disease\", is seen with chronic selenium toxicity.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm430-9; FCH325"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3558","question":"Name ONE cause of selenium toxicity.","answer":"Over supplementation; horses forced to eat selenium-rich plants because adequate feed is not available  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH725-4"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3559","question":"It's important to know if your region's soil is deficient in this mineral before supplementing.  Which mineral is it?","answer":"Selenium  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH725-4; HSm430-9"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3560","question":"Halitosis with an odor of garlic would be an indication of what specific mineral toxicity?","answer":"Selenium (FYI: Halitosis is bad breath.  Acute selenium toxicity can result in “blind staggers”.  Chronic selenium toxicity can result in “bobtail disease\".)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH325; ES142"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3561","question":"By itself, selenium doesn't have much antioxidant capacity. Its antioxidant properties become stronger when it’s paired with which vitamin?","answer":"Vitamin E  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH742-3"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3562","question":"Name ONE problem selenium deficiency causes.","answer":"White muscle disease, myopathy (muscle disease), weakness, encephalopathy (brain disease), tying up, impaired movement (trouble walking), loss of muscular coordination, difficulty in suckling and swallowing, respiratory problems, heart problems  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH730-3; HSm430-9; FCH31"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3563","question":"How is a nutritional calorie defined?","answer":"A “small calorie” is the amount of energy required to raise 1 gram of water 1 degree Celsius. (FYI:  A “large calorie” or kilocalorie is equal to 1000 calories.)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH384"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3564","question":"In a feed analysis, what does “dry matter” mean?","answer":"Matter left in a feed when all the moisture has been removed. (FYI:  Forages may range in dry matter content from 10 – 90%.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm410-1"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3565","question":"2-part question:  What are maltase, sucrase, and lactase and what does each do in the body?","answer":"Sugar-digesting enzymes; maltase breaks down maltose, sucrase breaks down sucrose, and lactase breaks down lactose  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH16"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3566","question":"In the US, are nutritional problems in horses more likely to be associated with overfeeding or underfeeding?","answer":"Overfeeding  <br/> <br/>ref:ES105-106"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3567","question":"When the percentage of moisture, crude fat or ether extract, total minerals or ash, crude fiber, and crude protein are added together and subtracted from 100, the remaining amount is called what?","answer":"Nitrogen free extract (FYI:  NFE is the amount of non-structural, soluble, non-fiber carbohydrates in feed.)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH116"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3568","question":"Name 3 things that many commercial supplements may include.","answer":"Vitamins, minerals, amino acids, protein, carbohydrates, fats, herbs, probiotics, microbials (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH742-1"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3569","question":"Name 3 nutrients that are absorbed in the small intestine.","answer":"Protein, fat, carbohydrates, vitamins—ADEK, minerals (calcium, phosphorus); components of above such as sugars, amino acids, glycerols  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm405-2; ES111"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"intermediate","number":"3570","question":"Give ONE advantage of knowing the amount of nutrients in feed.","answer":"To determine the quality of the feed; to determine if you're feeding your horse the right feed for its needs  <br/> <br/>ref:ES Chapter 7"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3571","question":"Carbohydrates and fats are similar chemically to what TWO fuels?","answer":"Gasoline and oil  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc33"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3572","question":"Name 3 ways in which grains differ NUTRITIONALLY.","answer":"Energy (digestible energy; carbohydrates and fats), proteins (crude protein), dry matter, fiber, vitamins, minerals  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm410-5; HIH742-1"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3574","question":"What element do proteins contain that carbohydrates and fats do not?","answer":"Nitrogen  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH12; DET221"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3575","question":"When comparing the nutrient value of Timothy and orchard grass in a hay sample, which provides the highest percent of crude protein?","answer":"Orchard grass (FYI:  Orchard grass hay has 11.4% CP; Timothy hay has 8.6% CP.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm410-5"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3576","question":"How many amino acids are found in proteins?","answer":"22 amino acids (FYI:  Horse Science page 33 says 22 amino acids.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH720-1; FCH13; ES117"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3577","question":"What are considered to be the building blocks of protein?","answer":"Amino acids  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH720-1; HSm410-3; HSc33; DET10"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3578","question":"Protein is composed of a chain of smaller units called what?","answer":"Amino acids (also accept polypeptides)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH720-1; HSm410-3; HSc33; DET10"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3579","question":"During digestion, proteins are broken down into what?","answer":"Amino acids (also accept polypeptides)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc34"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3580","question":"Where in the horse's digestive tract are amino acids synthesized?","answer":"Large intestine or hindgut (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc31"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3581","question":"What are the \"bricks and mortar\" from which bodies are made?","answer":"Proteins (specifically amino acids)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc33"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3582","question":"How many of the 22 amino acids are essential to the horse?","answer":"10 essential amino acids  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH720-1; HSc33"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3583","question":"What is an essential amino acid?","answer":"Amino acid that must be supplied in the diet  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH720-1; HSc33"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3584","question":"During rapid growth, foals need more of which TWO amino acids?","answer":"Lysine and threonine  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH765-1"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3585","question":"Name 3 essential amino acids.","answer":"Phenylalanine, tryptophan, leucine, isoleucine, lysine, methionine, valine, histidine, threonine, arginine  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH720-1; HSc33"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3586","question":"Name the amino acid that's necessary for growth and milk production.","answer":"Lysine  <br/> <br/>ref:DET173; HSc33"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3587","question":"Which amino acid has been found to be the most essential to the horse?","answer":"Lysine  <br/> <br/>ref:DET173; HSc33"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3588","question":"Which protein supplement contains more lysine than most other vegetable proteins?","answer":"Soybean meal  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm410-3"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3589","question":"Name ONE thing that determines the quality of the proteins.","answer":"Amount of essential amino acids; type and arrangement of amino acids (FYI: The higher the essential amino acids, the higher the quality.)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH13; HSc33"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3590","question":"Protein supplements should contain a good mixture of what?","answer":"Essential amino acids  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH13; HSc33"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3591","question":"Which is higher in protein, alfalfa or corn?","answer":"Alfalfa  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-41; HSm410"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3592","question":"Give ONE reason why a horse might need a protein supplement.","answer":"Horse is not getting enough protein in his current diet (poor quality forage); horse’s protein requirements increase (pregnant, lactating, growing)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc40"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3593","question":"Name 3 results of protein deficiency in horses.","answer":"Poor growth, un-thriftiness, weight loss, poor hair coat, poor hoof growth, decreased performance, decreased endurance, decreased reproduction, decreased milk production, decreased appetite, coprophagia (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH14"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3594","question":"After nitrogen is removed from proteins, what happens to the rest of the molecule?","answer":"It's converted into energy or stored as fat (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH15"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3595","question":"What happens when excess protein is fed?","answer":"Nitrogen is separated from the compound and is excreted in the urine; the rest of the molecule is used for energy.  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH15"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3596","question":"Name 4 elements that make up proteins.","answer":"Carbon, hydrogen, oxygen, nitrogen, sulfur, iron, phosphorus  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc33; HSm430-6; FCH12; ES33"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3597","question":"All proteins contain carbon, hydrogen, nitrogen, and oxygen.  Name ONE other element that some proteins contain.","answer":"Sulfur, phosphorus, or iron  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc33; HSm430-6; FCH12; ES117"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3598","question":"What is \"crude protein\"?","answer":"Total protein content of feed (level of amino acids and total nitrogen) [FYI:  Digestible protein is the amount of protein in feed that can be used by the horse.]  <br/> <br/>ref:DET74; HSm415-3; ES119HSm415-3; DET74"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3599","question":"What is digestible crude protein?","answer":"Amount of protein (nitrogen content) that's available to the horse during digestion  <br/> <br/>ref:ES119"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3600","question":"Name TWO ways protein is used in the horse's body.","answer":"Formation of tissue; formation of muscle; proper functioning of muscles; production of hormones; production of enzymes; production of antibodies; energy source  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH720-1; HIH750-1"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3601","question":"Which nutrient supplies the material from which body tissue is made?","answer":"Protein  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH720-1"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3602","question":"What protein is the key structural component of hair and hoof horn?","answer":"Keratin  <br/> <br/>ref:DET160"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3603","question":"Name 3 parts of the horse’s body that are made of the protein keratin.","answer":"Skin, hair, hooves  <br/> <br/>ref:DET160"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3604","question":"What percent protein is required by yearlings?","answer":"12% – 14% (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH765-2"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3605","question":"The protein requirements are greatest and most critical during what 3 phases of a horse's life?","answer":"Growth, reproduction, and lactation  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH13-14"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3606","question":"Give 3 reasons why it is NOT good to feed horses too much protein.","answer":"Expensive; not good for kidneys; affects acid-base balance; causes calcium imbalance (retention); can't be stored (as protein); increases water loss; produces excessive body heat; increases electrolyte deficiencies  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH720-1; HSm435-5"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3607","question":"A mature, idle horse needs what percentage of crude protein?","answer":"8% – 12% (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH745-5"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3608","question":"A feed containing 10% crude protein and 15% crude fiber would be appropriate for what type of horse?","answer":"Mature idle horse (horse that's not working, growing, or producing)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH745-5"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3609","question":"At weaning time, most foals six months of age should be fed a diet containing what protein level?","answer":"16% (accept any number between 14% – 18%)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH765-1"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3610","question":"Of a weanling, yearling, or two-year-old, which one needs the most protein?","answer":"Weanling (FYI: Weanlings need 14% – 18%, yearlings need 12% – 14%, and mature idle horses need 8% – 12% protein in their diets.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH765-1,2"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3611","question":"Name 3 protein supplements fed to horses.","answer":"Soybean meal, cottonseed meal, Brewer's dried grains, linseed meal, peanut meal, bone meal, fish meal, urea, milk protein (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm410-3; HIH799-1"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3612","question":"Cottonseed meal is used as what in a horse's diet?","answer":"Protein supplement (FYI:  Soybean meal is a higher quality source of protein than cottonseed meal.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm410-3"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3613","question":"What plant provides high quality protein, high levels of lysine, and is used as a common protein supplement?","answer":"Soybean  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH83"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3614","question":"What is the most common protein supplement used in horses?","answer":"Soybean meal  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH741-3; HSm410-3; HSc40"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3615","question":"Determining whether requirements are being met for most nutrients, other than energy, is difficult without doing what?","answer":"Analyzing the diet and comparing it to animal's nutritional requirements.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH755-1"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3616","question":"To formulate or change a horse's diet, you must know what 3 things?","answer":"Animal's nutrient requirements (body weight, physiological status, state of production), nutrient content of feed, amount being fed, amount needed to provide the nutrients  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm435-1; FCH113"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3617","question":"Name TWO ways you can use Nutrition Requirement Tables.","answer":"Check to see if ration being fed is balanced; formulate an adequate ration for your horse.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc42"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3618","question":"Why should overweight and underweight horses be fed separately?","answer":"So you can control or monitor the amount of feed each horse gets  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH790-3"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3619","question":"Horses can be divided into classes relative to their nutritional requirements.  Name 3 of these classes.","answer":"Maintenance (mature idle), working (exercising), producing (stallions, pregnant mares, lactating mares), growing  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH735-1; HSm435-2"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3620","question":"Name ONE nutrient exercising horses need more of than non-exercising horses.","answer":"Energy, water, electrolytes (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH755-1"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3621","question":"Name ONE result of energy deficiency in young animals.","answer":"Slow growth, poor condition, fatigue, weight loss  <br/> <br/>ref:ES144"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3622","question":"Name TWO nutrient requirements that are doubled during lactation.","answer":"Water and energy  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH231; HIH760-1"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3623","question":"Water, trace mineralized salt, and good pasture or good quality hay can supply all needed nutrients for what type of horse?","answer":"Mature idle horse (mature horse that's not growing, reproducing, or working hard)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH186"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3624","question":"When are the nutrient requirements of pregnant mares greatly increased?","answer":"Last 3 months of pregnancy (third trimester)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm530-2; HIH760-2"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3625","question":"Name ONE nutrient deficiency that can predispose foals to Developmental Orthopedic Disease (DOD).","answer":"Calcium, phosphorus, copper (FYI:  It is no longer thought that overfeeding protein causes DOD.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH765-1; HIH720-2"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3626","question":"Give 3 reasons for increasing the amount of dietary fat in an athletic horse’s diet.","answer":"Fats are more energy-dense; safer to add fats than to increase grain; easier for horse to cool itself (adding fat instead of carbohydrates decreases heat production in the hindgut); glycogen-sparing effect (doesn’t use glycogen stores in the muscles)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH755-2; FCH197"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3627","question":"Name ONE factor that influences a horse's nutritional requirements.","answer":"Age, size, exercise, fever, illness, injury, temperature, humidity, growth, pregnancy, lactation, breed, metabolic rate, individual differences (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH120-3; HSm150-2; HIH715-3,4; FCH186-87"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3628","question":"Name 4 factors that influence a horse’s nutritional requirements.","answer":"Age, size, exercise, fever, illness, injury, temperature, humidity, growth, pregnancy, lactation, breed, metabolic rate, individual differences (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH120-3; HSm150-2; HIH715-3,4; FCH186-87"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3629","question":"Give ONE reason why some older horses may have higher energy requirements.","answer":"Older horses may have problems chewing, digesting, and/or absorbing nutrients.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH770-1; FCH191"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3630","question":"What is the name of the residue remaining in feeds after complete burning of the organic material?","answer":"Ash (FYI:  Ash is the mineral portion of a feed.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET16; FCH381"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3631","question":"What is cellulose?","answer":"Plant fiber (complex carbohydrates in the cell walls of plants) [FYI:  ADF or acid detergent fiber is composed of cellulose, lignin, and other poorly digested components of feeds.]  <br/> <br/>ref:DET52; FCH385; HIH785-3;"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3632","question":"When reading a feed tag, the percent of crude fiber is the best indicator of what?","answer":"Energy content (FYI: The higher the crude fiber, the lower the digestible energy)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH745-3"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3633","question":"Would a feed with a 2% or 5% crude fiber have a higher digestible energy?","answer":"Feed with 2% crude fiber (FYI: The lower the crude fiber, the higher the digestible energy)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH745-3"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3634","question":"In feed analysis, what do the initials DE stand for?","answer":"Digestible Energy (FYI:  Grains have 50 – 60% more digestible energy per pound than hay.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH750-1; HSm410-2; FCH9"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3635","question":"What is the term for the digestible organic nutrients such as protein, fiber, nitrogen-free extract, and fat?","answer":"TDN or Total Digestible Nutrients  <br/> <br/>ref:DET263,271"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"intermediate","number":"3636","question":"In reference to feeds, what is TDN?","answer":"Total Digestible Nutrients  <br/> <br/>ref:DET263,271"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3637","question":"Name TWO types of nutrients needed by horses.","answer":"Water, carbohydrates, fats, protein, vitamins, minerals (also accept energy instead of carbohydrates or fats)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm410-1; HSc32; FCH-Ch1"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"jr bonus","number":"3638","question":"Name 3 types of nutrients needed by horses.","answer":"Water, carbohydrates, fats, protein, vitamins, minerals (also accept energy instead of carbohydrates or fats)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm410-1; HSc32; FCH-Ch1"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3639","question":"Name 5 types of nutrients needed by horses.","answer":"Water, carbohydrates, fats, protein, vitamins, minerals (also accept energy instead of carbohydrates or fats)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm410-1; HSc32; FCH-Ch1"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3640","question":"In reference to chemical makeup, what kind of compounds are vitamins?","answer":"Organic compounds (FYI:  Organic compounds contain carbon, hydrogen, and oxygen.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH730-1"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3641","question":"Give 3 reasons horses would need supplemental vitamins.","answer":"Prolonged drug therapy, high grain low forage diet, poor quality hay, stress, poor diet, heavy exercise, nervous horse, diseases (such as anemia), vitamin deficiencies (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm430; FCH43-44"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3642","question":"Name TWO vitamins that are found in green, leafy forages.","answer":"Vitamin A, vitamin E, vitamin K, B vitamins (FYI:  Horses get vitamin D from sunlight; vitamin K and some B vitamins are produced in the large intestine; vitamin C is produced in the liver.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm430-10-12, 14; HIH730-3"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3643","question":"Name 3 vitamins and give ONE thing each does in the horse's body.","answer":"Vitamin A—helps with vision, immune response; Vitamin B—most help with enzyme processes; Vitamin C—antioxidant; Vitamin D—calcium absorption and balance; Vitamin E—antioxidant; Vitamin K—blood clotting, bone metabolism, vascular health  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH730; HSm430; HSc34,35"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"intermediate","number":"3644","question":"What is one of the most unstable nutritional components of hay?","answer":"Vitamins  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-12"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3645","question":"What is the name of the essential organic compounds that are needed in small amounts by the horse?","answer":"Vitamins (FYI: Minerals are needed in small amounts, but they are not organic compounds.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH730-3; HSc34; FCH42"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3646","question":"How do vitamins differ from minerals?","answer":"Vitamins are organic (FYI:  Organic compounds contain carbon, hydrogen, and oxygen.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc34,35; HIH730-1; FCH42"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3647","question":"2-part question:  What vitamins are essential in the horse's diet and why?","answer":"A and E; because they can't be synthesized in the body  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH730-2; HSm430-10,11; FCH42"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3648","question":"Give TWO reasons why a horse might need supplemental vitamins.","answer":"Growing, working, producing (pregnant or lactating), stress, lack of vitamins in diet (poor quality forage, etc.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm430-10"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3649","question":"Name the two GENERAL TYPES of vitamins.","answer":"Fat soluble and water soluble (FYI: Fat soluble vitamins are ADEK; water soluble vitamins are B and C.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH730-1; HSm430-10; HSc34"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3650","question":"Why is an excess of fat-soluble vitamins more detrimental than an excess of water-soluble ones?","answer":"Water soluble vitamins are easily excreted from the body (fat soluble vitamins can be stored in the liver or in the fat).  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm430-10; HSc34; FCH42"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3651","question":"Name the 4 fat-soluble vitamins.","answer":"A D E K  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH730-1; HSm430-10; HSc35"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3652","question":"What is required in the diet to aid in the absorption of vitamins A, D, E, and K?","answer":"Fat  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH730-1; HSm430-10; HSc35; HSm405-1"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"jr bonus","number":"3653","question":"Name the 4 fat-soluble vitamins.","answer":"A D E K  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH730-1; HSm430-10; HSc35"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3654","question":"What is the precursor of Vitamin A?","answer":"Carotene (beta-carotene)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm415-1; HSm430-10; HIH730-5; ES123; FCH46"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3655","question":"What yellow pigment found in plant material is used to form Vitamin A in the horse?","answer":"Carotene (beta-carotene)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm415-1; HSm430-10; HIH730-2; ES123"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3656","question":"Give ONE reason why carotene may be lost in hay.","answer":"Carotenes are destroyed during the sun-curing process when making hay (FYI: The slow drying of forages in the sun can cause loss of up to 80%); carotene is lost during winter storage (FYI: Carotene is easily oxidized.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm415-1; HSm430-10; HIH730-2; HSc35"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3657","question":"What is carotene?","answer":"Plant pigment that is converted to Vitamin A. (FYI:  The precursor beta-carotene must be consumed in the diet.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm415-1; HSm430-10; HIH730-2; FCH45"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3658","question":"Name 3 symptoms of Vitamin A deficiency.","answer":"Night blindness, excessive tearing; reduced feed intake, decreased growth rate, reproductive problems; abnormal hair coat (accept any correct answers) [FYI:  Eye problems only occur after prolonged, severe deficiency.]  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH47,48; HSm430-11; HIH730-2"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3659","question":"Lack of what nutrient can cause a horse to go blind?","answer":"Vitamin A (FYI:  Eye problems only occur after prolonged, severe deficiency.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH730-2; HSm430-10; HSc35"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3660","question":"Deficiency of what vitamin is rare if good quality hay or pasture is available?","answer":"Vitamin A (FYI:  The plant pigment beta-carotene is present in the leaves of plants.  Horses convert beta-carotene into Vitamin A.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm430-10; HSc35"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3661","question":"Name TWO things vitamin A does in the horse's body.","answer":"Needed for vision (especially night vision); needed for healthy skin, muscles, and bones; needed for a healthy immune system; involved in reproductive function; antioxidant  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc35; DET284; HIH730-2; HSm430-10; ES123"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3662","question":"Horses get what vitamin from beta-carotene in green grass?","answer":"Vitamin A  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH730-2; HSm430-10; HSc35"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3663","question":"Which vitamin is higher in green forages than in hay?","answer":"Vitamin A (FYI:  The pigment beta-carotene that is present in green forage leaves is a precursor to vitamin A.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH730-2; HSm430-10; HSc35"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3664","question":"Name ONE function of Vitamin D in the horse's body.","answer":"Bone development, bone strength, calcium absorption, calcium and phosphorus balance, mineral balance (increases absorption of microminerals)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm430-11; HIH730-3; HSc35"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3665","question":"Name 3 functions of Vitamin D in the horse's body.","answer":"Bone development, bone strength, calcium absorption, calcium and phosphorus balance, mineral balance (increases absorption of microminerals)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm430-11; HIH730-3; HSc35"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3666","question":"Vitamin D regulates the absorption of what important mineral?","answer":"Calcium (also accept phosphorus)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm430-11; HIH730-3; HSc35"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3667","question":"Which vitamin is responsible for the strength and proper development of the bones?","answer":"Vitamin D  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm430-11; HIH730-3; HSc35"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3668","question":"What is rickets?","answer":"Weak, deformed bones due to deficiency of calcium, phosphorus, or vitamin D  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH730-2; HSm430-11; DET234"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3669","question":"Name ONE way horses get Vitamin D.","answer":"Through sunlight or sun-cured hay  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm430-11; HIH730-3; HSc35"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3670","question":"Why would horses stalled 24 hours a day need supplemental vitamin D?","answer":"Vitamin D comes from sunlight; if they're in the stall, they're not in the sun.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm430-11; HIH730-1,3; HSc35"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3671","question":"Decreased immune function is associated with what vitamin deficiency?","answer":"Vitamin E  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH730-3; HSm430-11"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3672","question":"The lack of which VITAMIN can cause white muscle disease?","answer":"Vitamin E  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH730-3; HSm430-11"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3673","question":"A deficiency of Vitamin E can cause white muscle disease.  What general age horse does this predominantly affect?","answer":"Young horses (horses less than 11 months)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH730-3; HSm430-11"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3674","question":"Name TWO things vitamin E does in the body.","answer":"Antioxidant (maintains and protects cell membranes from oxidation), enhances immunity, involved in DNA production, enhances absorption and storage of Vitamin A  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm430-11,12; HIH730-2,3"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3675","question":"Name ONE forage that is a good source of Vitamin E.","answer":"Alfalfa, orchard grass, fescue, Timothy  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH730-2,3"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3676","question":"Name 3 forms of Vitamin E that occur in nature.","answer":"Alpha-tocopherol (most common and most biologically active form), beta-tocopherol, gamma-tocopherol, delta-tocopherol, alpha-tocotrienol, beta-tocotrienol, gamma-tocotrienol, delta-tocotrienol  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH730-2; HSm430-11"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3677","question":"Alpha-tocopherol is the most common form and the most biologically active form of which Vitamin?","answer":"Vitamin E (FYI:  Vitamin E is present in nature as alpha, beta, gamma, and delta tocopherols and alpha, beta, gamma, and delta tocotrienols.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH730-2; HSm430-11"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3678","question":"Which VITAMIN is essential for blood clotting?","answer":"Vitamin K  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH730-3; HSm430-12,13; FCH50"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3679","question":"Which TWO vitamins are water soluble?","answer":"Vitamin C and B vitamins (B complex)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH730-1; HSm430-10"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3680","question":"Which vitamin is not needed in the horse's diet, but a lack of it in human diets causes scurvy?","answer":"Vitamin C (FYI:  Horses produce an enzyme in their liver that converts glucose into vitamin C.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm430-13; FCH60"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3681","question":"What vitamins are synthesized in the large intestine?","answer":"B vitamins  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH730-1,2; HSm430-13,14"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3682","question":"Give TWO reasons Vitamin B rarely needs to be supplemented in horses’ diets.","answer":"Good quality hay is an excellent source; significant amounts are produced in the horse’s intestines.  <br/> <br/>ref:ES126-129"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3683","question":"Name TWO B vitamins that brans contain.","answer":"Thiamine (B1) and Niacin (B3)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc31"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3684","question":"Name 4 B vitamins by name or number.","answer":"Vitamin B1—thiamine; vitamin B2—riboflavin; vitamin B3—niacin; vitamin B5—pantothenic acid; vitamin B6—pyridoxine; vitamin B7—biotin; vitamin B9—folate (folic acid); vitamin B12—cobalamin  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm430-13,14; FCH52-57; ES126"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3685","question":"Give the scientific name for 3 of the B vitamins.","answer":"Vitamin B1—thiamine; vitamin B2—riboflavin; vitamin B3—niacin; vitamin B5—pantothenic acid; vitamin B6—pyridoxine; vitamin B7—biotin; vitamin B9—folate (folic acid); vitamin B12—cobalamin  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm430-13,14; FCH52-57; ES126-27"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3686","question":"What forage has the highest concentration of biotin?","answer":"Alfalfa (FYI: Biotin is Vitamin B7.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH730-2; FCH413"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3687","question":"Supplementation with what SPECIFIC vitamin has been reported to cause a temporary growth increase in some horses with debilitated hooves?","answer":"Biotin (FYI: Vitamin A is necessary for the growth and development of normal hooves.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH505-6; FCH56,291"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3688","question":"In what TWO areas of the body is thiamin converted to its active form?","answer":"Kidneys and liver (FYI:  Thiamine is Vitamin B1.)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH52"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3689","question":"What nutrient is vital to life and is essential for all body systems?","answer":"Water  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH710-1; HSc32"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3690","question":"What is the most essential, easily available, and often overlooked nutrient?","answer":"Water  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-7"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3691","question":"How do suckling foals meet the majority of their water needs?","answer":"By drinking the mare's milk  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH710-1"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3692","question":"There are many tasks that water performs in the body.  Name 3.","answer":"Necessary for life, transports nutrients to cells, transports waste from cells, makes up most of the blood, regulates body temperature, acts as a lubricant, necessary in most of the body's chemical reactions (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc32"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3693","question":"Give ONE advantage to hand-watering your horse or letting it drink from a bucket instead of an automatic waterer.","answer":"You can monitor how much they drink; most horses prefer to drink from a bucket; horses tend to drink more at one watering when drinking from a bucket (FYI:  Horses tend to drink more often from an automatic waterer.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH710-2"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"jr bonus","number":"3694","question":"Excluding the age and size of the horse, name 3 factors that affect the water requirements for horses.","answer":"Exercise, sweating, temperature, humidity, fever, illness, specific diseases like Cushing's, lactation, amount of food, type of food, individual variations, medications such as Lasix (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH710-1; HSm305-7; HSc32"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3695","question":"Excluding the age and size of the horse, name 5 factors that affect the water requirements for horses.","answer":"Exercise, sweating, temperature, humidity, fever, illness, specific diseases like Cushing's, lactation, amount of food, type of food, individual variations, medications such as Lasix (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH710-1; HSm305-7; HSc32"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3696","question":"The water intake of individual horses with the same diet and under the same environmental and exercise conditions may vary by how much?","answer":"Up to 50%  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH710-1"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"3697","question":"Name 3 ways insects and other arthropods adversely affect their hosts.","answer":"Suck blood, feed on mucous discharges, spread diseases, cause pain, cause sores, interfere with digestion cause slow growth, frighten enough to cause injury, hurt ears so it’s hard to halter, make horses restless or ill at ease  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-1; HSc52"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"3698","question":"Name 4 GENERAL TYPES of external parasites that infest horses.","answer":"Flies, lice, mites, ticks, and ringworm (fungi)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415; HSm320"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"jr bonus","number":"3699","question":"Name 3 GENERAL TYPES of external parasites that infest horses.","answer":"Flies, lice, mites, ticks, and ringworm (fungi)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415; HSm320"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3700","question":"How many pairs of wings do adult flies have?","answer":"1 (one) pair of wings  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-1; HSm320-1 picture"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3701","question":"What are some of the most persistent pests of horses?","answer":"Flies  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-1; HSm320-1"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3702","question":"In reference to external parasites, what is \"sweet itch\"?","answer":"Allergic reaction to the (Culicoides) biting midge’s saliva (FYI:  Sweet itch is also called “Summer Itch” and Summer Seasonal Recurrent Dermatitis or SSRD.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm320-2; HSm355-6"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"3703","question":"Name TWO prerequisites for successful completion of the life cycle of house flies and stable flies.","answer":"Breeding materials, moisture, warmth  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-3; HSm320-2"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3704","question":"Name ONE non-chemical means of breaking the fly's life cycle.","answer":"Good sanitation, removing breeding materials (such as manure or soiled hay or straw), controlling moisture, mechanical control (such as using screens, fans, or fly tapes), biological control (such as parasitic wasps)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-3; HSm320-2"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3705","question":"Not including on the horse's body, name ONE location where external parasites lay their eggs.","answer":"Manure, decomposing hay or straw (stable flies), still or slow-moving water (mosquitoes), vegetation in moist areas (horse flies and deer flies), moving water (black flies), fresh cattle manure (face flies and horn flies), dead tissue (blow flies)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-1,2"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"3706","question":"Other than good sanitation, name 3 types of fly control.","answer":"Baits, foggers, mists, fly spray, fly tapes or strips, fly wipes, biological control (parasitic wasps) [accept any correct answers]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-3; HSm320-2-4"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"intermediate","number":"3707","question":"Give ONE reason why is it more difficult to control face flies than stable flies and house flies.","answer":"Face flies feed on the face where it's difficult to apply insecticide; face flies only land on the horse for a short period each day  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-4"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"intermediate","number":"3708","question":"Name ONE non-chemical way to keep flies out of areas such as feed rooms, tack rooms, and box stalls.","answer":"Use screens or fans  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-3; HSm320-3"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3709","question":"When using parasitic wasps or fly predators for fly control, what must be done to remain effective?","answer":"Must re-apply at set intervals  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-3; HSm320-3"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"3710","question":"What is meant by \"biological control\" of pests such as flies?","answer":"Using other insects (such as parasitic wasps) to break the life cycle  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-3; HSm320-3"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"3711","question":"Name 3 areas that are commonly missed when cleaning up horse properties to help with fly control.","answer":"Around fence posts, outside or under fences, feeders or hayracks, corners of stalls, around silos or other feed storage areas, around water source areas  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-3"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"novice","number":"3712","question":"The best way to control flies is to keep the barn what?","answer":"Clean (Remove breeding materials such as manure and soiled hay and bedding.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-3; HSm320-2"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3713","question":"Removal of manure and soiled bedding is a major factor in controlling what external parasite?","answer":"Flies  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-3; HSm320-2"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3714","question":"Why can continual use of insecticides to control flies have the opposite effect?","answer":"Flies can develop a resistance to the insecticide.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-3; HSm320-3"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"3715","question":"What is the most common form of commercial fly bait?","answer":"Granules (FYI:  Baits are best used as a supplement to other control efforts.  Fly bait is only effective against house flies.  It will NOT kill stable flies.  Fly bait must be kept away from horses, other livestock, pets, and children.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-4"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3716","question":"Overuse or continual use of insecticides can cause flies to develop what?","answer":"Resistance (FYI:  Good sanitation is VERY important for interrupting the life cycle of the fly.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-4; HSm320-3"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3717","question":"Who should you contact for information on recommended insecticides for your area?","answer":"Your vet or County Extension Office  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-8"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"jr bonus","number":"3718","question":"Name the 4 stages of the fly's life cycle.","answer":"Egg, larva, pupa, and adult  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-1"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"3719","question":"Name the 4 stages of the fly's life cycle.","answer":"Egg, larva, pupa, and adult  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-1"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"3720","question":"In reference to parasites, what is a larva?","answer":"Immature, worm-like developmental stage of certain parasites  <br/> <br/>ref:DET164"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"3721","question":"In reference to parasites, what is a maggot?","answer":"Larva of an insect (such as a fly)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET174; FCH167"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"3722","question":"In reference to parasites, what is a pupa? (pronounced PEW-pah)","answer":"Life cycle stage of an insect between the larval and adult stages  <br/> <br/>ref:DET223; HSc56"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"jr bonus","number":"3723","question":"Name 3 types of flies that are pests to horses.","answer":"House fly, stable fly, face fly, horn fly, horse fly, deer fly, yellow fly, black fly, mosquito, gnat, sand fly or biting midge, bot fly  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-1,2; HSm320-1,2"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"novice","number":"3724","question":"Name ONE type of fly that is a pest to horses.","answer":"House fly, stable fly, face fly, horn fly, horse fly, deer fly, yellow fly, black fly, mosquito, gnat, sand fly or biting midge, bot fly  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-1,2; HSm320-1,2"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"3725","question":"Name 5 types of flies that are pests to horses.","answer":"House fly, stable fly, face fly, horn fly, horse fly, deer fly, yellow fly, black fly, mosquito, gnat, sand fly or biting midge, bot fly  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-1,2; HSm320-1,2"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"3726","question":"2-part question:  Which fly, the house fly or the stable fly, is a more severe pest to horses and why?","answer":"Stable flies; because they have painful bites and they suck blood  <br/> <br/>ref:HIS415-1; HSm320-1"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"3727","question":"Which external parasite usually feeds on the inside ear folds and may cause a horse to be head shy?","answer":"Black flies or buffalo gnats (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-2; HSm320-2"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"3728","question":"What is another name for black flies?","answer":"Buffalo gnats  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-2; HSm320-2"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3729","question":"Where on a horse do black flies feed?","answer":"Inside the ears  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-2; HSm320-2"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"intermediate","number":"3730","question":"Name ONE way to prevent black flies from feeding in a horse’s ears besides using pesticides such as fly spray or wipes.","answer":"Put petroleum jelly (Vaseline) on the inside of their ears; use a fly mask with ear coverings.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-4"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3731","question":"Which flies lay eggs in dead tissues or wounds?","answer":"Blowflies  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH167"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3732","question":"What fly hovers about the horse, quickly darts toward the animal, and glues individual eggs to the hair in a matter of seconds?","answer":"Bot fly  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-4,5"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"intermediate","number":"3733","question":"What fly feeds on the mucous secretions from the horse's eyes and nostrils?","answer":"Face fly (FYI:  The face fly is Musca autumnalis and its principal host is cattle.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-2; HSm320-1"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"3734","question":"What do face flies feed on?","answer":"Mucous secretions from the horse's eyes and nostrils  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-2; HSm320-1"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"3735","question":"Where do FACE FLIES lay their eggs?","answer":"Very fresh cattle manure  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-2"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3736","question":"Give ONE name for ADULT cattle grubs.","answer":"Heel flies or bomb flies (FYI: They are large, hairy flies that are prevalent from late May through June that resemble honeybees. The larvae are called cattle grubs and they penetrate the skin and migrate through the connective tissue.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-5; HSm320-4"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"intermediate","number":"3737","question":"Name TWO flies that have bayonet-like mouthparts.","answer":"Horse fly and deer fly  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-2; HSm320-2"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3738","question":"Name ONE type of fly that is known for the female's painful bite.","answer":"Horse fly, deer fly, or yellow fly  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-2; HSm320-2"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"3739","question":"How big is a horse fly?","answer":"1/3 – 1 inch long (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-2"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"3740","question":"What is a Tabanid?","answer":"Horse fly  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-2"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"intermediate","number":"3741","question":"Where do HORSE flies deposit their eggs?","answer":"Plants near water (Do NOT accept manure.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-2"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"3742","question":"Both house flies and stable flies act as intermediate hosts for what parasite?","answer":"Stomach worms (Habronema species)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-1; HSm320-2"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3743","question":"Name ONE time of the day when mosquitos are most active.","answer":"Dusk or dawn  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-2; HSm320-5"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"3744","question":"Name 3 ways to reduce your horse's exposure to mosquitos.","answer":"Keep stabled at night, keep stable lights off, place incandescent bulbs 50 yards from the stables to attract mosquitoes, eliminate breeding grounds, clean water troughs weekly, remove birds, use mosquito repellent (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH665-2; HSm320-5"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"novice","number":"3745","question":"Name ONE way to reduce your horse's exposure to mosquitos.","answer":"Keep stabled at night, keep stable lights off, place incandescent bulbs 50 yards from the stables to attract mosquitoes, eliminate breeding grounds, clean water troughs weekly, remove birds, use mosquito repellent (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH665-2; HSm320-5"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3746","question":"Give ONE other name for biting midges.","answer":"Punkies, no-see-ums, or sand flies  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-2; HSm320-2"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3747","question":"Where do STABLE FLIES prefer to lay their eggs?","answer":"In rotting hay or straw mixed with horse or cattle urine or feces  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-1"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3748","question":"What part of the horse do stable flies bite?","answer":"Legs (especially the lower front legs)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-1; HSm320-1"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3749","question":"What is the scientific name for the stable fly?","answer":"Stomoxys calcitrans (pronounced stoe-MOX-is CAL-si-trans)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-1; HSm320-1"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3750","question":"What parasite causes ringworm?","answer":"Fungus (FYI:  Horses with ringworm have circular, hairless, crusted areas.  Ringworm is called dermatophytosis.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm355-8"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"3751","question":"Name TWO treatments for ringworm in horses.","answer":"Isolate infected horse, use antifungal shampoo or medicine, disinfect equipment, clip excess hair, remove hard crusts, apply Betadine solution, apply Nolvasan scrub, use white vinegar solution (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH168; ES187"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"intermediate","number":"3752","question":"Ringworm is caused by a fungus, NOT a worm.  Give 3 features of ringworm lesions.","answer":"Lesions are circular, hairless, and crusted and can be found on the face, trunk, and pasterns.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm355-8"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"intermediate","number":"3753","question":"Name ONE way lice can be spread from one horse to another.","answer":"Direct horse to horse contact; indirect contact (carried on harness, saddle, blanket, brushes, etc.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-5; ES186; HSc53"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"jr bonus","number":"3754","question":"Name 3 areas of the horse where lice are usually first noticed.","answer":"Head, mane, neck, and tail  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-6; HSm320-6"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"intermediate","number":"3755","question":"Give ONE reason why lice can be more problematic in horses in the winter.","answer":"Heavy hair coat; drier skin; biting lice prefer longer hair  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-6; HSm355-15"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3756","question":"A horse that has pediculosis is infested with what type of external parasite?","answer":"Lice (FYI:  Lice come in two types, biting and sucking.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm320-6; FCH399"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"3757","question":"How long can horse lice live off their host?","answer":"3 – 7 days (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:ES186; HSc40"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3758","question":"In reference to parasites, what are nits?","answer":"Lice eggs  <br/> <br/>ref:ES186; HSc53"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3759","question":"Where do adult lice attach their eggs?","answer":"Lice eggs or nits are glued to the hair (close to the skin).  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-6; HSm320-6"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"3760","question":"Name 3 symptoms of lice infestation.","answer":"Unthrifty appearance, hair loss, scruffy skin, unkempt coat, itching (pruritus), rubbing, scratching, biting (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-6; HSm320-6"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"3761","question":"Name 3 treatments for lice in horses.","answer":"Insecticides (permethrin), dewormers (Ivermectin or Moxidectin), dandruff shampoos (keratolytic, selenium sulfide), clip long hair, prevent spread by washing equipment, repeat treatments as recommended by vet (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-6; ES186"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"3762","question":"Name the TWO general kinds of lice.","answer":"Biting and sucking (FYI: Biting lice are Bovicola equi and sucking lice are Haematopinus asini.  Life infestation is called pediculosis.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-6; HSm320-6"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"3763","question":"What small arthropod burrows into the skin and causes mange?  Mange is also called \"itch\" or \"scab\".","answer":"Mite [FYI:  Several types of mites cause mange in horses—Sarcoptes (least common in horses and most severe type), Psoroptes (scab or wet mange), Chorioptes (leg mange; most common type in horses), and Demodex (very common in some areas).]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-8; HSm320-5; DET175"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3764","question":"Where are the eggs, larvae, and nymphs of sarcoptic mites found?","answer":"Under the skin (FYI:  Sarcoptic mange:  least common type in horses; most severe type; psoroptic mange:  “scab” or “wet mange”; chorioptic mange:  “leg mange”; most common type in horses; Demodex:  most common in some areas)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-8"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3765","question":"How is a mange infestation verified?","answer":"By skin scrapings (FYI:  Skin scrapings are looked at under the microscope.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-8; HSm355-4"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"3766","question":"Name 3 symptoms of mange.","answer":"Irritation, itching, inflammation, loss of hair, sores, moist appearance (some types), crusty scabs (some types), skin folding, skin thickening, lumps or hard knots under the skin, restlessness, weight loss, weakness (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-8; HSm320-5; E187"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"intermediate","number":"3767","question":"Irritation, itching, loss of hair, and sometimes crusty scab formation are symptoms of what condition caused by mites?","answer":"Mange (FYI:  Mange is caused by mites.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-8; HSm320-5; ES187"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"3768","question":"Because mites are difficult to treat, it’s important to confirm a diagnosis by skin scrapings.  After a diagnosis is confirmed, name 3 treatments for mange in horses.","answer":"Isolate infected horses, don’t share tack, disinfect tack, use insecticides (permethrin, lime-sulfur solutions), use de-wormers (Ivermectin), use special shampoos, clip long hair, may use steroids for pruritus (itching) [accept any correct answers]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-8"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"3769","question":"Name 3 types of mites that cause mange in horses.","answer":"Sarcoptes (sahr-COP-tees), Psoroptes (sore-OP-tees), Chorioptes (core-ee-OPT-tees), Demodex  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-7,8; HSm320-5,6"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3770","question":"Which type of mite causes foot or leg mange?","answer":"Chorioptes (core-ee-OP-tees)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-8; HSm320-5; HSm355-8; FCH168"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3771","question":"Which mite causes lumps or knots under the skin?","answer":"Demodex (FYI:  Demodex lives in skin pores and does not cause scabs in horses like the other 3 types of mange.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-8; DET78"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3772","question":"Which mite causes \"wet mange\"?","answer":"Psorptic or Psoroptes equi (sore-AHP-tic or sore-AHP-tees) [Psoroptic mites do NOT burrow beneath the skin.  They feed by breaking the skin which causes an exudate or leakage that hardens and covers the feeding mites.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-8; HSm320-5"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3773","question":"Which type of mange is not very common in horses, but is the most severe with intense itching, weakness, and weight loss?","answer":"Sarcoptic mange (FYI:  Sarcoptic and demodectic mange are the most common types in dogs, but they are caused by different species in horses.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm320-6"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"3774","question":"Not relating to specific diseases, name 3 symptoms of heavy tick infestations.","answer":"Anorexia (loss of appetite), depression, weight loss, blood loss (anemia), tick-bite paralysis (caused by neurotoxins in saliva), debilitation (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-6,7"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3775","question":"What do ticks feed on?","answer":"Blood  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-6"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"intermediate","number":"3776","question":"In reference to ticks, what is molting?","answer":"Shedding of the skin to transition from one stage to the next (FYI:  There are 4 life cycle stages of the tick—egg, 6-legged larva or “seed tick”, 8-legged nymph, and adult.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc54; HSc56; FCH160"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3777","question":"Name ONE type of tick that infests horse’s ears and may cause them to be head shy.","answer":"Cayenne tick, Gulf Coast tick, tropical horse tick, spinose ear tick  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-6,7; HSm320-5"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"3778","question":"Name 3 types of ticks that can transmit infectious diseases to horses.","answer":"Eastern Blacklegged/deer/bear and Western Blacklegged ticks (transmit Lyme disease and Equine Granulocytic Ehrlichiosis/EGE), Lone Star tick (EGE), Tropical Horse tick (Equine Piroplasmosis)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-6,7; HSm320-5"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3779","question":"Name ONE species of tick that causes “tick-bite paralysis” in horses and transmits Rocky Mountain Spotted Fever in humans.","answer":"American dog tick and the Rocky Mountain wood tick (FYI:  Both secrete a salivary neurotoxin that can cause paralysis, starvation, and death.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-7; HSm320-5"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3780","question":"Name ONE tick that is a vector for Lyme disease.","answer":"Eastern blacklegged tick (deer tick, bear tick, or Ixodes scapularis); Western blacklegged tick (Ixodes pacificus) [pronounced icks-OH-dees]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-7; HSm320-5"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3781","question":"Which tick is a vector for Equine Piroplasmosis?","answer":"Tropical horse tick (FYI:  Equine Piroplasmosis is an infectious disease that can cause multiple symptoms—fever, anorexia, weight loss, hemolytic anemia, jaundice, hemoglobinuria, edema, labored breathing, neurological problems, etc.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-7; HSm320-5"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3782","question":"What type of tick infests animals with long, heavy hair coats making the ticks hard to find?  Heavy infestations can cause anorexia, depression, weight loss, swollen abdomen, and debilitation.","answer":"Winter tick  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-7"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3783","question":"As a rule of thumb, about 20% of the horses in any herd are responsible for what percent of internal parasite egg production?","answer":"80% (FYI:  Up to 50% of horses in a herd are able to maintain relatively low strongyle egg counts without being de-wormed.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-9"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3784","question":"The tendency of some horses to harbor large numbers of internal parasites and, therefore, shed large egg amounts is due to what?","answer":"Genetic traits  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-9"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3785","question":"How does dragging, harrowing, or mowing pastures kill internal parasites?","answer":"Breaks up manure piles and exposes larvae to sun and high temperatures which kill them. (FYI:  Pastures should only be dragged during hot, dry conditions.  Dragging in autumn leaves the pasture contaminated all winter.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-6"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3786","question":"In reference to parasites, what can happen if too many horses are kept on a small pasture?","answer":"Horse can get worms.  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH162; HIH430-6"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3787","question":"Give ONE reason why horses should never be fed on the ground.","answer":"Horses can get parasites; horses can eat sand and develop colic.  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH162; HIH430-6"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3788","question":"Which is more important in parasite control, treatment or prevention?","answer":"Prevention  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc59"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"jr bonus","number":"3789","question":"Besides deworming, name 3 management practices that decrease internal parasites in herds.","answer":"Clean barns, compost manure, drag pastures (in the summer), don’t feed on the ground, provide clean water, don’t overgraze, don’t overstock, remove bot eggs, have vet do fecal egg counts (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH162; HSc58,59; HIH430; HSm325"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"3790","question":"Besides deworming, name 4 management practices that decrease internal parasites in herds.","answer":"Clean barns, compost manure, drag pastures (in the summer), don’t feed on the ground, provide clean water, don’t overgraze, don’t overstock, remove bot eggs, have vet do fecal egg counts (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH162; HSc58,59; HIH430; HSm325"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"jr bonus","number":"3791","question":"Describe 3 general stages of the life cycle of internal parasites.","answer":"Eggs, larvae (several stages), immature worms, adults  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430; HSm325"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3792","question":"To decrease internal parasites in your herd, what is the key to a successful parasite control program?","answer":"Breaking the parasite’s life cycle (removing manure from barn, using de-wormers, etc.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm325-4"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3793","question":"Why is it important to know the life cycle of various parasites?","answer":"So you can control them  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm325-4"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3794","question":"What is an anthelmintic? (pronounced ant-hell-MINT-ic)","answer":"Dewormer  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-6; HSm325-8"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3795","question":"What is it called when medication is given to decrease the number of internal parasites in horses?","answer":"Deworming (May accept \"worming\" from juniors.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm325-5"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3796","question":"In reference to internal parasites, what is ERP or egg reappearance period?","answer":"Time between deworming and the reappearance of eggs in the manure  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-7; HSm325-7"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"intermediate","number":"3797","question":"How can the effectiveness of dewormers be evaluated?","answer":"By having the vet check the fecal egg count (or egg reappearance period) after de-worming  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc59; HIH430; HSm325-6"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"intermediate","number":"3798","question":"In reference to internal parasites, what is a fecal egg count?","answer":"Lab procedure used to determine the number of parasite eggs in a fecal sample (FYI:  Treatment is not necessary if counts are up to 200 eggs per gram.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc59; HIH430; HSm325-6"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3799","question":"In reference to internal parasites, what is \"anthelmintic resistance\"?","answer":"Ability of worms to survive doses of anthelmintics (dewormers) that had previously been effective (FYI:  Effective de-wormers should be able to reduce the number of eggs shed by at least 90%.  If less than 90%, worms have developed resistance.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-7; HSm325-5"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3800","question":"Name ONE thing that can happen if de-wormers are not used as directed.","answer":"Worms can develop resistance; too high of a dose can hurt smaller horses, ponies, and foals.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-7,8; HSm325-5,7"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3801","question":"What is “tubing” a horse?","answer":"Inserting a nasogastric  or \"stomach\" tube to release gas or to give medications (such as colic medicine or dewormers)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH215"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"3802","question":"No deworming schedule fits all horses.  Name 3 factors that would influence a farm’s deworming program.","answer":"Climate, season (temperature and humidity), age of horse, health of horse, fecal egg count, nutrition, genetic factors, local parasite resistance, concentration of horses, type of herd (travel, new horses, etc.) (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-6,7"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3803","question":"Name TWO times of the year that are most important to deworm horses.","answer":"Spring and fall  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-10"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"3804","question":"Customizing your internal parasite control program will reduce your cost and diminish resistance in parasites.  Give the general recommended worming schedule for low, medium, and high contaminators.","answer":"Low (fecal egg counts of less than 200)—2 times a year in spring and fall; medium (fecal egg counts of 200 – 500)—3 times a year; high (fecal egg count over 500)—4 times a year  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-9"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"intermediate","number":"3805","question":"2-part question:  When deworming, what stage of the worm's life cycle do you particularly want to destroy and why?","answer":"Adult; so they can't lay eggs  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-7"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"3806","question":"Fenbendazole, Piperazine, Pyrantel and Ivermectin are examples of what type of medication?","answer":"Anthelminitic (dewormer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm325-6; DET106; DET156; DET213; DET224"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"intermediate","number":"3807","question":"Name ONE generic or brand name of de-wormer used for horses.","answer":"Ivermectin (Zimecterin), Pyrantel (Strongid, Strongid C), Fenbendazole (Panacur, Safe Guard), Oxibendazole (Anthelcide E.Q.), Moxidectin (Quest), Praziquantel (combos Equimax, Quest Plus, Zimecterin Gold), Piperazine (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-6; HSm325-6"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"3808","question":"Give 3 generic wormer names.","answer":"Ivermectin (Zimecterin), Pyrantel (Strongid, Strongid C), Fenbendazole (Panacur, Safe Guard), Oxibendazole (Anthelcide E.Q.), Moxidectin (Quest), Praziquantel (combos Equimax, Quest Plus, Zimecterin Gold), Piperazine (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-6; HSm325-5"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"3809","question":"Name the dewormer that's available in alfalfa-flavored pellets that is designed to be fed on a daily basis.","answer":"Strongid C  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH161"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3810","question":"Name ONE de-wormer or anthelmintic that is used to treat tapeworms.","answer":"Praziquantel (found in Equimax, Quest Plus, and Zimecterin Gold); pyrantel pamoate (found in Strongid) [FYI:  Pyrantel should be given as twice the standard dose.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-4"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3811","question":"In reference to parasites, what is refugia? (pronounced reh-FEW-gee-ah)","answer":"Refugia is the portion of the parasite population that has not been exposed to de-wormers.  (FYI:  Refugia should be kept as large as possible to decrease resistance to de-wormers.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-8; HSm32-6"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"3812","question":"Give the SCIENTIFIC name for 3 of the following 4 types of parasites:  pinworms, bloodworms, roundworms, and threadworms.","answer":"Oxyuris equi (pinworms), Strongylus vulgaris (bloodworms), Parascaris equorum (roundworms), Strongyloides westeri (threadworms)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH420; HSm325"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"3813","question":"2-part question:  What 3 internal parasites are currently considered the most problematic in horses?  Explain why.","answer":"Small strongyles (Cyathostomins)—primary pathogens of mature horses; ascarids (roundworms)—major parasite in foals; tapeworms (Anoplocephala)—can cause colic and intestinal blockage  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm325-1"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3814","question":"Name ONE type of worms or internal parasites that infect horses.","answer":"Bloodworms (strongyles), roundworms (ascarids), threadworms (strongyloides), pinworms, bots, tapeworms  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430; HSm325"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"jr bonus","number":"3815","question":"Name 3 INTERNAL parasites of horses.","answer":"Bloodworms (strongyles), roundworms (ascarids), threadworms (strongyloides), pinworms, bots, tapeworms  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430; HSm325"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"3816","question":"Name 5 INTERNAL parasites of horses.","answer":"Bloodworms (strongyles), roundworms (ascarids), threadworms (strongyloides), pinworms, bots, tapeworms  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430; HSm325"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"intermediate","number":"3817","question":"Name ONE internal parasite that is found more commonly in young horses.","answer":"Roundworms (ascarids); threadworms (Strongyloides) [FYI:  Roundworms affect horses up to 18 – 24 months of age; then horses develop immunity.  Threadworms affect suckling foals.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-1,2; HSm325-2,3"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3818","question":"Environmental conditions are critical to the transmission of both large and small strongyles. Eggs will only hatch and develop into infective larvae at what temperature?","answer":"45 – 85 degrees (accept any number within this range) [FYI:  Egg development stops below 45 degrees F.  Free-living stages are killed by temperatures greater than 85 degrees F.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-5"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"3819","question":"Name ONE complication of bloodworm larvae migrating in the arteries.","answer":"Blood clots, colic, and inflammation and thickening of the arterial walls.  (FYI:  Strongylus vulgaris migrates to the cranial mesenteric artery, which is the major arterial blood supply of the intestines.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-5"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"intermediate","number":"3820","question":"Because of their red appearance, what is the COMMON name for strongyles?","answer":"Bloodworms  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-4; HSm325-2"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"intermediate","number":"3821","question":"Which internal parasite is the most common and most significant?","answer":"Strongyles (bloodworms) [FYI:  Strongyles or bloodworms are prevalent worldwide and occur in horses of all ages except neonatal foals. Strongyles come in two types, large strongyles and small strongyles.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-5,8; HSm325-1"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"3822","question":"Describe 3 life cycle stages of LARGE strongyles or bloodworms.","answer":"Eggs are passed out to pasture, eggs become infective, eggs hatch, horse eats larvae, larvae migrate to large intestine, larvae may migrate to arteries and then back to large intestine, larvae mature into worms and reproduce in the large intestine  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-5,6; HSm325-4; ES188"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"3823","question":"What are the scientific names for the 3 types of large strongyles?","answer":"Strongylus vulgaris, Strongylus edentatus, and Strongylus equinus  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-5; HSm325-1; FCH155"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3824","question":"What blood vessel, that is a major blood supply source to the intestines, is damaged by the bloodworm Strongylus vulgaris?","answer":"Cranial mesenteric artery  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-5; HSm325-1,2"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3825","question":"Large strongyles are no longer present in most herds.  How can eradication and maintenance of eradication be accomplished in a closed herd?","answer":"Use 1 larvicidal treatment (Ivermectin, Moxidectin, Panacur) every 6 months. (FYI:  Since the life cycle of all 3 types of large strongyles is approximately 6 – 8 months, all will be eradicated within 18 months in a closed herd.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-8"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"3826","question":"Small strongyles are a group of 50 species in the Cyathostomin subgroup of the Strongylidae family.  Describe 3 life cycle stages of SMALL strongyles.","answer":"Eggs are passed out to pasture; eggs develop into larvae; horse eats larvae; LARVAE INVADE THE LARGE INTESTINE WALLS, ENCYST, AND BECOME DORMANT; when conditions are favorable, larvae mature into worms and reproduce in the large intestine  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm325-2"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3827","question":"Small strongyles are considered the primary pathogens of mature horses and are becoming increasingly resistance to anthelmintics.  Name ONE drug that is still effective against encysted small strongyles.","answer":"*Moxidectin (Quest), *Fenbendazole (Panacur, Safe-Guard, needs double dose for 5 consecutive days), Oxibendazole (Anthelcide E.Q.), Pyrantel (Strongid), Ivermectin (Zimecterin), Piperazime (must be given via stomach tube)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-7"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"jr bonus","number":"3828","question":"Describe 3 life cycle stages of common bots.","answer":"Bot fly lays eggs, horse bites or licks eggs and eggs hatch in mouth (where they live for 1 month), larvae migrate and attach to stomach wall (where they can live for up to 1 year), larvae are passed out in feces, pupae develop in soil, adult flies  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-4,5; HIH430-4,5; HSm320-4; HSm325-3; ES188"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"3829","question":"Explain why a boticide should be given one month after the first frost?","answer":"First frost will kill the adult flies; if a boticide is used one month later, the hatched larvae (that have migrated to the stomach) will be killed.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-4"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3830","question":"What insect does the adult bot fly look like?","answer":"Honeybee (FYI:  Bot flies have non-functional mouth parts, so they don't bite horses.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-5; HIH430-3; HSm320-4"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3831","question":"Name ONE time of the year that adult bot flies are most active.","answer":"Late summer; early fall (FYI:  Adult bot flies are active until the first frost.  Therefore, horses should be de-wormed with Ivermectin or Moxidectin (Quest) in the late fall or early winter when the adults stop laying eggs.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-5; HIH430-4"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"jr bonus","number":"3832","question":"Name 3 areas on the horse where the common bot fly lays her eggs.","answer":"Front legs, chest, neck, barrel, hind legs, flank (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-5; HIH430-4; HSm320-4"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3833","question":"Where on the horse do bot eggs hatch?","answer":"In the horse's mouth (FYI:  Eggs incubate on the horse’s hair for 1 – 5 days.  Larvae embed in the horse’s tongue where they live for a month.  Then they migrate to the horse’s stomach and attach to the stomach wall.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-5; HIH430-3; HSm320-4"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3834","question":"What causes bot eggs to hatch?","answer":"Moisture and warmth from the horse's tongue  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-5; HSm320-4"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3835","question":"How can you remove bot eggs?","answer":"Scrape them off (FYI:  You can use a small, hard sponge, a lice comb, or a disposable razor.  Do NOT use a moist sponge or rag.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-4"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3836","question":"Which common internal parasite of horses is a fly larva, not a worm?","answer":"Bot (FYI:  Bots cause no significant diseases, but they can cause colic, obstruction, perforation of the stomach, and paralysis of the esophagus.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-3,4; HSm320-4"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"3837","question":"During what TWO seasons are bot larvae passed out of the horse in the feces?","answer":"Spring and early summer (FYI:  Bot larvae burrow into the ground to pupate.  Adult flies emerge in later summer and early fall and lay their eggs on horses.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-4; HSm325-3"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"3838","question":"Where in the horse’s digestive tract do bot larvae attach?","answer":"Stomach  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-3,4; HSm320-4"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"intermediate","number":"3839","question":"How long can bot larvae live in the horse?","answer":"Up to 1 (one) year  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm325-3"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"3840","question":"2-part question:  There are 3 types of Gasterophilus or horse bot flies.  Give either their common name or scientific name and identify one area on the horse where they deposit their eggs.","answer":"Gasterophilus intestinalis (common bot fly)—legs, chest, neck, barrel, flanks; Gasterophilus nasalis (throat bot fly)— jaw, chin, throat; Gasterophilus haemorrhoidalis (nose bot fly)—upper and lower lips (FYI: Nose bot fly is rare; eggs are black.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-4; HSm320-4; HSc56"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3841","question":"Which TWO external parasites are intermediate hosts for cutaneous habronemiasis or \"summer sores\"?","answer":"House fly and stable fly (FYI:  Musca domestica and Stomoxys calcitrans)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm325-4; FCH167"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3842","question":"Which parasite causes dermatitis granulosa or summer sores?","answer":"Stomach worms (Habronema larvae)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm325-4; DET79; DET259"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3843","question":"What skin problem of the horse is also called cutaneous habronemiasis or dermatitis granulosa?","answer":"Summer sores (FYI:  Habronema larvae are deposited into wounds by house flies and stable flies which serve as vectors.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm325-4; DET79; DET259"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"3844","question":"What internal parasite in horses is seen when horses are grazed with cattle or other ruminants?","answer":"Hairworm (Trichostrongylous axei)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm325-4"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3845","question":"Horses infected with lungworms have generally been exposed to what animal?","answer":"Donkeys (FYI:  Infection of horses with lungworms or Dictyocaulas arnfieldi can result in parasitic pneumonia and bronchitis.  Most horses have no symptoms, but horses can have coughing, nasal discharge, and respiratory distress.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm325-4; FCH159"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3846","question":"What type of parasite usually only occurs in horses that are grazed in pastures with donkeys?","answer":"Lungworms (FYI:  Infection of horses with lungworms or Dictyocaulas arnfieldi can result in parasitic pneumonia and bronchitis.  Most horses have no symptoms, but horses can have coughing, nasal discharge, and respiratory distress.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm325-4; FCH159"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3847","question":"Where on the horse are pinworm eggs found?","answer":"Around the horse’s anus  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-3; HSm325-3"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3848","question":"Where do pinworms mature?","answer":"Large intestine  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-3; HSm325-3"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3849","question":"Name ONE sign of pinworm infestation.","answer":"Rubbed tail or rump, bare patches on the tail head or buttocks, anal irritation, presence of eggs around the anus  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH420-3; HSm325-3"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"3850","question":"The more mature ascarids are, the more they are susceptible to what?","answer":"Deworming agents  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-2"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3851","question":"What is the COMMON name for Parascaris equorum?","answer":"Roundworms (FYI: Roundworms or ascarids are seen in young horses.  Roundworms can grow to over one foot long and can be found in the liver, lungs, and small intestines.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-1; HSm325-2"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3852","question":"Why are horses older than 18 months not commonly infected with ascarids or roundworms?","answer":"They develop immunity after being exposed early in life.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-1,2; HSm325-2"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3853","question":"Generally speaking, what age horses are ascarid or roundworm infections restricted to?","answer":"Young horses (generally under 18 months)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-1,2; HSm325-2"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3854","question":"How long is the life cycle of the ascarid or roundworm?","answer":"2 – 3 months or 10 – 12 weeks (accept any number within these ranges)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-1,2; HIH975-14"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"3855","question":"Describe 3 life cycle stages of ascarids or roundworms.","answer":"Eggs passed out to pasture, eggs are swallowed, larvae hatch in intestinal tract, larvae migrate through blood stream to the liver and lungs, larvae are coughed up and swallowed, worms mature and reproduce in the small intestines  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-1; HSm325-2"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"3856","question":"Where do ascarid larvae develop into mature worms?","answer":"Small intestine  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-1; HSm325-2"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"3857","question":"Name TWO organs of the horse where roundworms are PRIMARILY found.","answer":"Small intestines, liver, and lungs  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-1,2; HSm325-2"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3858","question":"What internal parasite can cause fever, cough, nasal discharge, weight loss, and stunted growth in young horses?","answer":"Roundworms (Parascaris equorum) [FYI:  Roundworms or ascarids can cause intestinal obstruction in the small intestine, especially after de-worming because the dead worms can clump together.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-1; HSm325-2; FCH157"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"3859","question":"Name 3 problems in horses that are caused by ascarids or roundworms.","answer":"Unthriftiness or weight loss, stunted growth, pot belly, rough hair coat, colic, diarrhea, intestinal obstruction, intestinal rupture, liver problems, fever, depression or lethargy, anorexia, cough, respiratory problems, nasal discharge  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm325-2; ES189; FCH157; HSc57"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3860","question":"What causes unthriftiness, pot belly, rough hair coat, lack of growth, and cough in young horses?","answer":"Worms (specifically ascarids or roundworms)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc57; FCH159"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3861","question":"The oribatid mite is the intermediate host for which internal parasite?","answer":"Tapeworm (FYI:  Tapeworms or Anoplocephala perfoliata live in the ileocecal junction between the small intestine and large intestine.  When found in large numbers, tapeworms can cause colic and intestinal blockage.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-4; HSm325-3"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"3862","question":"Tapeworms infect horses through which intermediate host?","answer":"Mites (specifically oribatid or forage mite)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-4; HSm325-3"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3863","question":"What is the name of the flat worm that’s “considered highly prevalent and clinically relevant”? The oribatid mite is the intermediate host for this parasite?","answer":"Tapeworm (FYI:  Tapeworms or Anoplocephala perfoliata live in the ileocecal junction between the small intestine and large intestine.  When found in large numbers, tapeworms can cause colic and intestinal blockage.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-4; HSm325-3"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"3864","question":"Tapeworms live at the junction of the small intestine and cecum.  The presence of large numbers of tapeworms may result in what?","answer":"Intestinal blockage (colic)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-4; HSm325-3"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"intermediate","number":"3865","question":"Name ONE way foals are infected with strongyloides or threadworms.","answer":"Ingested in mare’s milk, larvae penetrating the foal's skin, ingested in pasture or paddock  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-2,3; HSm325-3"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"intermediate","number":"3866","question":"What internal parasite can cause diarrhea in suckling foals?","answer":"Threadworms (strongyloides or Strongyloides westeri)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-2,3; HSm325-3"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"3867","question":"Most foals infected with threadworms don't show any symptoms.  For those that do, what is the main symptom?","answer":"Diarrhea  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-2; HSm325-3"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"3868","question":"Which type of worm affects foals almost exclusively and can cause diarrhea, dehydration, and weight loss?","answer":"Threadworms (also called strongyloides or Strongyloides westeri) [Do NOT accept strongyles or blood worms.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-2,3; HIH975-14; HSm325-3"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3869","question":"What is the difference between an ectoparasite and an endoparasite?","answer":"Ectoparasite attaches to the skin or body openings on horse (external parasite); endoparasite lives in the internal organs, body cavities, or tissues (internal parasite).  <br/> <br/>ref:DET88; DET92; HSm320-1; HSm325-1"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3870","question":"What is the difference between external and internal parasites?","answer":"External parasites live on the outside of an animal; internal parasites live inside the animal.  <br/> <br/>ref:DET88; DET92; HSm320-1; HSm325-1"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3871","question":"What is a plant or animal that depends on another living animal for its food and shelter?","answer":"Parasite  <br/> <br/>ref:DET204; HSc52"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3872","question":"What is a parasite?","answer":"Plant or animal that lives in or on another living organism at whose expense it gets food and shelter (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET204; HSc52"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3873","question":"What is the term for a parasite that cannot survive away from the host animal?","answer":"Obligate parasite  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-1; HSm320-1"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3874","question":"What are obligate parasites?","answer":"Parasites that can't live away from their host  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-1; HSm320-1"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3875","question":"Which type of parasite is easier to eradicate or get rid of, external or internal?","answer":"External  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc52"},
    {"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"3876","question":"In reference to external parasites, what is a larvicide?","answer":"Insecticide designed to kill larvae (of mosquitoes and flies)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-4; HSm320-3"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"3877","question":"Why is the percentage of live foal births in feral horse populations greater than the average for live foal births in human-controlled breeding operations?","answer":"Because of human intervention (such as the manipulating estrus or breeding for certain characteristics) [FYI:  Percentage of live births in feral horse populations is 80 – 90%; percentage of live births in human controlled breeding is 50 – 60%.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-4,5"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"3878","question":"Of all our domestic animals, which animal has the lowest reproductive efficiency?","answer":"Horse  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-4"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"3879","question":"Name ONE of the main concerns when handling breeding stallions.","answer":"Safety; prevention of injury to stallion, mares or handlers; prevention of infections  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH990-1"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"3880","question":"Reproductive ability in the mare decreases after what age?","answer":"15 years of age (accept any number within the 15 – 18 age range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH930-2"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"3881","question":"What is the name for the specialized building where mares are bred?","answer":"Breeding shed  <br/> <br/>ref:DET39"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"3882","question":"What is a breeding shed?","answer":"Specialized building where mares are bred  <br/> <br/>ref:DET39"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"3886","question":"Name 4 documents that should be provided when breeding mares and stallions.","answer":"Registration certificate, health certificate, Coggins test, breeding contract, breeder's certificate, stallion breeding report, mare breeding records, boarding agreement, lease agreement, arrival form, departure form  <br/> <br/>ref:TH331-335"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"3887","question":"Name 4 expenses to consider when breeding your mare.","answer":"Stud fee, booking fee, mare boarding fees, mare transportation fees, mare veterinary fees, increased number and costs of vaccines for mare, increased cost of food and supplements for mares, foal veterinary fees, foal registration fees, feed for foal  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH910-1; TH331-335"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"3888","question":"What are TWO meanings of the term “stud”?","answer":"Stallion; an establishment at which horses are kept for breeding purposes  <br/> <br/>ref:DET258"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"3889","question":"What is the slang term for a horse breeding establishment?","answer":"Stud or stud farm (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET258; HH58"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"3890","question":"What do you call the charge for breeding services rendered by a stallion?","answer":"Stud fee  <br/> <br/>ref:DET258; HSc26"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"3891","question":"How is it determined that a stallion has ejaculated while breeding a mare?","answer":"Flagging or tail flagging (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm520-4"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"3892","question":"Name 3 types of teasing used to identify mares in heat.","answer":"Individual teasing:  stall teasing, teasing rail; group teasing:  cage or box teasing, teasing chute  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH940-1; HSm525-1"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"3893","question":"What is a common method used to determine if a mare is in heat?","answer":"Teasing  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH940-1; HSm525-1"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"3894","question":"Name 3 methods used to breed mares.","answer":"Live breeding (pasture breeding and hand breeding), artificial insemination, embryo transfer  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH237"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"3895","question":"What type of breeding has been one of the most important advances in commercial horse breeding?  With this type of breeding, collected semen is deposited artificially into a mare's vagina.","answer":"AI or Artificial Insemination (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET16; HIH950-1"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"3896","question":"AI or artificial insemination is accepted in most breed associations.  Name ONE breed that requires live cover breeding.","answer":"Thoroughbred  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH950-1"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"3897","question":"Name 3 ADVANTAGES of artificial insemination.","answer":"Larger gene pool, decreased injuries, decreased sexually transmitted infections, one ejaculate can inseminate many mares, mares susceptible to uterine infections are more likely to conceive with AI (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH950-1"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"3898","question":"Name TWO styles of artificial vaginas that are commonly used.","answer":"Missouri and Colorado  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH990-2"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"3899","question":"Name 3 DISADVANTAGES of artificial insemination.","answer":"Initial costs to stallion owner, need skilled staff, costs of semen shipping, evaluation of mare for AI, communication between owners of mare and stallion, semen must be ordered in advance (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH950-1"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"3900","question":"What is the term for the assisted reproductive technique where an embryo is flushed from the uterus of a donor mare 6 – 8 days after ovulation and is transferred to the uterus of a recipient mare?","answer":"Embryo transfer  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH960-1; DET91"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"3901","question":"What is embryo transfer?","answer":"Transfer of an embryo from the uterus of a pregnant donor mare to the uterus of a surrogate or recipient mare (FYI:  Embryo—usually a blastocyst—is flushed from the donor mare 6 – 8 days after ovulation.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH960-1; DET91"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"3902","question":"How long does it take for a foal's immune system to become functional and to produce significant levels of antibodies?","answer":"2 – 4 months (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm535-2"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"3903","question":"Foals must obtain adequate intake of colostrum within how many hours after birth?","answer":"12 – 24 hours (accept any number within this range) [FYI:  Foals’ digestive system can absorb the large immunoglobin molecules during this time.  Newborn foals MUST get immunoglobulins from colostrum so they can fight off infections.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm530-2; HIH975-4"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"3904","question":"A nursing foal's nutrient requirements exceed those provided by the dam's milk within how many months?","answer":"2 (two) months  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm535-3"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"3905","question":"It is very important that a foal receives colostrum from the mare soon after birth.  Foals should nurse within how many hours after birth?","answer":"1 – 3 hours (accept any number within this range) [FYI:  Colostrum is the mare’s first milk that is high in antibodies which fight off infection and high in fat which helps the foal pass the meconium or first stool.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH975-1; HSm535-1"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"3906","question":"Giving only one number, how many times do foals nurse an hour during the first week of life?","answer":"5 times an hour (accept any number between 4 and 7 times an hour) [FYI:  Newborn foals may drink 21 – 25% of their body weight per day.  By 7 weeks of age, foals usually only nurse once per hour.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH975-5; HSm535-2"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"3907","question":"A foal is normally weaned at what age?","answer":"4 – 6 months (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH975-7; HSm535-3"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"3908","question":"Give TWO reasons why it’s important to keep foals in familiar surroundings during the weaning process.","answer":"Decrease stress, decrease injury, decrease risk of infections (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH975-7; HSm535-3"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"3909","question":"Mare's milk production naturally decreases when foals are about 3 months of age.  Give ONE reason why foals should be started on grains and/or forages prior to weaning.","answer":"Reduces stress, reduces weight loss, reduces slowed growth rates  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH975-7; HSm535-3"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"3910","question":"Name 3 physical signs of immaturity in a newborn foal.","answer":"Underweight, silky hair, floppy ears, weakness, poor suckle reflex, illness, septicemia (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH930-4"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"3911","question":"Name 3 symptoms of meconium impactions in newborn foals.","answer":"Abdominal discomfort, vocalization, straining to defecate, abdominal distention, depression, not interested in nursing, flagging tail, increased heart rate (tachycardia), increased respiration rate (tachypnea)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH975-3"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"3912","question":"What is meconium?","answer":"First manure passed by the foal (FYI:  Meconium is the dark tarry stool formed prior to birth.  It normally begins to pass 30 minutes to 6 hours after birth.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH975-3; HSm535-2; FCH395"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"3913","question":"What is the name of the first feces that the foal excretes?","answer":"Meconium (FYI:  The next feces is a pasty, yellow feces called \"milk feces\".)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH975-3; HSm535-2; FCH395"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"3914","question":"What is the VERY FIRST step in taking care of a foal immediately after birth?","answer":"Remove anything from the foal's nostrils that might restrict its breathing.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH970-4; HSm535-1"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"3915","question":"Pandiculation is an indication of the well-being of a foal.  It usually occurs within 4 hours after birth. What is pandiculation?","answer":"Stretching  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH247"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"3916","question":"The umbilical cord connects which TWO structures?","answer":"Fetus and placenta  <br/> <br/>ref:DET278"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"3917","question":"Why should a newborn foal's naval stump be treated with an antiseptic such as a 0.5% Chlorhexidine solution?","answer":"To prevent infection (FYI:  The AAEP recommends using Chlorhexidine solution instead of 2% iodine solution because iodine can burn the surrounding skin.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH970-5; HSm535-1"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"3918","question":"How is the foal’s umbilical cord usually “disconnected” from the placenta after the birth of the foal?","answer":"Umbilical cord usually breaks 10 – 15 minutes after birth (when the foal struggles or the mare stands).  (FYI:  Never cut the umbilical cord because it can cause bleeding.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH970-4; HSm535-1"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"3919","question":"What does the urachus do?","answer":"Takes urine away from the fetus during pregnancy  <br/> <br/>ref:DET280; CAHA72"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"3920","question":"Name TWO causes of colic in newborn foals.","answer":"Meconium impaction, gastric ulcer, enteritis, inguinal hernia, overo lethal white foal syndrome, ruptured bladder, atresia coli, small intestinal volvulus, intussusception, gastric outflow obstruction  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH975-8"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"3921","question":"How does a healthy foal normally sleep?","answer":"On its side  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm535-2"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"3922","question":"A normal foal weighs what percent of the mare's body weight at birth?","answer":"8% – 10% (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm535-8"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"3923","question":"You do the math…A newborn foal normally weighs 8 - 10% of the mare’s body weight.  What would be the approximate weight of a foal if the mare weighs 1200 pounds?","answer":"96 – 120 pounds (accept a number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm535-8"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"3924","question":"Name ONE major cause of infertility in mares.","answer":"Human management, age, health problems, infections, hormone imbalances (low progesterone), anatomical problems (of cervix, uterus, etc.), endometriosis, nutritional factors (tall fescue, deficiencies), psychological issues (stress)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-3,5; HIH930-1,2,6"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"3925","question":"Name 3 causes of infertility in mares.","answer":"Human management, age, health problems, infections, hormone imbalances (low progesterone), anatomical problems (of cervix, uterus, etc.), endometriosis, nutritional factors (tall fescue, deficiencies), psychological issues (stress)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-3,5; HIH930-1,2,6"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"3926","question":"Name ONE cause of infertility in stallions.","answer":"Anatomical problems, hormone imbalances, decreased daylight hours, decreased libido, increased temperature in testes (fever), pain, injury (that prevents mounting), psychological (stress, rough handling), health problem, nutrition, infection  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH980-1-4; HIH990-1"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"3927","question":"Name 3 causes of infertility in stallions.","answer":"Anatomical problems, hormone imbalances, decreased daylight hours, decreased libido, increased temperature in testes (fever), pain, injury (that prevents mounting), psychological (stress, rough handling), health problem, nutrition, infection  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH980-1-4; HIH990-1"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"3928","question":"Name 3 parts of the reproductive tract of the mare.","answer":"Ovaries, oviducts or fallopian tubes, uterus, cervix, vagina, vulva  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-1-4; HSm5151-5; HSc22-26"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"3929","question":"Weakening of the broad ligaments can cause a downward tilting of the uterus and can predispose a mare to uterine infections and infertility.  Other than injury and illness, name TWO things that would contribute to the weakening of these ligaments.","answer":"Age of mare; parity (number of pregnancies the mare has had)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH910-3"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"3930","question":"What are the two, tough sheet-like structures that suspend the uterus?","answer":"Broad ligaments  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-3; HSm515-2"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"3931","question":"What is name of the muscular tissue that acts as a physical barrier between the vagina and the uterus?","answer":"Cervix (FYI:  The shape and characteristics of the cervix change significantly in response to hormones.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH910-3; HSm515-2; HSc22"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"3932","question":"What is an ovary?","answer":"Female sex organ that produces eggs (and sex hormones such as estrogen and progesterone)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-4; HSm515-2; HSc23"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"3933","question":"What is the shape of the mare’s ovaries?","answer":"Kidney bean-shaped (FYI:  Ovaries in horses vary in size and texture between breeding and non-breeding seasons.  In the summer when they’re active they’re the size of a handball.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-4; HSm515-2; HSc23"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"3934","question":"What reproductive organ in the mare is responsible for the production of estrogen, progesterone, and ova or eggs?","answer":"Ovary  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-4; HSm515-4; DET198; HSc23"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"3935","question":"Sex organs are organs that produce sex cells such as egg and sperm.  What is the primary sex organ of the mare?","answer":"Ovary (FYI:  The primary sex organ of the stallion is the testis.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc23"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"3936","question":"What is the name of the transient structure that forms on the ovary after ovulation?  This structure produces progesterone which prepares the body for pregnancy and prevents the mare from being receptive to stallions.","answer":"Corpus luteum  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-4; HSm515-3; DET69; HSc22"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"3937","question":"In reference to reproduction, what is the corpus luteum?","answer":"Mass that forms in the ovary after ovulation (FYI:  The corpus luteum produces progesterone that prepares the body for pregnancy, prevents the mare from returning to estrus, and maintains early pregnancy.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-4; HSm515-3; DET69; HSc22"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"3938","question":"What is the diameter of an ovarian follicle that indicates that a mare is ready to be bred?","answer":"35 millimeters (FYI:  Primordial follicles have one layer of epithelial cells.  Layers of cells are added to make secondary, tertiary, and Graafian follicles.  When Graafian follicles are 35 mm or bigger, they can palpated or seen on ultrasound.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-4; HSm515-3"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"3939","question":"In reference to reproduction, what is a follicle?","answer":"Bubble-like structure on the ovary which contains the egg  <br/> <br/>ref:DET111; HSc22; HIH920-4; HSm515-3"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"3940","question":"How many follicles are on an ovary?","answer":"Hundreds of thousands (CORRECTED 2020) [FYI:  When fillies are born, the ovarian cortex is full of oocytes.  No new ova will be produced.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-4; HSm515-3"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"3941","question":"2-part question:  Define sex organs and name the sex organs of the mare and of the stallion.","answer":"Organs that produce sex cells (egg and sperm); ovaries and testes  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc22,23"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"3942","question":"What is another name for the oviducts?","answer":"Fallopian Tubes  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-4"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"3943","question":"What tube in the mare carries the egg from the ovary to the uterus?","answer":"Oviduct or Fallopian tube (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-4"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"3944","question":"Name ONE function of the cilia in the oviducts.","answer":"Helps move the egg down the oviduct; helps move sperm up the oviduct.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-4"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"3945","question":"In reference to reproduction, what is the infundibulum?","answer":"Funnel-like membrane that surrounds the ovary and catches the egg (FYI:  The infundibulum is the widened ovarian-end of the oviduct.  Its finger-like projections called fimbriae help catch the egg.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-4; HSm515-2; DET152; HSc23"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"3946","question":"What is the name of the funnel-like membrane that surrounds the ovary and catches the egg?","answer":"Infundibulum (FYI:  The infundibulum is the widened ovarian-end of the oviduct.  Its finger-like projections called fimbriae help catch the egg.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-4; HSm515-2; DET152; HSc23"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"3947","question":"What are the names of the sex cells that ovaries produce?","answer":"Ova (Also accept eggs or oocytes which are immature ova.) [FYI: Ovum is singular; ova is plural.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-4; HSm515-2; DET199"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"3948","question":"What is the scientific name for the egg?","answer":"Ovum (Also accept oocyte which is an immature ovum.) [FYI: Ovum is singular; ova is plural.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-4; HSm515-2; DET199"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"3949","question":"What is ovulation?","answer":"Release of the egg from the ovary  <br/> <br/>ref:DET199; HSc23; HSm515-3"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"3950","question":"On a mare's udder, how many teats does she have?","answer":"2 (two) teats  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA69"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"3951","question":"What is another name for the mare's mammary gland?","answer":"Udder  <br/> <br/>ref:DET278; FCH262"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"3952","question":"What is mastitis?","answer":"Inflammation or infection of the udder (mammary gland)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET176; FCH234"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"3953","question":"What is the term for inflammation or infection of the udder?","answer":"Mastitis  <br/> <br/>ref:DET176; FCH234"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"3954","question":"What is the name of the structure in a mare's abdominal cavity that is multi-layered, hollow, Y-shaped, and is suspended by the broad ligaments?","answer":"Uterus  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-3; HSm515-2"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"3955","question":"What is the name of the large part of the mare’s reproductive tract in which the fetus develops?","answer":"Uterus (also accept womb)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-3; HSm515-2; DET280; HSc24"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"3956","question":"Name the 3 layers of the uterus.","answer":"Endometrium, myometrium, and serosal layer (perimetrium) [pronounced en-doe-MEE-tree-um, MY-oh-mee-tree-um,seer-OH-sah, PAIR-ih-mee-tree-um]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-3; HSm515-2"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"3957","question":"What is the name for the inner lining of the uterus?","answer":"Endometrium (pronounced in-doe-MEE-tree-um)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-3; HSm515-2; DET92"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"3958","question":"In reference to reproduction, what is the endometrium? (pronounced in-doe-MEE-tree-um)","answer":"Inner lining of the uterus  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-3; HSm515-2; DET92"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"3959","question":"What is the main purpose of the myometrium?","answer":"Contractions that expel the foal at birth  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-3; HSm515-2"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"3960","question":"Which layer of the mare's uterus is responsible for the powerful contractions which expel the foal at birth?","answer":"Myometrium (middle layer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-3; HSm515-2"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"3961","question":"Into what organ in the mare does a stallion deposit sperm during mating?  The foal also passes through this during birth.","answer":"Vagina  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-3; HSm515-2; DET281; HSc24"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"3962","question":"What is the name of the operation performed on mares where the labia of the upper part of the vulva are sutured together to reduce infection?","answer":"Caslick’s (FYI:  The medical term is episoplasty and it’s used to prevent pneumovagina or windsucking.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-1; HSm515-1; DET51"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"3963","question":"In reference to reproduction, what is a Caslick's operation?","answer":"Procedure where the labia of the upper part of the vulva are sutured together to prevent pneumovagina or windsucking (FYI:  Pneumovagina is when air and/or debris get sucked into the mare’s reproductive tract.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-1; HSm515-1; DET51"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"3964","question":"Give ONE cause of dystocia or difficulty foaling.","answer":"Abnormal presentation, foal too large for mare’s pelvis, twins, “red bag” (premature separation of the placenta), rectovaginal tear (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH970-4"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"3965","question":"During the second stage of labor, you notice the appearance of a red, velvety bulb at the vulva which looks like a basketball. This is commonly referred to as a “red bag”. What does this indicate?","answer":"Premature placental separation (FYI:  This is an emergency requiring immediate delivery of the foal.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH970-4"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"3966","question":"A red bag delivery is most commonly observed in mares that have grazed on what type of pasture?","answer":"Tall fescue (fescue)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH940-4"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"3967","question":"Name ONE thing that can be done to delay foaling until the veterinarian arrives if there is an indication of abnormal presentation of the foal.","answer":"Walk the mare; keep the mare standing  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH245"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"3968","question":"What is the term for the type of delivery in which the foal's rump or hind feet present first in the birth canal?","answer":"Breech  <br/> <br/>ref:DET38"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"3969","question":"In reference to reproduction, what is dystocia?","answer":"Difficulty giving birth (foaling problems)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH970-4; HSm530-3; DET87"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"3970","question":"In reference to dystocia, what is meant when it’s said that a foal is in the breech position?","answer":"Foal is positioned to be born butt first. (FYI: Dystocia means a difficult birth.)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH245"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"3971","question":"In reference to dystocia, what is a transverse dorsal position?","answer":"Foal’s back or withers are positioned to come out first.  (FYI: The head and legs are usually down and to one side.  Dorsal is related to the back; ventral is related to the abdomen or front.)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH245"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"3972","question":"In a normal birth, which legs should appear first?","answer":"Front legs  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH940-4; HSm530-3"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"3973","question":"During what GENERAL part of a day are most foals born?","answer":"Night  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm535-2"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"3974","question":"What is parturition?","answer":"Birth (FYI:  Labor is divided into 3 stages:  stage 1:  uterine contractions, cervical dilatation, usually lasts 1 – 4 hours; stage 2:  birth, usually lasts 30 minutes; stage 3:  expulsion of the placenta, usually lasts 1 – 3 hours.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm530-3; DET285; CAHA73"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"3975","question":"What is the correct medical terminology for giving birth?","answer":"Parturition (FYI:  Labor is divided into 3 stages:  stage 1:  uterine contractions, cervical dilatation, usually lasts 1 – 4 hours; stage 2:  birth, usually lasts 30 minutes; stage 3:  expulsion of the placenta, usually lasts 1 – 3 hours.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm530-3; DET205"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"3976","question":"In the pregnant mare, the first stages of labor can often mimic what condition?","answer":"Colic (FYI:  Labor is divided into 3 stages:  stage 1:  uterine contractions, cervical dilatation, usually lasts 1 – 4 hours; stage 2:  birth, usually lasts 30 minutes; stage 3:  expulsion of the placenta, usually lasts 1 – 3 hours.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH970-3; HSm530-4; FCH245"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"3977","question":"The placenta should be expelled within how many hours after delivery of the foal?","answer":"3 hours (accept any number within 1 – 3 hours) [FYI: The expulsion of the placenta is stage 3 of labor.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH970-5; HSm530-4"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"3978","question":"What is the LAST event to occur in the mare's labor?","answer":"Expulsion of the placenta or afterbirth (FYI:  The placenta should be passed within 3 hours of birth.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH970-5; CAHA73; FCH246"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"3979","question":"Describe what happens during the 3 stages of labor.","answer":"In stage 1 mare has uterine contractions and cervical dilatation.  Stage 2 is birth (parturition).  Stage 3 is expulsion of the placenta.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH970-3-6"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"3980","question":"Name 3 signs that indicate a mare is starting the first stage of labor.","answer":"Seeks isolation, walks aimlessly, acts colicky—becomes restless, lies down and stands up, looks at flank, paws, swishes or raises tail, rolls, passes smalls amounts of urine and/or feces frequently, sweats, stops eating (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH970-2,3; HSm530-3; FCH245"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"3981","question":"What is the difference between a barren mare and an open mare?","answer":"Barren mare was bred, but is not pregnant; open mare has had foals in the past, but was not bred this season.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH930-2; HSm530-1"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"jr bonus","number":"3982","question":"Name 3 reproductive classifications of mares.","answer":"Maiden; barren; open or yeld; pregnant or in foal; lactating, wet, or nursing  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH930-2; HSm530-1"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"3983","question":"Name 5 reproductive classifications of mares.","answer":"Maiden; barren; open or yeld; pregnant or in foal; lactating, wet, or nursing  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH930-2; HSm530-1"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"3984","question":"2-part question:  Reproductively, name TWO ways mares can be classified and explain each classification.","answer":"Maiden—never been bred; barren—been bred, but isn't in foal; open or yeld—had foals in the past, but isn't in foal this year; in foal—pregnant; lactating or wet—nursing a foal  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH930-2; HSm530-1"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"3985","question":"What is the term for a mare that was bred, but didn't produce a foal?","answer":"Barren  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH930-2; HSm530-1"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"3986","question":"In reference to reproduction, what is a barren mare?","answer":"Mare that was bred, but is not in foal.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH930-2; HSm530-1"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"3987","question":"What does the term \"in foal\" mean?","answer":"Mare is pregnant.  <br/> <br/>ref:DET152"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"3988","question":"What is the term for a mare that's never been bred?","answer":"Maiden mare  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH930-2; HSm530-1"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"3989","question":"In reference to reproduction, what is a maiden mare?","answer":"Mare that's never been bred  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH930-2; HSm530-1"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"3990","question":"In reference to reproduction, what is an open mare?","answer":"Mare that was not bred this season  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH930-2; HSm530-1"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"3991","question":"What is the reproductive term for a mare that was not bred this season?","answer":"Open mare  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH930-2; HSm530-1"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"3992","question":"2-part question:  Name and describe TWO of the stages of mare’s estrous cycles.","answer":"Estrus or heat—period when the mare is receptive to the stallion; metestrus—short stage following ovulation when the corpus luteum develops; diestrus—when the mare rejects the stallion; proestrus—period of rapid follicle growth prior to estrus  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm515-3,4; DET100; DET 179; DET81; DET220"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"3993","question":"What is the name of the long period between breeding seasons when the ovaries are inactive?","answer":"Anestrus  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-5; HSm515-3; DET11; HSc24"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"3994","question":"During what season would a mare be naturally in anestrus?","answer":"Winter  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-5; HSm515-3; DET11; HSc24"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"3995","question":"Diestrus is the period in the estrous cycle when the mare rejects the stallion.  How long does diestrus in mares generally last?","answer":"14 – 16 days (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-5; HSm515-4; DET81"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"3996","question":"During what part of the estrous cycle does the mare actively reject the stallion?","answer":"Diestrus (Do NOT accept anestrus which occurs during the winter when the mare is not cycling.  Mares are not responsive to stallions during anestrus.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-5, HSm515-3,4; DET81; DET11"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"3997","question":"Name 3 behaviors of a mare in diestrus towards a stallion.","answer":"Pinning ears, biting, kicking, pawing, striking, squealing, tail switching, or showing complete lack of interest (accept any correct answers) [FYI:  Mares in diestrus would receive a behavioral estrus score of 0 (zero).]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-5; HSm515-3; HIH940-2"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"3998","question":"Give ONE name for the part of the estrous cycle when mares are receptive to stallions.","answer":"Estrus or heat (FYI:  Estrus or heat in mares usually lasts 5 – 7 days.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-5; HSm515-3; HSm525-1"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"3999","question":"In reference to reproduction, what does estrus or heat mean?","answer":"Part of the mare’s estrous cycle when she’s receptive to the stallion (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-5; HSm515-3; HSm525-2"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4000","question":"Frequent urination and eversion of the vulva or winking will occur during what phase of the mare's reproductive cycle?","answer":"Estrus or heat (accept either) [FYI:  Mares in estrus or heat receive a behavioral estrus score of 4 (four).]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-5; HSm515-3; HSm525-1; FCH235"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"4001","question":"Name 3 signs of estrus or heat in the mare.","answer":"Mare shows intense interest in the stallion, mare turns her hindquarters towards him, mare leans towards him, squats or flexes her pelvis, lifts her tail, urinates frequently, winks vulva, calls (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-5; HIH940-2; HSm515-3; HSm525-2"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4002","question":"What is the term for the rhythmic opening and closing of the labia as exhibited in mares during estrus?","answer":"Winking  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-5; HSm515-3"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"4003","question":"What is foal heat?","answer":"Mare's first heat after foaling  <br/> <br/>ref:DET111; FCH238"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"4004","question":"What is the average length of estrus or heat period?","answer":"6 (six) days (accept any number between 3 – 7 days)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-5; HSm515-3; HSm525-1"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4005","question":"Name ONE time when conception rate is the highest in mares.","answer":"1 – 2 days prior to ovulation; at the end of estrus; during foal heat; when ovarian follicles are 35 mm or greater (FYI:  It’s best to breed mares 1 – 2 days before ovulation, but ovulation is hard to determine without using ultrasound.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-4; HIH940-1; HSm515-3; HSm525-1"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4006","question":"What event triggers the end of estrus or heat?","answer":"Ovulation (FYI: Ovulation USUALLY occurs 24 – 48 hours before the end of estrus.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-6; HSm525-1; FCH235"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4007","question":"GENERALLY, when during the estrous cycle does ovulation usually occur?","answer":"Towards the end of estrus (FYI:  USUALLY, estrus ends 24 – 48 hours after ovulation, but ovulation is not dependent on estrus and estrus does not ensure ovulation.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-6; HSm525-1; CAHA71"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4008","question":"In reference to reproduction, what is \"silent heat\"?","answer":"Ovulation without outward signs of estrus  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH235"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4009","question":"What is it called when a mare ovulates, but fails to show behavioral signs of estrus?","answer":"Silent heat  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH235"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"4010","question":"How long is the estrous cycle of the mare?","answer":"21 – 23 days (accept any number within this range) [FYI: EstrOUS is the whole 21 – 23 day cycle; estrUS is the 6 day heat period.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-5; HSm515-3; DET100; HSc23"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4011","question":"How does the length of the estrous cycle of a jennet compare to that of a mare?","answer":"Estrous cycle of a jennet is usually longer.  (FYI:  According to the AAEP, estrous cycles of jennets usually last 23 – 30 days.)  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA71"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4012","question":"Prostaglandin, human chorionic gonadotropin, and progesterone (Regumate) are 3 hormones that can be used to do what?","answer":"Manipulate estrus in mares  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH940-4; HSm525-3"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"4013","question":"Name 3 hormones that are used to manipulate estrus in mares.","answer":"Prostaglandin, Human Chorionic Gonadotropin, and Progesterone (FYI:  Prostaglandin F2 causes regression of the corpus luteum; HCG has high LH activity; progesterone can keep mares out of estrus, maintain early pregnancy, or cause ovulation.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH940-4; HSm525-3"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4014","question":"Regumate can be used early in the breeding season to induce estrus.  Mares treated with 14 days of Regumate followed by administration of Prostaglandin should ovulate how many days after treatment?","answer":"12 days (FYI:  Regumate is a synthetic progesterone that’s often used to prevent estrus in performance mares.  It can also be used to help maintain early pregnancy.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH940-4; HSm525-3; HSm370-9"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4015","question":"Give TWO uses of the synthetic progestin Regumate.","answer":"Prevents estrus, helps maintain early pregnancy, used (along with prostaglandin) to induce ovulation  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH940-4; HSm525-3; HSm370-9"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4016","question":"What ratio of daylight to darkness seems to bring mares into heat?","answer":"16 hours of daylight to 8 hours of darkness  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH940-3; HSm525-2"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4017","question":"Use of an artificial lighting program to induce early estrous cycling and ovulation should include 16 hours of light each day and should begin how long before the desired breeding season?","answer":"2 – 3 months (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH940-3; HSm525-2"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"4018","question":"Other than hormones, what can be used to bring mares into heat earlier than the normal breeding season?","answer":"Artificial lights (FYI:  Mares need 16 hours of light to 8 hours of darkness for 2 – 3 months to induce heat.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH940-3; HSm525-2"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"4019","question":"What is the most important environmental cue in inducing estrus in mares?","answer":"Light (more daylight hours)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH940-3; HSm525-2"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"4020","question":"When using a behavioral estrus system scoring of 0 – 4, a mare in estrus or heat would receive what score?","answer":"4 (four) [FYI:  Mare is very interested in the stallion.  She turns her hindquarters towards him, leans towards him, squats or flexes her pelvis, lifts her tail, urinates frequently, and winks her vulva.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH940-2; HSm525-2"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4021","question":"When using a behavioral estrus system scoring of 0 – 4, what behavior is seen in a mare scoring 1 (one)?","answer":"Mare isn't aggressive towards the stallion, but she isn’t interested either. (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH940-2; HSm525-2"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4022","question":"What is meant by the reproductive term “seasonally polyestrous”?","answer":"Mare undergoes multiple estrous cycles only during certain times of the year.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-5; HSm515-3; DET217; DET240; FCH235; HSc24"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4023","question":"What term describes when a mare undergoes multiple estrous cycles only during specific times of the year?","answer":"Seasonally polyestrous  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-5; HSm515-3; DET217; DET240; FCH235; HSc24"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4024","question":"In reference to reproduction, what is “short cycling” a mare?","answer":"Giving her hormones to make her go into heat before her next natural cycle (FYI:  Prostaglandin is often given to short-cycle mares.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH930-3"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4025","question":"In reference to equine reproduction, what does the term “abortion” mean?","answer":"Expulsion of the fetus before the time of normal foaling (accept any reasonable wording) [FYI:  Equine abortions have many causes—infections (EHV-1, EVA), toxins (tall fescue poisoning), twinning, too little progesterone, etc.]  <br/> <br/>ref:DET1"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"4026","question":"Name 3 causes of equine abortion.","answer":"Infections (EHV-1, EVA, bacteria), twinning, toxins (tall fescue), trauma, drugs, nutritional deficiencies, problems with fetus, umbilical cord, placenta, uterus (fibroids), implantation, hormones (too little progesterone in early pregnancy)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH240"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4027","question":"The most common cause of a spontaneous abortion is a placental or uterine infection.  Prior to the current widespread use of ultrasound, what accounted for about 25% of abortions and was considered to be the second most common cause?","answer":"Twinning (twins)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH240"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"jr bonus","number":"4028","question":"Name 3 important considerations in the management of pregnant mares.","answer":"Early pregnancy diagnosis, vet care, adequate nutrition, vaccines, de-worming, appropriate amount of exercise, prevention of injury, avoiding toxins such as tall fescue, vet care during delivery, vet care after foaling (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH Chapter 13"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"4029","question":"Name 3 vaccinations that are often given to a broodmare 4 – 6 weeks before foaling.","answer":"Equine Herpes Virus (rhinopneumonitis), EVA (Equine Viral Arteritis), tetanus, EEE, WEE, West Nile, influenza (flu), rabies, strangles, botulism, Potomac horse fever, rotavirus, VEE  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH930-5"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4030","question":"Why should a pregnant mare be dewormed 30 days before her foaling date?","answer":"To decrease passage of parasite eggs to the foal (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH930-6"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4031","question":"Give TWO reasons why early pregnancy diagnosis is important in mares.","answer":"Diagnose early pregnancy loss, determine cause of early pregnancy loss, mares with early pregnancy loss can be re-bred (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH930-3"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4032","question":"In reference to reproduction, what is the hormone eCG or PMSG used for in mares?","answer":"Equine Chorionic Gonadotropin or Pregnant Mare Serum Gonadotropin can be used as a blood test to diagnose pregnancy. (FYI:  Ultrasound is a better test since eCG/PMSG can remain elevated after pregnancy loss.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET220"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4033","question":"What technique of pregnancy diagnosis is the easiest and the most accurate? It can detect pregnancy as early as two weeks after conception.","answer":"Ultrasound  <br/> <br/>ref:DET278; FCH239"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4034","question":"Name TWO methods of diagnosing pregnancy in mares.","answer":"Ultrasound, rectal palpation, blood test for eCG/PMSG (Equine Chorionic Gonadotropin/Pregnant Mare Serum Gonadotropin), blood test for progesterone, urine test for estrogen (estrone sulfate), failure to come into heat (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET278; DET230; DET220; FCH239"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"4035","question":"Name 3 methods of diagnosing pregnancy in mares.","answer":"Ultrasound, rectal palpation, blood test for eCG/PMSG (Equine Chorionic Gonadotropin/Pregnant Mare Serum Gonadotropin), blood test for progesterone, urine test for estrogen (estrone sulfate), failure to come into heat (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET278; DET230; DET220; FCH239"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4036","question":"What is the term for an unborn animal in its earliest stages of growth and development?","answer":"Embryo (FYI:  A fetus is an unborn animal in its later stages of growth and development.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET91; DET106"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4037","question":"What is the term for an unborn animal in its later stages of growth and development?","answer":"Fetus (FYI:  An embryo is an unborn animal in its earliest stages of growth and development.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET106; DET91"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4038","question":"What is the process of the uniting of the sperm and egg?","answer":"Fertilization (FYI: Fertilization occurs in the oviducts.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET106"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4039","question":"Where does fertilization occur?","answer":"Oviducts (Fallopian tubes)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-4; HSm515-2"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4040","question":"What is a zygote?","answer":"Fertilized egg  <br/> <br/>ref:DET298"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4041","question":"How many days does it take for the fertilized egg to migrate to the uterus?","answer":"4 – 6 days (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH237"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"4042","question":"What is the gestation period or length of pregnancy of most horses in MONTHS?","answer":"11 months (FYI:  Average gestation is 335 – 342 days with a range of 320 – 400 days.  Foals born between 320 – 330 days may be small.  Foals born prior to 320 days show signs or prematurity.  Foals born prior to 300 days are unlikely to live.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET120; HIH930-4"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"4043","question":"What is the AVERAGE gestation period or length of pregnancy of most horses in DAYS?","answer":"335 – 342 days (FYI:  Gestation range is 320 – 400 days.  Foals born between 320 – 330 days may be small.  Foals born prior to 320 days show signs or prematurity.  Foals born prior to 300 days are unlikely to live.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH930-4"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"4044","question":"You do the math…A mare that was bred on May 20th should foal in what month the next year?","answer":"April  <br/> <br/>ref:DET120; HIH930-4"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"4045","question":"What is the term for the length of time for the development of the foal from the time of breeding until birth?","answer":"Pregnancy or gestation period (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET120"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4046","question":"Give TWO factors that may affect a horse's length of gestation.","answer":"Time of year (mares due in late winter/early spring may have longer gestations), fetal sex (males are carried longer than females), maternal nutrition, environmental stress, ingestion of toxins (tall fescue), breed (Belgians have longer gestations)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH930-4"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"4047","question":"Give 3 factors that may affect a horse's length of gestation.","answer":"Time of year (mares due in late winter/early spring may have longer gestations), fetal sex (males are carried longer than females), maternal nutrition, environmental stress, ingestion of toxins (tall fescue), breed (Belgians have longer gestations)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH930-4"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"4048","question":"Give ONE reason why it’s important to examine the placenta after it has been passed by the mare.","answer":"Make sure it’s all there (should only have one opening where the foal broke through); make sure it’s healthy (look for abnormalities in color and thickness)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH970-5; FCH250"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4049","question":"What is the placenta or afterbirth?","answer":"Membranous organ that attaches the fetus to the uterus (and transports nutrients and wastes between the fetus and the uterus via the umbilical cord)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET213"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"4050","question":"What is the correct name for the membranous organ referred to as the afterbirth?","answer":"Placenta  <br/> <br/>ref:DET213"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"4051","question":"Name TWO functions of the placenta.","answer":"Transport oxygen to the fetus; transport nutrients to the fetus; transport wastes away from the fetus.  <br/> <br/>ref:DET278"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4052","question":"What is the name of the soft, brown liver-like masses that may be passed with the placental fluids after birth?","answer":"Hippomanes (FYI:  Hippomanes are found in the allantoic fluids and are made of minerals, fats, and cellular debris.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET140; CAHA72"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4053","question":"What are the 3 membranes of the equine fetal placenta in its early stages?","answer":"Amnion, allantois, and chorion (FYI:  The amnion and amniotic fluid immediately surround the fetus.  The chorioallantois attaches to the mare’s endometrium.  Hippomanes are located in the allantoic fluid.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET10; DET56; CAHA72"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4054","question":"The amnion, chorion, and allantois comprise what structure? (pronounced AM-nee-on, CORE-ee-on, and ah-LAN-toe-is or ah-lan-TOE-is)","answer":"Placenta  <br/> <br/>ref:DET10; DET56; CAHA72"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4055","question":"What is the name of innermost placental membrane?","answer":"Amnion (pronounced AM-nee-on) [FYI:  The fetus is surrounded and protected by the amniotic fluid.]  <br/> <br/>ref:DET10; CAHA72"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4056","question":"When does the most rapid period of fetal growth take place?","answer":"During the last 3 – 4 months of pregnancy (last trimester)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH930-6"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4057","question":"In reference to reproduction, what is a teratogenic plant or drug?","answer":"One that can cause problems or physical defects in a developing fetus  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm370-4; HSm425-4,7; FCH332"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4058","question":"What general type of equine has the LOWEST incidence of twin pregnancies?","answer":"Ponies  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH240"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4059","question":"How are identical twins produced?","answer":"Single fertilized egg (zygote) divides and produces offspring with identical genetic makeup.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc25"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4060","question":"Which breed has the highest incidence of twinning?","answer":"Thoroughbred  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH240"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4061","question":"Most mares will foal within how many hours after the appearance of wax on the teats?","answer":"24 – 48 hours (accept any number within range) [FYI:  Waxing is when small amounts of colostrum leaks and dries on the ends of the teats.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH970-2; HSm530-3"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4062","question":"What is the term for the dried colostrum on the end of a mare’s teats that appears 12 – 24 hours before foaling?","answer":"Wax  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH970-4; HSm530-3"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4063","question":"What TWO hormones increase just before ovulation in the mare?","answer":"Estrogen (estradiol) and LH (Luteinizing Hormone)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-6"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"4064","question":"Name ONE of the ovarian hormones that controls the mare's estrous cycle.","answer":"Estrogens (such as estradiol 17-beta) and progestins (such as progesterone which is secreted by the corpus luteum)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-6; HSm515-4"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4065","question":"What is the general term for the hormones that stimulate the development and maintenance of feminine sexual characteristics?","answer":"Estrogens or estrogenic hormones (accept either) [FYI:  Estrogenic hormones include estradiol, estrone, and estriol.  When ovarian follicles reach 20 – 25 mm in size, they secrete estradiol.]  <br/> <br/>ref:DET100"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4066","question":"What hormone causes the cervix of the mare to become relaxed during estrus?","answer":"Estrogen (FYI:  During estrus, estrogen causes the cervix to appear pink due to increased vascularity, causes the cervix to produce an abundant, thin, watery mucus, and causes flaccid tone of the cervix which helps with live or artificial breeding.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-3; HSm515-2"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4067","question":"What SPECIFIC estrogen hormone does a maturing ovarian follicle secrete when the follicle reaches 20 – 25 mm in size?","answer":"Estradiol (estradiol 17-beta)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-6; HSm515-4"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4068","question":"What does FSH cause in the mare?","answer":"Follicle growth  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-6; HSm515-4"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4069","question":"What hormone from the anterior pituitary causes follicle growth?","answer":"Follicle Stimulating Hormone (FSH)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-6; HSm515-4"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4070","question":"In response to GnRH release from the hypothalamus, what structure releases FSH and LH?","answer":"Pituitary gland (specifically the adenohypophysis or anterior portion of the pituitary gland) [FYI:  GnRH is gonadotropin releasing hormone.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-6; HSm515-4; HSm520-3"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4071","question":"Name ONE thing that luteinizing hormone does in the mare.","answer":"Causes ovulation; initiates the formation of the corpus luteum  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-6; HSm515-4; CAHA71"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4072","question":"What hormone is responsible for both milk let-down and contractions during parturition?","answer":"Oxytocin  <br/> <br/>ref:DET200"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4073","question":"Name ONE thing the hormone oxytocin does in the mare.","answer":"Stimulates uterine contractions; stimulates “let down” or release of milk.  (FYI:  Oxytocin and vasopressin or ADH are secreted by the posterior pituitary or neurohypophysis.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET200"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4074","question":"In reference to reproduction, what is PMU?","answer":"Pregnant Mare Urine (FYI:  PMU is used as a source of human hormone replacement therapy.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH197O-1"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4075","question":"Name ONE thing the hormone progesterone does in the horse's body.","answer":"(Encourages glandular and tissue development) to help maintain early pregnancy, keeps mares out of estrus, along with prostaglandin helps induce ovulation, cervical changes—pale or blanched, tightly closed, produce thick sticky mucus  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-3,6; HIH940-5; HSm515-2,4; HSm525-3"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4076","question":"What hormone causes the cervix of the mare to be tightly closed during diestrus?","answer":"Progesterone (FYI:  During diestrus, progesterone causes the cervix to appear pale or blanched and it causes the cervix to produce thick, sticky mucus.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-3; HSm515-2"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4077","question":"What hormone do the luteal cells within the corpus hemorrhagicum and corpus luteum secrete?","answer":"Progesterone (FYI:  Progesterone helps maintain early pregnancy.  If the mare is not pregnant, prostaglandin (F-2-alpha) is released from the uterus which destroys the corpus luteum and returns the mare to cycling.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-6; HSm515-4"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4078","question":"What does the hormone prolactin do?","answer":"Initiates lactation (milk production)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET221"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4079","question":"What hormone, released by the uterus if the mare isn't pregnant, is responsible for the regression of the corpus luteum and the return of the mare cycling?","answer":"Prostaglandin (prostaglandin F-2-alpha)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH920-6; HIH940-4; HSm515-4; CAHA71"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4080","question":"A mare will produce what PERCENTAGE of her body weight in milk daily?","answer":"2% – 3% (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH975-5"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4081","question":"What breed type of horse is often used as nurse mares because they produce more milk?","answer":"Draft or draft-cross mares (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH273"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"4082","question":"What is a nurse mare?","answer":"Mare that will take care of a strange foal (and let it nurse)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH975-6"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4083","question":"What does agalactia mean?","answer":"Mare's inability to produce milk (FYI:  Agalactia may be due to fescue poisoning.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET4"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"4084","question":"Lactation means the production of what?","answer":"Milk  <br/> <br/>ref:DET163; FCH234"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4085","question":"Lactating mares have an increased need for water due to what?","answer":"Milk production (lactation)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH44"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"4086","question":"What is the term used for a lactating mare that takes care of an orphaned foal as her own?","answer":"Nurse mare  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH975-6"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"4087","question":"What is lactating?","answer":"Producing milk  <br/> <br/>ref:DET163; FCH234"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4088","question":"How long before foaling does colostrum develop?","answer":"2 – 4 weeks (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH970-2; HIH975-4"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"4089","question":"What is the nutritious, first milk for the foal called?","answer":"Colostrum  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH975-4; HSm530-1"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"4090","question":"What is colostrum?","answer":"First milk a mare produces after the birth of a foal  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH975-4; HSm530-1"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4091","question":"In reference to foaling, what is \"failure of passive transfer of immunity\" or “FPT”?","answer":"Foal doesn’t receive adequate antibodies from mare’s colostrum (FYI:  Causes:  failure to nurse, failure of mare to produce adequate quantity or quality of colostrum, leakage of colostrum prior to parturition, tall fescue poisoning)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH975-4; HSm530-2"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4092","question":"What are the proteins in colostrum that provide the foal with temporary immunity against infectious diseases?","answer":"Immunoglobulins  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH975-4; HSm530-1"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"4093","question":"Name TWO substances in colostrum that are very important to foals.","answer":"Immunoglobulins (protect foals from infections), laxatives (fats that help foals pass meconium or first stool), energy, protein, minerals, vitamin A (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm530-1; HIH975-3,4; DET62"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4094","question":"How long does the mare produce colostrum?","answer":"Up to 48 hours after birth of the foal (FYI: Foal absorbs antibodies from colostrum for 36 hours.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm530-2,3"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4095","question":"What is the term for the change that occurs in an animal that results in the animal being able to produce sex cells?","answer":"Puberty  <br/> <br/>ref:DET222"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4096","question":"At what age does puberty occur in stallions?","answer":"1 (one) year of age  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc23"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"4097","question":"At what age can you start using a stallion for breeding purposes?","answer":"2 (two) years of age (only for limited breeding)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc23"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"4098","question":"Name 3 parts of the stallion's reproductive system.","answer":"Scrotum, testes (testicles), epididymis, vas deferens, seminal vesicles or vesicular glands, prostate, bulbourethral or Cowper's glands, urethra, penis  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH980-1; HSm520-1-3; HSc22-24"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4099","question":"What are the glands called that are located along the urethra of the male horse that produce fluids that nourish and preserve the sperm?","answer":"Accessory glands (FYI:  The accessory glands are the vesicular glands (seminal vesicles), the bulbourethral glands (Cowper’s glands), and the prostate.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH980-1; HSm520-2"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"4100","question":"What are the 3 accessory glands located along the urethra in the stallion?","answer":"Prostate, seminal vesicles or vesicular glands, Cowper's glands or bulbourethral glands  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH980-1; HSm520-2"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"4101","question":"When collecting semen for AI, it’s important to know that semen emitted during ejaculation occurs in fractions.  Name the 3 fractions.","answer":"Pre-sperm fraction (secreted by the bulbourethral glands; cleans the urethra); sperm-rich fraction (secreted by the ampulla); sperm-poor fraction (secreted by the vesicular glands; contains the gel portion which is discarded)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH980-5; HIH990-5; HSm520-2,3"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4102","question":"Name ONE function of the epididymis.","answer":"Area where sperm are stored; area where sperm undergo modification and maturation  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH980-3; HSm520-2; DET97; HSc22"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4103","question":"In what part of the stallion's reproductive tract do sperm undergo modifications or maturation?","answer":"Epididymis  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH980-3; HSm520-2; DET97; HSc22"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4104","question":"Mares are often placed under lights to bring them into heat earlier.  Why would stallions be placed under lights?","answer":"Increase testicular activity (FYI:  Use of artificial lights may increase libido and sperm counts during the winter months.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH980-3"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"4105","question":"What is the name of the sac-like pouch that suspends the testes outside the male animal and aids in temperature regulation for proper sperm production?","answer":"Scrotum (FYI:  The scrotum raises and lowers the testes to aid in temperature regulation.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH980-4; HSm520-2"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4106","question":"In reference to reproduction, what is the function of the cremaster muscle?","answer":"Raises and lowers the scrotum (to assist in temperature regulation) [FYI:  The cremaster muscle is located along the spermatic cord.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH980-4; HSm520-2"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4107","question":"Name TWO structures in the scrotum that are responsible for thermoregulation of the testes.","answer":"Sweat glands in the skin, cremaster muscle (muscle located along the spermatic cord), tunica dartos (smooth muscle layer in the scrotal sac), pampiniform plexus (convoluted bundle of blood vessels) [accept specific or general answers]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH980-4; HSm520-2"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4108","question":"Why is it important that the testes are suspended outside the abdominal cavity?","answer":"Temperature regulation (FYI:  The sweat glands in the skin of the scrotum, the tunica dartos in the scrotal sac, the cremaster muscle along the spermatic cord, and the pampiniform plexus all aid in thermoregulation for spermatogenesis.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH980-4; HSm520-2"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"4109","question":"What is the general term for the substance emitted by a stallion during the breeding of a mare?","answer":"Semen (FYI:  Semen is composed of spermatozoa (sperm) and seminal plasma.  The accessory glands secrete the components of seminal plasma.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm520-2; DET241"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4110","question":"Name ONE way semen is collected from stallions for use in artificial insemination.","answer":"By using an artificial vagina with a jump mare or breeding phantom; chemical collection (used for injured stallions); ground collection (using an artificial vagina without the jump mare or breeding phantom; manual stimulation is required)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH990-2"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"4111","question":"Name 3 of the criteria used to evaluate stallion semen.","answer":"Appearance volume, concentration, motility, morphology (shape), pH  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH990-6,7; HSm520-7"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"4112","question":"What are 3 reasons for doing a semen evaluation?","answer":"Monitor stallion’s semen quality, estimate the number of mares that could be bred, maximizing use of single time breeding, shipping cooled semen, freezing semen for later use, quality control (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH990-1"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4113","question":"What substance do the sebaceous glands in the prepuce of a stallion produce?","answer":"Smegma  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH980-5; CAHA5; DET249"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4114","question":"What is the term for the black, waxy substance that can build up in a horse's sheath?","answer":"Smegma  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH980-5; CAHA5; DET249"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4115","question":"In reference to stallion hygiene, what is a “bean”?","answer":"Bean-shaped piece of smegma (that’s found in the urethral fossa and should be removed)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH990-4"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"4116","question":"Sex organs are organs that produce sex cells such as egg and sperm.  What is the primary sex organ of the stallion?","answer":"Testis (also accept testicle) [FYI:  Testis is singular; testes is plural.  The primary sex organ of the mare is the ovary.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH980-3; HSm520-4"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"4117","question":"What do the terms ridgling or cryptorchid mean?","answer":"Male horse that has retained one or both testicles in his body cavity.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm520-1; DET74; DET234; HSc23"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"4118","question":"Give ONE term used when a male horse has retained one or both testicles in his body cavity.","answer":"Ridgling or cryptorchid  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm520-1; DET74; DET234; HSc23"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4119","question":"2-part question:  What is a bilateral cryptorchid stallion and explaining your answer, can he be used for breeding?","answer":"Stallion that's retained both testicles in its body cavity; no, he can’t be used for breeding because he's infertile.  (FYI:  Bilateral cryptorchid stallions exhibit normal secondary sexual characteristics, but they have suppressed spermatogenesis.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH980-1"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"4120","question":"Name the 3 parts of the sperm cell.","answer":"Head, midpiece, and tail  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc23"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4121","question":"What is spermatogenesis?","answer":"Production of sperm cells (FYI:  Spermatogenesis occurs in the cells that form the lining of the seminiferous tubules.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH980-3; HSm520-4"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4122","question":"Where in the testes does spermatogenesis occur?","answer":"Seminiferous tubules (in the cells that form the inner lining of the seminiferous tubules)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH980-3; HSm520-2"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4123","question":"What is the term for the production of sperm cells?","answer":"Spermatogenesis (FYI:  Spermatogenesis occurs in the cells that form the lining of the seminiferous tubules.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH980-3; HSm520-4"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4124","question":"What is the tube through which both semen and urine pass?","answer":"Urethra  <br/> <br/>ref:DET280"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4125","question":"What is the vas deferens?","answer":"Tube that carries sperm from the epididymis to the urethra  <br/> <br/>ref:DET281"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4126","question":"What tube carries sperm from the epididymis to the urethra?","answer":"Vas deferens  <br/> <br/>ref:DET281"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4127","question":"What hormone, produced by the pituitary gland, stimulates the Sertoli cells in the seminiferous tubules to produce sperm?","answer":"FSH or Follicle Stimulating Hormone (accept either) [FYI:  Sertoli cells are located within the epithelium of the seminiferous tubules and are responsible for spermatogenesis.  Both LH and FSH are under the influence of GnRH.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH980-2; HSm520-3"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4128","question":"What hormone, secreted by the hypothalamus, stimulates the anterior pituitary to secrete FSH and LH?","answer":"GnRH or Gonadotropin Releasing Hormone (accept either) [FYI:  Increased daylight hours, transmitted by the optic nerve, signal the pineal gland to decrease the production of melatonin.  This signals the hypothalamus to secrete GnRH.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH980-2; HSm520-3"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4129","question":"Leydig cells in the stallion are responsible for the production of what TWO hormones? (pronounced LIE-dig)","answer":"Testosterone and estrogen (FYI:  Leydig cells are located between the seminiferous tubules and are influenced by LH or Luteinizing Hormone.  Both LH and FSH are under the influence of GnRH or Gonadotropin Releasing Hormone.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH980-2; HSm520-3"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4130","question":"What hormone, produced by the pituitary gland, stimulates the Leydig cells in the testes to produce testosterone?","answer":"LH or Luteinizing Hormone (accept either) [FYI:  Leydig cells are located between the seminiferous tubules.  Leydig cells also produce estrogen. Both LH and FSH are under the influence of GnRH or Gonadotropin Releasing Hormone.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH980-2; HSm520-3"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"4131","question":"Name 3 things that happen hormonally that stimulates spermatogenesis in the stallion when there’s an increase in daylight hours.","answer":"Increase in daylight hours signals the pineal gland to decrease production of melatonin; which signals the hypothalamus to secrete GnRH; which stimulates the pituitary to release FSH; which stimulates the testes to produce sperm  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH980-2; HSm520-3"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"4132","question":"What hormone, produced in the testes, is responsible for the masculine characteristics of the stallion?","answer":"Testosterone (FYI:  Testosterone is also produced in the adrenal glands.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET265; HIH980-2; HSm520-3"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"jr bonus","number":"4133","question":"What are the terms used for a baby horse, a baby female horse, and a baby male horse?","answer":"Baby horse is a foal, baby female horse is a filly, and baby male horse is a colt.  <br/> <br/>ref:DET111; DET107; DET62; HSc22"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"4134","question":"What are sex characteristics?","answer":"Masculinity in the stallion and femininity in the mare  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm385-2"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"novice","number":"4135","question":"What is the mother of a horse called?","answer":"Dam  <br/> <br/>ref:DET77; HH56"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"novice","number":"4136","question":"What is a filly?","answer":"Female foal or immature female horse (FYI:  Some 4-H sources say a filly is up to 3 years of age, but that Thoroughbreds may be considered fillies up to 4 years of age.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH110-5; DET107; FCH389; HSc22"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"novice","number":"4137","question":"What is the term for a young or immature female horse?","answer":"Filly  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH110-5; DET107; FCH389; HSc22"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"4138","question":"The owner of the mare at the time of breeding is called what?","answer":"Breeder  <br/> <br/>ref:DET38; HH56"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"novice","number":"4139","question":"What is a mare?","answer":"Mature female horse (FYI:  Some 4-H sources say 3, some say 4, and some say 5 for Thoroughbreds.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH110-5; DET175; HSc23"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"4140","question":"What is the breeding term for the offspring of a DAM?","answer":"Produce  <br/> <br/>ref:DET220; HH56"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"novice","number":"4141","question":"What is a foal?","answer":"Colt or filly under one year of age (baby horse)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET111; HSc22"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"novice","number":"4142","question":"What is a colt or filly under one year of age called?","answer":"Foal  <br/> <br/>ref:DET111; HSc22"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"novice","number":"4143","question":"What is a weanling?","answer":"Weaned foal (FYI: Foals are weaned at 4 – 6 months.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET288; HSc24"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"4144","question":"What is a \"long yearling\"?","answer":"Horse between 1 and 2 years of age (that's closer to 2)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET171"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4145","question":"What does the term \"proud cut\" mean?","answer":"Gelding that shows stallion-like behavior  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm520-3,4"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"novice","number":"4146","question":"What is the correct term for a male foal or an immature male horse?","answer":"Colt  <br/> <br/>ref:DET62; FCH385"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"novice","number":"4147","question":"What is a colt?","answer":"Male foal or immature male horse (FYI:  Some 4-H sources say a colt is an intact, male horse up to 3 and others say up to 4 years of age.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET62; FCH385; HSc22"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"novice","number":"4148","question":"What is a gelding?","answer":"Castrated male horse  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm520-1; HIH110-5; DET119; FCH390; HSc22"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"novice","number":"4149","question":"What is the term for an altered or castrated male horse?","answer":"Gelding  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm520-1; HIH110-5; DET119; FCH390; HSc22"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"4150","question":"Give 3 terms that mean the removal of the testicles in a horse.","answer":"Alter, geld, and castrate  <br/> <br/>ref:DET7; DET119;  DET51; HSc22"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"4151","question":"In reference to male horses, what does it mean to alter or geld?","answer":"Castrate a male horse  <br/> <br/>ref:DET7; HSc22"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"jr bonus","number":"4152","question":"Name 3 advantages of gelding or castrating horses.","answer":"Safer for children and novice horsemen, no accidental pregnancies, less prone to injuries, easier to care for, easier to haul, can keep in pen with mares, can keep in pen with geldings (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH226; HIH920-2; HSm520-1"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"4153","question":"Name 4 advantages of gelding or castrating horses.","answer":"Safer for children and novice horsemen, no accidental pregnancies, less prone to injuries, easier to care for, easier to haul, can keep in pen with mares, can keep in pen with geldings (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH226; HIH920-2; HSm520-1"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"4154","question":"What is the breeding term for the offspring of a SIRE?","answer":"Get  <br/> <br/>ref:DET120; HH56"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"novice","number":"4155","question":"What is the father of a horse called?","answer":"Sire  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm505-1; DET246; HH58"},
    {"category":"Reproduction","level":"novice","number":"4156","question":"What do you call an unaltered, adult male horse?","answer":"Stallion (also accept stud)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH110-5; DET254; HSc24"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4157","question":"When catching a horse, what area of the horse should you walk towards?","answer":"Neck or shoulders (accept either) [FYI:  Avoid the biting and kicking ends!!  Horses' prey response tells them to run or kick at things approaching them from the rear.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm205-3"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4158","question":"Why should you speak to your horse when approaching it from the rear?","answer":"To let him know you're there. (Horses can't see directly behind; if you startle him, he may kick.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm205-4"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4159","question":"When petting a horse, where should you FIRST place your hand?","answer":"Shoulder or neck (FYI:  Avoid petting the head or nose unless you know the horse.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH51"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4160","question":"If you have to work around a horse's hindquarters, why is it important to stay close?","answer":"If the horse kicks, you won't get the full impact of the kick.  <br/> <br/>ref:HH51"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"easy","number":"4161","question":"Horses kept in tie stalls must be taught to do what before you walk in beside them?","answer":"Move over (so you're not crowded against the wall) [FYI:  Draft and driving horses are often kept in tie stalls.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HH51"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4162","question":"What is the safest way to comb a horse's tail?","answer":"Stand off to the side and bring the tail around to you.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm205-5"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"sr bonus","number":"4163","question":"Name 3 safety features you should incorporate when building a barn.","answer":"Adequate ventilation, proper temperature, adequate lighting, safe convenient electrical outlets, safe convenient waterers, windows, alley width, stall door width, stall size, safe stall doors (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4164","question":"Conduits are coverings for electrical wires and are often made of metal.  Give ONE reason why electrical wiring in a barn always run in conduits.","answer":"So horses can’t chew or rub on the wires (and get shocked); fire safety; keep wires from breaking; to make the wires last longer; to keep rodents from chewing on the wires; to keep wires from horse’s feet or shoes (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm210-2; HIH320-6; HIH340-3"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"intermediate","number":"4165","question":"If possible, pastures should have rounded corners for safety.  What is a big problem with square corners in pastures?","answer":"One horse can trap another.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH330-3"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4166","question":"Why should you keep a halter and lead rope by each stall?","answer":"In case of emergency (so you can lead horses out quickly)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH340-2; HSm210-3"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"easy","number":"4167","question":"Name TWO things barn owners should do when making barn escape plans.","answer":"Plan ahead; post evacuation plans, barn layout, water source locations, master electrical switch location; have working fire extinguishers, halter and lead ropes by stalls, emergency holding area, fire drills, blindfolds; NEVER padlock stall doors  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm210-3"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"jr bonus","number":"4168","question":"Name 3 things barn owners should do when making barn escape plans.","answer":"Plan ahead; post evacuation plans, barn layout, water source locations, master electrical switch location; have working fire extinguishers, halter and lead ropes by stalls, emergency holding area, fire drills, blindfolds; NEVER padlock stall doors  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm210-3"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"sr bonus","number":"4169","question":"Name 4 things barn owners should do when making barn escape plans.","answer":"Plan ahead; post evacuation plans, barn layout, water source locations, master electrical switch location; have working fire extinguishers, halter and lead ropes by stalls, emergency holding area, fire drills, blindfolds; NEVER padlock stall doors  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm210-3"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4170","question":"Why should smoking NEVER be allowed in a barn?","answer":"It could cause a fire.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH340-2; HSm205-8"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"jr bonus","number":"4171","question":"Name 3 possible causes of a stable fire.","answer":"Smoking, lightning, spontaneous combustion, problems with electrical wiring, animals chewing through wires, appliances such as heaters, flammable substances, machinery, dust or cobwebs on electrical surfaces (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH340-1; HSm210-1"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"sr bonus","number":"4172","question":"Name 4 possible causes of a stable fire.","answer":"Smoking, lightning, spontaneous combustion, problems with electrical wiring, animals chewing through wires, appliances such as heaters, flammable substances, machinery, dust or cobwebs on electrical surfaces (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH340-1; HSm210-1"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"sr bonus","number":"4173","question":"An accelerant is a substance that increases the speed at which fires spread.  Name 3 common accelerants.","answer":"Gasoline, kerosene, oil, aerosol cans, paint thinner, charcoal lighter fluid (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH340-2"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"jr bonus","number":"4174","question":"Name 3 highly flammable materials found in barns.","answer":"Hay, bedding (straw, shavings, sawdust, or shredded newspaper), cobwebs, dust, grain dust, horse blankets, paint, fertilizer, pesticides, herbicides (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH340-1"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"sr bonus","number":"4175","question":"An ignition source is something that can cause an accelerant or flammable material to ignite or smoke.  Name 3 common ignition sources.","answer":"Cigarettes, matches, sparks, motors, heaters, electrical appliances, fence chargers, electrical fixtures, wires, batteries, broken glass, chemicals (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH340-2"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"intermediate","number":"4176","question":"For fire safety, how far away from the barn should manure piles be?","answer":"At least 20 feet (to reduce the chance of a combustion fire)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH340-4"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"easy","number":"4177","question":"What are the TWO most common causes of summer barn fires?","answer":"Lightning and spontaneous combustion (from improperly cured hay)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH340-1; HSm210-1"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"intermediate","number":"4178","question":"Name ONE area where fire extinguishers should be hung in a barn.","answer":"All exterior doorways, in the middle of long aisles, next to the electrical panel box, not greater than 75 feet apart (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH340-4; HSm210-2"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4179","question":"Give TWO fire safety rules for barns.","answer":"NO smoking, flammable substances, vehicles or machinery, portable heaters; HAVE fire extinguishers, automatic sprinklers, smoke alarms,  inside water supply and hose, exterior stall doors, space between buildings (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH340-2"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"jr bonus","number":"4180","question":"Give 3 general fire safety rules for barns.","answer":"NO smoking, flammable substances, vehicles, machinery, or portable heaters; HAVE fire extinguishers, automatic sprinklers, smoke alarms, inside water supply and hose, exterior stall doors, space between buildings (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH340-2; HSm210"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"sr bonus","number":"4181","question":"Give 4 general fire safety rules for barns.","answer":"NO smoking, flammable substances, vehicles, machinery, or portable heaters; HAVE fire extinguishers, automatic sprinklers, smoke alarms, inside water supply and hose, exterior stall doors, space between buildings (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH340-2; HSm210"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"easy","number":"4182","question":"What safety precaution should be used when using a hay net?","answer":"It should be tied high enough and tight enough to prevent the horse from getting its foot caught.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1150-2"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4183","question":"In showing your horse at halter, how much space should be left between your horse and another horse?","answer":"1 horse length or 8 feet (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm205-7"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4184","question":"When riding in groups, what kind of distance should you keep between horses?","answer":"1 horse length or 8 feet (accept either) [FYI:  On trail rides, the distance between horses should increase as the pace increases.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm205-3"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4185","question":"A horse length equals how many feet?","answer":"8 (eight) feet  <br/> <br/>ref:HH21"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4186","question":"What should you do as a safety precaution if your horse is known to kick?","answer":"Put a red ribbon in its tail.  <br/> <br/>ref:DET230; PNW51"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4187","question":"What direction should you turn the horse when leading it?","answer":"Away from you or to the right (so you don't get stepped on)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm205-3"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4188","question":"If your horse resists or doesn't want to move while you are trying to lead it, what should you NOT do?","answer":"Don't get in front and try to pull him.  <br/> <br/>ref:HH52"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4189","question":"What is the safest way to turn your horse loose in a pasture or stall?","answer":"Lead him completely through the gate or door, turn him to face the direction from which you just came, remove the halter or bridle, and don't let him bolt away because it’s a bad habit and you might get kicked. (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH52"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4190","question":"What should you NEVER do with a lead rope or reins?","answer":"Never wrap them around your hand, wrist, or body.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm205-3"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4191","question":"What is the safest position from which to lead a horse?","answer":"On the horse's left side next to the throat area (UPDATED 2020)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm205-3"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4192","question":"What should you do if your horse rears up while you are leading it?","answer":"Release the hand nearest the halter so you can stay on the ground.  <br/> <br/>ref:HH52"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4193","question":"Describe how the halter lead rope should be held.","answer":"Right hand holds the lead near the halter; left hand holds the excess lead either folded in a figure 8 or coiled loosely.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm205-3"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4194","question":"What is the safest way to lead a horse through a narrow opening or gate?","answer":"Step through first and move to one side to avoid being crowded.  <br/> <br/>ref:HH52"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4195","question":"Disregarding simple safety rules in handling horses can result in what?","answer":"Serious injury  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm205"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4196","question":"Why is it important to learn and practice safety rules?","answer":"So they'll become habits (and will keep you safe)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm210-3"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4197","question":"Why is it NOT a good idea to pair a young rider and a young horse?","answer":"Both are inexperienced (and don't know how to react in an emergency) [accept any reasonable explanation]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH210-1"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4198","question":"Give ONE reason why it's important to keep your horse under control and to keep a secure seat when riding.","answer":"Horses are easily frightened; so you won't fall off  <br/> <br/>ref:HH53"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4199","question":"When going up and down hills, you should always use which gait?","answer":"Walk (let him pick his own way so he doesn't slip or fall)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH52"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4200","question":"Which gait should you use when riding on rough ground or in mud, ice, or snow?","answer":"Walk (let him pick his own way so he doesn't slip or fall)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH53"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"sr bonus","number":"4201","question":"Name 3 safety precautions for riding in a group.","answer":"Don't run past other horses, keep horses spaced, red ribbon in tail, cross roads together, ride on same side of road, most experienced in lead, least experienced in middle, don’t leave riders behind, warn other riders of obstacles, take cell phone  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm210-7"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4202","question":"Why should you NOT run past other horses and riders?","answer":"It will make the other horses want to run and someone could get hurt (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm205-8; HH54"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"sr bonus","number":"4203","question":"When trail riding in a group with riders and horses of varying experience, describe the riding order—experience-wise—that's the safest.","answer":"Most experienced in front, least experienced in the middle, and a strong rider bringing up the rear (FYI:  Riders should ride to the level and pace of the least experienced rider.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm205-7"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4204","question":"How can you prevent many riding-related head injuries?","answer":"Wear a helmet  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm205"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4205","question":"If a rider falls off a horse while jumping and can’t move once she hits the ground, what should you do?","answer":"DON'T move her; CALL 911 if she's injured. (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH54"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4206","question":"For safety, what MUST a rider wear on his or head while jumping?","answer":"Helmet (FYI:  Helmets are required for ALL 4-H members riding or driving horses.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm205-6"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"easy","number":"4207","question":"Give ONE reason why it's a good safety practice to face the rear of the horse when mounting.","answer":"Easier to keep your balance; easier to your control horse  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm205-4"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4208","question":"Why should you NEVER mount or dismount near fences, barns, or overhanging projections?","answer":"You may get hurt.  <br/> <br/>ref:HH53"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"easy","number":"4209","question":"When riding a young or green horse, what's the SAFEST way to cross a paved road?","answer":"Dismount and lead him across  <br/> <br/>ref:HH53"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4210","question":"On what side of the road should you ride your horse?","answer":"With traffic or the side required by state law (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH53"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4211","question":"When riding, if an obstacle frightens your horse, what should you do?","answer":"Steady him and give him time to overcome his fear and then ride by the obstacle.  (Accept any correct answer or reasonable wording.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH53"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4212","question":"While riding, what should you do if your horse becomes frightened and tries to run away?","answer":"Do a one rein stop. (Turn him in a circle and tighten the circle until he stops.) [Accept any correct answers.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HH53"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4213","question":"When saddling your horse, what may happen if you drop the saddle down quick or hard on the horse's back?","answer":"You might scare the horse or hurt his back (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH53"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"jr bonus","number":"4214","question":"Name 3 times you should check your cinch.","answer":"After saddling, after walking a few steps, after mounting and riding a short distance  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm205-6"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4215","question":"When using a double-rigged saddle, which cinch should you LOOSEN FIRST?","answer":"Back cinch  <br/> <br/>ref:HH53"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4216","question":"When using a double-rigged saddle, which cinch should you BUCKLE LAST?","answer":"Back cinch  <br/> <br/>ref:HH52"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4217","question":"Why should you recheck the cinch just before mounting the horse?","answer":"Because the cinch often loosens after you walk your horse around  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm205-5"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4218","question":"What should you check on your saddle just before you mount or get on?","answer":"Cinch or girth (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm205-6"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4219","question":"In using a double rigged saddle, which cinch should you BUCKLE FIRST?","answer":"Front cinch  <br/> <br/>ref:HH53"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"easy","number":"4220","question":"What type of knot should be used when tying a rope around a horse’s neck?  This type of knot will not slip or tighten and choke the horse.","answer":"Bowline  <br/> <br/>ref:DET36"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4221","question":"Why should you NEVER tie a horse with the reins?","answer":"He might pull back, break the reins, or injure his mouth (accept any)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm205-9"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"easy","number":"4222","question":"Why should you NEVER tie your horse to an insecure or unstable object?","answer":"Horse could get scared or injured.  (FYI:  If the horse pulls back, it can break free and startle or injure the horse.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm205-3"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4223","question":"What is the only thing you should tie your horse with?","answer":"Lead rope, halter rope, or halter and lead rope (accept any)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm205-9"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4224","question":"What is the recommended knot for tying a halter rope to a fixed object?","answer":"Quick release knot  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm205-3"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"easy","number":"4225","question":"Name TWO basic knots that every horse person should know.","answer":"Quick release; bowline (also accept square knot, half hitch, double half hitch)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm645-10; HIH1125-3; HIH1150-2; PNW49"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4226","question":"You should NEVER tie a horse with what?","answer":"Reins or bridle (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH52"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"easy","number":"4227","question":"Why should a horse be tied at a level higher than its withers?","answer":"So the horse doesn’t get its leg over the rope  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm205-3"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4228","question":"Why should you tie your horse far away from strange horses?","answer":"So they won’t fight  <br/> <br/>ref:HH52"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4229","question":"When your horse is tied, what should you ALWAYS do before removing the halter?","answer":"Untie the horse (so if the horse pulls back, you won't get hurt)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH52"},
    {"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4230","question":"NEVER tie a horse at a level below what point of the horse?","answer":"Withers (UPDATED 2020)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm205-3"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4231","question":"2-part question:  What is the MINIMUM height for an indoor arena and why is a higher ceiling more desirable?","answer":"14 feet minimum; the higher the ceiling, the better lit the arena will be (with fewer shadows) [FYI: Indoor arenas used for JUMPING should be at least 16 feet tall.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-6"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4232","question":"What is the preferred indoor arena width for group riding and driving activities?","answer":"At least 60 feet wide (UPDATED 2020)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-6"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4233","question":"Name 3 things to consider before beginning construction when planning a horse facility.","answer":"Cost, safety, quality, purpose, design, layout, maintenance, number of animals, zoning laws, room for future expansion, geography, topography, climate, environmental impact, landscape, style, utilities (electricity and water), resale value  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-1; HSm225"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4234","question":"Name 3 functions of housing for horses.","answer":"Provide for welfare of horse, provide for safety of handlers, provide for comfort of handlers, make efficient use of labor, cost effective, shelter, confinement (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-1; HSm235-1"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4235","question":"Name 3 safety features for barn electrical systems.","answer":"Follow code, safe panel boxes, protected switch boxes, protected outlets, wires in conduits, thermostats on water heaters, protected light bulbs, grounded appliances, power shutoff prominently marked, lightning rods, no portable heaters  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm210-2"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4236","question":"When building a barn, what is a common mistake regarding the installation of electrical outlets?","answer":"Not providing enough electrical outlets (FYI: There should be at least one double outlet for every two stalls.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-6; HSm215-3"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4237","question":"Which type of barn light bulbs is initially expensive, but requires less power and lasts longer?","answer":"LED (FYI: There are 3 types of light bulbs—incandescent, compact fluorescent (CFL), and light-emitting diode (LED). Incandescent generates heat.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm215-3"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4238","question":"Give ONE reason why steel or aluminum is not an ideal material for building horse barns.","answer":"Often not well insulated; can be hot in the summer; can be cold in the winter  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-8"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4239","question":"Name TWO materials from which barns are made.","answer":"Steel, aluminum, wood, concrete (accept any correct answers) [FYI:  Steel and aluminum buildings can be hot in the summer and cold in the winter.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-8"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4240","question":"What is probably the best all-around material for building horse barns?","answer":"Wood (FYI:  Wood is strong, attractive, and is a good insulator.  It’s easier to install ventilation systems in wood buildings.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-8"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4241","question":"What should be the spacing of bars that are used on the upper part of the stall wall?","answer":"3 ½ – 4 inch spacing (accept any number within this range) [FYI: An adult horse’s foot is usually 4 – 6 inches in diameter; a foal’s foot can be 2 – 2 ½ inches in diameter.  Therefore, adjustments would need to be made for a foal stall.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-4; HSm215-3"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"novice","number":"4242","question":"Give ONE major purpose of a stall door.","answer":"Keep the horse safely in the stall, to let the horse into the stall, or to let the horse out of the stall.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-5"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4243","question":"Name 3 types of stall doors.","answer":"Sliding—half-wood/half-bar, full wood, and full mesh; full one-pieced hinged doors; hinged double doors (Dutch doors); stall guards (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-5"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"hard","number":"4244","question":"2-part question:  Give ONE advantage and ONE disadvantage of using Dutch or hinged double doors on stalls.","answer":"Advantages—top door can be left open for better ventilation, more light, less boredom, emergency exit; disadvantages—tend to sag, horse may try to go over the top, possibility that one door may not be closed tightly  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-5; HSm215-3"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"jr bonus","number":"4245","question":"Name 3 advantages of using Dutch or open top exterior doors for each horse stall.","answer":"Better ventilation, more light, more fresh air, allows horse to hang its head out of the stall, decreases respiratory problems, decreases boredom and vices, provides a fire exit (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm215-3; FCH920-23; HIH320-5"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4246","question":"Name ONE disadvantage of hinged stall doors.","answer":"Hinges and latches can sag; safety hazard when opened into alleyways or high-traffic areas.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-5"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4247","question":"What type of stall door is the safest and the easiest to use around horses?","answer":"Sliding door  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-6"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4248","question":"Give TWO advantages of using a stall guard instead of a stall door.","answer":"Better ventilation, more light, horse can hang its head out of the stall, decreases respiratory problems, decreases boredom and vices, provides a fire exit, cheaper (FYI:  The disadvantage of stall guard is that it’s easier for horses to escape.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-12; HIH320-5"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4249","question":"When using wire mesh as a stall front, why should the holes be 2 x 2 inches or smaller?","answer":"Safety (so horses can’t get their foot caught) [FYI: A foal’s foot can be as small as 2 inches wide.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-4"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4250","question":"Horses that are kept in stalls for any length of time depend on a good stall floor for comfort and safety.  Name 3 factors you would look for in choosing flooring material for your horse.","answer":"Durable, non-slip, absorbent, easy to clean, resistant to pawing, cost, amount of bedding needed, availability, non-toxic (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-2; HSm215-2"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"hard","number":"4251","question":"What substance helps to reduce the ammonia level in stalls?","answer":"Hydrated lime (accept lime)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH193"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4252","question":"Name ONE thing that should be done to prepare stall floors before installing rubber mats.","answer":"Make sure the floor is level, make sure the floor is well-packed, or make sure there's adequate drainage.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-3"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4253","question":"Name 3 of the more commonly used materials for stall floors.","answer":"Clay, clay and sand mix, limestone dust, wood, concrete, asphalt, rubber mats (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-2; HSm215-2; HSm225-4"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4254","question":"What type of stall floor material has many of the same disadvantages as concrete?","answer":"Asphalt (FYI:  If a seal coat is applied, asphalt floors can be slippery and can require more bedding.  Unsealed asphalt floors allow drainage through the floor making them less slippery and making then require much less bedding than concrete.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-3"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"jr bonus","number":"4255","question":"Name 3 disadvantages of using concrete floors in horse stalls.","answer":"Hard, requires more bedding, cold, slippery, increased leg problems  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-3; HSm215-2"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"hard","number":"4256","question":"When properly applied, what type of stall floor material will be as hard as concrete, but without concrete’s disadvantages?","answer":"Limestone dust  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-2; HSm215-2"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4257","question":"How thick should rubber mats that are used for stall flooring be?","answer":"At least 5/8 inch (FYI:  Floor should be level and well-packed before installing mats.  Ideally, mats should be in one piece—or in as few pieces as possible—and should fit close to the walls.  Bedding should be added to absorb urine.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-3; HSm215-2"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4258","question":"Name ONE disadvantage of using wood floors in stalls.","answer":"Slippery when wet, prone to attract rodents, difficult to clean, harbor odors (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-3; HSm215-2"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"intermediate","number":"4259","question":"Why should wood floors in stalls be at least two inches thick?","answer":"To decrease risk of rotting or decay  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-3"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4260","question":"What is the MINIMUM size recommended for a box stall?","answer":"10 feet x 10 feet  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-3; HSm215-2"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4261","question":"What is the PREFERRED box stall size?","answer":"12 feet x 12 feet (also accept 10 feet x 12 feet)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm215-1; HIH320-3"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"intermediate","number":"4262","question":"What is the MINIMUM size recommended for a foaling stall?","answer":"12 feet x 14 feet (also accept 14 feet by 14 feet) [FYI:  Ideally, one or two stalls in the barn should have a removable wall so a regular box stall can be converted into a foaling stall with double the length.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-3; HSm215-2"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"intermediate","number":"4263","question":"What is the MINIMUM size recommended for a draft horse stall?","answer":"14 feet x 14 feet  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH181"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4264","question":"What is the MINIMUM size recommended for a stallion stall?","answer":"14 feet x 14 feet (also accept 12 feet x 14 feet)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-3; HSm215-2"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4265","question":"Although not used as much as in the past, what is the typical size for a tie stall used for horses?","answer":"5 feet x 9 feet (FYI:  Tie stalls used for ponies are usually 3 feet x 6 feet.  Tie stalls used for draft horses are around 5 feet by 12 feet.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-3; HSm215-2"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"hard","number":"4266","question":"2-part question:  Give ONE advantage and ONE disadvantage of using concrete when building stalls and stall partitions.","answer":"Advantages—sturdy, easy to clean, easy to paint; disadvantages—expensive, must be reinforced so it doesn’t fall down, can result in serious injury  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-4; HSm215-3"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4267","question":"How should the stall partitions be placed so the horse's legs can't get caught under them?","answer":"Flush with or slightly below the floor  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-3"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4268","question":"Name ONE problem with using “green” oak for partitions, windows, or doors when building stalls.","answer":"It will shrink and/or twist as it dries.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-4"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"intermediate","number":"4269","question":"Name TWO things that should be considered when constructing interior stall walls.","answer":"Safety and durability (smooth, rugged materials free from any projections that can injure the horse)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-3; HSm215-2"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"intermediate","number":"4270","question":"Why should treated lumber be used for the bottom boards of stall partitions?","answer":"To prevent rotting  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-4"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4271","question":"What is the recommended height for a stall PARTITION?","answer":"Up to 7 (seven) feet from the floor (FYI:  Stall partitions should have at least one foot of space between the top of the partition and the ceiling for air movement.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-4; HSm215-1"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"novice","number":"4272","question":"What is one of the most desirable materials for building a stall?","answer":"Wood (FYI:  Rough cut oak is the strongest of wooden materials.  Tongue and groove treated yellow pine is not as hard as oak but is stronger than white pine.  Stalls and partitions can also be made of concrete which has several disadvantages.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-4; HSm215-3"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4273","question":"In the stable, adequate ventilation is necessary to reduce the presence of air contaminants.  Name TWO examples of air contaminants.","answer":"Dust, mold, microscopic debris, airborne bacteria, irritating gases (such as ammonia or methane) [accept any correct answers]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-6; HSm215-4; HSm215-1"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4274","question":"2-part question:  Name two barn conditions that are the most detrimental to a horse's health and explain why.","answer":"Extreme temperatures and high humidity; can cause respiratory problems  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-1"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4275","question":"The biggest mistake in most barns is that they are built for human comfort, not for equine health. What is the primary fault found in these barns?","answer":"Poor ventilation  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-1"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4276","question":"Give ONE reason why horse barns must be well ventilated.","answer":"Provide plenty of fresh air, decrease respiratory problems, remove air contaminants (improve air quality), decrease humidity, prevent overheating, prevent condensation, prevent odor buildup  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-6,7; HSm215-4"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4277","question":"Name ONE horse health problem that can be caused by a poorly ventilated or drafty barn.","answer":"Respiratory problems (such as heaves or COPD, pneumonia, etc.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-7; HSm215-4; HSm365-3"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4278","question":"Adequate ventilation of a stable area is defined as how many air changes per hour?","answer":"4 – 8 changes per hour (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-7; HSm215-4"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4279","question":"What is the main purpose of a cupola on a barn roof?","answer":"Ventilation (FYI:  A cupola is a dome, cylinder, or rectangular area on top of a roof that let’s more air and/or light into a building.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-8"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4280","question":"Name ONE structure commonly found on a barn roof that functions to properly ventilate a barn.","answer":"Cupola; ridge vents  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-7"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"hard","number":"4281","question":"What is the rule of thumb for ridge ventilation?","answer":"1 (one) foot of ridge ventilation for each horse or stall in the barn (FYI: A ridge vent is installed lengthwise at the peak of a roof. A gap is left which allows warm, humid air to escape.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-7; HSm215-4"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4282","question":"You do the math…Following the rule of thumb recommendation for adequate ventilation in a barn, a barn with 8 stalls would require how much ridge ventilation?","answer":"At least 8 feet of ridge ventilation (1 foot per stall)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-7; HSm215-4"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"intermediate","number":"4283","question":"You do the math…If it's 70 degrees outside, what should the MAXIMUM temperature be inside the barn?","answer":"75 degrees (FYI:  The inside of the barn should be no more than 5 degrees hotter than the outside of the barn.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-7; HSm215-4"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4284","question":"The temperature inside a barn should be no more than 5 degrees above what?","answer":"Outside temperature  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-7; HSm215-4"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4285","question":"Name 4 factors that should be considered when selecting appropriate bedding for your horse's stall.","answer":"Absorbent, dust-free, affordable, readily available, easy to dispose of, easy to handle, unpalatable, non-toxic, biodegradable, specific use (foaling stall) [accept any correct answers]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm245-2,3"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4286","question":"What is the GENERAL term used for materials placed on stall floors that absorb moisture and provide comfort to the horse?","answer":"Bedding  <br/> <br/>ref:DET26"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4287","question":"Name 3 FUNCTIONS of bedding.","answer":"Encourages horse to lie down or rest, cushions horse’s feet and legs, and soaks up urine and moisture.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH350-1,2"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4288","question":"What is bedding?","answer":"Material used to cover the stall floor to provide comfort for the horse and to absorb moisture.  <br/> <br/>ref:DET26"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"jr bonus","number":"4289","question":"Name 3 factors that should be considered when selecting appropriate bedding for your horse's stall.","answer":"Absorbent, dust-free, affordable, readily available, easy to dispose of, easy to handle, unpalatable, non-toxic, biodegradable, specific use (foaling stall) [accept any correct answers]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm245-2,3"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4290","question":"Name TWO types of bedding.","answer":"Straw, sawdust, shavings, wood pellets, shredded newspaper, cornstalks, ground corn cobs, peanut shells, peat moss, rice hulls (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH350-1,2; HSm245-3"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"jr bonus","number":"4291","question":"Name 3 types of bedding.","answer":"Straw, sawdust, shavings, wood pellets, shredded newspaper, cornstalks, ground corn cobs, peanut shells, peat moss, rice hulls (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH350-1,2; HSm245-3"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4292","question":"Name 4 types of bedding.","answer":"Straw, sawdust, shavings, wood pellets, shredded newspaper, cornstalks, ground corn cobs, peanut shells, peat moss, rice hulls (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH350-1,2; HSm245-3"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4293","question":"What type of shavings range in color from coffee brown to purplish black?","answer":"Black walnut  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH322"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4294","question":"2-part question:  When using wood shavings for bedding, what specific wood should be avoided and why?","answer":"Black walnut; it can cause laminitis or founder  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH350-1; HSm375-11; DET29,30"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"jr bonus","number":"4295","question":"Name 3 advantages to using recycled newsprint for bedding","answer":"Less dust, no pollen, absorbent, softer and more comfortable than shavings or straw, less allergies, less respiratory problems, less heavy, less labor intensive, inexpensive, eco-friendly (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH350-2; HSm245-3"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4296","question":"2-part question:  Give TWO advantages and TWO disadvantages of using sawdust or wood shavings for bedding.","answer":"Advantages—less volume, less labor, easier disposal, less combustible, seldom eaten, less odor, absorbent, good for compost; disadvantages—cost, dusty, may cause respiratory problems, some types can cause problems (oak, black walnut, and cedar)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH350-1; HSm245-3"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4297","question":"2-part question:  Give TWO advantages and TWO disadvantages of using straw for bedding.","answer":"Advantages—cheap, absorbent, comfortable, attractive, low dust, doesn’t stick to newborn foal’s nostrils or clog airway; disadvantages—highly combustible, horses will eat it, labor intensive (large volume of debris, hard to dispose of)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH350-1; HSm245-3"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4298","question":"You are trying to decide between straw and wood shavings for bedding for your 10-horse boarding facility. Straw is cheaper, but why would it be more economical to use shavings?","answer":"Shavings are less labor intensive, so you'd save on labor expenses.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH350-1; HSm245-3"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4299","question":"Why is straw preferred over shavings in bedding for a foaling stall?","answer":"Shavings can stick to the nostrils of the newborn foal.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH350-1; HSm245-3"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4300","question":"What is the ideal bedding for a foaling stall?","answer":"Straw (FYI: Shavings or sawdust can get stuck in the newborn's nostrils.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH350-1; HSm245-3; FCH243"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"hard","number":"4301","question":"In reference to management of horse facilities, what do the initials BMP stand for?","answer":"Best Management Practices  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm205-6; HIH360-1"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"intermediate","number":"4302","question":"When introducing new horses into a herd, biosecurity measures would include isolating the new horses for a MINIMUM of how many days?","answer":"14 days (FYI:  Ideal is 21 days.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH475-1; HIH445-1; ES195"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4303","question":"In regard to biosecurity, identify 3 ways to diminish the possibility of transferring infective agents with your boots.","answer":"Disinfect boots using a spray disinfectant, wear disposable boots or boot covers, disinfect boots with a boot dip, change boots (between farms or between clean and dirty areas) [accept any correct answers]  <br/> <br/>ref:ES194"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"intermediate","number":"4304","question":"Name TWO features of a good horse fence.","answer":"Strong, visible, safe, high, tight (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH330-1"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4305","question":"What is the MINIMAL width of a gate that will be used to move equipment—such as a tractor and manure spreader—in and out of a pasture?","answer":"14 feet (CORRECTED 2020) [FYI:  Gates used for HAY EQUIPMENT should be at least 16 feet wide.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH330-6"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4306","question":"Name 3 considerations when installing a paddock gate.","answer":"Sturdy, safe, aesthetically pleasing, level with the top board of the fence, at least 6 inches off the ground, located in the middle of the fence, easy to open and shut, of adequate size (for horses and handlers, for vehicles, or for equipment)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH330-6"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4307","question":"For the average 15 hand horse, what is the MINIMUM height for a perimeter or outside pasture fence?","answer":"5 feet (FYI:  Divider fences should be at least 4 ½ feet tall.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH330-1"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"hard","number":"4308","question":"Give ONE reason why the top of the fence for small paddocks, corrals, and stallion pens should be at eye level with the horse’s head in a natural upright position.","answer":"Discourage fighting over the fence with other horses; discourage horses from putting their head and neck over the fence  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH330-1"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4309","question":"Give TWO meanings of the word paddock.","answer":"Small fenced area smaller than a pasture and larger than a run; area where racehorses are saddled and viewed before a race  <br/> <br/>ref:DET201; FCH398"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4310","question":"Name TWO types of horse fences that have short life expectancies.","answer":"Board, post and rail, or plastic  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH330-3"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4311","question":"Name 4 types of fencing for horses.","answer":"Board, post and rail, wire (hot, barbless, high tensile, stock, 5 diamond V mesh), pipe, panels, PVC, vinyl, chain link (used for small pens and paddocks), cable, rubber (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH330-1-5"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"jr bonus","number":"4312","question":"Name 3 types of fencing for horses.","answer":"Board, post and rail, wire (hot, barbless, high tensile, stock, 5 diamond V mesh), pipe, panels, PVC, vinyl, chain link (used for small pens and paddocks), cable, rubber (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH330-1-5"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4313","question":"Wooden fence posts should be at least what diameter?","answer":"4 inches in diameter (FYI:  Round fence posts are stronger than square fence posts.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH330-2"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4314","question":"High-tensile vinyl fencing consists of two or three high-tensile wires embedded into a four- or five-inch vinyl rail.  Give TWO advantages of using high tensile vinyl fencing.","answer":"Safe, strong, durable, low maintenance, long-lasting, cost effective (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH330-5"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4315","question":"Give ONE advantage and ONE disadvantage of rigid and flexible PVC fencing.","answer":"Advantages—strong, flexible, low maintenance, cost-effective, don’t require painting, decreased injury to horse or fence; disadvantage—high initial cost  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH330-5"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"jr bonus","number":"4316","question":"Name 3 things that can be done to keep horses from leaning on and stretching wire fences.","answer":"Add sight board to the top, add a board in the middle of the fence, add hot wire  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH330-3"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"jr bonus","number":"4317","question":"Name 3 types of WIRE fencing.","answer":"Five-diamond-V-mesh, rectangular woven wire, stock wire, high-tensile wire, electric wire, barbless wire, barbed wire (accept any correct answers) [FYI:  Stock wire with large holes and barbed wire are considered unsafe for horses.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH330-3,4"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4318","question":"Name 4 types of WIRE fencing.","answer":"Five-diamond-V-mesh, rectangular woven wire, stock wire, high-tensile wire, electric wire, barbless wire, barbed wire (accept any correct answers) [FYI:  Stock wire with large holes and barbed wire are considered unsafe for horses.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH330-3,4"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4319","question":"Name ONE type of wire fence that is strongly DISCOURAGED for use with horses.","answer":"Barbed wire; stock wire or woven wire with large holes  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH330-3,4"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"intermediate","number":"4320","question":"What is one of the strongest and safest wires for horse fencing?","answer":"Five-diamond V-mesh (FYI:  Its strong, flexible, and its close weave prevents even foals from getting their hooves caught in the fence.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH330-3"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"hard","number":"4321","question":"Give ONE reason why five-diamond V-mesh is considered one of the safest and best wires for horse fencing.","answer":"Strong, flexible, safe, long lifespan, low maintenance (FYI:  Its close weave prevents even foals from getting their hooves caught in the fence.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH330-3"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4322","question":"Name ONE type of electric fencing that is more easily seen than uncoated wire.","answer":"Braided electric rope, polywire, electric tape (poly-tape)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH330-4"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4323","question":"What device is used to keep horses off the fence therefore reducing  damage to the fence and injury to the horse?","answer":"Hot wire or electric wire  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH330-4"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4324","question":"When fencing  horse pastures, what is the most effective way to use an electric fence?","answer":"In conjunction with another fence (use the electric fence at the top of the fence to keep the horses off of the other fence)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH330-4"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4325","question":"Name ONE disadvantage of electric tape fencing.","answer":"It can wear, stretch, loosen, or break.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH330-4"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4326","question":"Name ONE disadvantage of electric wire fencing.","answer":"Not very visible; T-posts can cause injury; not very durable; shorts out easily  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH330-4"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4327","question":"For a 5-foot-high wooden board fence, what size boards should be used?","answer":"1 x 6 (1-inch-thick by 6 inches wide) [FYI:  Boards for fences that are 6 feet high should be 1 x 8.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH330-2"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4328","question":"Name TWO disadvantages of wooden board fencing.","answer":"Expensive, hard to maintain, boards can be pushed off, horses can chew on the boards, can splinter, can break, can rot (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH330-1,2"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4329","question":"Give ONE reason why the bottom board on a fence should be 12 inches above the ground.","answer":"For mowing; to prevent foals from rolling under it (FYI:  If OVER 12 inches above the ground, foals can roll under the fence.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH330-2"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4330","question":"2-part question:  On what side of the post should fence boards be nailed and why?","answer":"Inside; so the horse can't knock the boards off  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH330-2"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4331","question":"Board fencing is expensive, but practical for several things.  Name 3.","answer":"Stallion paddocks, show paddocks, sale paddocks, turn-out pens, arenas, and creating a good-looking effect for front paddocks and along driveways to barns (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH330-1"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4332","question":"Why should fence boards for corrals and small paddocks be at least two inches thick?","answer":"To decrease injury to the horse and/or fence (FYI: It's harder for horses to stop in a small area so they might run into the fence.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH330-2"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4333","question":"You have just finished installing a beautiful white painted fence around your pasture, but you have a problem.  Your horses are leaning on the fence and fighting over it.  What can you do to keep the horses off the fence?","answer":"Put a hot wire on the top board on each side of the fence.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH330-3"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4334","question":"Name 3 DISADVANTAGES of a post and rail fence.","answer":"Expensive to install, expensive to maintain, rails can slip out of posts, posts tend to split, doesn't hold up well (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH330-3"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4335","question":"If NOT properly installed, what can happen with post and rail fencing?","answer":"Rails can slip out of the posts (which causes an unsafe fence, risk of loose horses, and higher maintenance costs)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH330-3"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4336","question":"In general, do pressure-treated or untreated posts last longer?","answer":"Pressure-treated (FYI:  Pressure-treated posts last 4 times longer than untreated posts.  Posts made from osage orange, Western red cedar, Western juniper, and black locust last a long time without being treated.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH330-2"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4337","question":"Name TWO types of wood used for fence posts that have long life expectancies and do not need to be pressure-treated.","answer":"Black locust, cedar (Western red cedar), osage orange, or western juniper  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH330-2"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4338","question":"Oak has been the wood traditionally chosen for construction of wood fences on equine facilities.  What is the major advantage of using hardwoods, especially oak, for a fence?","answer":"Oak is too hard for horses to chew.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH330-3"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4339","question":"2-part question:  Which type of wood is LEAST preferred for horse fences and give ONE reason why?","answer":"Soft pines or firs; weak in strength, horses like to chew it  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH185"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"hard","number":"4340","question":"Name TWO microorganisms that may be transmitted between horses and humans through fecal material.","answer":"Bacteria (such as E. coli or Salmonella) and protozoa (such as Giardia)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH365-5"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4341","question":"What is meant by the term \"mucking out\"?","answer":"Cleaning a stall (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET183"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4342","question":"What term refers to the process of cleaning out a horse stall by removing the manure and soiled bedding?","answer":"Mucking out (also accept stripping, picking out the stall, or other correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET183"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4343","question":"Name ONE thing that is destroyed in manure when temperatures reach 131 degrees F for 3 days.","answer":"Parasites, weed seeds, pathogenic bacteria  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH360-3"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4344","question":"Name 3 specific microorganisms that can contaminate water.","answer":"Salmonella, E. coli, Leptospira, Cryptosporidium, Giardia, blue-green algae (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH710-2"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4345","question":"Name TWO recommended methods for manure management.","answer":"Compost (remove and compost), stockpile (remove and store in piles), land application (remove daily and spread on cropland)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH365-2,3; HSm245-1,2"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4346","question":"When using a two-bin composting system, how long is it before the composted manure in the first bin is ready to use?","answer":"2 – 4 months (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH365-3"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"hard","number":"4347","question":"Composting stall waste for one to two months reduces the volume of waste by what percentage?","answer":"40 – 70 percent (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH360-3"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4348","question":"To keep fly larvae from developing in the outer layers of stockpiled manure for compost heaps, manure piles should be covered with what?","answer":"Black plastic  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-3; HSm320-2"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4349","question":"What is “compost tea”?","answer":"Compost soaked in water (FYI:  Compost is soaked in water so the nutrients leach into the water.  This nutrient rich liquid has become a popular liquid fertilizer.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH367-2,3"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"hard","number":"4350","question":"Why is properly composted manure and bedding safe to spread on pastures without worry about the spread of parasites, pathogenic bacteria, or weed seeds?","answer":"Composted manure will reach a temperature that will destroy these problems.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH360-3"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4351","question":"What is the method of managing manure that results in biodegradation of organic material?","answer":"Composting  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm245-1; HIH365-2"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4352","question":"On what type of land is it suitable to spread uncomposted manure?","answer":"Crop land or other un-grazed, vegetated areas (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH365-6"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4353","question":"How often should a manure pile be turned for aeration for optimum composting?","answer":"Every 10 days  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH360-3"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4354","question":"When properly composted, manure can be used for what?","answer":"Fertilizer or soil conditioner (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH365-2"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4355","question":"Name 3 ways you can use compost at home.","answer":"Flower beds, vegetable gardens, new planting areas, surface mulch, lawn topdressing, potting mix, compost tea, spreading on pastures (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH367-2"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"hard","number":"4356","question":"Name ONE thing that can happen if too much composted manure or bedding is added to the surface of a riding arena.","answer":"It can hold excess moisture and cause horses to slip and fall; it can have excessive dust and odor.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH365-5"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"hard","number":"4357","question":"2-part question:  Name TWO  factors that must be optimum for microbes when composting manure.","answer":"Temperature, moisture, oxygen, carbon to nitrogen ratio (FYI:  The C:N ratio should be between 25:1 and 30:1.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH365-2"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4358","question":"What should be done after rotating horses off pasture in order to spread the manure out in a thin layer for drying?","answer":"Drag or harrow the pasture  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH360-4"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4359","question":"How is manure usually managed in a pasture?","answer":"Spread  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH120-3; HIH360-4; HIH365-2"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"intermediate","number":"4360","question":"How far should a manure storage area be from a DRINKING WATER WELL?","answer":"100 feet (FYI:  Manure containers or piles should be at least 200 feet away from private water sources and 500 feet away from public water sources.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH360-2; HSm245-2"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4361","question":"What can you do to prevent mud holes around gates, water tanks, and feeding areas?","answer":"Fill the areas with gravel (or use geo-textile fabrics)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm420-4"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"jr bonus","number":"4362","question":"Your horse is a living animal that depends upon you for its basic needs.  Name 3 basic needs that must be provided for your horse.","answer":"Food, water, space, shelter, hoof care, health care (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH120-3"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4363","question":"Which is generally higher, the purchase price of a horse or the  maintenance costs of a horse?","answer":"Maintenance costs  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH210-3"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4364","question":"What health factor must be considered when purchasing paint or stain for horse stalls or fences?","answer":"Must be non-toxic  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH185; HIH330-1"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"jr bonus","number":"4365","question":"Give 3 characteristics of a good pasture area for horses.","answer":"Forage, water, salt, no weeds or toxic plants, shelter or shade, no junk, no holes, good fence, fence of adequate height, no barbed wire, adequate size (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH103"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4366","question":"You should check your pasture or turnout area for unsafe conditions.  Name 4.","answer":"Junk, holes, poisonous plants, broken fences, loose boards, sharp objects (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH103"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"jr bonus","number":"4367","question":"You should check your pasture or turnout area for unsafe conditions.  Name 3.","answer":"Junk, holes, poisonous plants, broken fences, loose boards, sharp objects (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH103"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"intermediate","number":"4368","question":"Ideally, how many acres of pasture are needed per horse to maintain forage productivity that will meet the nutritional requirements of a 1000 lb. horse?","answer":"2 – 3 acres per horse (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-1"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"intermediate","number":"4369","question":"If you have less than 1 ½ acres of pasture per horse, the grass won't be able to do what?","answer":"Grow adequately (or maintain productivity under constant grazing)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-5"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"intermediate","number":"4370","question":"Referring to pastures, what is \"carrying capacity\"?","answer":"Number of animals that a habitat can support  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc39"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4371","question":"In reference to horse paddocks, what is a dry lot?","answer":"Paddock with no plants  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH387"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"hard","number":"4372","question":"If the soil test indicates, what should be applied to a pasture to improve forage growth and to raise the pH of the soil?","answer":"Lime  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH360-4"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4373","question":"Fertilizing and liming are two important components of the management of what?","answer":"Pastures (FYI:  Soil tests should be done before fertilizing so that you only apply needed nutrients.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-5; HIH360-4"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4374","question":"What method is used to determine how much fertilizer a pasture needs in order to maintain it in top condition?","answer":"Soil test  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-5; HIH360-4; HSm240-1; HSm420-2"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4375","question":"What height should pasture grasses be for grazing horses?","answer":"4 – 8 inches (accept any number within this range) [FYI:  Grass height recommendations vary from source to source and from species to species.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm240-1; HSm420-3; HIH735-2"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4376","question":"Generally, at what grass height should horses be removed from a pasture to prevent overgrazing?","answer":"Less than 4 inches in height (FYI:  Most cool season pastures can be grazed to about 2 – 3 inches, but close grazing severely stunts pasture regrowth.  Horses should then be removed until the pasture regrows to a height of at least 6 – 8 inches.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm240-2; HSm420-3; HIH360-4"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4377","question":"What is the primary cause of runoff on horse farms?","answer":"Overgrazing  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH360-4"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4378","question":"Name ONE thing that should be prevented in good pasture management to maximize regrowth of pastures and minimize weed invasion.","answer":"Overgrazing; soil compaction  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm425-1; HIH360-4"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4379","question":"Name ONE thing that may happen to a pasture if you turn too many horses out in a small pasture and allow the pasture to be overgrazed.","answer":"Pasture will become a “dry lot” (grass will die); pasture will not be able to provide enough forage for the horses; erosion (FYI:  Overgrazing can cause erosion, water runoff, and water pollution.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm240-2; HIH740-5"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4380","question":"Give ONE reason why horses should be rotated to fresh pasture every two weeks.","answer":"To allow the pasture time to regrow or to reduce parasite infestations  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm420-3; HSm240-2; HIH430-6"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4381","question":"What TWO things will become a problem when 10% or more of the soil is exposed as a result of overgrazing?","answer":"Weeds and erosion  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH360-4"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4382","question":"How does rotational grazing increase pasture productivity?","answer":"Allows time for the pasture to re-grow. (Allows leaf tissue and carbohydrate levels to be replenished.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-5"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4383","question":"What is the advantage to rotating horses with cattle or sheep in a pasture?","answer":"Breaks the parasite life cycle  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH430-7; HIH365-6"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4384","question":"Name ONE thing resting your pasture does.","answer":"Gives grass time to regrow; lets grass develop strong roots to prevent soil erosion  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH735-2; HSm240-2; HSm420-3"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4385","question":"What is rotational grazing?","answer":"Letting horses graze one pasture for a while, then moving them to another pasture (so the first pasture can rest)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm240-2; HSm420-3; FCH105"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4386","question":"In reference to pasture management, give ONE meaning for the term \"spot grazer\".","answer":"Horses choose to graze in preferred areas; horses prefer specific types of plants; horses avoid eating grass that is contaminated with feces.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-5"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4387","question":"Name 3 steps in good pasture management. (ACCEPT ANY CORRECT ANSWERS)","answer":"Don't overstock, don’t overgraze, rotate pastures, mow pastures, re-seed pastures, soil test, fertilize as needed, scatter manure piles, create sacrifice area, no junk, no toxic plants, no noxious weeds, keep horses off wet pasture  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm420-2,3; HSm425-1; HIH740-5"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4388","question":"2-part question:  Besides dragging your pasture, name TWO ways to  get better manure distribution and to avoid concentration of manure in isolated spots.","answer":"Move feeding troughs periodically, have several watering facilities available, split pastures, rotate pastures  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH365-2"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4389","question":"Give TWO benefits to keeping your pastures clipped or mowed.","answer":"Aid in weed control, remove old growth grasses, prevents plants from becoming too mature, helps maintain balance of grasses and legumes, helps spread manure  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH360-4"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4390","question":"In general, how often should a pasture be re-seeded?","answer":"Every 3 – 5 years (accept any number within this range) [Also accept as indicated by lack of forage and ground cover.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH365-6; HIH360-4"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4391","question":"In reference to pasture management, what is a sacrifice area?","answer":"Designated area where animals are enclosed so pastures can rest (FYI:  Sacrifice areas are usually dirt paddocks that allows horses to exercise, socialize, and get fresh air.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm240-1"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4392","question":"In regard to pasture management, name TWO circumstances when horses should be kept off the pasture.","answer":"During pesticide spraying, during fertilizing, after re-seeding, to reduce overgrazing, when pasture is lush, during the winter, when the soil is wet (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH360-3,4"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4393","question":"Name ONE thing that can happen to a pasture if horses are allowed out when the soils are wet.","answer":"Turf damage, trampled forage, soil compaction, manure runoff  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH360-4; HIH365-2"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4394","question":"How many times a year should pastures be mowed and chain harrowed or dragged to break up manure piles and expose parasite eggs to the elements?","answer":"2 – 4 times per year (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH365-6"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4395","question":"A complete set of records should be kept on every horse. Name 5 pieces of information that should be kept. (ACCEPT ANY CORRECT ANSWERS)","answer":"ID info—name, sex, breed, color, markings, tattoo, brand, height, weight; proof of ownership—brand inspection, bill of sale, registration certificate; boarding info; feeding info; health info—vaccinations, hoof care, deworming, dental, Coggins test  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH210-1-4; HIH445-1; HSm220-3"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"jr bonus","number":"4396","question":"A complete set of records should be kept on every horse. Name 3 pieces of information that should be kept. (ACCEPT ANY CORRECT ANSWERS)","answer":"ID info—name, sex, breed, color, markings, tattoo, brand, height, weight; proof of ownership—brand inspection, bill of sale, registration certificate; boarding info; feeding info; health info—vaccinations, hoof care, deworming, dental, Coggins test  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH210-1-4; HIH445-1; HSm220-3"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"hard","number":"4397","question":"Drainage from a 3-sided run-in shed to an absorption pit or grass waterway should have what percent of slope?","answer":"2%  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH360-3"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4398","question":"Name 3 advantages of an open front shed.","answer":"Inexpensive, no daily stall cleaning, less labor, well ventilated, less fire risk, less space needed per horse, less bedding required, horses have room to move (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH181"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4399","question":"Name 3 features that would be desirable in an open front shed.","answer":"Should face away from the prevailing winds (or towards the winter sun), have adequate drainage (2% slope), have opening wide enough for all horses to safely run out, have roof slope away from the opening, be built on high ground, be 20 feet deep  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-7; FCH181"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4400","question":"As opposed to keeping horses in separate stalls, name ONE disadvantage of using open front shelters or run-in sheds for several horses.","answer":"Unable to monitor diet of each individual horse, unable to monitor the amount of exercise of each horse, increased risk of injuries (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH181"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4401","question":"In order to allow water to drain away from buildings and to prevent muddy conditions, the site for building a barn should have what slope?","answer":"Slope of 2 – 6%  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH320-2"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"hard","number":"4402","question":"What term describes the shape and the slope of the land?","answer":"Topography  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH310-1"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4403","question":"As part of an environmental analysis, name 3 natural environment features that should be considered before building a new horse facility.","answer":"Topography or slope of land, drainage, prevailing winds, solar radiation, precipitation, vegetation, soil characteristics, available water (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH310-1; HSm225-1"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"intermediate","number":"4404","question":"Name TWO important features to consider when constructing a wash rack.","answer":"Location, drainage, footing when wet, access to water, access to hot water (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm225-4,5; DET287,288"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"hard","number":"4405","question":"In reference to water quality management, what is nonpoint source water pollution?","answer":"Pollutants from many sources contaminate a waterway (such as runoff carrying soil, wastes, chemicals, etc.) [FYI:  Point source water pollution has a single identifiable cause such as a pipe draining sewage into a waterway.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH360-1"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4406","question":"Name ONE thing that can cause ground water contamination.","answer":"Improperly constructed wells, pesticides, fertilizers, fuel spills, leaking storage tanks, hazardous waste dumping, chemicals being mixed near wells or waterways, improperly functioning septic tanks, herbicides, manure (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH360-1"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"hard","number":"4407","question":"What are TWO important considerations when evaluating water quality for horses?","answer":"Presence of biological contaminants (such as pathogenic microorganisms); presence of chemical compounds [FYI:  Presence of chemical compounds is tested by evaluating TDS (Total Dissolved Solids).]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH710-2"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"hard","number":"4408","question":"What is used as the standard test for bacteriological safety of water?","answer":"Fecal coliform counts  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH360-1"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"hard","number":"4409","question":"What is the significance of TDS or total dissolved solids in water quality management?","answer":"Lower the TDS, the purer the water (FYI:  TDS measures the concentration of ions dissolved in water.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH710-2; FCH7"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4410","question":"Give 3 ways to protect streams and riverbanks from trampling, destruction of vegetation, and contamination.","answer":"Deny access with fencing, limit access with fencing, create natural buffer zones, use water tanks instead of allowing stream access, no chemicals near stream, no chemicals in storm drains or sewers, dispose of chemicals properly  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH360-4,5"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4411","question":"2-part question:  Name TWO goals of a water quality management plan.","answer":"Reduce runoff; protect ground water from contamination  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH360-1"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4412","question":"Name 3 ways to reduce runoff and water contamination.","answer":"Waste management (proper manure removal, storage, and disposal), pasture management (rotational grazing, soil testing, and providing a sacrifice area), watercourse and runoff management, and river and stream bank management  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH360-1-4"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4413","question":"Give ONE purpose of a buffer strip in watercourse management.","answer":"Slows down runoff water, increases absorption of runoff water, filters animal wastes, filters soil out, helps prevent soil erosion (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH360-4"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4414","question":"Give 3 purposes of increasing the vegetative cover between steep slopes and waterways.","answer":"Slows down runoff water, increases absorption of runoff water, filters animal wastes, filters soil out, helps prevent soil erosion (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH360-4"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4415","question":"Erosion of pastures is affected by what 3 environmental or topographical factors?","answer":"Soil type, slope of the land (topography), amount of precipitation, and vegetative cover (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH360-4"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"novice","number":"4416","question":"What do you call an unwanted or out of place plant that can grow in bare areas of pastures?","answer":"Weed  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm420-2"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4417","question":"Prevention is the most cost-effective method of weed control.  Weeds often appear in bare areas so avoid overgrazing and maintain healthy pasture growth.  Name ONE way to control weeds once they are established.","answer":"Mechanical—pull weeds, mow weeds; chemical—herbicides or weed killers (FOLLOW DIRECTIONS); biological—use insects or diseases to kill weeds; re-seed bare areas (accept general or specific)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm425-2; HSm240-1; HIH740-5"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"jr bonus","number":"4418","question":"Prevention is the most cost-effective method of weed control.  Weeds often appear in bare areas so avoid overgrazing and maintain healthy pasture growth.  Name 3 ways to control weeds once they are established.","answer":"Mechanical—pull weeds, mow weeds; chemical—herbicides or weed killers (FOLLOW DIRECTIONS); biological—use insects or diseases to kill weeds; re-seed bare areas (accept general or specific)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm425-2; HSm240-1; HIH740-5"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4419","question":"When using herbicides to control weeds, it's important to do what?","answer":"Follow the directions  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-5; HSm425-2"},
    {"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4420","question":"Give ONE reason why it's important to identify which weeds are present in your pasture.","answer":"So you can use the right product to control them, so you can identify if any are poisonous, so they won’t crowd out the grass (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH740-5; HSm240-1"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4421","question":"What device—normally made of metal or rubber—is attached to the headstall and is used to regulate the position of the horse's head and to help control the pace and direction of the horse?","answer":"Bit  <br/> <br/>ref:DET29; HIH1100-8-10"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4422","question":"In cold weather, what should a rider do before placing the bit in the horse's mouth?","answer":"Warm the bit.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH420-3"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4423","question":"The corner of the horse's mouth should have how many wrinkles with a properly fitted bridle?","answer":"1 or 2 wrinkles  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-8; HSm155-6"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4424","question":"When the bridle is correctly adjusted, the bit will rest on what part of the horse's mouth?","answer":"Bars or interdental space (space between the incisors and the premolars)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-8"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"sr bonus","number":"4425","question":"Name 3 different materials used to make bit mouthpieces.","answer":"Stainless steel, German silver, solid nickel, copper, aluminum, rubber, vulcanite, brass, leather, Happy Mouth, sweet iron (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-10"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4426","question":"Which mouthpiece material is very lightweight, brittle, and may cause the horse's mouth to be dry?","answer":"Aluminum  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-10"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4427","question":"Which material, when used in a bit mouthpiece, increases salivation?","answer":"Copper (also accept sweet iron)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-10"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4428","question":"Give ONE reason why copper is sometimes used in bit mouthpieces.","answer":"Increases salivation; makes the horse's mouth more responsive to the bit  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-10"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"4429","question":"German silver is NOT made from silver, but is made from a combination of three other metals.  Name ONE of these metals.","answer":"Copper, nickel, and stainless steel  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-10"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"4430","question":"What is the name of the soft, apple-flavored, rubber mouthpiece that's very gentle and is hypo-allergenic?","answer":"Happy Mouth  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-10"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4431","question":"What \"never rust\" material is used in making bits?","answer":"Stainless steel (FYI:  Stainless steel is a steel alloy that contains iron, chromium, and nickel.  Chrome keeps bits rust-free and easy to clean; nickel adds durability.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-10"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4432","question":"What is the most common material used in making bits?","answer":"Stainless steel (FYI:  Stainless steel is a steel alloy that contains iron, chromium, and nickel.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-10"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4433","question":"What is the term for a bit mouthpiece that has a hinge in the middle?","answer":"Broken or jointed mouthpiece (Do NOT accept curb or snaffle; both can have solid or broken mouthpieces.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET40"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4434","question":"In reference to bits, what does the term \"mullen mouth\" mean?","answer":"Bit mouthpiece that has a slight bow or curve  <br/> <br/>ref:DET183"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4435","question":"What is the term for the type of solid bit mouthpiece that has a slight bow in the middle instead of a port?","answer":"Mullen mouth  <br/> <br/>ref:DET183 picture; HIH1100-11 picture"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4436","question":"In general, how do bits operate?","answer":"By applying pressure to certain parts of the mouth or head  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-8; HSm155-5,6"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"sr bonus","number":"4437","question":"Name 3 areas where a bit or bridle applies pressure.","answer":"Corners of the mouth, bars, tongue, roof of the mouth, curb groove, nose, poll  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-8; HSm155-6"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4438","question":"How can you remove rust spots from a bit?","answer":"Use steel wool  <br/> <br/>ref:HH31"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"jr bonus","number":"4439","question":"Name 3 factors that affect the severity of a bit.","answer":"Thickness of the mouthpiece, type of mouthpiece, texture of mouthpiece, amount of leverage (length of shanks), position of horse's head, pressure points, pinching of bit, shape of horse’s mouth, quality of rider’s hands (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm155-5"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"sr bonus","number":"4440","question":"Name 4 factors that affect the severity of a bit.","answer":"Thickness of the mouthpiece, type of mouthpiece, texture of mouthpiece, amount of leverage (length of shanks), position of horse's head, pressure points, pinching of bit, shape of horse’s mouth, quality of rider’s hands (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm155-5"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"jr bonus","number":"4441","question":"Name 3 bits.","answer":"Snaffle (O-ring or loose ring, D-ring, eggbutt, half cheek, full cheek), curb, hackamore, Kimberwicke, Pelham, Weymouth, Liverpool, spade, Tom Thumb, walking horse, bar, roper curved cheek, Baucher, Fulmer (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100; HSm155"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"sr bonus","number":"4442","question":"Name 5 bits.","answer":"Snaffle (O-ring or loose ring, D-ring, eggbutt, half cheek, full cheek), curb, hackamore, Kimberwicke, Pelham, Weymouth, Liverpool, spade, Tom Thumb, walking horse, bar, roper curved cheek, Baucher, Fulmer (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100; HSm155"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4443","question":"Explain the differences between a snaffle bit, a curb bit, and a hackamore.","answer":"Snaffle bit has no shanks (reins attach directly to rings on the mouthpiece), curb bit has shanks (that cause leverage), and hackamore has no mouthpiece.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-8; HSm155"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4444","question":"Name the basic 3 classifications of bits.","answer":"Snaffle, curb, hackamore (bit-less bridle)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-8; HSm155"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"intermediate","number":"4445","question":"What influences the severity of a bosal?","answer":"Stiffness of the bosal (FYI:  The bosal is the braided rawhide noseband on a hackamore.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH28"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"4446","question":"What is the name for a bit, used in conjunction with a halter, that has three small rings—two for the cheek pieces and one for a lead rein?  It's used to help control horses that rear.","answer":"Anti-rearing bit or Chifney (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET13"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4447","question":"Referring to bits, what is a cricket?","answer":"Attachment on a bit's port that spins when the horse moves its tongue (a roller)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET72"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4448","question":"What is the name of the attachment on the port of a curb bit that will spin in the horse's mouth as it moves its tongue?","answer":"Cricket or roller (accept either) [FYI:  A “half breed” Western bit has a roller in the port that’s usually made of copper; it helps keep the horse’s mouth moist.]  <br/> <br/>ref:DET72; HIH1100-10"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4449","question":"What is a curb chain?","answer":"Chain strap that is attached to a curb bit (and is over the curb or chin groove of the horse)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET75"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4450","question":"What is the name of the strap commonly seen on a Western bridle, but not seen on a simple English bridle?","answer":"Curb strap or curb chain (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET75; HSm155-5"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4451","question":"2-part question:  What part of a curb bit's mouthpiece curves up over the tongue and what is its purpose?","answer":"Port; relieves pressure on the tongue or applies pressure to the roof of the mouth (accept either purpose)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-10; HSm155-7"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4452","question":"In reference to bits, what is the port?","answer":"Raised curved \"bump\" in the bit mouthpiece (that applies pressure to the roof of the mouth and/or relieves tongue pressure) [accept any reasonable wording]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-10; HSm155-7"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4453","question":"Name TWO purposes of the port on a curb bit.","answer":"Relieves tongue pressure; applies pressure to the roof of the mouth.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-10; HSm155-7"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4454","question":"What is created when shanks are added to a bit?","answer":"Leverage  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-8; HSm155-6"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4455","question":"In reference to a curb bit, what is the shank?","answer":"Part of the bit from the mouthpiece down  <br/> <br/>ref:DET243; HIH1100-10; HSm155-6"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4456","question":"What is the portion of the bit from the mouthpiece down?","answer":"Shank  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-8; HSm155-6"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4457","question":"What part of a bit enables it to be classified as a leverage bit?","answer":"Shanks  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-8; HSm155-1"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"4458","question":"In reference to bridles, where would a stabilizer or roper’s bar be found?","answer":"On a curb bit (FYI: It is bar that connects the shanks near where the reins attach.  It's also called a connecting bar or bit bar.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET67"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4459","question":"Name TWO other places where a leverage bit applies pressure besides the mouth.","answer":"Poll; under the chin (chin groove or curb groove)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-8; HSm155-5"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4460","question":"What is a Liverpool bit?","answer":"Curb bit commonly used for driving (FYI: A Liverpool bit has several rein attachment slots.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm155-7"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4461","question":"What type of Western curb bit is GENERALLY considered the most severe?","answer":"Spade bit (FYI:  Other severe bits are gag bits, elevator bits, and mechanical hackamores.  These should only be used by extremely experienced horsemen.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-10; HSm155-7"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4462","question":"What kind of bit is a Tom Thumb?","answer":"Curb bit (with a jointed mouthpiece) [Do NOT accept snaffle bit even though it's often called a \"cowboy snaffle\".  It is a curb bit because it has shanks.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm155-7"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4463","question":"Identify this bit:  It's a curb bit with short, straight, swivel shanks, and a broken mouthpiece; it's sometimes called a “cowboy snaffle”.","answer":"Tom Thumb  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm155-7; DET270"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4464","question":"What TWO bits does the double bridle use?","answer":"Snaffle (bridoon) and curb (Weymouth) [pronounced WAY-muth]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-10; HSm155-6"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4465","question":"A bridoon and a curb are typically used with what type of bridle?","answer":"Weymouth, full, or double bridle (accept any) [pronounced WAY-muth]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-10"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4466","question":"What is the name for the small ring snaffle that when combined with a curb bit makes up a Weymouth or double bridle?","answer":"Bridoon (FYI:  A bridoon carrier is a strap that holds the bridoon in place.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-10; HSm155-6"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4467","question":"What is a bridoon?","answer":"Snaffle bit used on a double bridle (also accept another name for a snaffle bit)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-8; HSm155-6"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4468","question":"Describe a Kimberwicke bit.","answer":"English bit that looks similar to a D-ring snaffle that has slots for attaching the headstall, hooks for attaching a curb chain, and may have separate slots for attaching snaffle and curb reins.  (FYI:  Only one rein is used on a Kimberwicke bit.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-10; HSm155-6; DET4890"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4469","question":"Which bit looks similar to a D-ring snaffle, but has slots for attaching the headstall and hooks for attaching a curb chain? It may also have snaffle and curb rein slots.","answer":"Kimberwicke  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-10; HSm155-6"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4470","question":"Describe a Pelham bit.","answer":"English bit with shanks and rings for snaffle reins and rings for curb reins.  (FYI:  It may have jointed, low port, or other types of mouthpieces.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-10; HSm155-6"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"intermediate","number":"4471","question":"What bit is capable of acting as two bits in ONE mouthpiece? With TWO sets of reins, there are both snaffle and curb actions?","answer":"Pelham (Do NOT accept Kimberwicke which has one set of reins or double, full, or Weymouth which has two different bits.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-10; HSm155-6"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4472","question":"What common piece of tack does the term jaquima refer to? (pronounced HAH-kee-mah)","answer":"Bosal or hackamore (pronounced boe-SAL or BOE-sal)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-10; HSm155-7"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4473","question":"Name TWO types of hackamores.","answer":"Bosal, mechanical, sidepull, bit-less bridle (pronounced boe-SAL or BOE-sal)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-10; HSm155-7"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"intermediate","number":"4474","question":"What is the Spanish word for hackamore?","answer":"Jaquima (pronounced HAH-kee-mah)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-10; HSm155-7"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4475","question":"Explain the difference between a TRUE hackamore and a hackamore \"bit\".","answer":"True hackamore or \"jaquima\" has a bosal noseband; hackamore bit is a mechanical hackamore (which is a jointed \"leverage bit\" with metal shanks and a curb chain).  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-10; HSm155-7"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4476","question":"What is the braided rawhide or rope noseband on a hackamore called?","answer":"Bosal (pronounced boe-SAL or BOE-sal)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-10; HSm155-7"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4477","question":"In reference to tack, what is a bosal? (pronounced boe-SAL or BOE-sal)","answer":"Noseband of a hackamore (often made of braided rawhide) [If they answer hackamore, they need to describe it.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-10; DET35; HSm155-7"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4478","question":"What is a throatlatch made of cord that fastens the bottom of the bosal to the headstall?","answer":"Fiador (pronounced FEE-ah-door)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm155-7; DET106; HH27"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4479","question":"What is the \"ball\" that joins the ends of the braided sections of a bosal?  The mecate attaches to this area of the bosal. (pronounced meh-CAHT-ay)","answer":"Heel knot or hackamore knot  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm155-7"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4480","question":"In reference to tack, what is a mecate? (pronounced meh-CAHT-ay)","answer":"Combination of lead rope and reins on a bosal hackamore (FYI:  Traditionally, mecates are 22 feet long horsehair ropes that are attached to the bosal and are a combination of lead rope and reins.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm155-7"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4481","question":"What is the term for the combination of lead rope and reins on a hackamore?","answer":"Mecate (pronounced meh-CAHT-ay) [FYI:  Traditionally, mecates are 22 feet long horsehair ropes that are attached to the bosal and are a combination of lead rope and reins.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm155-7"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4482","question":"Name ONE area to which a hackamore applies pressure.","answer":"Nose, face, jaw, chin, poll, and cheeks (Do NOT accept mouth.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm155-7"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"sr bonus","number":"4483","question":"Name 3 areas to which a hackamore applies pressure.","answer":"Nose, face, jaw, chin, poll, and cheeks (Do NOT accept mouth.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm155-7; HIH1100-8"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4484","question":"What is a non-leverage bit?","answer":"Bit without shanks (snaffle)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm155-5,6; HIH1100-8"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4485","question":"A rider's pull on the reins of a snaffle causes what kind of pressure?","answer":"Direct pressure  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm155-5,6; HIH1100-8"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4486","question":"Why is a snaffle called a direct action bit?","answer":"Reins attach directly to rings on the mouthpiece which causes a direct pulling action.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm155-5,6; HIH1100-10"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"sr bonus","number":"4487","question":"Name 3 pressure points affected by a snaffle bit.","answer":"Corners of the mouth, bars, and tongue (FYI:  Snaffle bits do NOT apply pressure to the poll.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm155-6; HIH1100-8"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4488","question":"Which snaffle bit is more severe, an eggbutt with a mouthpiece as thick as your pinkie or a D-ring with a mouthpiece as thick as your thumb?","answer":"Eggbutt with the thinner mouthpiece  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm155-6; HIH1100-10"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4489","question":"2-part question:  The width of a snaffle bit is very important.  Explain what can happen from a bit that's too narrow and a bit that's too wide.","answer":"If the bit’s too narrow it causes pinching; if the bit’s too wide it causes loss of control.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm155-6; HIH1100-8"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4490","question":"Name ONE of the most common bits used for Thoroughbred racehorses.","answer":"Ring bit; loose ring snaffle (UPDATED 2020) [FYI:  A ring bit includes a ring that passes through the horse's mouth and encircles the lower jaw. The Dexter ring bit is used in conjunction with a snaffle bit and is the most commonly used ring bit.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm175-8"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4491","question":"What is the main difference in the appearance of a D-ring snaffle and an egg butt snaffle?","answer":"Shape of the rings  <br/> <br/>ref:DET85,89"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4492","question":"What are you referring to when you're using the terms D-ring, round, or full cheek?","answer":"Snaffle bits (specifically the rings of snaffle bits)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm155-6; HIH1100-8"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"intermediate","number":"4493","question":"What is a snaffle key bit?","answer":"Snaffle bit with small metal pieces dangling from the center of the mouthpiece (FYI: It's used in training colts.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET250; HH29"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4494","question":"What is another name for an English double bridle?","answer":"Weymouth or full bridle (pronounced WAY-muth)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm155-6; HIH1100-10; HH27"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4495","question":"What kind of bridle uses TWO bits?","answer":"Weymouth, double bridle, or full bridle (accept any) [pronounced WAY-muth]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm155-6; HIH1100-10; HH27"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"4496","question":"On an English double bridle, what does the lip strap do?","answer":"Positions the curb chain  <br/> <br/>ref:DET170"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4497","question":"What is the term for a noseband on an English bridle?","answer":"Cavesson  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-6; HH27"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4498","question":"What noseband is a cross between a cavesson and a figure 8 noseband?","answer":"Flash noseband  <br/> <br/>ref:DET109"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4499","question":"Give TWO meanings of the term cavesson.","answer":"Noseband on an English bridle; headstall used for longe line training  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-6; HH27"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"sr bonus","number":"4500","question":"Name 3 types of nosebands or cavessons.","answer":"Plain, longeing, dropped, flash, figure 8, crank (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET109; DET107; DET86; DET171"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4501","question":"What is the function of a cavesson?","answer":"To keep the horse's mouth closed  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-6; HH27"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"4502","question":"2-part question:  On a Pelham bridle, which rein functions as the snaffle rein and which rein functions as the curb rein?","answer":"Upper rein is the snaffle; lower rein is the curb rein.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-10; HSm155-6; HH28"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"jr bonus","number":"4503","question":"Name the 3 MAIN parts of a bridle.","answer":"Reins, bit, and headstall  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-6; HSm155-3; HH27"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4504","question":"What piece of the bridle goes around the horse's forehead?","answer":"Brow band  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-9; DET41; HH28"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4505","question":"What part of the bridle keeps the crownpiece from sliding down the horse's neck?","answer":"Brow band  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-6; DET41"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4506","question":"What is the brow band on a bridle?","answer":"Part of the bridle that goes across the forehead (above the eyes)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-9; DET41; HH28"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4507","question":"What is the purpose of a brow band?","answer":"To keep the bridle from sliding down the horse's neck  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-6; DET41"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4508","question":"What is the name of the SPECIFIC part of the headstall that holds the bit up in the horse's mouth?","answer":"Cheek piece  <br/> <br/>ref:DET94"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4509","question":"In reference to parts of a bridle headstall, what are cheek pieces?","answer":"Side pieces of the bridle (that hold the bit in the mouth)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-9"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4510","question":"What part of the bridle lies at the top of the horse's head behind the ears?","answer":"Crown piece  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-8; DET74"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4511","question":"To what SPECIFIC part of the English bridle's headstall does the throatlatch attach?","answer":"Crown piece  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-7"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4512","question":"When bridling, which ear should be pulled under the crownpiece LAST?","answer":"Left ear (FYI:  The right ear should be pulled under the crown piece first.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm205-5; HH53"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4513","question":"Name the TWO pieces of the bridle that apply pressure to the poll and under the chin when using a curb bit.","answer":"Crown piece applies pressure to the poll; curb strap or curb chain apply pressure under the chin.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-8"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4514","question":"What is the collective term for the parts of the bridle minus the bit and reins?","answer":"Headstall  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-6; HSm155-5"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4515","question":"What is the main function of a headstall?","answer":"To hold the bit in place  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-6"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4516","question":"Name the part of the bridle that's found on an English bridle, but NOT on most Western ones.","answer":"Noseband or cavesson (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-7,9"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4517","question":"What part of the headstall keeps the horse from rubbing the bridle off?","answer":"Throatlatch  <br/> <br/>ref:DET267"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4518","question":"Give ONE name for the type of reins that are connected to each other with a romal.","answer":"California reins or closed reins, or romal reins (FYI:  The romal is actually the flexible quirt attached to California or closed reins.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-8; HH20"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4519","question":"What is the purpose of the headstall, bit, and reins?","answer":"Provides communication between the horse and rider  <br/> <br/>ref:HH1100-6"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"sr bonus","number":"4520","question":"Name 3 types of English reins.","answer":"Laced, plain, web, rubber (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-6; HSm170-5"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4521","question":"Name ONE advantage of web, laced, or rubber reins.","answer":"More secure grip; not slippery when wet  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-6; HSm170-3"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4522","question":"Name TWO equestrian events where rubber reins would be used.","answer":"Racing, steeplechase, eventing, cross country, jumping  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-6; HSm170-5"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4523","question":"What type of reins are covered with a pebbled surface on the handgrip portions and are used in racing to provide a secure grip?","answer":"Rubber reins  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-6; HSm170-7"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4524","question":"When riding with romal reins in Stock Seat Equitation, how much distance should there be between the hand holding the reins and the hand holding the romal? (pronounced roe-MAL)","answer":"At least 16 inches  <br/> <br/>ref:HH24"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4525","question":"What is the name for the flexible quirt that's attached to California-style reins?","answer":"Romal (pronounced roe-MAL)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-8"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4526","question":"In addition to ropers, what other type of rider would use roping reins?","answer":"Gymkhana (games) riders or barrel racers (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-8"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4527","question":"Describe roping reins.","answer":"Reins are one continuous strap. (FYI:  They are used by ropers and gymkhana riders so the rider doesn't drop or lose the reins.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-8"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4528","question":"What type of Western reins is one continuous strap and is used so the rider doesn't drop or lose a rein?","answer":"Roping reins  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-8"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4529","question":"Why are roping reins one continuous strap?","answer":"To prevent dropping or losing the reins  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-8"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4530","question":"What are the most commonly used type of Western reins?","answer":"Split reins  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-8"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4531","question":"What is a war bridle?","answer":"Emergency bridle made of rope (also a \"come along\" which is made of stiff rope and is used for leading unruly horses)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET287"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4532","question":"What is an emergency bridle made of rope called?","answer":"War bridle  <br/> <br/>ref:DET287"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4533","question":"What type of bridle is often made of stiff lariat rope and is used in leading unruly horses by exerting pressure on the poll?  It is sometimes called a “come-along”.","answer":"War bridle  <br/> <br/>ref:DET287"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4534","question":"On a Western bridle, on what side of the horse does the throatlatch buckle?","answer":"Left side  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-8"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4535","question":"Describe a SLIP (S-L-I-P) ear headstall.","answer":"Small loop is added to the crownpiece to go around the ear.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-8; HSm155-5"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4536","question":"What is the difference between a SPLIT ear and a SLIP ear bridle?","answer":"SPLIT ear bridle has a split in the crownpiece for the ear to pass through; SLIP ear bridle has a loop added to the crownpiece for the ear to pass through.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-8; HSm155-6"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4537","question":"Describe the following Western headstalls:  split ear, slip ear, and conventional.","answer":"SPLIT ear bridle has a split in the crownpiece for the ear to pass through; SLIP ear bridle has a loop added to the crownpiece for the ear to pass through; conventional has a browband.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-8; HSm155-5"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4538","question":"On tack, name ONE area where leather is most likely to break.","answer":"Around buckles, bends, or attachments  <br/> <br/>ref:HH34"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"sr bonus","number":"4539","question":"Name 3 things leather should be inspected for, especially when buying used tack.","answer":"Cracked, stiff, dried out, thin or worm, broken stitching, stretched out or enlarged holes (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH34"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4540","question":"Under what conditions should leather and rope halters be stored?","answer":"In a dry place  <br/> <br/>ref:HH34"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4541","question":"What is the main problem with stiff or dried out leather tack?","answer":"It can break.  (It's brittle and will crack easily.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH34"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4542","question":"Name TWO products commonly used to keep leather soft and pliable.","answer":"Leather oil, saddle soap, leather conditioner (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET188; HH34"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4543","question":"What ONE thing should NEVER be done to leather, no matter how wet it gets?","answer":"Never place it near heat.  <br/> <br/>ref:HH34"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4544","question":"What is Neatsfoot oil?","answer":"Oil used for conditioning, softening, or preserving leather (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET188; HH34"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4545","question":"Name TWO ways to take care of leather tack.","answer":"Protect it from moisture, keep it clean, keep it oiled or conditioned, sponge it after use, don't place it near heat (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH34"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4546","question":"How does leather conditioner work?","answer":"Puts vital oils back into the leather.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-14; HH34"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4547","question":"Name ONE practice that can extend the use and life of any leather article.","answer":"Regular cleaning, regular conditioning or oiling, protection, don't place it near heat (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH34"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"novice","number":"4548","question":"What should you do if you find a strap that's thin from wear or torn?","answer":"Replace it as soon as possible.  <br/> <br/>ref:HH23; HH34"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4549","question":"Give ONE reason why a stable is a poor place to store leather.","answer":"Temperature, dampness, rodents, ammonia from urine or manure  <br/> <br/>ref:HH34"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4550","question":"For what purpose is glycerin soap used?","answer":"To clean leather tack  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-14; HH34"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4551","question":"Why should tack be sponged or wiped off after use?","answer":"To remove dirt and/or sweat  <br/> <br/>ref:HH34"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"intermediate","number":"4552","question":"Saddles, stirrups, bits, and chariots were all invented in what continent?","answer":"Asia  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm130-8"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"jr bonus","number":"4553","question":"Name 3 criteria you should consider when selecting a saddle.","answer":"Should fit the horse, should fit the rider, should be appropriate for the desired style of riding, should not interfere with performance or ability of horse (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-3"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"intermediate","number":"4554","question":"Give ONE purpose of a saddle.","answer":"To make riding more comfortable for the horse and rider; to distribute the rider's weight over the horse's back; to give the rider a sense of security (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET239"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"jr bonus","number":"4555","question":"Name 3 types of saddles.","answer":"Western (pleasure, trail, cutting reining, barrel racing, roping), English (dressage, all purpose, forward seat, saddle seat or cut back), Australian,  racing, polo, endurance, pack (sawbuck or crossbuck, Decker) [accept any correct answers]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm155-1-4; HSm135; HIH1100-1,5"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4556","question":"Identify this saddle:  has high thigh rolls located near the front of the saddle which keeps the rider firmly in place; usually has no horn; is popular with trail riders.","answer":"Australian, Outback, or Poley (accept any)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm155-2; HIH1100-4"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4557","question":"What is the term for a pad with a cinch which may include stirrups and is used for exercising a horse?","answer":"Bareback pad, pad saddle, or exercise saddle (accept any)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET202"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4558","question":"What is the term for a wide cord girth used on a Western saddle?","answer":"Cinch  <br/> <br/>ref:DET56; HSm155-3; HIH1100-3"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4559","question":"In reference to tack, what is a cinch?","answer":"Girth used on a Western saddle  <br/> <br/>ref:DET56; HSm155-3; HIH1100-3"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4560","question":"What is the purpose of a back cinch on a roping saddle?","answer":"To keep the saddle from flipping up when roping or dallying (FYI:  Flank cinch connectors that attach the rear or flank cinch to the front cinch should be used when using a back cinch.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm155-3; HIH1100-5"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"4561","question":"What English girth style reduces chaffing of your horse's elbows?","answer":"Elastic-end contour leather (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-3"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"4562","question":"Referring to English tack, what fitting is being described by the terms string, elastic–end contour, threefold leather, and balding leather?","answer":"Girths (English girths)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm155-1; HIH1100-3"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4563","question":"Where on the horse should the girth of an English saddle lie?","answer":"Heart girth area (belly area directly behind the front legs)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm155-3; HIH1100-3"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"sr bonus","number":"4564","question":"Name 3 types of English girths.","answer":"String, elastic-end contour leather, 3-fold leather, Balding leather, web, neoprene, fleece, wool back, memory foam, gel (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-3; HSm155-1"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4565","question":"Give TWO definitions of the term girth.","answer":"Circumference of the horse's body back of the withers; piece of equipment that goes around the horse’s body to hold the saddle on  <br/> <br/>ref:HH27"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4566","question":"What is the name of the four-in-hand knot that's tied the same as a knot on a man's tie and is used to secure a saddle in place when a buckle isn't used?","answer":"Cinch knot  <br/> <br/>ref:DET57"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"sr bonus","number":"4567","question":"Name 4 types of saddle riggings.","answer":"Full or double (seen on roping, cutting, or sawbuck/crossbuck packing saddles; 7/8 (seen on trail saddles); ¾; in skirt (seen on barrel racing saddles); centerfire (seen on Decker pack saddles and bucking saddles)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm155-2; HH34"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"4568","question":"In reference to saddles, what does the term rigging mean?","answer":"Style and/or location of how the cinch is attached to the saddle (FYI:  Rigging positions include full double, 7/8, 3/4, and center fire.  Rigging styles include ring, in-skirt, and flat plate.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm155-2; DET234; HH34"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"4569","question":"Which of the following types of Western saddle riggings would accommodate only one cinch:  center fire, full, or 3/4?","answer":"Center fire  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm155-2"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4570","question":"What is the term for a type of saddle that has the cinch hung from the center?","answer":"Centerfire  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm155-1; HH34"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4571","question":"In reference to saddles, what is \"center fire\"?","answer":"Saddle with the cinch hung from the center  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm155-1; HH34"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4572","question":"Name ONE type of saddle that uses a double-rigged cinch.","answer":"Roping saddle, sawbuck/crossbuck saddle, and cutting saddle (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm155-1; HIH1125-3; HIH1100"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4573","question":"What is a double-rigged saddle?","answer":"Saddle with two cinches  <br/> <br/>ref:DET84"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4574","question":"The McClellan saddle is single rigged.  What does this mean?","answer":"Only has one cinch or girth (FYI:  Double rigged means the saddle has two cinches.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1125-1; DET52"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"sr bonus","number":"4575","question":"Name 3 factors that might contribute to a saddle resting on the horse's withers instead of clearing them.","answer":"Fork of saddle too wide, saddle tree too wide, withers too high, withers too narrow, combination of these (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH33"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4576","question":"What measurement is necessary to have a properly fitted girth?","answer":"Heartgirth (from girth buckle to girth buckle)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm155-1; HIH1100-3"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4577","question":"What are you check for if you're placing two fingers between your horse's withers and the fork of the saddle?","answer":"Proper fit  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-3"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"novice","number":"4578","question":"Name ONE thing a poor fitting saddle can cause.","answer":"Saddle rolling during mounting or dismounting, saddle slipping or sliding during use, horse objecting to being cinched, horse bucking, horse tossing head (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH33"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"sr bonus","number":"4579","question":"Name 4 things that could happen when a poorly fitted saddle is used on a horse.","answer":"Saddle rolling during mounting or dismounting, saddle slipping or sliding during use, horse objecting to being cinched, horse bucking, horse tossing head (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH33"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4580","question":"Where on the horse do most saddle fitting problems occur?","answer":"Withers  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm155-2; HIH1100-13"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"intermediate","number":"4581","question":"In reference to saddles what is the difference between an Arabian tree and a Quarter Horse tree?","answer":"Arabian tree is wider.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-3"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4582","question":"What part of the Western saddle should FIRST be considered when fitting a horse?","answer":"Tree  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-3"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4583","question":"What kind of saddle should be selected for a Western horse with low, thick withers?","answer":"Western saddle with a wide tree (Quarter Horse or Arabian tree)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-5"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4584","question":"What is the biggest problem with foam saddle pads?","answer":"They don't breathe (or allow sweat to evaporate).  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-6"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"jr bonus","number":"4585","question":"Name 3 functions of a saddle pad.","answer":"Protect horse's back, absorb sweat, protect saddle, help saddle fit better, absorb shock (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-5; HSm155-5"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"sr bonus","number":"4586","question":"Name 4 functions of a saddle pad.","answer":"Protect horse's back, absorb sweat, protect saddle, help saddle fit better, absorb shock (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-5; HSm155-5"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"intermediate","number":"4587","question":"What is the term for the large colorful roll around the edges of some saddle pads?","answer":"Corona  <br/> <br/>ref:DET69; HH27"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"sr bonus","number":"4588","question":"Name 3 materials used to make Western saddle pads.","answer":"Wool, cotton, felt, fleece or sheepskin, gel, foam, nylon, rayon, rubber, plastic (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-5,6"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4589","question":"What is the name for a colorful woven blanket made of wool that's used with a Western saddle?","answer":"Navajo blanket  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-5"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4590","question":"What type of saddle would be used with a Navajo blanket?","answer":"Western or stock saddle (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-5"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4591","question":"A TRUE Navajo blanket is made from what material?","answer":"Wool  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-5"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"jr bonus","number":"4592","question":"Name 3 parts of an English saddle and a Western saddle that are the same.","answer":"Pommel, cantle, seat (also accept skirt) [FYI: Both types also have D-rings and billets, but they are not in the same places.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-2,4; HSm155-11"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"sr bonus","number":"4593","question":"Name 3 parts of an English saddle that are NOT found on a Western saddle.","answer":"Stirrup irons, stirrup bars, flap, sweat flap, panel, twist, lining, buckle guard (FYI: Billets and D-rings are also on Western saddles, but they are in different locations.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-2,4; HSm155-11"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4594","question":"Where is the cantle of the saddle located?","answer":"Back of the saddle (just behind the seat)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-2,4; HSm155-11"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4595","question":"What is the term for the raised back area of the saddle that's behind the seat?","answer":"Cantle  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-2,4; HSm155-11"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4596","question":"How many billets are on each side of an All-Purpose English Saddle?","answer":"3 (three) billets (on each side of the saddle)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-2; HSm155-11"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4597","question":"On an English saddle, the billets attach what to the saddle?","answer":"Girth  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-2; HSm155-11"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4598","question":"In reference to tack, what are billets?","answer":"Straps used to tighten the girth on an English saddle (also accept straps used to attach the front and back cinches on a Western saddle)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-2; HSm155-11"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4599","question":"Referring to an English saddle, what is the collective term for stirrup leathers, stirrup irons, and girth?","answer":"Fittings  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-9; HSm155-1"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4600","question":"In reference to tack, what are \"fittings\"?","answer":"Stirrup leathers, stirrup irons, and girth for English saddles  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-3,9; HSm155-1"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4601","question":"What is the term for the wide piece of leather on an English saddle that's similar to the fender on a Western saddle?","answer":"Flap  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-2; HSm155-11"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4602","question":"In reference to an English saddle, what is the name for the channel that runs down the center of the underside of the saddle between the panels?","answer":"Gullet  <br/> <br/>ref:DET125,126"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"4603","question":"What part of an English saddle rests on the horse's back?","answer":"Panel  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-2; HSm155-11"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4604","question":"Where is the pommel on an English saddle?","answer":"In front of the seat (FYI:  The pommel is the raised area in front of the seat.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-2; HSm155-11"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4605","question":"How much room should there be on each side of the widest part of a rider's foot in an English stirrup?","answer":"¼ inch  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-3; HSm155-1"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4606","question":"You do the math…There should be ¼ inch of room on each side of the hunt seat rider’s foot when it’s in the stirrup.  The total width of the stirrup tread should be how much wider than the width of the boot?","answer":"½ inch  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-3; HSm155-1"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"intermediate","number":"4607","question":"In reference to saddles, what is a sweat flap?","answer":"Small flap on an English saddle that's under the flap or between the billets and the horse (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-2; HSm155-11"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"4608","question":"Where is the twist on an English saddle?","answer":"Between the pommel and the seat  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-2; HSm155-11"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4609","question":"What is the front part of the Western saddle that's just below the horn?","answer":"Pommel (also accept swells or fork)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-4; HSm155-11"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"4610","question":"What is a saddle nail?","answer":"Rivet  or nail on the front side of the skirt near the pommel on English saddle (FYI: It's used to measure the size of an English saddle.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-3; HSm155-11"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4611","question":"The rider sits in the deepest part of the saddle between which TWO parts?","answer":"Pommel and cantle  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-2,4; HSm155-11"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4612","question":"Why is a breakaway stirrup important to a beginner rider?","answer":"Foot will be quickly released if the rider falls.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm155-1"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4613","question":"What does a safety stirrup do?","answer":"Let's the rider's foot come free from the stirrup in case of a fall (FYI:  A heavy rubber band releases the foot.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-3; HSm155-1"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4614","question":"Referring to saddles, what is the tree?","answer":"Frame of the saddle  <br/> <br/>ref:HH29"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4615","question":"Fender, D-ring, skirt, and front jockey are all parts of what?","answer":"Western or stock saddle (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-4; HSm155-11"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"4616","question":"On the Western saddle, what is the term for the outside back of the cantle?","answer":"Cantle drop or Cheyenne roll (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET47"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4617","question":"2-part question:  On the Western saddle, what is a D-ring and where is it located?","answer":"Ring that holds the cinch straps; located under or in front of the fender  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm155-11"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4618","question":"Referring to saddles, what are fenders?","answer":"Wide pieces of leather along the stirrup leathers (on a Western saddle)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-4; HSm155-1"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"intermediate","number":"4619","question":"Give ONE definition of the fork of a saddle.","answer":"Front part of the saddle that fits over the withers; front raised part of a Western saddle that supports the saddle horn; front of the saddle tree;  part of the swells of a Western saddle that makes up the gullet  <br/> <br/>ref:DET112; HSc27; H4-34"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"4620","question":"In reference to saddles, what does the term \"slick\" mean?","answer":"Shape of the fork on a Western saddle (forks or swells that are narrow at the top and are wide at the bottom)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH29"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"4621","question":"Where on a Western saddle would the hobble strap be found?","answer":"At the bottom of the fender above the stirrup (FYI: Hobble straps help prevent the stirrups from falling off.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-4; HSm155-1"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4622","question":"What was the original purpose of the horn on a Western saddle?","answer":"To hold roped calves or cows (dally)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH32; DET77"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"4623","question":"Referring to tack, what is being described by the following terms:  pelican, gourd, Appleton, dinner plate, and dally?","answer":"Types of saddle horns  <br/> <br/>ref:DET14; DET77; DET81; DET123; DET207"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4624","question":"What are the small flaps on the side of the saddle called?","answer":"Jockey or jockey skirt (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-4; HSm155-11"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4625","question":"Referring to a saddle, what is a \"jockey\"?","answer":"Small flaps on the side of the saddle  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-4; HSm155-11"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4626","question":"In reference to saddles, what is a \"latigo\"?","answer":"Strap on a Western saddle that's used to tighten the cinch or tie the cinch knot  <br/> <br/>ref:DET165"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4627","question":"Which part of the Western saddle is used for tying equipment to the saddle?","answer":"Lace strings or saddle strings (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-4"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4628","question":"What is the basic foundation of all stock saddles?","answer":"Tree  <br/> <br/>ref:DET274; HH31"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4629","question":"What part of the saddle must be fitted to the rider?","answer":"Seat (also accept stirrups)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-3; HH25"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"4630","question":"What is the size of a youth-sized English saddle?","answer":"12 – 16 inches (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-3"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"4631","question":"What is the size of an adult-sized English saddle?","answer":"16 – 18 inches (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-3"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4632","question":"An English saddle size is measured from what TWO points?","answer":"From the saddle nail to the mid-point of the cantle  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-3"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4633","question":"2-part question: You are looking to purchase an English saddle for your 6-foot-tall father who wants to trail ride. There is a 14-inch all-purpose saddle advertised in the local paper. Will this saddle be adequate for your father? Explain your answer.","answer":"No.  The all-purpose type will work, but the saddle is too small.  (Adult-sized English saddles are 16 – 19 inches.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-3"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4634","question":"How is the size of a stock saddle measured?","answer":"From the base of the horn to the top of the cantle (FYI: Youth to small adults use 12 – 14 inch saddles; average to extra-large adults use 15 – 18 inch saddles.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH33"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4635","question":"From what material are most English saddles made?","answer":"Leather  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-3"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4636","question":"Name TWO kinds of saddles that roughly fit under the heading of English saddles.  These saddles are not classified as hunt seat or saddle seat saddles.","answer":"Racing and polo saddles  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-1"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"sr bonus","number":"4637","question":"Name the 3 saddle types in the hunt seat or forward seat category.","answer":"All purpose, close contact, and dressage  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-1; HSm155-1"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4638","question":"Dressage, close contact, and all-purpose are examples of what type of English saddle?","answer":"Forward seat or hunt seat (accept either) [FYI:  The two main types of English saddles are forward seat or hunt seat and saddle seat.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-1; HSm155-1"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"4639","question":"Identify this type of saddle:  type of forward seat saddle; has a deep seat, a forward flap, and a padded knee roll; rider’s hip angle is more relaxed; this type of saddle is good for beginners, eventing, equitation, and pleasure or trail riding.","answer":"All purpose  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-1"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"intermediate","number":"4640","question":"Which type of forward seat saddles is the most popular for trail riding?","answer":"All purpose (FYI:  All purpose, close contact or jumping, and dressage are types of hunt seat or forward seat saddles.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-1; HSm155-1"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"4641","question":"Identify this type of saddle:  type of hunt seat saddle; design includes a flat seat with forward short flaps, and no extra knee roll; rider appears “perched” when using this saddle; this type of saddle is ideal for jumping.","answer":"Close contact saddle  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm155-1; BEG108-1"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4642","question":"What is the main purpose of the close contact saddle?","answer":"Jumping  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-1; HSm155-1"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"4643","question":"Identify this type of saddle:  type of forward seat saddle; knee rolls are optional; rider has a straight hip angle; has a deep seat and a straight, longer flap which gives the rider optimum leg contact with the horse.","answer":"Dressage saddle  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-3; HSm155-1"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"intermediate","number":"4644","question":"Which type of forward seat saddle gives the rider optimum leg contact with the horse?","answer":"Dressage saddle (FYI:  There are 3 types of forward seat or hunt seat saddles—all purpose, close contact, and dressage.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-1,2"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4645","question":"Give ONE other name for a saddle seat saddle.","answer":"Cutback or flat saddle (also accept park or Lane Fox saddle)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-1; HSm155-5"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4646","question":"The saddle seat saddle is cut back in the pommel to accommodate certain conformational aspects of the breeds used in saddle seat classes.  Name ONE of these conformational aspects.","answer":"High withers, high head carriage, or high neck carriage (FYI:  Saddlebreds, Tennessee Walking Horses, Morgans, and Arabians are often shown in saddle seat saddles.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-1"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"4647","question":"In English riding, what saddle is used to ride \"on the flat\" just behind the center of your horse?","answer":"Saddle seat saddle (also accept cutback, flat, park, or Lane Fox saddle)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-1; HIH135-5; HSm155-1"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"jr bonus","number":"4648","question":"Name 3 breeds of horses that are commonly shown in cutback or saddle seat saddles.","answer":"Saddlebred, Tennessee Walking Horse, Morgan, Arabian, National Show Horse, Hackney (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-1"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4649","question":"What is the primary “goal” of the pleasure saddle?","answer":"Comfort  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-4"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4650","question":"Give TWO advantages of a synthetic saddle.","answer":"Less expensive, lightweight, easier to take care of  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-3"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"sr bonus","number":"4651","question":"Name 4 types of Western saddles.","answer":"Pleasure, trail, endurance, reining, roping, cutting, barrel racing, equitation, gymkhana (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm155-2-3; HIH1100-1"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4652","question":"In what COUNTRY are most Western saddles made?","answer":"United States  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-3"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"novice","number":"4653","question":"Which type of saddle was originally developed in the western United States and is used for ranch work?","answer":"Western or stock saddle (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH32"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4654","question":"Identify this saddle:  lightweight; gives the rider a straight leg position and a deep seat for security and balance; tall horn gives the rider something to grab onto during turns; skirts are often rounded.","answer":"Barrel racing saddle  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm155-3; HIH1100-5"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"novice","number":"4655","question":"What type saddle should be used for roping?","answer":"Roping saddle (with sturdy horn and front and back cinches)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm155-3; HIH1100-5"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"novice","number":"4656","question":"What is the general term for all of the leather equipment used to ride and/or drive a horse?","answer":"Tack  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-1; HSm155-1"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"novice","number":"4657","question":"What is the proper name for a storage room where bridles, saddles, and other equipment used in horseback riding are kept?","answer":"Tack room  <br/> <br/>ref:DET262"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"novice","number":"4658","question":"Name 3 items you'd see in a tack shop.","answer":"Saddle, bridle, halter, lead rope, brushes, saddle pad, blanket, medicines, hoof pick, apparel (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-1"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"novice","number":"4659","question":"What does it mean to \"tack up\"?","answer":"Put tack on a horse (bridle, saddle, harness, etc.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-1; HSm155-5"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4660","question":"Name ONE piece of training equipment that can become a “crutch” to horses and riders and are best left to experienced riders and trainers.","answer":"Martingales; draw reins  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-10"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"intermediate","number":"4661","question":"What is the term for the combination of a bridle, harness pad, and crupper that teaches a horse to flex at the poll?","answer":"Bitting rig  <br/> <br/>ref:DET29; HH27"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"intermediate","number":"4662","question":"What is the purpose a bitting rig?","answer":"To teach a horse to flex at the poll (FYI: A bitting rig is a combination of a bridle, harness pad, and crupper.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET29; HH27"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4663","question":"Give ONE purpose of a whip, crop, or bat.","answer":"Cues, punishment, appointments, make horse go faster (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET292"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4664","question":"In reference to tack and equipment, what is a \"bat\"?","answer":"Short, flat riding whip  <br/> <br/>ref:DET25"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"4665","question":"What type of reins are fastened to the girth and then passed through the rings of the snaffle bit into the rider's hands?","answer":"Draw reins  <br/> <br/>ref:DET231"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4666","question":"What is a strap that runs from the girth, between the front legs, to the bridle called?","answer":"Martingale or tiedown (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-10; HSm155-7"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4667","question":"Name the TWO most common types of martingales.","answer":"Running and standing  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-10; HSm155-7"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4668","question":"Name ONE type of martingale that attaches to the reins.","answer":"Running, Irish, or German  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-6; HSm155-7-9"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4669","question":"Explain the difference between a standing martingale and a running martingale.","answer":"Standing martingale attaches to the back of the noseband; running martingale has a Y-shaped strap with rings on the ends that the reins pass through.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm155-9; DET76; DET256"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4670","question":"What is the basic purpose of a martingale?","answer":"To keep a horse's head in a desired position  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-10; HSm155-7"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"4671","question":"Which type of martingale combines the action of both the snaffle rein and a draw rein?","answer":"German martingale  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm155-9; DET120"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4672","question":"What piece of equipment needs to be used with a running martingale to prevent the martingale from interfering with the bit?","answer":"Rein stops  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-12; HSm155-9"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4673","question":"Which type of martingale has rings through which the reins pass?","answer":"Running martingale  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-12; HSm155-9"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4674","question":"The upper end of a standing martingale connects to what part of the bridle?","answer":"Cavesson or noseband (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-10; HSm155-7"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4675","question":"What is the English term for a tiedown?","answer":"Standing martingale  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-10; HSm155-7"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4676","question":"What is the Western version of a standing martingale?","answer":"Tiedown  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-10; HSm155-7"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4677","question":"Name TWO types of bars found on tack.","answer":"Stirrup bar, bars of saddle tree, bar mouthpiece, part of bit mouthpiece, stabilizer bar on curb or mechanical hackamore (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-2,3; HH30; PNW98"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4678","question":"What is the name for the rubber or leather ring that lies between the horse's cheek and the bit that prevents rubbing or pinching of the skin?","answer":"Bit guard  <br/> <br/>ref:DET29"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4679","question":"Why may putting a blanket on a horse with a winter coat actually make the horse colder rather than warmer?","answer":"Horse's winter coat traps heat between the hair; putting a blanket on may compress the hair (eliminating the air layer and reducing the horse's natural protection against the cold).  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm305-6; INT204-2"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4680","question":"Referring to outerwear for your horse, what is the purpose of a horse blanket?","answer":"To keep the horse warm in cold weather (FYI:  Blankets are generally heavier than sheets.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-16"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"jr bonus","number":"4681","question":"Name 3 different types of outerwear for your horse.","answer":"Turnout blanket, turnout sheet, cooler, mesh sheet, stable blanket, stable sheet, blanket, sheet, sleazie, hood, fly mask (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-16"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4682","question":"Name ONE type of horse outerwear that helps your horse cool off and dry off after a workout.","answer":"Cooler; mesh sheet; anti-sweat sheet (FYI:  Coolers are usually made of polar fleece or wool.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-16"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"4683","question":"What is the term for the type of sheet that is placed under the saddle and saddle pad and is used while exercising a horse outdoors in cold weather?  It runs from the withers to the hindquarters.","answer":"Half sheet  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-16"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"4684","question":"What is the use of a half sheet?","answer":"Used for warmth when exercising horses outdoors in cold weather (FYI: Half sheets and quarter sheets are often used with English saddles and they cover the back half of the horse.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-16"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4685","question":"Give ONE purpose of a lighter-weight horse blanket.","answer":"Shipping; turnout  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-16"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4686","question":"Give TWO uses of a mesh sheet.","answer":"Aids in cooling out the horse; keeps flies away  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-6"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4687","question":"What type of sheet is used to keep flies away from your horse?","answer":"Mesh sheet (also accept fly sheet)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-16"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4688","question":"Give ONE purpose of an anti-sweat sheet.","answer":"Keep horse warm while it cools down after exercise; wicks sweat away after exercise  <br/> <br/>ref:DET13"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4689","question":"What is the name of the protective boots that fit over the coronet band and the bulbs of the heel?","answer":"Bell boots or overreach boots (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET26; DET199; HH34"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4690","question":"Name ONE part of the horse that bell or overreach boots protect.","answer":"Coronet bands; bulb of the heel (CORRECTED 2020)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET26; DET199; HH34"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4691","question":"What type boots protect the back of the rear fetlocks from abrasions during sliding movements?","answer":"Skid boots or sliding boots (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET246; HH34"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4692","question":"What is the purpose of splint boots?","answer":"To support or protect the splint and/or cannon bones  <br/> <br/>ref:DET252; HH34"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4693","question":"Which piece of tack is used to keep the saddle from slipping FORWARD when going downhill?","answer":"Breeching or crupper (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1125-3; HSm160-2"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"4694","question":"Explain the difference between batwing chaps and shotgun chaps.","answer":"Batwing chaps are flared; shotgun chaps fit close to leg.  <br/> <br/>ref:DET54"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4695","question":"What are chaps?","answer":"Seatless overalls or leggings (usually made of leather; used to protect the legs, keep the legs warm, or for show)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm170-4; DET54; HH20"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4696","question":"Give ONE purpose of chaps.","answer":"To protect the legs from cuts or cold; used for show  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm170-8; HH20"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4697","question":"What type of Western chaps extends slightly beyond the knees, but does not cover the rider’s shins?","answer":"Chinks (Do NOT accept half chaps which are English chaps that cover the ankle and shin.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET55"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4698","question":"Give ONE reason why you should NOT leave a halter on a loose horse.","answer":"Horse could catch its foot in it; horse could catch halter on a fence post (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:PNW99"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4699","question":"Give ONE reason why a halter should be fitted correctly to the horse.","answer":"If the halter is too tight, it can rub or irritate the horse; if it’s too loose, the halter could slip off, the horse could catch its foot in the halter, or the horse could catch the halter on a fence. (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:PNW99"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4700","question":"What are straps that fasten the front legs of a horse together so that the horse can't walk around called?","answer":"Hobbles  <br/> <br/>ref:DET140; HH27"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4701","question":"In reference to tack, what are hobbles?","answer":"Straps fastened to the front legs of a horse to prevent him from straying or walking around  <br/> <br/>ref:DET140; HH27"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"4702","question":"What type of knot is used on the end of a rope to keep it from unraveling?","answer":"Crown knot  <br/> <br/>ref:DET74"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4703","question":"What is the name for the eye formed on the end of the lariat through which the rope is passed to form a loop?","answer":"Honda  <br/> <br/>ref:DET141; HH29"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4704","question":"What is a rope, often made of rawhide, with a running noose that's used for catching cattle?","answer":"Lariat or lasso (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET164; HH29"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"intermediate","number":"4705","question":"What is the Spanish term for lasso or lariat?","answer":"Reata  <br/> <br/>ref:DET230; HH29"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4706","question":"In reference to tack, what is a reata?","answer":"Spanish word for lasso, lariat, or rope (accept any)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET230; HH29"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4707","question":"How long should a longe line be?","answer":"20 – 30 feet (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH395; DET171; PNW85"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4708","question":"A strap or rope 25 – 30 feet long that's used to circle or work a horse is called what?","answer":"Longe line  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH395; DET171; PNW5"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4709","question":"What piece of equipment, other than the longe line and halter, might be needed when teaching a foal to lunge?","answer":"Whip  <br/> <br/>ref:DET171 picture; PNW85"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4710","question":"What are the toothed wheels on spurs called?","answer":"Rowels  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm155-7; HH29"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4711","question":"What are rowels?","answer":"Toothed wheels on spurs  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm170-7; HH29"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"intermediate","number":"4712","question":"What is a surcingle?  (pronounced SIR-sing-el)","answer":"Broad strap around the horse's girth (that may be used along with a bridle for ground training)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET259; HH29"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"intermediate","number":"4713","question":"What is the term for a girth-like band that's passed over the horse's back and around the belly?  It's used with a bridle in ground training horses.","answer":"Surcingle (pronounced SIR-sing-el)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET259; HH29"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"intermediate","number":"4714","question":"What is a tapadera?","answer":"Stirrup cover  <br/> <br/>ref:DET263; HH29"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"intermediate","number":"4715","question":"What is the name for the cover on a stirrup?","answer":"Tapadera  <br/> <br/>ref:DET263; HH29"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"intermediate","number":"4716","question":"What is the name for the restraining device that's put around a horse's upper lip?","answer":"Twitch  <br/> <br/>ref:DET277; H5-35"},
    {"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"4717","question":"What is the term for the person who makes the metal parts of tack such as bits, curb chains, and stirrup irons?","answer":"Lorimer  <br/> <br/>ref:DET172"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"hard","number":"4718","question":"Until what age can a horse be accurately identified by its teeth?","answer":"10 – 14 years of age (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-1; HSm315-2"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"novice","number":"4719","question":"By looking at a horse’s mouth, how can you guess its age?","answer":"By looking at its teeth (appearance, cups, wear, eruption, slant or angle, and Galvayne’s groove)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-1; HSm315"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"sr bonus","number":"4720","question":"Name 3 factors that may affect the technique of aging a horse by its teeth and that may make the horse appear different than its actual age.","answer":"Prolonged drought, parrot mouth, cribbing, grazing on sandy soil, bishoping (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH405; HIH240-1"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4721","question":"Name TWO things about a horse's teeth that can be used to estimate the age of the horse.","answer":"Shape, wear or disappearance of cups, slant or angle of incidence, occurrence of teeth or eruption pattern, Galvayne's groove  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm315"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"sr bonus","number":"4722","question":"Name 4 ways to estimate age of horses by its teeth.","answer":"Eruption pattern or occurrence of teeth, wear or disappearance of cups, slant or angle of incidence or bite, Galvayne's Groove, shape of the surface of the permanent teeth, dovetail notch, hooks  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-1; HSm315-2"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"jr bonus","number":"4723","question":"Name 3 ways to estimate age of horses by its teeth.","answer":"Eruption pattern or occurrence of teeth, wear or disappearance of cups, slant or angle of incidence or bite, Galvayne's Groove, shape of the surface of the permanent teeth, dovetail notch, hooks  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-1; HSm315-2"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4724","question":"What is the angle of incidence?","answer":"Angle at which the upper and lower incisors meet (as viewed from the side)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-3; HSm315-2; DET11; HSc14"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4725","question":"What is the term for the profile view of the angle formed where the upper and lower incisors meet?","answer":"Angle of incidence (FYI:  Angle of bite is an old term for the outer angle at which the upper and lower incisors meet.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-3; HSm315-2; DET11; HSc14"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"hard","number":"4726","question":"What is the angle of incidence in young horses?","answer":"160 – 180 degrees (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-3; HSm315-2"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"hard","number":"4727","question":"The angle of incidence is approximately 160 – 180 degrees in young horses and becomes what angle in older ones?","answer":"90 degrees or less  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-3; HSm315-2"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"hard","number":"4728","question":"In reference to teeth, what is \"bishoping\"?","answer":"Practice of trying to replace the cups on worn incisors to make the horse appear younger than its actual age (FYI:  Unscrupulous horse dealers used silver nitrate to create cups.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-4; HSm315-7"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"4729","question":"At what age do the cups start disappearing?","answer":"6 (six) years of age  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm315-2"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4730","question":"What are the hollow spaces on the wearing surfaces of the incisors called?","answer":"Cups  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-3; HSm315-2"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"4731","question":"In reference to teeth, how can cups be used to estimate a horse's age?","answer":"Cups become smooth or wear down at different times (FYI: This is the order of disappearance of cups: lower centrals, lower intermediates, lower corners, upper centrals, upper intermediates, and upper corners.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-3; HSm315-2"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"4732","question":"Referring to teeth, what are cups?","answer":"Hollow spaces on the wearing surfaces of the incisors (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-3; HSm315-1"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"sr bonus","number":"4733","question":"A horse's age can be estimated from 6 – 11 years of age by the order in which the cups become smooth.  What is this order?","answer":"Lower centrals, lower intermediates, lower corners, upper centrals, upper intermediates, upper corners  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-3; HSm315-2"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4734","question":"What is it called when the biting surfaces of the upper and lower incisors are smooth?","answer":"Smooth mouthed (FYI: Smooth mouth occurs between 10 – 12 years of age.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-3; HSm315-2"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"4735","question":"2-part question:  What is \"smooth mouth\" and when does it occur?","answer":"When the cups on the incisors have smoothed out; it occurs between 10 – 12 years of age (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-3; HSm315-2"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"4736","question":"On what teeth are dental stars first evident?","answer":"Central incisors (specifically the lower centrals) [FYI:  Dental stars first appear at age 6 and are very visible by age 8.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm315-2; FCH387"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"4737","question":"As the cups on the horse's incisors disappear, what starts to form first as a narrow, elongated yellow mark?","answer":"Dental star (FYI:  A dental star is the exposed pulp cavity on the wearing surface of a permanent incisor.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm315-2; CAHA48"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"hard","number":"4738","question":"What marker on the grinding surface of the horse's tooth is revealed when the tooth is worn down to the pulp cavity?","answer":"Dental star (FYI:  Dental stars are anterior to (in front of) the cups or enamel spots.  Dental stars appear around 8 years of age.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm315-2; CAHA48"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"4739","question":"Which teeth have a dental star?","answer":"Permanent incisors (FYI:  A dental star is the exposed pulp cavity on the wearing surface of a permanent incisor.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-3; HSm315-2"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"hard","number":"4740","question":"As horses age, the incisors slant more forward and outward which causes the surfaces of the lower corner incisors to not wear all the way back to the surfaces of the upper corner incisors.  What condition does this cause?","answer":"Dovetail notch or 7-year hook (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-3; HSm315-2"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"hard","number":"4741","question":"2-part question:  In reference to teeth, what causes a dovetail notch and when does a dovetail notch usually appear?","answer":"Surface of the lower corners is not worn all the way to the back edges of the upper ones as the angle of bite changes; this leaves a notch on the upper corners at 7 years of age. (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-3; HSm315-2"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"sr bonus","number":"4742","question":"Organize the following 4 types of permanent teeth by their age of eruption:  canines, 1st premolars, 2nd premolars, intermediate incisors.","answer":"1st premolars (wolf teeth) erupt at 5 – 6 months, 2nd molars erupt at 2 years, intermediate incisors erupt at 3 ½ years, and canines erupt at 4 – 5 years.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm315-2"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"4743","question":"At what age have ALL the milk teeth erupted?","answer":"8 months (accept any number within the 6 – 9 month range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH405-1; HSm315-2"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"4744","question":"A young male horse 10 months old has 24 deciduous teeth.  Name TWO types of teeth he does NOT have that he’ll develop later as permanent teeth.","answer":"Molars and canines  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-2; HSm315-2"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4745","question":"By what age does a horse generally have all its teeth and is considered full mouthed?","answer":"5 years of age  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm315-1"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4746","question":"What is the term for a horse that has all of its permanent teeth?","answer":"Full mouthed (FYI: Full mouth occurs around 5 years of age.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm315-1; FCH400"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4747","question":"What is meant by the term \"full mouth\"?","answer":"Horse has all of its permanent teeth. (FYI: Full mouth occurs around age 5.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-3; HSm315-1"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4748","question":"In reference to horse's teeth, explain the difference between full mouth and smooth mouth.","answer":"Full mouth is when the horse has all of its teeth (occurs at 5); smooth mouth is when the cups have disappeared from the incisors (occurs at 10 – 12).  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-3; HSm315-7; HSc15"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"4749","question":"By what age have the temporary central incisors erupted?","answer":"8 days (erupt from birth to 8 days of age)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-1; HSm315-1"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"4750","question":"Which teeth are present at birth or erupt during the first week of life?","answer":"Deciduous or temporary central incisors  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH405-1; HSm315-2"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"4751","question":"At what age do the permanent centrals erupt?","answer":"2 ½ years of age  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-1"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"4752","question":"When do the corner deciduous incisors erupt?","answer":"8 months (accept any number within 6 – 9 months)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH405-1; HSm315-2"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"4753","question":"At what age do permanent corners erupt?","answer":"4½ years  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm315-1; HIH405-1"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"4754","question":"In determining the age of a horse by its teeth, a horse would be about 4½ years old if he’d just gained which permanent incisors?","answer":"Corner incisors  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH405-1; HSm315-1"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"4755","question":"At what age do the deciduous intermediate incisors erupt?","answer":"6 weeks (accept any number within 4 – 8 weeks)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH405-1,2; HIH240-1,2; HSm315-2; HSc15"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"4756","question":"At what age do the permanent intermediates erupt?","answer":"3 ½ years  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm315-1; HIH405-1"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"4757","question":"By what age does the FIRST set of the horse's molars erupt?","answer":"By 1 (one) year of age  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH405-1; HSm315-2"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"sr bonus","number":"4758","question":"Molars are present in horses only as permanent teeth. By what ages do the first, second, and third sets of molars erupt?","answer":"1st molars erupt by 1 year, 2nd molars erupt by 2 years, and 3rd molars erupt by 3½ - 4 years.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH405-1; HSm315-2"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"4759","question":"At what age does the SECOND set of molars erupt?","answer":"2 years of age  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm315-2; HIH240-1"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"4760","question":"At what age does the THIRD set of the horse's molars erupt?","answer":"3 ½ – 4 years (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH405-1; HSm315-1"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"sr bonus","number":"4761","question":"The wolf teeth are technically the first premolars.  They erupt as permanent teeth at 5 - 6 months of age.  At what ages do the other PERMANENT premolars erupt?","answer":"2nd premolars erupt around 2 ½ years of age; 3rd premolars erupt around 3 years of age; 4th premolars erupt around 4 years of age  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH405-1; HSm315-2"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"4762","question":"By what age do a foal's temporary premolar teeth appear?","answer":"2 (two) weeks of age  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-2; HIH405-1; HSm315-2"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"4763","question":"At what age do wolf teeth erupt?","answer":"5 – 6 months of age (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH405-1; HSm315-1"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"intermediate","number":"4764","question":"At what age does Galvayne's groove appear on the upper corner incisors?","answer":"10 years of age  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm315-2"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"intermediate","number":"4765","question":"By looking at a horse's teeth, how old is a horse whose Galvayne's groove is halfway down the upper corner incisor?","answer":"15 years of age  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm315-2"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"intermediate","number":"4766","question":"What would be the estimated age of a horse if Galvayne's groove extends to the wearing surface of the corner upper incisor?","answer":"20 years of age  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-4; HSm315-2"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"intermediate","number":"4767","question":"What is Galvayne's groove?","answer":"Groove that appears at the gum line of the upper corner incisor at 10 years of age  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-3; HSm315-2"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"sr bonus","number":"4768","question":"A mature male horse usually has 40 teeth.  How many of each type of teeth does he have?","answer":"12 incisors, 12 premolars, 12 molars, and 4 canines  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-1; HSm315-1"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4769","question":"Excluding wolf teeth, how many teeth does a yearling have?","answer":"24 (FYI: 12 incisors and 12 premolars)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-2"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4770","question":"Excluding wolf teeth, how many teeth does a mare or female horse have?","answer":"36 (FYI:  12 incisors, 12 premolars, and 12 molars)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-2"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4771","question":"An adult male horse with NO wolf teeth will usually have how many total teeth?","answer":"40 (FYI: 12 incisors, 12 premolars, 12 molars, and 4 canines)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-3; HSm315-1"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"hard","number":"4772","question":"At what age are a horse's teeth very slanted, are triangular-shaped, and have large dental stars?","answer":"20 – 21 years of age (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-4"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"4773","question":"How does the shape of the chewing surfaces of the teeth change as the horse ages?","answer":"Changes from oval to triangular  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm315-5"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"hard","number":"4774","question":"Give TWO ways temporary teeth are distinguished from permanent teeth.","answer":"Temporary teeth are small, white, and have a distinct neck; permanent teeth are larger, stronger, more yellow, have no neck; younger horses will have distinct cups on their permanent incisors; older horse's incisors become more triangular  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-2; HSm315-5"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"4775","question":"At the age of 20, what is the shape of the chewing surface a horse's permanent central incisor?","answer":"Triangular  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm315-5; CAHA48"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"sr bonus","number":"4776","question":"At what ages are the following permanent teeth in wear or have contact with each other:  centrals, intermediates, and corners?","answer":"Centrals 3 years, intermediates 4 years, and corners 5 years  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm315-1"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"4777","question":"What dental term means that teeth are in contact with each other?","answer":"Wear  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-2"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"4778","question":"What is the PROPER name for the foal's baby teeth?","answer":"Deciduous or temporary teeth (FYI: “Milk teeth” is another common name.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm315-2"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4779","question":"Give ONE other name for a temporary or non-permanent tooth.","answer":"Milk tooth, baby tooth, or deciduous tooth  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH405-1; HSm315-2; DET180; FCH396"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"jr bonus","number":"4780","question":"Give 3 other names for a foal's baby teeth.","answer":"Temporary teeth, milk teeth, deciduous teeth  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH405-1; HSm315-2; DET180; FCH396"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4781","question":"Where is the interdental space?","answer":"Gum space between the incisors and the premolars  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm315-1"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4782","question":"What is the gum space between the incisors and the premolars?","answer":"Interdental space or bars (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET153; DET23; HSm315-1; HH29"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"sr bonus","number":"4783","question":"The permanent upper and lower teeth are located in what 3 bones?","answer":"Maxilla, mandible, and incisive bones  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA41"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"sr bonus","number":"4784","question":"Name 3 benefits of shortening and blunting the canine teeth.","answer":"Easier insertion or removal of the bit, less chance of injury due to horse catching canine on object, less injury inflicted in fights, reduced risk of injury to people (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH405-4"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4785","question":"Name ONE benefit of providing regular dental care for your horse.","answer":"Extends life, improves health, improves performance, helps maintain weight, decreases discomfort, decreases pain-related behavioral problems (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH405-1"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4786","question":"What practice can prevent an unopposed tooth from becoming too tall or too long?","answer":"Floating the teeth  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH405-3"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4787","question":"What is the best way to prevent dental problems in your horse?","answer":"Regular dental check-ups  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH415-1; HSm305-7"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4788","question":"Why would NOT taking care of a horse's mouth add to the expense of keeping a horse?","answer":"You may need to give the horse more food. (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH420-3"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"4789","question":"How do you examine a horse's INCISOR teeth?","answer":"Hold the halter near the chin with one hand and roll the lips back with the other hand.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-1; HSm315-1"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"4790","question":"How do you examine a horse's MOLAR teeth?","answer":"Open the horse's mouth, grasp the tongue with the right hand, and grasp the lower lip with the left hand.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-1; HSm315-2"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4791","question":"How do you get a horse to open its mouth?","answer":"Put 1 – 2 fingers in the corner of its mouth (in the bars or interdental space) and apply pressure if needed.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm315-1"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4792","question":"In reference to teeth, what is \"floating\"?","answer":"Filing off the sharp edges of the teeth  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH405-2; HSm305-7"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4793","question":"What is the term for filing off the sharp edges of a horse's teeth?","answer":"Floating the teeth  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH405-2"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4794","question":"How often is it recommended to float horses' teeth?","answer":"Once yearly (or as recommended by your vet)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH405-2"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4795","question":"Name ONE type of movement of the horse’s jaw that is necessary for it to grind its food.","answer":"Lateral (side to side) movement; vertical (up and down) movement (FYI: Sharp enamel points develop because they lower jaw is narrower than the upper jaw and feed is ground with lateral movements of the lower jaw.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH405-1,2; HIH450-4"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4796","question":"Which jaw of the horse is wider?","answer":"Upper jaw (maxilla)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH405-2"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"hard","number":"4797","question":"2-part question:  Describe how the upper jaw teeth fit over the lower teeth and vice versa.","answer":"Upper teeth extend over the lower ones on the outside; lower teeth extend on the inside of the upper ones.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH405-2"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4798","question":"What are the TWO movements of horses' jaws?","answer":"Vertical and lateral (up and down and sideways)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH450-4"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4799","question":"What is the top part of a tooth that protrudes above the gum?","answer":"Crown  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA48; HSc14-15"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"jr bonus","number":"4800","question":"What are the 3 parts of a temporary tooth?","answer":"Crown, neck, and root (fang)  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA49; HSc14"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4801","question":"What is the part of the tooth between the crown and the root that's located at the surface of the gums?","answer":"Neck  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA48; HSc14-15"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4802","question":"What is the neck of the tooth?","answer":"Part between the crown and the root (located at the surface of the gum)  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA48; HSc14-15"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4803","question":"What is the crown of the tooth?","answer":"Top part of the tooth (that protrudes above the gum)  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA48; HSc14-15"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"hard","number":"4804","question":"What is periodontal disease?","answer":"Inflammation of the tissue that anchors the tooth to the bone (gum disease)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH405-3"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"hard","number":"4805","question":"What is inflammation of the periodontium which is the tissue that anchors the tooth to the bone?","answer":"Periodontal disease (periodontitis)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH405-3"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"hard","number":"4806","question":"What is the periodontium? (pronounced pair-ee-oh-DAHN-tee-um)","answer":"Tissue that anchors the tooth to the bone  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH405-3"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"4807","question":"What percent of horses have some degree of overbite?","answer":"30% – 60% (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH405-4"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4808","question":"Name ONE thing sharp edges on the teeth can cause the horse to do.","answer":"Chew food slowly, waste food, lose weight, rear, buck, toss head, quid (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH405-1; HSm305-7"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4809","question":"What vice would a horse probably have if his upper incisors are evenly worn off?","answer":"Cribbing  <br/> <br/>ref:HH49"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"sr bonus","number":"4810","question":"Name 3 dental problems in horses.","answer":"Hooks, points, retained baby teeth (caps), wolf teeth, malaligned teeth, infected teeth, long or tall teeth, long or tall canines, lost tooth, broken tooth (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH405-1; HSm305-7"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"hard","number":"4811","question":"Why are problems resulting from tooth discomfort common in horses between 2 ½ to 4 ½ years of age?","answer":"Horse is losing and gaining lots of teeth. (All deciduous incisors and premolars are shed and replaced and the molars erupt during this time.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH405-1; HSm315-2"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4812","question":"What should be checked if a horse eats with its head sideways or if it spills a lot of grain from its mouth?","answer":"Teeth (also accept mouth)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH405-1"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"sr bonus","number":"4813","question":"Name 3 signs that would indicate your horse needs to have his teeth checked.","answer":"Weight loss, slobbering, head tilting, difficulty chewing, dropping feed, quidding, head tossing, bit chewing, tongue lolling, tail wringing, bucking, fussing with bit, refusing bit (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH405-1; HSm305-7"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"hard","number":"4814","question":"What is the term for temporary teeth that stay attached to the gums after being pushed out by the erupting permanent teeth?","answer":"Caps  <br/> <br/>ref:DET48; FCH384"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"hard","number":"4815","question":"In reference to teeth, what are caps?","answer":"Temporary teeth that fail to fall out when replaced by the permanent teeth  <br/> <br/>ref:DET48; FCH384"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4816","question":"Name ONE type of sharp protrusions that develop on the molars due to uneven wear.","answer":"Hooks; points  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm315-2"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4817","question":"Name ONE part of the horse's mouth that may be damaged by sharp edges on the teeth.","answer":"Tongue; cheek  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH405-1,2; HSm305-7"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"hard","number":"4818","question":"What causes hooks on the horse's cheek teeth?","answer":"Change in position of the teeth causes the teeth to wear unevenly; the part of the tooth that is not in wear becomes longer or taller.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH405-2; HSm315-2"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"hard","number":"4819","question":"In the horse's mouth, the upper cheek teeth are often positioned slightly forward toward the nose as compared to the lower ones.  Name ONE problem this can cause.","answer":"Hooks; long or tall tooth  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH405-2"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"4820","question":"On what side of a horse's UPPER tooth do points develop?","answer":"Cheek side (buccal side) [FYI:  Points develop on the tongue or lingual side of the lower cheek teeth.]  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA48"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"hard","number":"4821","question":"Sharp enamel points develop on the outside of the upper cheek teeth and on the inside of the lower cheek teeth.  What causes points?","answer":"Uneven wear because the lower jaw is narrower than the upper jaw (FYI:  Points occur on the sides of the teeth; a hook occurs on the front or back of a tooth.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH405-2"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"sr bonus","number":"4822","question":"Give 3 signs that a horse has an infected tooth.","answer":"Slow eating, weight loss (progressive un-thriftiness), quidding, tilting head, swelling of face or jaw, nasal drainage or drainage tracts (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH405-3"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"4823","question":"Name ONE cause of an infected tooth in the horse.","answer":"Trapped food, decomposing food, jaw fracture, periodontal disease  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH405-3"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"hard","number":"4824","question":"What is the SLANG term for when the diseased tissue in the pulp cavity of a tooth is removed and is replaced by amalgam?","answer":"Root canal (FYI:  A \"root canal\" is when the diseased pulp is removed from the roots of a tooth; an apicoectomy is when the apex of the root is removed.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH405-3"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"4825","question":"In reference to eating, what is a horse doing when he is quidding?","answer":"Dropping partially chewed feed from his mouth  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH405-3"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"4826","question":"What term is used when a horse drops partially chewed food from his mouth?","answer":"Quidding  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH405-3"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"4827","question":"What part of the horse should be closely examined if the horse is quidding?","answer":"Teeth or mouth (accept either) [FYI: Quidding is when a horse drops partially chewed food from its mouth.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH405-3"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"4828","question":"What causes a long or tall tooth to occur in the horse's mouth?","answer":"Missing tooth leaving an unopposed space that lets a tooth grow longer  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH405-2"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"4829","question":"Why would the teeth of stabled horses look less worn than the teeth of horses grazed on sandy pastures?","answer":"Sand wears down the teeth at a faster than normal rate.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-1"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"hard","number":"4830","question":"What do the letters ICPM stand for in the dental formula?","answer":"Incisors, canines, premolars, molars  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA48"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"4831","question":"Name TWO types of teeth in the male horse that only occur as permanent teeth and that never occur as deciduous teeth.","answer":"Molars, canines, wolf teeth  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-1; HSm315-1"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4832","question":"Where in the mouth are the canine teeth located?","answer":"Bars or interdental space (space between the incisors and the premolars)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-3; HSm315-2; CAHA48; HSc12"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4833","question":"What teeth, seen in the interdental space, erupt around 4 ½ years of age, and are present mostly in male horses?","answer":"Canine teeth (Do NOT accept wolf teeth which are present in both sexes fairly equally. Wolf teeth erupt from 5 – 6 months of age.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-3; HSm315-1"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4834","question":"Give ONE other name for a canine tooth.","answer":"Fang, tusk, tush, or bridle tooth  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-3; HSm315-1"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4835","question":"Canine teeth are usually NOT present in which sex of horse?","answer":"Mare (female) [FYI:  Newer information states that both male and female horses have wolf teeth which are different than canines.  Wolf teeth are small teeth in front of the first premolars.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm315-1; CAHA48"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"4836","question":"What TWO types of teeth are collectively called the cheek teeth?","answer":"Premolars and molars  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm315-1"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4837","question":"How many INCISORS does a yearling have?","answer":"12 (twelve) [FYI: Deciduous incisors erupt by ages 8 days, 8 weeks, and 9 months.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-1; HSm315-1"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"4838","question":"How many incisors do horses have in each of their upper and lower jaws?","answer":"6 (six) in each jaw  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH405-1; HSm315-1"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"jr bonus","number":"4839","question":"What are the names of the horse's 3 sets of incisors?","answer":"Centrals, intermediates, and corners  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-1; HSm315-1"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"sr bonus","number":"4840","question":"At what ages do the following PERMANENT teeth erupt:  central, intermediate, and corner incisors?","answer":"Centrals—2½ years; intermediates—3½ years; corners—4½ years  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH405-1; HSm315-1"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4841","question":"Which teeth can be examined for wear and slant to best estimate the age of a horse?","answer":"Incisors (FYI:  Centrals, intermediates, and corners are the 3 sets of incisors.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-1; HSm315-1"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4842","question":"What are horses’ front, cutting teeth called?","answer":"Incisors (FYI:  Centrals, intermediates, and corners are the 3 sets of incisors.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm315-1; HSc14"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4843","question":"What are the first centrally located incisors called?","answer":"Centrals (FYI:  Deciduous centrals erupt from birth to 8 days of age; permanent centrals erupt at 2 ½ years of age.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-1; HSm315-1"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4844","question":"What is the name of the third set of incisors—those that are closest to the interdental space?","answer":"Corners (FYI:  Deciduous corners erupt around 8 months of age; permanent corners erupt at 4 ½ years of age.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-1; HSm315-1"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4845","question":"What is the name of the second set of incisors?","answer":"Intermediates (FYI:  Deciduous intermediates erupt from 4 to 8 weeks of age; permanent intermediates erupt at 3 ½ years of age.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-1; HSm315-1"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4846","question":"What is another name for the horse's rear grinding teeth?","answer":"Molars (FYI:  Premolars and molars are called \"cheek teeth\".)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-1; HSm315"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4847","question":"In reference to teeth, what are molars?","answer":"Rear grinding teeth (FYI:  Horses have 3 sets of premolars in each jaw and 3 sets of molars in each jaw.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-1; HSm315"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4848","question":"Name ONE type of tooth in horses that erupts only as a permanent tooth.","answer":"Molar, canine, or wolf tooth (FYI:  Incisors and premolars erupt as deciduous teeth which are replaced by permanent teeth.  Molars, canines, and wolf teeth erupt only as permanent teeth.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm315-2; HIH405-1; HIH240-1; CAHA48"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"4849","question":"How many premolars does a foal of either sex have?","answer":"12 premolars (FYI:  Deciduous premolars erupt from birth to 2 weeks of age.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH240-1; HSm315-2"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"4850","question":"2-part question:  How many premolars and how many molars does an adult horse have?","answer":"12 premolars; 12 molars  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm315-2; ES215"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4851","question":"Give ONE reason why wolf teeth are usually removed.","answer":"May interfere with the bit; may cause pain or discomfort; may cause behavioral problems (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm315-1"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4852","question":"In the horse's lower jaw, how many wolf teeth are NORMALLY found?","answer":"None  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH405-1; HSm315-1"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4853","question":"In the horse's upper jaw, how many wolf teeth MAY be present?","answer":"None, one, or two (accept any)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH405-1; HSm315-1"},
    {"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"4854","question":"What teeth are in front of the 2nd upper premolars and are usually removed because they can interfere with the bit or cause pain?","answer":"Wolf teeth (FYI:  Wolf teeth are usually present only in the upper jaw and are called the 1st premolars.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm315-1; CAHA48"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"sr bonus","number":"4855","question":"Name 3 documents you should carry with you when you travel across state or border lines with your horse.","answer":"Current health certificate, proof of ownership, proof of negative Coggins test, brand inspection, other documents required by your destination or border crossing (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1150-2; HSm220-3"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"medium","number":"4856","question":"What TWO things are mandatory when transporting horses across MOST state lines?","answer":"Negative Coggins test and current health certificate (FYI:  Brand inspection is NOT required by all states.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1150-2; HSm220-3"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"medium","number":"4857","question":"What is a brand inspection?","answer":"Proof of ownership issued by a brand inspector (FYI:  Brand inspections are required by many Western states and are required when traveling out of a “brand territory”, which is a designated livestock ownership inspection area.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm220-3"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"jr bonus","number":"4858","question":"Name 3 feeding guidelines that can help decrease stress and colic while traveling with your horse.","answer":"Offer water every 3 – 4 hours when trailering, bring something to mask the taste of strange water, bring your own hay, bring horse’s own buckets, feed free-choice hay when trailering, limit grain when trailering, give bran mash before traveling  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1150-2"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"4859","question":"What is the MAXIMUM time horses should be trailered without being unloaded, exercised, and allowed time to eat and drink?","answer":"18 hours (FYI:  It’s best to limit travel to 8 – 12 hours a day.  Horses should be offered water every 3 – 4 hours on long trips.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1150-3"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"hard","number":"4860","question":"What is the “twenty-eight-hour law”?","answer":"Law in the U.S. that prohibits transporting livestock for a period of longer than 28 consecutive hours without unloading, feeding, watering and resting for at least 5 hours before resuming transportation.  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH407"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"4861","question":"At minimum, how long before you travel should your horse's vaccinations be brought up to date?","answer":"At least 2 weeks before leaving  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1150-1"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"4862","question":"On long trailer trips, how often should you offer your horse a drink of water?","answer":"Every 3 – 4 hours (accept any number within this range)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1150-2; HSm220-3"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"4863","question":"When trailering your horse long distances, it's recommended that you offer him water every 3 – 4 hours. Since you can't carry enough water for the entire trip, how can you deal with taste changes in the water?","answer":"Use something to mask the taste (like lemonade, Gatorade, electrolyte solutions, soft drinks, Kool-Aid) [accept any reasonable answer]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm220-3,4"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"sr bonus","number":"4864","question":"Give 3 features of a horse trailer that provide added safety for the horse.","answer":"Butt bar or butt chain, chest or wall padding, screened windows, rubber mats, safety ties (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1155-3; HSm220-2"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"sr bonus","number":"4865","question":"Name 3 things you should check on your trailer regularly.","answer":"Floorboards, door hinges, hitch, safety chains, lights, brakes, tire wear, tire inflation, hitch weld, wheel bearings, sharp projections on trailer (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1155-2"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"4866","question":"What is the MOST important consideration when trailering a horse?","answer":"Safety  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1155-1; HSm220-1"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"4867","question":"What part of a straight load trailer gives the horse something to brace on rather than the door?","answer":"Butt bar or butt chain (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1150-3; HSm220-2"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"4868","question":"Name ONE structure that acts as a horse trailer safety feature by helping prevent a horse from falling out of the trailer if the door opens.","answer":"Butt bar, butt chain, trailer dividers (FYI:  Butt bars and butt chains are usually seen in straight load trailers; dividers are usually seen in slant load trailers.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1150-3; HSm220-2"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"4869","question":"Why should you NEVER undo the butt chain or open the trailer door before untying your horse?","answer":"Horse might try to back out as soon as the trailer door opens.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1150-1; HSm220-2"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"4870","question":"When unloading a horse from a trailer, what should you do before you release the butt chain or open the door?","answer":"Untie the horse  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1150-3; HSm220-2"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"jr bonus","number":"4871","question":"Name 3 connections between the tow vehicle and the horse trailer.","answer":"Hitch, safety chains, lights, brakes, stabilizer bars (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1155-1; HSm220-1"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"4872","question":"Name ONE safety device that attaches the trailer to the tow vehicle besides the hitch.","answer":"Safety chains (also accept lights, brakes, stabilizer bars) [FYI:  Safety chains should also attach to the frame of the tow vehicle.  They should be long enough to allow adequate turning, but short enough to not drag on the ground.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1155-1; HSm220-1"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"4873","question":"Why should electric brakes be added to a truck and trailer?","answer":"To help stop the trailer (FYI:  Trailers carrying horses are heavy and can be hard to stop.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1155-2"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"4874","question":"Why should chains be used to attach the horse trailer to the truck?","answer":"To provide added safety (If the hitch comes loose, the truck and trailer will still be attached by the chains.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1155-1; HSm220-1"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"4875","question":"When trailering horses, what is one of the most important things to check?","answer":"Hitch (also accept trailer door or any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1155-1; HSm220-1"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"4876","question":"For safety reasons, ALL trailer hitches should also be attached to what part of the tow vehicle?","answer":"Frame  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1155-1; HSm220-1"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"4877","question":"For safety reasons hitches should always be attached to the frame of the tow vehicle.  With what type of trailer connection is the trailer attached to a ball in the truck bed?","answer":"Gooseneck (also accept 5th wheel)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1155-1; HSm220-1"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"sr bonus","number":"4878","question":"Name 3 driving practices you should follow when pulling a trailer.","answer":"Start and stop slowly, make turns slowly, drive defensively, check hitch, make sure doors are closed (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1150-1"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"4879","question":"What GENERAL color of trailers may cause profuse sweating or heat stroke in the summer?","answer":"Dark  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1150-3"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"4880","question":"To prevent horses from getting too hot, trailers should be what?","answer":"Well ventilated (also accept a light color)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1150-3; HSm220-2"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"4881","question":"Give ONE reason why horse trailers are required by law to have trailer lights.","answer":"So the trailer is visible in the dark; so other drivers know what changes in movements the trailer is making (FYI:  Blinkers and brake lights are required to indicate trailer movements to other drivers.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1155-2; HSm220-1"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"4882","question":"If you tie your horse in a trailer, what kind of knot should you use?","answer":"Quick release knot (FYI: You can also use trailer ties with panic snaps.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1150-3; HSm220-4"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"4883","question":"Give ONE reason why rubber mats should be periodically removed from a horse trailer.","answer":"To check for rot, to check for rust, to allow floors to dry, to prevent rot, to prevent corrosion of metal floors (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1155-2; HIH220-2"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"4884","question":"When trailering your horse, what can you use on the floor to reduce concussion or pounding on your horse's legs?","answer":"Rubber mats or shavings (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1155-2; HSm220-2"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"sr bonus","number":"4885","question":"Name 4 pieces of equipment used to protect your horse when trailering.","answer":"Leg wraps, tail wrap, shipping boots, head bumper, blanket, hock pads, knee pads, hobbles, bell boots (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1150-3; HSm220-4"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"jr bonus","number":"4886","question":"Name 3 pieces of equipment used to protect your horse when trailering.","answer":"Leg wraps, tail wrap, shipping boots, head bumper, blanket, hock pads, knee pads, hobbles, bell boots (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1150-3; HSm220-4"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"4887","question":"Name the piece of tack that keeps a horse from injuring its head in a trailer.","answer":"Head bumper  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1150-3; HSm220-4"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"4888","question":"2-part question:  When and why would a head bumper be used on a horse?","answer":"When—during trailering; why—tall horse, bad shipper, horse that throws its head or rears during loading or unloading (also accept when leading a horse into a barn with low ceilings or low doorways)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1150-3; HSm220-4"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"4889","question":"Shipping boots or leg wraps for shipping should extend from the knees and hocks downward past what part of the horse's leg?","answer":"Coronet band (FYI:  Protection of the coronet band is important because it’s the area from which the hoof wall grows.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1150-3; HSm220-2"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"4890","question":"Name ONE piece of tack that protects horses’ legs when being trailered.","answer":"Shipping boots or leg wraps (FYI:  Shipping boots should extend from the knees or hocks downward past the coronet band.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1150-3; HSm220-4"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"4891","question":"Give ONE reason why you would you use leg wraps or bandages on your horse when it is traveling.","answer":"To protect the legs, to prevent swelling, or to prevent fatigue (FYI:  Shipping boots should extend from the knees or hocks downward past the coronet band.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1160-1; HSm220-4"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"medium","number":"4892","question":"2-part question:  Give ONE advantage and ONE disadvantage of using a tail wrap during trailering.","answer":"Advantages—keeps hair from rubbing on butt bar, keeps tail clean; disadvantages—if put on too tight, may cut off circulation or cause hair to fall out  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1150-3; HSm220-4"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"4893","question":"How high should the ceiling of a horse trailer be?","answer":"High enough so the horse doesn't hit its head (10 inches higher than the horse's head in a normal resting position)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1155-2; HSm220-2"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"4894","question":"How much room should there be on each side of a horse in a trailer stall?","answer":"3 (three) inches  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1155-2; HSm220-1"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"medium","number":"4895","question":"You do the math...If a horse is leaning against the divider in the horse trailer, how many inches should there ideally be between his other side and the trailer wall?","answer":"6 inches (should have 3 inches on each side when standing properly)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1155-2; HSm220-2"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"sr bonus","number":"4896","question":"Name 3 factors you should consider when choosing a vehicle to pull a trailer.","answer":"Truck size, engine size, electrical system, single or double axle, ball size, type of hitch, tire size, braking system, towing capacity, cooling system, weight capacity of truck, cost; type, weight, length of trailer (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1155-1; HSm220-1"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"jr bonus","number":"4897","question":"Name 3 types of horse trailers.","answer":"Slant, stock, straight load, in-line, horse van, gooseneck, bumper pull (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1155-2; HSm220-1"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"sr bonus","number":"4898","question":"Name 4 types of horse trailers.","answer":"Slant, stock, straight load, in-line, horse van, gooseneck, bumper pull (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1155-2; HSm220-1"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"4899","question":"Name TWO ways horses can enter a horse trailer.","answer":"Ramp or step (Also accept from the rear of the trailer or from the side of the trailer.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1155-3; HSm220-1"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"jr bonus","number":"4900","question":"Name 3 ways horses can ride in a horse trailer.","answer":"Slant, head to head, head to tail, side by side, loose as in a stock trailer (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1155-3; HSm220-2"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"sr bonus","number":"4901","question":"Name 4 ways horses can ride in a horse trailer.","answer":"Slant, head to head, head to tail, side by side, loose as in a stock trailer (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1155-3; HSm220-2"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"sr bonus","number":"4902","question":"Give 3 advantages of a slant load trailer.","answer":"Horses ride easier, horses are more stable during turns, horses encounter less stress, and horses load and unload easier. (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1155-3; HSm220-2"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"4903","question":"Describe a slant load trailer.","answer":"Horses ride side by side on a slant with dividers separating them.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1155-3; HSm220-2"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"4904","question":"Which type of trailer is a favorite because horses ride more easily, have less stress, and are more stable on stops and starts?","answer":"Slant load  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1155-3; HSm220-2"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"4905","question":"Which type of trailer is a safe and popular way to transport a mare and foal?","answer":"Stock trailer (FYI:  Foal should NOT be tied.  Mare can be tied or left untied.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1155-3; HSm220-2"},
    {"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"4906","question":"When shipping one horse in a two-horse straight load trailer, on which side should the horse be loaded?","answer":"Left side (FYI:  Due to the crown of the road, this will give the horse a smoother, more comfortable ride)  <br/> <br/>ref:PNW 83"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"medium","number":"4907","question":"Approximately how long will a horse maintain CARDIOVASCULAR fitness after beginning a layoff?","answer":"6 – 8 weeks (accept any number within this range) [FYI: Musculoskeletal fitness declines faster.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH851-9"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"intermediate","number":"4908","question":"What is the process of building up the horse's cardiovascular system, tendons, and ligaments called?","answer":"Conditioning  <br/> <br/>ref:DET63"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"sr bonus","number":"4909","question":"Identify 3 physiological and/or anatomical factors that would indicate a horse’s racing performance or athletic ability.","answer":"Conformation, respiratory capacity, cardiovascular capacity, gait, type of muscle fibers, proportion of muscle fibers (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH435a-1"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"4910","question":"Name TWO parts of a fitness program.","answer":"Diet and exercise  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH851; HH35"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"medium","number":"4911","question":"How quickly a horse’s heart rate decreases and returns to its resting value is an indication of what?","answer":"Fitness of the horse  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH206"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"sr bonus","number":"4912","question":"Successful conditioning of the equine athlete is dependent on several factors.  Name 3.","answer":"Genetics, training, age, soundness, feeding (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH851-1"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"4913","question":"Name ONE vital sign that provides a good monitor of how horses respond to exercise.","answer":"Heart rate or pulse; respiratory rate  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH851-1; HSm305-1"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"sr bonus","number":"4914","question":"Prior to a work or exercise period, name 3 ways you can evaluate the fitness and soundness of your horse for training.","answer":"Heart rate, temperature, respiratory rate, capillary refill time, visual observation at walk or trot, soreness or sensitivity of back or loin noted while grooming, soreness or lameness when flexion testing, soreness or lameness during warm-up ride  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH851-3"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"4915","question":"Give ONE result of overtraining for a specific event.","answer":"Horse gets sour, horse doesn't want to perform, horse can get injured (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH851-1"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"hard","number":"4916","question":"Recovery heart rate can be helpful in determining fitness.  What are the TWO things you should be looking for?","answer":"Speed of recovery; how low the heart rate falls in a specific recovery time  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH851-6"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"hard","number":"4917","question":"In some facets of the horse industry, exercise is used for purposes other than improving a horse’s endurance, speed, or athletic potential.  What is the main goal in fitting halter horses?","answer":"To maximize muscular development or to improve body tone (accept either) [FYI:  Stock-type horses have a higher percentage of fast twitch muscles which will increase in diameter with trotting, loping, round pen work, etc.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH851-8"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"4918","question":"How should a WORKOUT conclude?","answer":"With a cool down period (also accept on a positive note)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH851-9; HSm360-3"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"hard","number":"4919","question":"Is exercise of low intensity such as walking, trotting, and cantering, where the heart rate stays below 150 BPM and glucose and fatty acids are used as fuels, considered aerobic or anaerobic work?","answer":"Aerobic work  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH895-1"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"hard","number":"4920","question":"What is oxidative phosphorylation or aerobic metabolism?","answer":"Breakdown of nutrients in the presence of oxygen to produce energy (such as ATP)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-5; HIH850-1"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"hard","number":"4921","question":"Is exercise of high intensity such as short sprints or long, fast gallops, where the heart rate is over 150 BPM and glycogen, ATP, and creatine phosphate used as fuels, considered aerobic or anaerobic work?","answer":"Anaerobic work  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH895-1"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"hard","number":"4922","question":"What is glycolysis or anaerobic metabolism?","answer":"Breakdown of energy in the absence of oxygen.  (FYI:  Glucose is broken down into pyruvic acid.  Pyruvic acid is metabolized AEROBICALLY to produce 36 ATP molecules and is metabolized ANAEROBICALLY to produce 2 ATP and 2 lactic acid molecules.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-5; HIH850-1"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"medium","number":"4923","question":"What is the study of movement in horses called?","answer":"Biomechanics (also accept kinesiology)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH850-4; HSm380-6"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"4924","question":"If you've ridden your horse hard, when should you let him have his fill of water?","answer":"After he's cooled out  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH710-7"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"4925","question":"What is the term for a horse that's neither hot to the touch nor breathing hard after it's been exercised?","answer":"Cooled out  <br/> <br/>ref:DET68; HH36"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"4926","question":"Why is it a good practice to walk your horse for the last half mile on a ride?","answer":"To cool him out  <br/> <br/>ref:DET68; HH23"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"4927","question":"A cool down period consists of light work that gradually brings the horse back to a resting state.  In reference to muscles, why is a cool down period important?","answer":"To prevent sore muscles (FYI:  Several minutes of slow trotting followed by walking will help the blood remove lactic acid from the muscles.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH851-9; HIH895-1; HSm360-3"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"4928","question":"Name ONE way to cool out a hot horse.","answer":"Walk him, spray him with a hose, sponge him down, give him a couple of swallows of water every few minutes (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH710-7"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"hard","number":"4929","question":"In reference to training, what does the term \"fartlek\" mean?","answer":"Alternating periods of slow and fast work (FYI:  Fartlek comes from the Swedish word meaning \"speed play\".)  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH389"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"hard","number":"4930","question":"Feeding fat in the diet and gradual conditioning of the horse can help prevent depletion of what polysaccharide that’s stored in muscles?","answer":"Glycogen (FYI:  Glycogen is how carbohydrates are stored in the muscle and liver.  It takes one to five days to replenish glycogen stores.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH851-6"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"hard","number":"4931","question":"What is lactic acid?","answer":"Byproduct of anerobic metabolism (that can cause muscle soreness and stiffness)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH895-1"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"hard","number":"4932","question":"After performing strenuous exercise, a cool down period is suggested to remove what byproduct of metabolism from the muscles?","answer":"Lactic acid (also accept ammonia)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH851-9; HSm360-1"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"hard","number":"4933","question":"What is the purpose of LSD or long, slow distance work?","answer":"It’s used for the initial or early phase of conditioning of a horse. (FYI:  Horses are exposed to low heart rate, aerobic exercise over a period of about 30 days.  Activities progress from suppling to walking and slow trotting to faster gaits.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH851-2,3; FCH203"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"sr bonus","number":"4934","question":"Name 3 things that can be included in an exercise program for racehorses.","answer":"Walking, trotting, cantering, galloping, breezing, “working”, LSD (long slow distance), free exercise (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm175-6; FCH382; HIH851-2"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"hard","number":"4935","question":"In reference to horse racing, what is the term for a short, fast training run of 3 – 4 furlongs?","answer":"Blowout  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH382"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"hard","number":"4936","question":"In reference to horse racing, what is the term for an easy workout where the horse is worked at  moderate speed, under restraint, and without any encouragement by the rider?","answer":"Breeze  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH383"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"4937","question":"Give ONE reason why you should warm up your horse before a workout.","answer":"Loosen up horse's muscles; decrease injury (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm360-3"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"4938","question":"Name TWO things to do when warming up your horse.","answer":"Walk, trot, lateral flexion, vertical flexion  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH851-4"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"medium","number":"4939","question":"Explain the general steps you’d use when teaching your horse to respond to cues.","answer":"Give your horse a cue, if he responds to the cue praise him and release the pressure; if he doesn’t respond, give a stronger cue; end training sessions on positive notes; repeat process so the horse learns by repetition (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330; HH21"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"4940","question":"When training horses, why should your cues be consistent?","answer":"So you don’t confuse the horse (so he’ll understand what is being asked)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH250-2"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"4941","question":"In training, how does a foal learn?","answer":"By repetition  <br/> <br/>ref:HH39"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"4942","question":"When teaching foals to lead, what is a rump or tail rope?","answer":"Cotton rope that's wrapped around the foal's hindquarters to teach it to lead  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH950-4; HSm535-3"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"4943","question":"Name ONE way to teach a young foal to lead.","answer":"Have someone lead the mare so the foal can follow and apply light pressure on the foal's halter so he knows he's being led; use a rump rope; pull gently forward or to the side, if he takes a step forward, praise him (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH950-4; HSm535-3"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"4944","question":"Using a rump rope can help teach a foal to do what?","answer":"Lead  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH950-1; HSm535-3"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"4945","question":"What is the SLANG term for using a sack, saddle blanket, or tarp as part of gentling and training a foal?","answer":"Sacking out  <br/> <br/>ref:HH47"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"jr bonus","number":"4946","question":"Name 3 things you should teach a foal.","answer":"To lead, to be groomed, to be clipped, to have feet worked with, to load in the trailer (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:PNW85-89"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"4947","question":"Give ONE reason why training sessions with foals should be short and should be repeated often.","answer":"Young foals have short attention spans, young foals have a limited capacity to absorb new things  <br/> <br/>ref:HH39"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"jr bonus","number":"4948","question":"Name 3 things that can be included in ground training.","answer":"Manners, longeing, line driving, in-hand work (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET125"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"4949","question":"What is the difference between longeing and round pen work?","answer":"Round pen work doesn't require a longe line (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET125; PNW57,85,86"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"novice","number":"4950","question":"What is ground training?","answer":"Training the horse from the ground  <br/> <br/>ref:DET125; PNW89"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"sr bonus","number":"4951","question":"Name 3 things you can teach a horse by ground driving.","answer":"Teach horse to get used to bit, control speed, control direction, respond to verbal cues, respond to trainer (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:PNW89,90"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"novice","number":"4952","question":"What is it called when a horse travels around a handler in a large circle on a longe line?","answer":"Longeing  <br/> <br/>ref:DET171; FCH395; HH40"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"jr bonus","number":"4953","question":"Name 3 pieces of equipment you need to longe a horse.","answer":"Halter or longeing cavesson, whip, and longe line  <br/> <br/>ref:PNW89,90"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"4954","question":"Give TWO reasons to longe horses.","answer":"Letting your horse work off steam, training a young horse, teaching horse to respect you (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:PNW88"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"4956","question":"When longeing, where should you stand to keep the horse moving forward?","answer":"Out from the hip (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:PNW88"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"4957","question":"When longeing, where do you step to signal a horse to stop?","answer":"Step forward (towards the shoulder)  <br/> <br/>ref:PNW88"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"medium","number":"4958","question":"Name TWO factors that are fundamental to the psychology of horse training.","answer":"Stimuli or cues, responses, and reinforcements  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1240-7; HSm330-4-5"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"medium","number":"4959","question":"What is the acquisition period of training?","answer":"When the horse is learning a task  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-6"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"medium","number":"4960","question":"What is the term for a response that's learned through practice?","answer":"Conditioned response  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1240-1; HSm330-5"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"hard","number":"4961","question":"What is the difference between conditioned and unconditioned responses?","answer":"Conditioned response is a learned response; unconditioned response is a natural response.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1220-1; HSm330-4"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"hard","number":"4962","question":"When cues are presented without reinforcement, a learned response will gradually diminish to the pre-training level.  What is this called?","answer":"Extinction  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-6"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"medium","number":"4963","question":"What term is used to describe the process of desensitization of the newborn foal to being handled by humans such as with grooming, working with the feet, etc.?","answer":"Imprint training  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH525-2; HSm330-4"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"medium","number":"4964","question":"In reference to training, what is imprinting?","answer":"Rapid learning that occurs with a foal within the first several hours of birth (desensitizing a newborn foal to being handled by humans) [accept any reasonable wording]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-4"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"hard","number":"4965","question":"In reference to training, how are punishment, escape, and avoidance similar?","answer":"They all involve aversive or negative stimuli.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1240-3"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"medium","number":"4966","question":"What is the term used when a horse moves away from pressure to avoid a more severe punishment?","answer":"Avoidance  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-4"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"medium","number":"4967","question":"What psychological term is used to describe when a horse tries to get away from an aversive stimulus?","answer":"Escape  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-5"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"4968","question":"Why should you NOT punish your horse for shying?","answer":"Because with its power of association, it would blame the object for the punishment and it might develop the habit of shying at every strange object (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-5"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"novice","number":"4969","question":"Why is it important when you have to punish a horse, that you do it immediately?","answer":"He won't understand why he's being punished if you wait. (FYI:  To be effective, reinforcement or punishment must be contingent or given immediately in relation to responses or behaviors.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-5"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"4970","question":"How soon should you punish a misbehaving horse?","answer":"Immediately (FYI:  To be effective, reinforcement or punishment must be contingent or given immediately in relation to responses or behaviors.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-5"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"medium","number":"4971","question":"What is the aim of punishment?","answer":"To weaken or eliminate an undesirable behavior (FYI: In operant conditioning in psychology, punishment is considered \"positive punishment\" and “negative reinforcement” is the removal of an aversive stimulus.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-5"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"4972","question":"Why should you NEVER punish your horse when you're angry?","answer":"Your punishment will be too severe.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc54"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"medium","number":"4973","question":"In reference to training, what is “power of association”?","answer":"Ability to link an action and a reaction (or stimulus and response) [accept any reasonable wording]  <br/> <br/>ref:DET219; HSc7"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"medium","number":"4974","question":"Why is the horse's power of association useful in training?","answer":"Horse will try to do as asked to earn a reward or to avoid a punishment (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET219; HSc7"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"hard","number":"4975","question":"What is the difference between positive reinforcement and negative reinforcement?","answer":"Positive reinforcement is when an animal is rewarded for a correct response; negative reinforcement is when an animal works to get rid of an aversive stimulus. (Also accept punishment as negative reinforcement.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1240-3; DET189; DET218; HSm330-5"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"hard","number":"4976","question":"What is a schedule of reinforcement called when not every response is reinforced?","answer":"Intermittent reinforcement  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-6; HIH1240-5"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"jr bonus","number":"4977","question":"Name 3 different TYPES of rewards that can be used in training horses.","answer":"Food, praise, petting, removal of pressure, discontinuing work, letting horse relax (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-5"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"4978","question":"How should you end each TRAINING session?","answer":"On a positive note (also accept with a cool down period)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH851-9"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"4979","question":"Name ONE thing you should do when your horse does well.","answer":"Pat him, praise him, or release pressure (FYI:  To be effective, reinforcement or punishment must be contingent or given immediately in relation to responses or behaviors.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-5"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"medium","number":"4980","question":"What type of reinforcement is reward training?","answer":"Positive reinforcement [FYI:  In psychology’s operant conditioning, there are positive reinforcement, negative reinforcement, positive punishment (what we think of as punishment) and negative punishment.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1240-3; HSm330-5"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"medium","number":"4981","question":"Give the common term for positive reinforcement.","answer":"Reward training [FYI:  In psychology’s operant conditioning, there are positive reinforcement, negative reinforcement, positive punishment (what we think of as punishment) and negative punishment.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1240-3; HSm330-5"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"hard","number":"4982","question":"In reference to training, what is the correct term for the acts or movements a horse makes when given cues or stimuli?","answer":"Responses  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-4"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"medium","number":"4983","question":"What do you call a stimulus that naturally causes a response?","answer":"Unconditioned stimulus  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm330-4"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"hard","number":"4984","question":"What term classifies the following devices: twitch, hobbles, breeding hobbles, cross ties?","answer":"Restraints  <br/> <br/>ref:DET277, 140, 38,73"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"sr bonus","number":"4985","question":"Name 3 methods of restraining a horse.","answer":"Tying, chute, hobbles, high line, picket line, blindfolding, twitch, lifting foot, holding ear or tail (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET277, 140, 38,73, 56"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"4986","question":"In reference to training, what is a \"finished\" horse?","answer":"One with a lot of training  <br/> <br/>ref:DET107"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"4987","question":"In reference to training, what is a \"green\" horse?","answer":"One with little training  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH391"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"hard","number":"4988","question":"In reference to training, what does the term \"trial\" mean?","answer":"Practice  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1240-6"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"4989","question":"When first teaching a horse to neck rein, why would you need to use two hands?","answer":"One to pull (direct rein) and one to push (bearing rein)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH41"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"medium","number":"4990","question":"Why is a hackamore used to start young horses in training?","answer":"Provides control, but doesn’t injure the mouth.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH1100-10"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"medium","number":"4991","question":"What is the general term for teaching a horse what actions are expected in response to the handler's cues?","answer":"Training  <br/> <br/>ref:DET273"},
    {"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"medium","number":"4992","question":"What system of training horses has its roots in classical Greek horsemanship and became recognized during the Renaissance when the great European riding masters developed it?","answer":"Dressage  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH181D-1"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"4993","question":"What is a blemish?","answer":"Any mark or deformity that diminishes the beauty, but not the usefulness of a horse  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH230-1; HSc13"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"4994","question":"What is the term for a mark or deformity that decreases the beauty, but NOT the usefulness of the horse?","answer":"Blemish  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH230-1; HSc13"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"4995","question":"Give ONE example of a blemish.","answer":"Scar, rope burn, capped hock, capped elbow or shoe boil, windpuff, thoroughpin (accept any reasonable answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH230-1; HSc12"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"intermediate","number":"4996","question":"What COMMON term describes swelling of the superficial flexor tendon due to tendonitis?","answer":"Bowed tendon  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-7; HIH455-7; HIH230-4; DET36; CAHA19"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"4997","question":"What are bowed tendons?","answer":"Enlarged tendons behind the cannon bone (FYI:  Bowed tendons are more common in the front legs.  Severity can be from a simple tendon inflammation to a serious strain or rupture of the tendon.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-7; HIH455-7; HIH230-4; DET36; CAHA19"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"sr bonus","number":"4998","question":"Name 3 signs, symptoms, or features of an acute tendon strain or \"bowed tendon\".","answer":"Lameness; heat, swelling, and/or pain at the injury site; \"bowed\" or enlarged tendon can be palpated (felt)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH455-7"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"sr bonus","number":"4999","question":"Name 3 things that predispose a horse to bowed tendons.","answer":"Poor conformation (of knee, fetlock, pastern, etc.), improper trimming or shoeing (long toe, low heels, etc.), improper conditioning, muscle fatigue, working on soft ground, repeated work on hard surfaces, uneven footing  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH455-7"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5000","question":"Name ONE treatment for a bowed tendon.","answer":"Rest, ice or cold hosing, support bandages, medications (such as anti-inflammatory drugs)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH455-7"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5001","question":"What structure is USUALLY involved in a bowed tendon?","answer":"Superficial flexor tendon (of the front leg) [FYI:  The deep digital flexor tendon or the tendons on the hind legs are occasionally involved.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH455-7"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"jr bonus","number":"5002","question":"Name 3 INITIAL treatments for both splints and bowed tendons.","answer":"Rest, ice or cold hosing, support bandages, medications (such as anti-inflammatory drugs)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH455-7"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"sr bonus","number":"5003","question":"Name 4 INITIAL treatments for both splints and bowed tendons.","answer":"Rest, ice or cold hosing, support bandages, medications (such as anti-inflammatory drugs)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH455-7"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5004","question":"Identify the following condition:  more common in young horses in vigorous training; starts as soreness but it can persist and form a swelling on the front of the cannon.","answer":"Bucked shin  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-7; FCH271; DET42"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5005","question":"What bone does a bucked shin affect?","answer":"Cannon bone  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-7; FCH271; DET42"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5006","question":"In reference to unsoundness, what is a bucked shin?","answer":"Inflammation or enlargement of the front of the cannon (FYI: Bucked shins are like shin splints in humans and are usually due to trauma of the periosteum.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-7; FCH271; DET42"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5007","question":"Give ONE term for a soft swelling of the point of the elbow.","answer":"Capped elbow or shoe boil (FYI: It's also called olecranon bursitis.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-7; DET244; FCH384; HSc13"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5008","question":"What is the most common cause of shoe boil or capped elbow?","answer":"Elbow being irritated by the shoe or hoof of the front foot (when the horse is lying down)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-7; DET244; FCH384; HSc13"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5009","question":"Where on a horse would a \"shoe boil\" be found?","answer":"On a horse's elbow (FYI: Shoe boil is also called capped elbow and olecranon bursitis and it’s due to irritation from the hoof or shoe of the front foot rubbing on the elbow when the horse is lying down.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-7; DET244; FCH384; HSc13"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5010","question":"Describe a capped hock.","answer":"Capped hock (FYI:  Capped hock is often caused by repeated trauma such as stall kicking.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-7; DET47; FCH385; HSc13"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5011","question":"Is capped hock a blemish or an unsoundness?","answer":"Blemish (FYI:  A capped hock is a soft swelling at the point of the hock that is often caused by repeated trauma such as stall kicking.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-7; DET47; FCH385; HSc13"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5012","question":"What is the MEDICAL term for an enlargement of the knee due to trauma?","answer":"Carpitis (FYI:  The slang term is \"popped knee\".)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-7; DET48; FCH384"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5013","question":"What is carpitis?","answer":"Inflammation that results in enlargement of the knee (FYI:  The slang term is \"popped knee\" and it’s usually caused by trauma.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-7; DET48; FCH384"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5014","question":"What condition causes cloudiness of the eye lens and may result in blindness?","answer":"Cataract  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH465-4; HIH1060-5; DET51"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5015","question":"What is a cataract?","answer":"Cloudy or opaque appearance of the eye (more specifically the lens of the eye)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH465-4; HIH1060-5; DET51"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"intermediate","number":"5016","question":"Name ONE cause of cataracts in horses.","answer":"Inherited; secondary to intraocular inflammation [FYI:  Cataracts can be congenital (animal is born with one) or acquired (may develop after injury, inflammation, or disease).]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH465-4"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"intermediate","number":"5017","question":"Cataracts are a condition where a cloudiness or opacity forms in what structure in the horse's eye?","answer":"Lens  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH465-4; HIH1060-5; DET51"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5018","question":"Name this condition:  usually limited to horse's hind legs; partial dislocation of the fetlock can occur; shortening of the tendons on the back of the fetlock can cause the fetlock to bend forward.","answer":"Cocked ankle  <br/> <br/>ref:DET60; HH49; HSc11"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5019","question":"What is the term for inflammation and thickening of the plantar tarsal ligament below the point of the hock?","answer":"Curb (FYI:  Curbs may occur in extremely sickle-hocked horses.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-7; HIH230-4; DET74; FCH386; CAHA32"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5020","question":"A horse that's extremely sickle hocked is prone to what unsoundness of the hock?","answer":"Curb (FYI: A curb a hard swelling below the point of the hock.  It's inflammation of the plantar tarsal ligament.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-5; FCH386"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5021","question":"Name the unsoundness described as a hard swelling below the point of the hock.","answer":"Curb (FYI: A curb is inflammation of the plantar tarsal ligament. It's seen in extremely sickle-hocked horses.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-7; HIH230-4; DET74; FCH386; CAHA32"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5022","question":"Describe the unsoundness known as a curb.","answer":"Hard swelling below the point of the hock (due to thickening of the plantar tarsal ligament)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-7; HIH230-4; DET74; FCH386; CAHA32"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5023","question":"What is the name for inflammation and enlargement of the growth plates of the long bones in rapidly growing horses?","answer":"Epiphysitis (pronounced eh-pih-fiss-EYE-tis)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET98; FCH388"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5024","question":"What GENERAL age of horses is epiphysitis associated with?  (pronounced eh-pee-fiss-EYE-tis)","answer":"Young horses (FYI: Epiphysitis is inflammation of the growth plates.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET98; FCH388"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5025","question":"In reference to unsoundness and blemishes, what is poll evil?","answer":"Inflamed swelling between the ears (FYI:  Inflammation of the cranial nuchal bursa that's caused by trauma or infection.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET217; HSc 13"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5026","question":"Name the unsoundness that's described as an inflamed swelling between the ears.","answer":"Poll evil  <br/> <br/>ref:DET217; HSc 13"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5027","question":"What is the COMMON name for an infection of the cranial nuchal or supra-atlantal bursa? (pronounced NUKE-al)","answer":"Poll evil  <br/> <br/>ref:CAHA20"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"intermediate","number":"5028","question":"What is the name for a condition in which an infection of the withers leads to an abscess?","answer":"Fistulous withers  <br/> <br/>ref:DET108; HSc13"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"intermediate","number":"5029","question":"In reference to unsoundness and blemishes, what are fistulous withers?","answer":"Inflammation of the withers (FYI:  Fistulous withers is a chronic inflammation of the supraspinous bursa near the withers. It can be caused by trauma or infection such as Brucella abortus bacteria.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET108; HSc13"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5030","question":"What is it called when an organ or tissue protrudes through a body wall or cavity?","answer":"Hernia  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH975-7; HIH1060-5; DET139; FCH393; HSc12"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5031","question":"What is a hernia?","answer":"Protrusion of internal organs or tissues through a body wall or cavity (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH975-7; HIH1060-5; DET139; FCH393; HSc12"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5032","question":"Name ONE type of hernia that only occurs in male horses.","answer":"Scrotal (also accept inguinal)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH975-5; HIH1060-5"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5033","question":"Name TWO of the most common types of hernias seen in foals.","answer":"Umbilical, scrotal, and inguinal areas  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH975-7,8; HIH1060-5"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5034","question":"What is lameness?","answer":"Any irregularity of gait resulting from moving with pain or difficulty  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-3; HIH455-1; DET163; HSc13"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5035","question":"Give ONE reason why there is less lameness and unsoundness in the hind feet and legs.","answer":"Hind legs support less weight and do less work.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH230-1; HSm345-7"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5036","question":"What is the term for any irregularity in gait that results from moving with pain or difficulty?","answer":"Lameness  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-3; HIH455-1; DET163; HSc13"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"sr bonus","number":"5037","question":"Name 3 causes (NOT examples) of lameness.","answer":"Inherited, congenital, trauma, infection, metabolic (such as laminitis), neurological, developmental, conformation flaws, circulatory disorder, combination (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm380-3; HIH455-1; HSm375"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5038","question":"What is a horse doing if he's said to be \"favoring\" a foot?","answer":"Limping slightly  <br/> <br/>ref:DET104; HSc12"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5039","question":"Name ONE disease or condition that causes symptoms such as pointing, a short stubby painful stride, and lameness.","answer":"Navicular; laminitis or founder  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH540-3-5"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5040","question":"In reference to unsoundness, explain the phrase \"go short\".","answer":"Take short steps (indicative of lameness)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET123"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"sr bonus","number":"5041","question":"2-part question:  Name and describe 3 of the Obel grades of pain or lameness.","answer":"Grade 1:  sound at walk, shortened stride at trot; Grade 2:  moves willingly, may limp and nod head at the walk and trot; Grade 3:  reluctant to move, doesn’t want feet picked up; Grade 4:  VERY reluctant to move or is lying down  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm375-13"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5042","question":"Name ONE way to determine the exact location of a horse's lameness.","answer":"Compare the sore leg to the opposite leg, look and feel for swelling, feel for tenderness, use hoof testers, have vet take radiographs or x-rays, have vet do nerve blocks (accept any correct answer)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc13"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5043","question":"If a horse is lame on a front foot, describe the way he would walk.","answer":"Head bobs when the lame foot strikes the ground. (Accept any correct answer.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc13"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5044","question":"How is the horse's head carried when he's lame in BOTH front feet?","answer":"Head is carried higher than usual.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc13"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5045","question":"When the lame foot of a horse touches the ground, what position will the horse's head be in?","answer":"Jerked up  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc13"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5046","question":"When a horse is trotting and he lifts his head when his right front foot hits the ground, in what leg or legs is he lame?","answer":"Right front and/or left rear  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc13"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5047","question":"Lameness is usually most pronounced or seen at what gait?","answer":"Trot  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH455-1"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5048","question":"In which legs, front or hind, does most lameness occur?","answer":"Front legs (FYI: Front legs carry about 65% of the horse's weight.  70% of unsoundness occurs in the front legs, 95% are at the knees or below, and 80% are in the foot and ankle.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH455-1"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5049","question":"In reference to lameness, what is pointing?","answer":"Horse stands with one front foot extended more than normal (as a sign of foot pain or lameness)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET215; HIH455-2"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5050","question":"What term is used when, as a sign of lameness, the horse stands with one front foot extended more than normal?","answer":"Pointing  <br/> <br/>ref:DET215; HIH455-2"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5051","question":"What is another name for laminitis?","answer":"Founder (FYI:  Founder is a lay term for laminitis that means the bone has dropped to the bottom as a ship founders and sinks.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm375-11; HIH640-1"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5052","question":"What condition is defined as an inflammation of the laminae of the foot?","answer":"Laminitis (also accept founder) Founder [FYI:  Founder is a lay term for laminitis that means the bone has dropped to the bottom as a ship founders and sinks.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm375; HIH455-1; HSc13"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5053","question":"What is another name for founder?","answer":"Laminitis (FYI:  Founder is a lay term for laminitis that means the bone has dropped to the bottom as a ship founders and sinks.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm375-11; HIH640-1"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5054","question":"Name TWO causes of laminitis or founder.","answer":"Colic, sudden feed changes, too much grain, too much lush pasture, obesity,  foot concussion, weather changes, stress, injuries, diseases, infections, toxins, surgery, drugs, allergies, endotoxemia, retained placenta, dystocia  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm375-12; HIH540-4; HIH640-1"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"sr bonus","number":"5055","question":"Name 3 possible causes of laminitis or founder.","answer":"Colic, sudden feed changes, too much grain, too much lush pasture, obesity,  foot concussion, weather changes, stress, injuries, diseases, infections, toxins, surgery, drugs, allergies, endotoxemia, retained placenta, dystocia  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH540-4; HSm375"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5056","question":"How does a diet that’s high in simple carbohydrates, such as too much grain or too much lush pasture, cause laminitis?","answer":"Too many carbohydrates in the hindgut cause lactic acid to be a byproduct of microbial fermentation.  Too much lactic acid can cause laminitis (by affecting the intestinal flora which secrete toxins).  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm360-2; HIH795-1-2"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5057","question":"Give ONE reason why laminitis or founder can be life-threatening to a horse.","answer":"Coffin bone may rotate or sink; coffin bone may penetrate through the bottom of the sole; subsequent infection and pain which may lead to the death of the horse; tearing action of the deep digital flexor tendon  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH540-4; HSm375-16-18"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5058","question":"In reference to laminitis or founder what does it mean if the coffin bone has “sunk”?","answer":"Downward rotation of the coffin bone  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH455-1; HSm375; HH9"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5059","question":"What can happen in cases of severe founder if the coffin bone is not stabilized?","answer":"Downward rotation of the coffin bone or “dropped sole” (FYI:  Coffin bone may penetrate through the bottom of the sole which can cause pain, infection, and death.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH540-4; HSm375; HH9"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5060","question":"Describe a founder ring.","answer":"Visible ridges and grooves in the hoof wall (FYI: Grooves are close together at the toe and are widely separated at the heels)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm375-19; DET113"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"sr bonus","number":"5061","question":"Name 3 of the phases of founder.","answer":"Developmental, acute, sub-acute, and chronic (FYI:  Not all sources agree on the phases of founder.  Developmental is from the inciting agent to lameness.  Acute is from lameness to coffin bone rotation.  Chronic is after coffin bone rotation.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH640-1; HSm375"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5062","question":"What phase of founder has the signs of lingering lameness and irregular rings in the hoof wall?","answer":"Chronic phase (FYI:  The chronic phase begins when the coffin bone rotates.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH540-5; HSm375"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5063","question":"How many HOURS does the developmental phase of founder usually last?","answer":"24 – 72 hours (accept any number within this range) [According to this source, the developmental phase starts with the contact with the inciting agent and ends with the first episode of lameness.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH640-1; HSm375"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5064","question":"During which phase of founder does damage to the feet occur?","answer":"Developmental phase (FYI:  The developmental phase goes from the inciting agent or cause until the first episode of lameness.  Since there are no clinical signs, treatment is to eliminate the inciting cause.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH640-1; HSm375"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5065","question":"Name TWO ways of preventing laminitis due to grass founder.","answer":"No pasture, limit pasture, turn out in the early morning, feed hay before turning out, use a grazing muzzle, no lush fast-growing pastures, no spring pasture when it has been sunny and has then gotten cold (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH795-2; HSm375"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"sr bonus","number":"5066","question":"Name 3 ways of preventing laminitis due to fructan consumption (grass founder).","answer":"No pasture, limit pasture, turn out in the early morning, feed hay before turning out, use a grazing muzzle, no lush fast-growing pastures, no spring pasture when it has been sunny and has then gotten cold (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH795-2; HSm375"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"sr bonus","number":"5068","question":"Name 4 signs or symptoms of acute laminitis.","answer":"Lameness (usually in front feet), reluctance to move, warm feet, pounding pulses at the back of the pastern, sitting dog stance (leaning back on the hind feet to take pressure off the front feet), feet sensitive to touch, pain on standing, stiffness  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH540-4; HSm375"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"jr bonus","number":"5069","question":"Name 3 signs or symptoms of acute laminitis.","answer":"Lameness (usually in front feet), reluctance to move, warm feet, pounding pulses at the back of the pastern, sitting dog stance (leaning back on the hind feet to take pressure off the front feet), feet sensitive to touch, pain on standing, stiffness  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH540-4; HSm375"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"sr bonus","number":"5070","question":"Name 4 characteristics of a chronically foundered hoof.","answer":"Founder rings (rings are closer together at the toe and further apart at the heels), dropped sole (downward rotation of the coffin bone), widened white line, long toe, curled toe, dished hoof, bulging sole, flattened sole (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm375"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"jr bonus","number":"5071","question":"Name 3 characteristics of a chronically foundered hoof.","answer":"Founder rings (rings are closer together at the toe and further apart at the heels), dropped sole (downward rotation of the coffin bone), widened white line, long toe, curled toe, dished hoof, bulging sole, flattened sole (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm375"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5072","question":"When moving, horses with navicular tend to land on the toe to avoid concussion to what part of the foot?","answer":"Heel (FYI:  Navicular disease or syndrome is also called caudal heel pain syndrome.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH455-2; HSm375-10"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5073","question":"What is navicular disease?","answer":"Inflammation or pain in the navicular bone (or surrounding areas) [FYI: Navicular disease are syndrome is also called caudal heel pain syndrome.]  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm230-9; HIH540-3; HSc50"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"sr bonus","number":"5074","question":"Name 3 structures in the foot that are affected in horses with navicular disease.","answer":"Navicular bone, navicular bursa, deep digital flexor tendon, ligaments (suspensory ligaments and Impar ligament), cartilage  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm375-10; HIH540-3; HIH455-2; CAHA27"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5075","question":"What condition causes lameness, a short stubby stride, and pointing of the affected foot while standing?  This condition results from inflammation of the navicular bone and surrounding areas.","answer":"Navicular disease (FYI:  Navicular disease or syndrome is also called caudal heel pain syndrome.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm375-10; HIH455-2; CAHA27"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"jr bonus","number":"5076","question":"Name 3 predisposing or risk factors to navicular disease.","answer":"Large, heavy-bodied horses with small feet; upright pasterns; improper trimming or shoeing (long toes and low heels); improper conditioning; excessive concussion; club foot (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH455-2; HIH540-3; HSm375-10"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"sr bonus","number":"5077","question":"Name 4 predisposing or risk factors to navicular disease.","answer":"Large, heavy-bodied horses with small feet; upright pasterns; improper trimming or shoeing (long toes and low heels); improper conditioning; excessive concussion; club foot (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH455-2; HIH540-3; HSm375-10"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5078","question":"A large, heavy-bodied horse with small feet is predisposed to what condition of the feet?","answer":"Navicular disease (FYI:  Navicular disease or syndrome is also called caudal heel pain syndrome.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH455-2; HIH540-5"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5079","question":"Name ONE way to diagnose navicular disease.","answer":"MRI, radiographs (x-rays), nerve blocks, use of hoof testers  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm375-9; HIH540-3"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"jr bonus","number":"5080","question":"Name 3 signs or symptoms of navicular disease.","answer":"Lameness, pointing, shortened stride, \"walking on eggs\", going up on toes (to keep weight off heels), reluctance to go downhill, shuffling gait contracted heels (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH455-2; HIH540-3; HSm375-9"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"sr bonus","number":"5081","question":"Name 4 signs or symptoms of navicular disease.","answer":"Lameness, pointing, shortened stride, \"walking on eggs\", going up on toes (to keep weight off heels), reluctance to go downhill, shuffling gait contracted heels (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH455-2; HIH540-3; HSm375-9"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"sr bonus","number":"5082","question":"Name 3 treatments of navicular disease.","answer":"Egg bar shoe (with heel support), rocker toe shoe, raise heel with wedges, trim toes short, medications that increase circulation (Isoxsuprine or Osphos), anti-inflammatory medications, “nerving” (severing the posterior digital nerves)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm375-10,11; HIH540-3,4"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5083","question":"Why can \"nerving\" a horse with navicular be risky?","answer":"Horse feels no pain so it may unintentionally injure itself or its rider.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH540-4; HSm375-11"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5084","question":"What is the term for cutting the digital nerve to relieve pain?","answer":"Nerving (FYI: Nerving is also called posterior digital neurectomy, palmar digital neurectomy, and plantar digital neurectomy and it’s used as one of the last resorts in the treatment of navicular.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm375-11; HIH540-4"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5085","question":"In reference to unsoundness, what are osselets?","answer":"Bony growths on the front of the fetlock (FYI:  Osselets are a type of traumatic arthritis of the fetlock.  They are caused by repeated concussion and short, steep pasterns.  They’re most often seen young racehorses.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-7; HIH455-5"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5086","question":"What are bony growths on the front of the fetlocks that are commonly seen in young racehorses?","answer":"Osselets  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-7; HIH455-5"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5087","question":"Describe the unsoundness known as ringbone.","answer":"Bony growth on the pastern (FYI: Ringbone can affect the pastern or coffin joints.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-7; HIH455-6; DET234; FCH401"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5088","question":"Which feet, the front or the hind, are usually affected by ringbone?","answer":"Front feet  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH455-6"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5089","question":"What is the difference between low ringbone and high ringbone?","answer":"Low ringbone occurs in the coffin joint (between the coffin and short pastern); high ringbone occurs at the pastern joint (between the short pastern and long pastern) (FYI:  Low ringbone is more serious; high ringbone is more common.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-7; HIH455-6; DET234; FCH401"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"intermediate","number":"5090","question":"Name ONE joint that ringbone affects.","answer":"Pastern joint; coffin joint (FYI:  High ringbone or ringbone of the pastern joint is more common; low ringbone or ringbone of the coffin joint is more serious.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-7; HIH455-6; DET234; FCH401"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5091","question":"What is the term for bony growths on the pastern?","answer":"Ringbone (FYI: Ringbone can affect the pastern or coffin joints.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-7; HIH455-6; DET234; FCH401"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"sr bonus","number":"5092","question":"Name 3 causes of ringbone.","answer":"Conformation faults—short steep pasterns, long sloping pasterns, pigeon toe, splay foot, base wide, base narrow; improper trimming—long toes and low heels; improper conditioning; trauma; strain; working on hard, soft, or uneven ground  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH455-6"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"intermediate","number":"5093","question":"Which type of ringbone occurs at the pastern joint and is more common, high or low ringbone?","answer":"High ringbone (FYI:  Low ringbone occurs at the coffin joint.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-7; HIH455-6; DET234; FCH401"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"intermediate","number":"5094","question":"Which type of ringbone occurs at the coffin joint and is more serious, high or low ringbone?","answer":"Low ringbone (FYI:  Low ringbone is more likely to affect the joint function.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-7; HIH455-6; DET234; FCH401"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"sr bonus","number":"5095","question":"Name 3 predisposing factors for sidebone.","answer":"Conformation faults (pigeon toe or splay foot), improper trimming or shoeing, repeated concussion (from working on hard surfaces or from carrying a lot of weight), trauma  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH455-5"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5096","question":"2-part question:  On which legs, the front or the hind, is sidebone usually seen and does sidebone usually cause lameness?","answer":"Front legs; sidebone does not usually cause lameness (except in the formative stage)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH455-5"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5097","question":"Describe the unsoundness known as sidebone.","answer":"Ossification of the lateral cartilages of the coffin bone  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-7; HIH230-4; DET245"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5098","question":"What term is used to describe the unsoundness that is commonly referred to as “hard at the heels” and its most common in draft horses?  With this unsoundness there’s calcification of the collateral cartilages of the coffin bone.","answer":"Sidebone  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-7; DET245; FCH403"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5099","question":"2-part question:  Explain where sidebone would most likely develop due to the following conditions:  toe in and toe out.","answer":"Toe in—lateral or outside; toe out—medial or inside  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH455-5"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5100","question":"What does it mean when we say a horse is \"sound\"?","answer":"No injuries, disease, or unsoundness (accept any)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET250; HSc12"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5101","question":"What common term refers to a horse that's free from injuries and flaws?","answer":"Sound  <br/> <br/>ref:DET250; HSc12"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5102","question":"Why is soundness in the horse of extreme importance?","answer":"Unsoundness affects his usefulness. (If he's not sound, you can't use him.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH230-1; HSc12"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5103","question":"What is meant by the term \"serviceably sound\"?","answer":"Horse has abnormalities that have only LIMITED effects on its usefulness.  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH230-1"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5104","question":"What is the term used to indicate that a horse may have a structural problem or deviation which may have only limited effect on his ability to perform?","answer":"Serviceably sound  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH230-1"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"sr bonus","number":"5106","question":"Name 3 types of spavin of the hocks.","answer":"Blind or occult spavin, bog spavin, bone or jack spavin, blood spavin  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-7; FCH404; DET various"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5107","question":"A spavin refers to various abnormalities of what joint?","answer":"Hock (tarsus)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-7; FCH404; HSc13"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5108","question":"Give ONE term for a hock spavin that causes lameness without visible evidence of an abnormality.","answer":"Occult spavin or blind spavin  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-7; DET195; DET30; FCH404"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5109","question":"In reference to unsoundnesses and blemishes, what is a blind or occult spavin?","answer":"Type of hock spavin that causes lameness without visible evidence of an abnormality  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-7; DET195; DET30; FCH404"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5110","question":"What is the term for the swelling of the saphenous vein as it crosses a bog spavin?","answer":"Blood spavin  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-7; DET33; FCH404"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5111","question":"In reference to unsoundnesses and blemishes, what is a blood spavin?","answer":"Swelling of a vein on the inside of the hock (FYI:  A blood spavin is a swelling or varicosity of the saphenous vein as it crosses a bog spavin.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-7; DET33; FCH404"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5112","question":"What is a soft swelling on the inner front part of the hock that's caused by inflammation of the synovial membrane?","answer":"Bog spavin  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-7; DET34; FCH404"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5113","question":"In reference to unsoundnesses and blemishes, what is a bog spavin?","answer":"Soft swelling of the front, inner part of the hock (FYI:  A bog spavin is caused by inflammation of the synovial membrane and it’s seen higher on the hock than a bone spavin.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-7; DET34; FCH404"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5114","question":"Describe the unsoundness known as a bone spavin or jack spavin.","answer":"Arthritis of the lower joints of the hock (bony growth on the inside lower portion of the hock)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-7; HIH230-4; DET34; FCH404"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5115","question":"Give ONE term for a bony growth found on the inside lower portion of the hock that's due to arthritis of the lower hock joints.","answer":"Bone spavin, jack spavin, or true spavin  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-7; HIH230-4; DET34; FCH404"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5116","question":"A thoroughpin is a soft, fluid-filled enlargement of the lateral or outside surface of a joint in which fluid can be pushed from the outside to the inside surface of the joint.  What SPECIFIC structure is involved?","answer":"Deep digital flexor tendon sheath (FYI:  A thoroughpin is a distention of the deep digital flexor tendon sheath caused by strain on that tendon.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-7; DET267; FCH406"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5117","question":"In reference to unsoundnesses and blemishes, what is a thoroughpin?","answer":"Soft swelling of the upper outside surface of the hock (FYI:  A thoroughpin is a distention of the deep digital flexor tendon sheath caused by strain on that tendon.  Fluid can be pushed from the outside to the inside.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-7; DET267; FCH406"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5118","question":"What is the cause of thoroughpin?","answer":"Strain on the deep digital flexor tendon  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH406"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5119","question":"What is the puffy swelling on the upper part of the hock which is a distention of the tendon sheath of the deep digital flexor tendon?","answer":"Thoroughpin  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-7; DET267; FCH406"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"intermediate","number":"5120","question":"What conformation fault is most likely to be seen in a horse with splints?","answer":"Bench knee or off-set knee (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH230-4; HIH455-6-7; DET252; FCH404"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"intermediate","number":"5121","question":"In reference to unsoundness and blemishes, what is a \"splint\"?","answer":"Bony enlargement in the groove between the splint and cannon bones (FYI:  Splints usually occur on the inside of the front legs, but they may occur on the outside or on the hind legs.  Splints may be high, low, forward, or backward.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH230-4; HIH455-6-7; DET252; FCH404"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"sr bonus","number":"5122","question":"Name 3 predisposing factors for splints.","answer":"Conformation faults (bench knee, base narrow, toed-out), hard training, improper trimming or shoeing, rapid growth, trauma, training on hard ground (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH455-7; FCH404"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5123","question":"Name TWO treatments of splints.","answer":"Ice packs or cold hosing, anti-inflammatory drugs such as Bute, support wraps, rest  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH455-7; FCH404"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5124","question":"Are most splints found on the inside or outside of the cannon?","answer":"Inside of the cannon (medially)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH455-6-7; HIH230-4; FCH404"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"intermediate","number":"5125","question":"In reference to unsoundness and blemishes, what is the term for a bony enlargement in the groove between the splint and cannon bones?","answer":"Splint (FYI:  Splints usually occur on the inside of the front legs, but they may occur on the outside or on the hind legs.  Splints may be high, low, forward, or backward.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH230-4; HIH455-6-7; DET252; FCH404"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5126","question":"What GENERAL age category of horses is prone to splints?","answer":"Young horses (FYI:  Splints often occur in young horses entering training.  Exercise or trauma may damage the interosseous ligaments between the splint and cannon bones.  Horses may be lame initially, but later may only have a “bump” in the area.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH455-6-7; DET252; FCH404"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5127","question":"Give ONE name for the for the condition where there is upward fixation of the horse's patella.","answer":"Stifled, stifling, or patellar fixation (FYI:  Stifling occurs when the joint if fully extended.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET256; FCH399"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5128","question":"Describe the unsoundness known as \"stifled\".","answer":"Upward fixation of the horse's patella (FYI:  Stifling occurs when the joint if fully extended. It can be relieved by manipulating the leg forward or backing the horse several steps.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET256; FCH399"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5129","question":"Name TWO maneuvers that cause stringhalt to be especially obvious.","answer":"Backing; turning sharply  <br/> <br/>ref:FCH405"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5130","question":"What is stringhalt?","answer":"Excessive jerking of the hind leg (FYI:  Stringhalt or “goose-stepping” is a neuromuscular disorder of the hindquarters that causes a sudden, violent flexing or jerking up of the hind leg. Backing and turning sharply make it worse.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET258; HSc13; FCH405"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5131","question":"Name the unsoundness described as excessive jerking up or flexing of the hind leg.","answer":"Stringhalt (FYI:  Stringhalt or “goose-stepping” is a neuromuscular disorder of the hindquarters that causes a sudden, violent flexing or jerking up of the hind leg. Backing and turning sharply make it worse.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET258; HSc13"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5132","question":"In reference to unsoundness and blemishes, what is shoulder sweeny?","answer":"Atrophy or decrease in size of the shoulder muscles (FYI:  Shoulder sweeny is usually due to damage to the suprascapular nerve.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET260; HSc13"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5133","question":"Injury of what SPECIFIC tissue causes atrophy of the supraspinatus and infraspinatus muscles in shoulder sweeny?","answer":"Suprascapular nerve  <br/> <br/>ref:DET260; CAHA22"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5134","question":"What is the term for atrophy or decrease in size of the shoulder muscle due to nerve damage?","answer":"Sweeny  <br/> <br/>ref:DET260; HSc13"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5135","question":"What is atrophy?","answer":"Decrease in size or wasting away of a body part or tissue  <br/> <br/>ref:DET17; HSc13"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5136","question":"What is the term for abnormal bone growth from the surface of a bone?","answer":"Exostosis (bone spur) [pronounced ex-ahs-TOE-sis]  <br/> <br/>ref:DET101"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5137","question":"What is exostosis? (pronounced ex-ahs-TOE-sis)","answer":"Formation of new bone on the surface of a bone (bone spur)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET101"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5138","question":"In reference to unsoundness, what is gonitis?","answer":"Inflammation of the stifle joint (FYI:  Gonitis can be an acute or chronic condition.  It can be caused by trauma, wounds, or strains.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET123"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5139","question":"What is ossification? (pronounced ah-sih-fih-CAY-shun)","answer":"Cartilage changing into bone or the process of bone formation (accept either)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET197; CAHA12"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5140","question":"What is the term for the changing of cartilage into bone?","answer":"Ossification (specifically endochondral ossification)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET197; CAHA12"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5141","question":"What is the term for the practice of applying a hot iron or needle as a treatment for an unsoundness or blemish?","answer":"Firing or pin firing  <br/> <br/>ref:DET108; DET212"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5142","question":"What marking is described as a muscular depression of unknown origin, is usually seen on the neck, and is sometimes seen on the shoulder?","answer":"Prophet's Thumb  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm110-9; DET221"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5143","question":"What is sesamoiditis?","answer":"Inflammation of the PROXIMAL sesamoid bones or the surrounding soft tissues (FYI:  Sesamoiditis may be caused by trauma, strain, or nutritional imbalances and it may result in chronic lameness.)  <br/> <br/>ref:DET242"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5144","question":"What is unsoundness in a horse?","answer":"Any abnormality that interferes with the usefulness of the horse (accept any reasonable wording)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH230-1; DET279; HSc12"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"sr bonus","number":"5145","question":"Name 4 unsoundnesses that do NOT result in lameness.","answer":"Blindness, cataracts, monkey mouth, parrot mouth, fistulous withers, poll evil, hernia, heaves, roaring, infertility, tipped vulva (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc12,13"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"sr bonus","number":"5146","question":"Name 4 unsoundnesses of the head.","answer":"Cataract, blindness, poll evil, parrot mouth, monkey mouth jaw  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH455; HSc13"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"jr bonus","number":"5147","question":"Name 3 unsoundnesses of the head.","answer":"Cataract, blindness, poll evil, parrot mouth, monkey mouth jaw  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH455; HSc13"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5148","question":"On what GENERAL part of the horse would the following conditions be found:  quittor, corns, thrush, and gravel?","answer":"Feet  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc13"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5149","question":"Both base wide and base narrow stances place weight unevenly on the hoof.  Name TWO unsoundnesses that tend to develop due to this uneven weight distribution.","answer":"Ringbone and sidebone  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH230-3"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5150","question":"Name ONE common cause of unsoundnesses of the legs.","answer":"Injury, excess stress or strain, faulty conformation  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc13"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"sr bonus","number":"5151","question":"Give 3 general causes of most leg unsoundnesses.","answer":"Trauma, stress, strain, heavy work, faulty conformation (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc13; HSm345-3-7; HIH230"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5152","question":"What is the MAIN cause of hind leg unsoundness?","answer":"Trauma (such as sprains, strains, or twists)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSc13"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"sr bonus","number":"5153","question":"Name 4 unsoundnesses or blemishes, NOT conformation faults, of the front legs.","answer":"Splints, windpuffs, bowed tendons, ringbone, sidebone, bucked shins, osselets, sesamoiditis, popped knee, navicular, laminitis, corns, abscesses, quittor, hoof cracks (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH230-4; HIH455"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"sr bonus","number":"5154","question":"Name 4 unsoundnesses or blemishes, NOT conformation faults, of the hind leg.","answer":"Hip down (knocked down hip), stifled (patella fixation), stringhalt, curb, thoroughpin, bog spavin, bone or jack spavin, blind or occult spavin, blood spavin, capped hock (accept any correct answers)  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH455"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5155","question":"Name TWO unsoundnesses or blemishes of the horse's hocks.","answer":"Thoroughpin, bone or jack spavin, bog spavin, blind or occult spavin, capped hock, curb  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-7; HSc13"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5156","question":"In reference to unsoundness and blemishes, what are windpuffs?","answer":"Soft, fluid-filled swellings on the fetlock or pastern (FYI:  Windpuffs are also called windgalls, road galls, and road puffs.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-7; DET294; CAHA14"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5157","question":"Name ONE cause of windpuffs.","answer":"Trauma, heavy work, too much work on hard roads, improper conditioning (working too hard too fast)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-7; DET294; CAHA14"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5158","question":"What is the term for the condition that results from an excessive amount of synovial fluid in the fetlock joint capsule that is commonly seen in horses that are worked hard?","answer":"Windpuffs  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-7; DET294; CAHA14"},
    {"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5159","question":"What are soft, puffy, fluid-filled swellings around a joint, usually the fetlock or pastern?","answer":"Windpuffs (FYI:  Windpuffs result from enlargements of the bursa or fluid-filled sacs, protrusion of the joint capsule from synovial fluid, or swelling of the tendon sheaths.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-7; DET294; CAHA14"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"5160","question":"Who was foundation sire of the American Saddlebred Horse?","answer":"Denmark (Also accept Harrison Chief.) [FYI:  Denmark was a Thoroughbred stallion.]  <br/> <br/>ref:TH30; HSm115-5"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"5161","question":"Name 4 breeds from which the American Saddlebred horse was developed.","answer":"Narragansett Pacer, Thoroughbred, Canadian Pacer, and Morgan (Also accept Arabians, Galloway horses, and Hobby horses.)  <br/> <br/>ref:TH29; HIH169B-1"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"intermediate","number":"5162","question":"What famous Quarter Horse, foaled in 1915, was used in a line-breeding program by the King Ranch of Texas because he fit their ideal of a working cow horse?","answer":"Old Sorrel (FYI: Old Sorrel was the grandson of Peter McCue.)  <br/> <br/>ref:TH16"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"intermediate","number":"5163","question":"What horse was the famous grandsire of Wimpy P-1? He was foaled in 1915 on the King Ranch in Texas.","answer":"Old Sorrel (FYI: Old Sorrel was the grandson of Peter McCue.)  <br/> <br/>ref:TH16"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"5164","question":"What horse, foaled in 1895 in Illinois, was the famous grandsire of Old Sorrel?","answer":"Peter McCue (FYI: Peter McCue was an important sire in the development of the Quarter Horse breed. More than 20% of Quarter Horses registered prior to 1948 traced back to Peter McCue on the male side.)  <br/> <br/>ref:TH16"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"5165","question":"What term is primarily used for a feral donkey? This term is the Spanish word for donkey.","answer":"Burro  <br/> <br/>ref:TH45"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"5166","question":"Why are asses called donkeys?","answer":"The word “dun” describes the usual color of asses.  <br/> <br/>ref:TH45"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"5167","question":"Donkeys are usually gray-dun but they can be other colors.  Name 4 other colors of donkeys.","answer":"Brown, black, bay, roan, ivory, spotted, dappled roan, frosted gray, ivory white, frosted spotted white (Also accept red, chestnut, or sorrel.)  <br/> <br/>ref:TH45-46; HSm125-11"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"5168","question":"What is the term for the small dark spots on the throatlatch of donkeys? These spots are good for identifying particular donkeys.","answer":"Collar buttons  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm125-11"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"5169","question":"What is the maximum height of donkeys registered in the National Miniature Donkey Association?","answer":"36 inches  <br/> <br/>ref:TH46"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"5170","question":"What is the minimum height for a female American Mammoth Jack?","answer":"56 inches  <br/> <br/>ref:TH46"},
    {"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"5171","question":"What is the minimum height for a male American Mammoth jack?","answer":"58 inches  <br/> <br/>ref:TH46"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"5172","question":"2-part question: Which is a more serious condition – toed in or toed out—and why?","answer":"Toed out; because legs can interfere or strike each other.  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm345-2; HIH230-2; HIH230-5; HH12; TH96"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"5173","question":"Give ONE term for when a horse's height at the withers is lower than its height at the hip.","answer":"Walking downhill, running downhill, or built downhill  <br/> <br/>ref:TH86; HIH220-6"},
    {"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"5174","question":"What do the conformation terms \"walking downhill\" or \"running downhill\" mean?","answer":"Horse's height at the hip is higher than its height at the withers (Accept any reasonable wording.)  <br/> <br/>ref:TH86; HIH220-6"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"5175","question":"Name 4 of the trots recognized in dressage riding.","answer":"Collected trot, medium trot, working trot, extended trot (Also accept lengthening of stride, passage, and piaffe.)  <br/> <br/>ref:TH115"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"intermediate","number":"5176","question":"Which type of walk in dressage is slower and shorter-strided than the other walks?","answer":"Collected walk  <br/> <br/>ref:TH113"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"intermediate","number":"5177","question":"Which type of walk in dressage is ground-covering?  The hind feet overreach the prints of the fore feet.  The topline remains level.  The head and neck usually nod up and down twice during each stride.  The head and the neck are extended.","answer":"Extended walk  <br/> <br/>ref:TH113"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"5178","question":"Which type of walk in dressage is an unconstrained walk that is relaxed? The hind feet touch the ground in front of the prints of the fore feet.","answer":"Medium walk  <br/> <br/>ref:TH113"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"5179","question":"With which type of trot in dressage is the horse’s neck raised and arched? The hocks are well-engaged and flexed. The horse’s steps are shorter, but the elasticity and cadence are not lessened.","answer":"Collected trot  <br/> <br/>ref:TH113"},
    {"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"5180","question":"With which kind of trot in dressage is the stride moderate in length?","answer":"Medium trot  <br/> <br/>ref:TH113"},
    {"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"5181","question":"Name TWO things that describe the ideal motion of the horse.","answer":"Straight, true, long stride, well-coordinated stride, free of deviation (Accept any correct answers.)  <br/> <br/>ref:HH12"},
    {"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"5182","question":"What medication is used to treat bradycardia?","answer":"Atropine  <br/> <br/>ref:HSm425-; DET17"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"5183","question":"What farrier tool is used to make a crease in hand-forged shoes or to repair damaged creases during shaping?","answer":"Fullering iron  <br/> <br/>ref:TH512-513"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"5184","question":"What size horseshoe fits most average-sized horses?","answer":"Number 1 (FYI: Sizes of \"keg\" or pre-made shoes are 000, 00, 0, 1, and 2.)  <br/> <br/>ref:TH515"},
    {"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"5185","question":"Giving only ONE number, how much does an aluminum racing plate weigh?","answer":"Accept any number between 2 – 3 ounces. (FYI: Depending on the size, type, and use, steel keg shoes may weigh from 7.2 ounces to 14.4 ounces with a Classic Rim size 1 shoe weighing 0.6 pounds.)  <br/> <br/>ref:TH515, 516"},
    {"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"5186","question":"According to the National Research Council, the percent of crude protein should be balanced with the percent of what specific nutrient in horse rations?","answer":"Lysine  <br/> <br/>ref:HIH745-2"}
]
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    